<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">7 Westferry Circus • Canary Wharf • London E14 4HB • United Kingdom Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report Caprelsa vandetanib</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2011-11-17">17 November 2011</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">7 Westferry Circus • Canary Wharf • London E14 4HB • United Kingdom Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report Caprelsa vandetanib</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2011-11-17">17 November 2011</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>An agency of the European Union</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T03:25+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Product information</head><p>Invented name of the medicinal product: Caprelsa</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Applicant:</head><p>AstraZeneca AB AstraZeneca European Regulatory Affairs (ERA) Building 411A Floor 4 S-151 85 Södertälje Sweden</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Active substance: vandetanib</head><p>International Nonproprietary Name/Common Name: vandetanib</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmaco-therapeutic group (ATC Code):</head><p>Protein kinase inhibitors (L01XE12)</p><p>Therapeutic indication: Caprelsa is indicated for the treatment of aggressive and symptomatic medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic disease. 'For patients in whom rearranged during transfection (RET) mutation is not known or is negative, a possible lower benefit should be taken into account before individual treatment decision (see important information in sections 4.4 and 5.1)).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmaceutical form:</head><p>Film-coated tablet 1. Background information on the procedure</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1.">Submission of the dossier</head><p>The applicant AstraZeneca AB submitted on 1 September 2010 an application for Marketing</p><p>Authorisation to the European Medicines Agency (EMA) for Caprelsa, through the centralised procedure falling within the Article 3 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Scientific discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Introduction</head><p>Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma</p><p>Carcinoma of the thyroid is the most common malignancy of the endocrine system and include mostly (85%-95%) well-differentiated tumors (papillary or follicular), about 2.5% to 10% of thyroid cancers are medullary carcinoma and other are anaplastic, both of which carry a worse prognosis for patients.</p><p>MTC is a distinct subtype, arising from the parafollicular cells (C-cells) of the thyroid, that has particular prognostic and genetic features: it presents mainly as a sporadic cancer (75% of cases) or as part of a hereditary syndrome (25%).</p><p>- Patients with FMTC develop only MTC). Patients with hereditary MTC carry a germline mutation of the RET gene, leading to constitutive activation of the RET tyrosine kinase.</p><p>-The sporadic form of MTC most often presents in middle-aged patients as a solitary nodule in the thyroid. RET was found to be mutated in some tumors of patients with sporadic MTC, and patients with RET mutations (especially the common M918T mutation) are more likely to have regional lymph node involvement or distant metastases and a worse outcome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms and Prognosis</head><p>Patients with MTC often have localization to the neck and mediastinum. Main symptoms are mostly diarrhoea, pain, opiod use, fatigue, respiratory symptoms, flushing, weight loss and dysphagia.</p><p>Metastatic MTC spreads most often to the regional lymphatics as well as to the liver, lungs, and bones.</p><p>Metastases can be anticipated by increasing levels of calcitonin and are often evident on radiographic imaging studies.</p><p>The 5-year survival for medullary cancer with regional spread is about 78%. For medullary cancer which spread to distant sites or lymph node the 5-year survival rate is approximately 40% and median overall survival is 2-3 years in patients with distant metastatic disease. Approximately 35% of patients present with tumor extending beyond the thyroid with regional lymph node involvement, and 13%</p><p>have metastatic disease at initial diagnosis. Metastatic disease is the most common cause of death in patients with MTC, and approximately 90% of patients with metastatic disease die of progressive cancer.</p><p>Patients with the hereditary form of the disease generally have a better prognosis than patients with the sporadic form. However, if patients are matched for age and disease stage, no differences in survival are seen, suggesting that patients with sporadic disease may be diagnosed later with more advanced disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatment</head><p>Patients with MTC can be cured only by thyroidectomy, performed when the tumour is confined to the thyroid gland. The tumour is relatively unresponsive to conventional doses of radiation therapy and to chemotherapeutic regimens (none of which have been approved in this indication yet).</p><p>About the product Caprelsa, vandetanib, is an orally administered tyrosine kinase inhibitor (TKI) with activity against the Rearranged during transfection (RET) proto-oncogene, the Vascular endothelial growth factor receptor (VEGFR) and Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor (EGFR).</p><p>Initially, the Applicant claimed vandetanib was indicated for the treatment of adult patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic medullary thyroid cancer.</p><p>Subsequently, as a result of the evaluation procedure, the approved indication states as follows:</p><p>Caprelsa is indicated for the treatment of aggressive and symptomatic medullary thyroid cancer <ref type="bibr">(MTC)</ref> in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic disease. For patients in whom Rearranged during Transfection (RET) mutation is not known or is negative, a possible lower benefit should be taken into account before individual treatment decision (see important information in sections 4.4 and 5.1).</p><p>Treatment should be initiated and supervised by a physician experienced in treatment of MTC and in the use of anticancer medicinal products and experienced in the assessment of electrocardiogram (ECG). Only one supply per prescription is allowed. For a further supply, a new perscription is required.</p><p>The recommended dose is one 300 mg tablet once a day, taken with or without food at about the same time each day.</p><p>If a dose is missed, it should be taken as soon as the patient remembers. If it is less than 12 hours to the next dose, the patient should not take the missed dose. Patients should not take a double dose (two doses at the same time) to make up for a forgotten dose.</p><p>Patients treated with Caprelsa must be given the patient alert card and be informed about the risks of Caprelsa.</p><p>Vandetanib may be administered until patients with MTC are no longer benefiting from treatment.</p><p>QTc interval should be carefully assed prior to initiation of treatment. In the event of common terminology criteria for adverse events (CTCAE) grade 3 or higher toxicity or prolongation of the ECG QTc interval, dosing with vandetanib should be at least temporarily stopped and resumed at a reduced dose when toxicity has resolved or improved to CTCAE grade 1. The 300 mg daily dose can be reduced to 200 mg (two 100 mg tablets), and then to 100 mg if necessary. The patient must be monitored appropriately. Due to the 19-day half-life, adverse reactions including a prolonged QTc interval may not resolve quickly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Quality aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1.">Introduction</head><p>Caprelsa contains the active substance vandetanib. For other ingredients see the SmPC. The product is formulated as immediate release tablets of two strengths. The 100 mg strength is presented as a round, biconvex, white, film-coated tablet with 'Z100' impressed on one side; the other side is plain.</p><p>The 300 mg strength is presented as an oval-shaped, biconvex, white, film-coated tablet with 'Z300' impressed on one side; the other side is plain.</p><p>The product is packaged in PVC/PVDC/alu blisters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Active Substance</head><p>The chemical name of the active substance is N-(4-bromo-2-fluorophenyl)-6-methoxy-7-[(1methylpiperidin-4-yl) methoxy] quinazolin-4-amine.</p><p>The corresponding molecular formula is C 22 H 24 BrFN 4 O 2 , molecular weight is 475.36 g/mol. The compound is achiral.</p><p>The structure of vandetanib was confirmed by elemental analysis, mass spectrometry, infra red spectroscopy, nuclear magnetic resonance spectroscopy, ultraviolet spectroscopy, differential scanning calorimetry and X-ray crystallography.</p><p>Vandetanib is a white to off-white powder. The substance exhibits pH-dependent aqueous solubility (with best solubility at acidic pH) and is defined as class II (low solubility/high permeability) under the Biopharmaceutics Classification System (BCS). Vandetanib shows varied solubility in organic solvents (sparingly soluble in tetrahydrofuran and ethanol, slightly soluble in ethylacetate, very slightly soluble in acetonitrile).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture</head><p>The applicant decided to use some elements of quality by design (QbD) approach for the active substance synthesis. The manufacture of vandetanib is a seven step process starting from three starting materials. Three intermediates are key intermediates; however, only one of them is routinely controlled. Specifications for starting materials and this intermediate have been adequately justified.</p><p>Regarding the other isolated intermediates, suitable specifications for skip testing have been set.</p><p>A design space with respect to impurities formation has been defined for each of the intermediates. No critical process parameters were identified, as the level of impurities remained well below the tolerated levels at all times. Consequently, the ranges established during the screening have been considered as proven acceptable ranges.</p><p>The design space boundaries have been established using a combination of prior knowledge, significant manufacturing experience and experimentation in conjunction with science-based risk management processes. The vandetanib design space boundaries are justified based on an examination of all the information from the development of the vandetanib synthetic process, the manufacture of clinical trial batches and extensive systematically designed multi factorial studies.</p><p>For the purification step of vandetanib, the applicant has also described the approach to determine process parameters and identified the region of thermodynamic stability of anhydrate. Process parameters for the distillation and residual water post-distillation have been set and impurity interaction experiments have been performed. Based on these additional data, the boundaries of the design space for the purification step correspond to the ranges explored in the design of experiments.</p><p>The applicant has agreed to verify at commercial scale any movement of the manufacturing process to a different area of the design space, other than the area of the design space already authorised, according to the agreed process verification protocol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Specification</head><p>A number of critical quality attributes (CQA) for the active substance were considered during the establishment of the proposed vandetanib design space. Some of the CQAs are controlled in the active substance specification -these are description, identification, assay, purity, contents of residual solvents, sulphated ash and particle size. For the rest of CQAs a justification why this is not necessary was provided.</p><p>Vandetanib is routinely controlled by in-house monograph which includes appearance, identification, assay, organic impurities, residual solvents and particle size. An exhaustive discussion has been provided on impurity profile; detailed information was provided for intermediates, reaction by-products and the active substance degradants. The impurity limits are considered safe, based on toxicology data. Absence of routine control of starting materials, potential genotoxic impurities, residual solvents and heavy metals has been sufficiently justified by additional data.</p><p>Analytical methods used for the active substance control have been sufficiently described and appropriately validated.</p><p>Batch results starting from early development batches were provided. Recent production batches were manufactured within the proposed design space limits at the set points. All results conform to the active substance specification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stability</head><p>Stability studies according to the relevant EU/ICH stability guidelines have been submitted with late development batches. Based on stability results submitted up to 48 months at long term conditions, a retest period of 60 months can be granted with the special storage "stored in the primary packaging protected from light".</p><p>Vandetanib solid is found to be stable to both thermal and hydrolytic degradation but a small degree of degradation is observed under stressed photolytic conditions. In solution, vandetanib is degraded under acidic, oxidative and light stress conditions but it is stable under basic conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3.">Finished Medicinal Product</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmaceutical Development</head><p>All excipients, used in the finished product manufacture, are of compendial quality. Dibasic calcium phosphate dihydrate and microcrystalline cellulose are used as fillers, crospovidone as disintegrant, povidone as binder and magnesium stearate as lubricant. Purified water is used in wet granulation but is not present in the finished product. The tablets are film-coated with a mixture of hypromellose, polyethylene glycol, titanium dioxide and purified water.</p><p>The applicant proposed to have flexible range in the amount of some of the excipients (dibasic calcium phosphate dihydrate, microcrystalline cellulose, magnesium stearate and the film coating). This, however, was only accepted for magnesium stearate and the film coating, based on the knowledge gained during the development. The amounts of dibasic calcium phosphate dihydrate and microcrystalline cellulose have been fixed during the procedure.</p><p>Physicochemical properties of the active substance and its compatibility with the excipients were extensively studied. Pharmaceutical development of the finished product contains QbD elements.</p><p>Both the formulation and manufacturing development have been evaluated through the use of design of experiments including the risks identified during risk assessments. A design space has been defined for the wet granulation and the dry granulate milling. Critical process parameters forming the design space are clearly set and found acceptable. Particle size reduction of vandetanib is performed prior to the finished product manufacture. Particle size within the set specification limit does not affect dissolution performance of the tablets. Data from process screening also demonstrated that dissolution performance is not affected by tablet hardness.</p><p>It has been demonstrated that dissolution is not critical for the in vivo performance, as the limiting factor for bioavailability is the absorption rate. Several tablet variants were prepared and tested for dissolution behaviour. In vitro dissolution tests can differentiate between these variants; however, as seen from their in vivo behaviour in a clinical study, they can be considered bioequivalent.</p><p>Dissolution experiments were conducted at varied conditions for the pH and use of surfactant.</p><p>Dissolution rate is related to disintegration time. A discriminating dissolution method has been developed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adventitious agents</head><p>No materials used in the manufacture of the finished product are of human or animal origin.</p><p>Magnesium stearate is of vegetable origin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture of the product</head><p>Conventional wet granulation approach was selected as vandetanib has sub-optimal compression properties and is incorporated into the tablets in a high load. Risk assessment of individual manufacturing steps and their impact on the quality of the product was performed.</p><p>Both tablet strengths are manufactured from the common granulate.</p><p>The manufacturing process starts with dispensing of the ingredients which are then dry mixed. The mixture is granulated with purified water, the wet mass is de-lumped on a screening mill and the granulate is dried. The dried granulate is afterwards mixed with magnesium stearate and compressed into tablet cores. The tablet cores are film-coated in a coating pan. The finished product is packed into blisters.</p><p>In-process controls are performed at each step of the manufacturing process as part of the overall control strategy; the critical process parameters are tested to ensure that the product is manufactured inside the design space. Non-critical in process controls are performed to confirm continuous quality of the product on-line and to reduce testing at release. The batch size has been defined.</p><p>Traditional approach has been followed with respect to manufacturing process validation.</p><p>The manufacturing process was sufficiently described and validated to the extent required for the marketing authorisation approval. At the time of the CHMP Opinion the proposed design space was only partly verified at commercial scale. Only a target area of the restricted approved design space has been verified. This is acceptable and no concerns are raised about the capability and reproducibility of the manufacturing process, when operating in this target area. However if the applicant wishes to move to other areas of the design space, then this move should be verified with an appropriate verification scheme. It should be noted that the currently approved verification scheme has a limited value in assessing the risk of such moves. Therefore prior to moving to areas of the design space not already verified, the applicant needs to submit a revised verification scheme (submitted as a variation in section 3.2.R), including consideration of the requirement for a running-in period based on the assessment of the risk attributed to new areas of the design space.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Product specification</head><p>The critical quality attributes were defined: identity, assay, degradation products, uniformity of dosage units, dissolution and microbial purity. These are also specification parameters, together with description.</p><p>Reduced finished product testing approach, based on the results of real time testing, has been proposed for the release testing. The dissolution test will not be performed routinely at the time of release as it is controlled via the GSA and disintegration in-process tests. Nevertheless, it will be performed on stability. The uniformity of dosage units by weight variation will not be performed routinely either; however, all batches would comply with the limit if tested. The test for microbial purity has been included in the finished product control strategy. All batches would pass the test if tested.</p><p>The reduced testing at release has been accepted in principle. However, it cannot be applied before the outcome of the running-in period is available. Release testing frequency will be revised through a risk assessment process, based on the outcome of the proposed running-in-period scheme (i.e. full testing for five commercial batches per strength). The switch from parallel testing to reduced testing will be done through a variation.</p><p>Adequate descriptions of the in-house analytical methods are given. The methods are appropriately validated. Batch results starting from development batches and including clinical batches produced at the proposed commercial manufacturing site, have been provided. All results comply with the finished product specification.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stability of the product</head><p>Three batches of vandetanib 100 mg tablets and three batches of 300 mg tablets manufactured at production scale at the commercial site were stored in the proposed commercial packaging, i.e. PVC/PVDC/alu blisters. The tablets were also tested in bulk and at stressed conditions (high temperature, light).</p><p>Samples have been tested at each time point for description, assay, dissolution, degradation products and water content. In addition, microbial purity has been tested annually. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparability Exercise for Finished Medicinal Drug Product</head><formula xml:id="formula_0">N/A GMO N/A</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4.">Discussion on chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>Initial major objections related to the design space for both the active substance and the finished product have been satisfactorily solved. The design space has been partly reduced as compared to the initial application. The boundaries of the design space are now adequately set to ensure desired quality of the finished product.</p><p>The quality of the product is considered acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5.">Conclusions on the chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>Information on development, manufacture and control of the drug substance and drug product has been presented in a satisfactory manner. The results of tests carried out indicate satisfactory consistency and uniformity of important product quality characteristics, and these in turn lead to the conclusion that the product should have a satisfactory and uniform performance in the clinic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.6.">Recommendation(s) for future quality development</head><p>N/A</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Non-clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Introduction</head><p>The non-clinical development program comprises of pharmacology, pharmacokinetic and toxicology studies which have been performed in accordance with Good Laboratory Practices (GLP).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacodynamic studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacodynamics in vitro</head><p>Vandetanib potently and selectively inhibited VEGFR-2, EGFR and RET kinase activity, which are 3 key targets in MTC.</p><p>Vandetanib more effectively inhibited phosphorylation of EGFR/L858R mutants (substitution of Leucine at codon 858 with Arginine) than wild-type EGFR. Phosphorylation of the gatekeeper mutants, EGFR/T790M (substitution of Threonine at codon 790 with Methionine) and RET/V804, showed decreased sensitivity to Vandetanib.</p><p>In in vitro model of angiogenesis, Vandetanib inhibited VEGF-stimulated endothelial cell migration, proliferation, survival and new blood vessel formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacodynamics in vivo</head><p>In vivo, Vandetanib significantly reduced VEGF-induced and tumour cell-induced angiogenesis, tumour vessel permeability and tumour microvessel density, and inhibited tumour growth and metastasis in human and murine xenograft and orthotopic models of cancer.</p><p>In various human tumour xenograft models in mice, Vandetanib significantly inhibited tumour growth and angiogenesis and induced tumour regressions. These anti-tumour effects became more pronounced as the dose increased and were independent on tumour size at the start of treatment.</p><p>When treatment was stopped tumours rapidly re-grew, but growth was re-inhibited when treatment was restarted, indicating that tumours remain responsive to Vandetanib without developing resistance and that sustained treatment with Vandetanib is required to maintain inhibition of tumour growth.</p><p>In the PC-9 human lung cancer model, Vandetanib produced a more sustained anti-tumour effect, whereby PC-9 tumours did not re-grow when treatment was stopped. The antitumor activity and inhibition of angiogenesis was enhanced when Vandetanib was given in combination with taxanes.</p><p>The 2 metabolites of Vandetanib, N-desmethyl and N-oxide Vandetanib, showed similar inhibitory activity against both VEGFR-2, VEGFR-1, EGFR and FGFR-1 compared to Vandetanib. The N-oxide metabolite was less potent than the N-desmethyl metabolite against all kinase enzymes.</p><p>Vandetanib showed broad-spectrum antitumour activity in vivo. This antitumour activity extended to a range of models (subcutaneously or orthotopically implanted human tumour xenografts or syngeneic murine tumours) and histological types, including lung, colon, breast, prostate, ovarian, glioma, head and neck.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary pharmacodynamic studies</head><p>In a murine model of wound healing, Vandetanib did not prevent wound healing, but was associated with a reduced skin breaking strength.</p><p>In an in vitro selectivity screen, Vandetanib bound significantly to 59/334 receptor or enzyme targets including several protein kinases previously identified in other screening assays. Ten receptors were bound by Vandetanib with sufficient affinity (IC 50 &lt; 1µM) to suggest the potential for receptor interactions. Then, next to targets directly involved in tumour proliferation and angiogenesis (VEGFR-2, EGFR and RET), Vandetanib is active against other targets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety pharmacology programme</head><p>Vandetanib inhibited the hERG channel with an IC 50 of 0.4 µM, produced an increase in action potential duration at concentrations of ≥1 µM in isolated Purkinje fibers and increased QTcV by up to 15% in anaesthetised dogs. These results suggest clearly a hERG channel-mediated risk of QT interval prolongation in humans.</p><p>When Vandetanib was given in combination with ondansetron, an anti-emetic drug, an increase in hERG channel inhibition was observed.</p><p>Vandetanib increased blood pressure in rats and dogs and then, might also have the potential to induce hypertension in humans.</p><p>In conscious rats, a single oral dose of Vandetanib up to 200 mg/kg did not affect respiratory function.</p><p>At these doses, no effect in humans is expected since 40 mg/kg produced a protein free Cmax similar to that seen in patients at a therapeutic dose of 300 mg which is significant lower than the dose rates tested in this study. A single oral dose of 50 mg/kg Vandetanib did not affect renal function in conscious rats.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacodynamic drug interactions</head><p>No pharmacodynamic drug interaction studies have been submitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">Pharmacokinetics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Absorption</head><p>Vandetanib was absorbed slowly with a T max ranged from 2 to 8 hours after single or repeated oral administration of vandetanib to rats and dogs, the oral bioavailability was generally good (50 to 90 %).</p><p>The C max and area under the curve (AUC 0-24 ) increased fairly dose-proportional up to about 25 mg/kg and thereafter slightly less than proportional in rats after repeated administration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution</head><p>The protein binding of 14 C-Vandetanib in plasma of mice, rats, rabbits dogs and human was moderate, from 83 to 90%. The tissue distribution of vandetanib and/or metabolites in pigmented and non pigmented male rats after single oral dosing was slow but extensive, and consistent with the distribution pattern of a lipophilic compound. Highest concentrations of vandetanib and/or its metabolites were seen in the majority of tissues at 6-8 hours after administration. The distribution of radioactivity to brain was evident. Retention of radioactivity was seen in pigmented tissues indicating melanin affinity. A significant distribution of radioactivity was seen in milk of lactating rats and further on in the plasma of suckling pups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Metabolism</head><p>The metabolism of vandetanib seemed to be similar in the toxicology species, rat and dog, as well as in mouse and human. The 2 major metabolites identified in excreta, were N-desmethyl-vandetanib and vandetanib-N-oxide. In mouse, a minor metabolite was also identified as O-desalkyl-vandetanib glucuronid. A glucuronide conjugate was also detected in human urine.</p><p>Metabolism as well as biliary excretion appears to be most important for the elimination of vandetanib in preclinical species. CYP identification studies in vitro, suggest that CYP3A4 is involved in the formation of N-desmethyl-Vandetanib. vandetanib-N-oxide is formed via FMO1 and FMO3</p><p>(FMO=flavine mono-oxygenase). Both these enzymes are also found in kidney indicating that renal excretion might be contributed to the clearance of vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Excretion</head><p>Excretion of 14 C-Vandetanib in faeces (via bile) was the major route in mouse, rat and dog with excretion in urine being a minor route. The rate of excretion was generally slow and consistent with the plasma half-lives of vandetanib. As vandetanib was the major component detected in rat faeces it is likely that N-oxide is excreted into the faeces and then reduced back to vandetanib in the gut. In dogs, the major component in faeces was unchanged vandetanib and it is possible that a similar reduction had occurred in the gut of dogs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetic Drug Interactions (in vitro)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vandetanib and hepatic cytochromes</head><p>Vandetanib is metabolized through the CYP3A4 about 10% and the FMO1 and FMO 3, about 2%, yielded to N-desmethyl vandetanib and to vandetanib-N-oxide, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cytochrome inhibition by vandetanib</head><p>Vandetanib produced some inhibition of CYP2D6 with IC50 and Ki values of 25 and 13 μg/mL, respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cytochrome induction by vandetanib</head><p>Induction of CYP1A2, 2C9 and 3A4 by vandetanib was evident in studies using human hepatocytes.</p><p>Maximal induction of CYP1A2 activity (3-fold increase in activity, 28% of the positive control (βnaphthoflavone) response), CYP2C9 activity (2,3-fold, 38% of the positive control (rifampicin) effect) and CYP3A4 activity (17,2 -fold increase, 33% of the positive control (rifampicin) effect), occurred at 0,95 μg/mL of vandetanib, a concentration close to the therapeutic one at 300 mg, i.e. 0,81 μg/mL</p><p>Vandetanib showed a weak inhibition of P-gp (IC50 = 8.7 μg/ml) and BCRP (IC50 = 11.9 μg/ml).</p><p>Considering that the steady-state concentrations of vandetanib following 100 mg and 300 mg daily dosing are approximately 0,32 μg/ml and 0,81µg/ml, respectively, it is unlikely that vandetanib will markedly affect the disposition of P-gp and BCRP substrates. However, since these transporters are located at the intestinal level and since the concentrations of vandetanib are much higher in the gastro-intestinal tract than in plasma, inhibition of P-gp and BCRP at this level cannot be excluded.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OCT2</head><p>Vandetanib was an inhibitor of OCT2 inhibiting the uptake of the selective OCT2 marker substrate</p><p>[14C]-creatinine by HEK-OCT2 cells, with a mean IC50 value of approximately 2, 1 μg/ml (study KMX083).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4.">Toxicology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single dose toxicity</head><p>A single oral dose of Vandetanib at 2000 mg/kg to mice or rats was not tolerated and all animals died or were killed for humane reasons. A single oral dose of 1000 mg/kg resulted in the death of 1 out of 10 mice while in rats there were no adverse effects at this dose. An IV single dose of 50 mg/kg in mice resulted in early death in 1 of 10 mice. No IV single dose toxicity was performed in rats due to intolerance to the vehicle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repeat dose toxicity</head><p>Repeat dose toxicity studies were performed in rats (up to 6 months) and in dogs (up to 9 months) using the oral route. In addition, repeat dose toxicity studies up to 14 days IV dosing were performed in rats and dogs.</p><p>Dose-limiting toxicities in 1, 6 and 9 month studies included gastrointestinal effects in dogs, and skin and hepatotoxicity in rats. As a result of such toxicity, exposures in the toxicity studies in most cases did not reach margins of clinical exposure.</p><p>Key findings in the repeat dose toxicity studies included adverse signs (emesis, loose faeces/diarrhoea), hepatobiliary toxicity, dysplasia of teeth and epiphysial growth plate, folliculitis of the skin, renal papillary necrosis, phospholipidosis in variety of tissues and haematological effects and ovarian atrophy. These findings were generally in accordance with what would be expected from an inhibition of VEGFR and EGFR signalling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Genotoxicity</head><p>Vandetanib was evaluated over a range of concentrations between 5 and 5000 μg/plate using 4 strains of Salmonella typhimurium (TA1535, TA1537, TA98 and TA100) and 2 strains of Escherichia coli (WP2P and WP2 uvrA), in the presence and absence of a rat liver-derived metabolic activation system (S9mix). Vandetanib showed no mutagenic potential. Vandetanib was not clastogenic to cultured human lymphocytes.</p><p>Vandetanib did not increase the incidence of micronucleated polychromatic erythrocytes in the bone marrow of male rats when administered as a single oral dose of up to 1000 mg/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carcinogenicity</head><p>No carcinogenicity studies have been submitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reproduction Toxicity</head><p>The reproductive toxicity of Vandetanib was investigated in a series of studies to assess embryofoetal toxicity, male and female fertility as well as pre and post-natal development.</p><p>Vandetanib significantly affected all stages of female reproduction in rats. A decrease in the number of corpora lutea was observed in the ovaries of rats dosed at 75 mg/kg/day in the 1 month toxicology study. In the absence of maternal toxicity in a female fertility study, there was a trend towards increased oestrus cycle irregularity in animals dosed at 10 or 25 mg/kg/day. A dose-related increase in early intra-uterine deaths, resulting in a reduced number of live embryos and increased post-implantation loss, was observed at 10 and 25 mg/kg/day. Following a 4 week withdrawal period there were no effects on oestrus cycles, pre-or post-implantation losses, or on the number of lives embryos.</p><p>In the embryofetal development study in rats, heart vessel abnormalities (aortic arch interrupted or right sided, subclavian artery arising from ductus arteriosus or pulmonary arch; subclavian artery retro-oesophageal; innominate artery absent) and precocious ossification of some skull bones were observed at 25 mg/kg/day. Heart vessel abnormalities were observed also at lower doses (10 mg/kg/day and 1 mg/kg/day) and a no-effect level was not established.</p><p>In a rat pre-and post-natal development study, an increase in pre-birth loss was observed at 10 mg/kg/day. Reduced post-natal pup growth was observed in all treated groups. There were no effects on behavioural tests, mating performance, fertility and gestation of the F1 generation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicokinetic data</head><p>Toxicokinetic data was submitted for repeat dosing in rats and dogs.</p><p>Total steady state AUC 0-24 after 100 mg/day (~1.43 mg/kg/day) dosing in humans (7530 ng.h/ml) was similar to that achieved at the highest oral dose level (10 mg/kg/day) in the rat 6 month study (8114 ng.h/ml) and ~3-fold higher than that achieved at the high dose, 15 mg/kg/day, in the 9 month dog study (2273 ng.h/ml).</p><p>Steady state AUC 0-24 after 300 mg/day dosing, 18782 ng.h /ml, was consequently higher than those determined in the 6 and 9 month studies.</p><p>In the 6 months study in the rat, at the NOAEL (1 mg/kg/day), animals were 23.5 times less exposed (799 ng.h /ml) than human at 300 mg/day (18782 ng.h /ml). In the 9 months study in the dog at 5 mg/kg/day, animals are 18 times less exposed (1 035 ng.h /ml) than human at 300 mg/day (18782 ng.h /ml).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Local Tolerance</head><p>No local tolerance studies have been submitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other toxicity studies</head><p>Phototoxicity Vandetanib absorbs light in the wavelength of 290-700 nm and a phototoxic potential of Vandetanib was demonstrated in an in vitro cytotoxicity assay.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impurities</head><p>A control strategy was developed. Some impurities (BNAN, Aminodibenzyl, Vandetanib 4-Amino MA and 2, 4-Dibromo-6-fluoroaniline) were considered as not to be genotoxic; however, assays are not in compliance to international guidelines. For the other impurities, no assays were available (Vandetanib N-Formyl and Vandetanib t-Butyl). No environmental risk has been identified as a consequence of the use of Vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.5.">Ecotoxicity/environmental risk assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.6.">Discussion on non-clinical aspects</head><p>Vandetanib is a potent inhibitor of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor-2 (VEGFR-2 also known as kinase insert domain containing receptor [KDR]), epidermal growth factor receptor (EGFR) and</p><p>Rearranged during Transfection (RET) tyrosine kinases. Vandetanib is also a sub-micromolar inhibitor of vascular endothelial receptor-3 tyrosine kinase.</p><p>Vandetanib inhibits VEGF-stimulated endothelial cell migration, proliferation, and survival and new blood vessel formation in in vitro models of angiogenesis. In addition, vandetanib inhibits epidermal growth factor (EGF) -stimulated EGF receptor tyrosine kinase in tumour cells and endothelial cells.</p><p>Vandetanib inhibits EGFR-dependent cell proliferation and cell survival in vitro. Vandetanib also inhibits both wild type and the majorities of mutated, activated forms of RET, and significantly inhibits the proliferation of medullary thyroid tumour (MTC) cell lines in vitro.</p><p>In vivo vandetanib administration reduced tumour cell-induced angiogenesis, tumour vessel permeability, tumour microvessel density, and inhibited tumour growth of a range of human xenograft tumour models in athymic mice. Vandetanib also inhibited the growth of MTC xenograft tumours in vivo.The precise mechanism of action of vandetanib in locally advanced or metastatic MTC is unknown</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.7.">Conclusion on the non-clinical aspects</head><p>Vandetanib has shown no mutagenic or clastogenic potential.</p><p>In repeat-dose toxicity studies of up to 9 months duration, effects included emesis, body weight loss and diarrhoea in dogs and physeal dysplasia in young dogs and rats with open growth plates. In rats, effects on teeth, kidney and skin were noted. These findings occurred at clinically-relevant plasma concentrations, were largely reversible within 4 weeks of cessation of dosing and were attributable to inhibition of vascular endothelial growth factor receptor (VEGFR) or EGFR.</p><p>Effects noted in other studies included inhibition of human ether-a-go-go related gene (hERG) current and prolongation of QTc interval in dogs. Elevation of systolic and diastolic blood pressure were observed in rats and dogs. In mice, vandetanib was shown to delay but not prevent wound healing.</p><p>Vandetanib also showed evidence of phototoxic potential in an in vitro cytotoxicity assay. In an animal model of wound-healing, mice dosed with vandetanib had reduced skin-breaking strength compared with controls. This suggests that vandetanib slows but does not prevent wound healing. The appropriate interval between discontinuation of vandetanib and subsequent elective surgery required to avoid the risks of impaired wound healing has not been determined. In clinical studies, a small number of patients had surgery while receiving vandetanib and there were no reported wound healing complications.</p><p>Vandetanib had no effect on fertility in male rats. In a female fertility study, there was a trend towards increased oestrus cycle irregularity, a slight reduction in pregnancy incidence and increase in implantation loss. In a repeat-dose toxicity study in rats, there was a decrease in the number of corpora lutea in the ovaries of rats given vandetanib for 1 month.</p><p>In rats, embryofoetal toxicity was evident as foetal loss, delayed foetal development, heart vessel abnormalities and precocious ossification of some skull bones. In a rat pre-and post-natal development study, at doses producing maternal toxicity during gestation and/or lactation, vandetanib increased pre-birth loss and reduced post-natal pup growth. Vandetanib was excreted into milk in rat and found in plasma of pups following dosing to lactating rats.</p><p>As the development of vandetanib was performed only by oral route, which is the clinical route of administration, no specific local tolerance studies were performed. In line with ICH S9, no carcinogenicity studies have been conducted.</p><p>Based on the review of the data on non clinical aspect, the CHMP considers that the application is approvable and requested the inclusion of the following statements in section 4.6 of the SmPC:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>Women of childbearing potential must use effective contraception during therapy and for at least four months following the last dose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>There is a limited amount of data on the use of vandetanib during pregnancy. Vandetanib has shown significant effects on all stages of female reproduction in rats. If vandetanib is used during pregnancy or if the patient becomes pregnant while receiving vandetanib, she should be apprised of the potential for foetal abnormalities or loss of the pregnancy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>There are no data on the use of vandetanib in breast-feeding women. Vandetanib and/or its metabolites is excreted into milk in rats and found in plasma of pups following dosing to lactating rats. Breast-feeding is contraindicated while receiving vandetanib therapy (section 4.3 and 4.6 of the SmPC).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1.">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GCP</head><p>The Clinical trials were performed in accordance with GCP as claimed by the applicant.</p><p>The Applicant has provided a statement to the effect that clinical trials conducted outside the community were carried out in accordance with the ethical standards of Directive 2001/20/EC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>The clinical pharmacokinetic documentation consists of 16 phase I studies, 3 phase II studies and 3 phase III studies. The main features of these studies are summarised in the table below. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1240/1237</head><p>Patients with locally-advanced or metastatic NSCLC after failure of at least 1 prior cytotoxic chemotherapy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method of analysis</head><p>All assays used to analyse vandetanib in plasma employed LC-MS/MS detection. Assays were also validated for vandetanib and metabolites in plasma, urine and plasma ultra-filtrate (PUF).</p><p>The calibration range for vandetanib in plasma was generally 5-1000 ng/mL, and for the metabolites 1-200 ng/mL, however, there were considerable variations between methods. The calibration range in urine was 100-50000 ng/mL and in PUF 1-200 ng/mL.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Absorption</head><p>The PK parameters after single and repeated dosing of vandetanib are presented in the table below. a) n = 9 for C ss, max and t max only, b) determined from the population analysis, c) V dist mean population value, R ac =Accumulation ratio (index)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioavailability</head><p>No studies have been submitted with intravenous administration of vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bioequivalence</head><p>A number of formulations have been utilised throughout the clinical development of vandetanib. The commercial tablet formulation has been used in some Phase II studies and in all Phase III studies. No significant difference has been detected between the Phase I, IIa and III formulations. Alterations in particle size, process and formulation did not translate into relevant changes in exposure. Moreover, the similar concentration profile of the solution and the different tablet formulations indicate that the absorption pattern of vandetanib is not dependent on dissolution, and therefore the formulation has little impact.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Influence of food</head><p>Vandetanib rate and extent of absorption did not significantly change when taken with a high-fat breakfast (data not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution</head><p>The volume of distribution has not been determined in humans as no intravenous formulation has been developed. In patients, vandetanib was approximately 93% bound to plasma proteins; both albumin and α-1-acid-glycoprotein bind to vandetanib. The plasma protein binding of the N-desmethyl metabolite is similar as for vandetanib, and the binding of the N-oxide metabolite could not be determined due to analytical difficulties. Although the bioavailability of vandetanib is not known, the Vss/F indicates immense distribution into tissues, which is also confirmed in preclinical studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Metabolism</head><p>The metabolism of 14C-vandetinib was investigated in 4 healthy volunteers (Study 25) following a single oral dose of 800 mg. Vandetanib represented 80% of the circulating radioactivity during the first day but this declined slowly with time. Due to the low radiochemical dose, long half-life of vandetanib and high volume of distribution, concentrations of radioactive material were low in plasma, urine and faeces. Using qualitative LC-MS, unchanged vandetanib and 2 known metabolites (vandetanib N-oxide and N-desmethyl vandetanib) were detected in plasma. N-desmethyl-vandetanib was found to be the major circulating metabolite of vandetanib; relative to vandetanib, the exposure to N-desmethylvandetanib was ~10 % and for N-oxide-vandetanib the exposure relative to vandetanib was &lt;2% (studies 16, 22 and 26). The same metabolites were found in both urine and faeces, where an additional minor metabolite was also present. This was shown by mass spectroscopy to be a glucuronide conjugate. Using TLC, the ratio of vandetanib: N-desmethyl vandetanib excreted in faeces was estimated 5:1.</p><p>Vandetanib is not a substrate for P-gp, BCRP, MRP1 or OCT2. Vandetanib was found to be a weak inhibitor of P-gp and BCRP, although at concentrations higher than what are expected in plasma.</p><p>Vandetanib is also an inhibitor of OCT2, a transporter involved in the excretion of creatinine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Elimination</head><p>Plasma clearance has not been determined in humans as no intravenous formulation has been developed. CL/F is approximately 10 L/h, although highly variable.</p><p>The elimination has not been fully elucidated, and no metabolite profiling was performed in the human mass balance study. Clearance of vandetanib occurs by metabolism and excretion in urine and faeces of unchanged vandetanib. Total recovery of radioactivity was 69% after 21 days and was still ongoing, which is caused by the slow elimination of vandetanib, and twice as much radioactivity was excreted in the faeces (44%) compared to urinary (25%) excretion. Qualitative measurements identified Ndesmethyl-vandetanib and vandetanib-N-oxide in plasma as well as in urine and faeces. In urine, a glucorinide conjugate was also found. No quantitative results of the concentrations of the metabolites and parent compound in plasma, urine and faeces could be provided from the mass balance study, which is considered a deficiency. However, due to the long half-life of vandetanib, only a low dose of radioactive material could be given, and thereby the concentration levels of the metabolites were too low for characterization. The approach to search for the N-desmethyl and N-oxide metabolites was based on data from mass balance studies in the pre-clinical program.</p><p>Urine concentrations were determined in a healthy volunteer study, indicating that less than 5% is excreted in urine as unchanged drug over the first 72 h. This indicates that renal excretion is not the major route of elimination. Rather, the amount excreted unchanged in urine, in combination with the large proportion radioactive material found in faeces indicated that metabolism and biliary excretion are likely important mechanisms for vandetanib elimination.</p><p>A long terminal elimination half-life (8-19 days) was observed in both single and multiple-dose studies, and is consistent with the low clearance (8.7L/h) of vandetanib. Longer half life is estimated in the target patient population (MTC) with a mean T1/2 of approximately 20 days (4-85 days). Such discrepancy is not clearly explained. The mean CL/F was approximately 10-13 L/h across studies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetics of Metabolites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose proportionality and time dependency</head><p>In healthy volunteers, the pharmacokinetics seemed to be independent of dose over the dose range 300-1200 mg single doses. There was no clear indication of non-proportionality in exposure in patients receiving 50 -600 mg, or in patients receiving 100 mg every other day or 100 -300 mg daily, although there were a limited number of patients in several of the dose groups. Also, the variability in exposure between patients was high, which could possibly mask a dose dependency. The pharmacokinetics of vandetanib seemed to be independent of time. In the population pharmacokinetics models, the estimates of the inter-individual variability were approximately 40% for CL/F and 50% for Vc/F. 300 mg was selected as the dose with which to begin treatment in clinical studies. The rationale for the using the 300 mg dose was based primarily on: (1) preclinical data, which demonstrated that the greatest benefit (in terms of maximizing inhibition against key targets) is seen when vandetanib is used at the maximum tolerated dose (MTD), <ref type="formula">(2)</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Intra-and Inter-individual variability</head><p>The intra-subject variability following single oral dose of 300 mg vandetanib tablet under both fed and fasted conditions was assessed in 15 healthy volunteers using a replicate design (Study 24). Intrasubject variability in exposure to vandetanib was found to be small; the overall estimate for intrasubject variability was 8% for AUC and 11% for Cmax. In phase I studies inter-subject variability was typically approximately 30%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetics in target population</head><p>Pharmacokinetics of vandetanib in patients with MTC was evaluated by popPK analyses. The results are summarized in the table below. The PK parameter estimates between patients and healthy volunteers do not indicate large PK differences between patients and healthy volunteers. Estimated elimination half-life (~18 days) was longer in phase 3 popPK analysis than in the phase I studies (~ 8 days), in which elimination half-life was determined after single dose administration. Data across studies are comparable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Special Populations</head><p>Population pharmacokinetic analysis predicted weight as covariates of vandetanib clearance and volume of distribution. The mean estimated clearance for median weight (68 kg) was 13.2 ± 0.306 L.h-1. A steady-state AUC on Day 56 of 13.75 μg.h/mL (27% lower than the median of all subjects that received 300 mg up to Day 56) is estimated for the heaviest patient with a body weight of 125 kg.</p><p>This exposure is greater than the threshold for a probability of stable disease to be 50% (7.05 μg.h/mL) as estimated by the response analysis. The estimated weight effect is, however, modest and no dose adjustment for weight is necessary.</p><p>Pharmacokinetics of vandetanib was not different in Caucasian and Oriental patients (Studies 01, 43, 04, 58). Gender and age (Study 58) had no effect on the pharmacokinetics of vandetanib.</p><p>Pharmacokinetics of vandetanib has not been studied in children.</p><p>A study in renally impaired subjects indicated a clear trend towards higher exposure with decreased renal function. Unbound vandetanib concentrations were on average 16%, 46% and 57% higher in subjects with mild, moderate and severe renal impairment. Adequate recommendations have been introduced in the SmPC regarding the use of vandetanib (not recommended) in patients with moderate or severe renal insufficiency for whom very limited data are available with the proposed 300 mg dose (and none with other doses) in patients with MTC.</p><p>In a study with hepatically impaired patients without tumours in the liver, there was no increase in AUC or C max in patients with mild, moderate or severe hepatic impairment, but rather a slight decrease. The AUC and C max of the N-desmethyl metabolite were decreased in hepatic impairment, while the AUC and C max of the N-oxide were increased.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetic Interaction Studies</head><p>The effect of inhibition of CYP3A4 by itraconazole was assessed in healthy volunteers in Study 15. The 9% increase in exposure (AUC0-504h) was not considered to be clinically meaningful.</p><p>The effect of induction of CYP3A4 by rifampicin was assessed in healthy volunteers in Study 26. The estimate of the treatment ratio for vandetanib AUC0-504h indicates a statistically significant 39.9% reduction, when taken in combination with rifampicin, compared with vandetanib alone. The presence or absence of rifampicin did not significantly influence the Cmax.</p><p>The metabolite formed by CYP3A4 metabolism has been identified as N-desmethylvandetanib and consistent with induction of CYP3A4, there was a 266% increase in the exposure (AUC) to this metabolite when vandetanib was, in combination with rifampicin compared to vandetanib alone and the exposure relative to vandetanib increased from about 7% to 43%. Levels of vandetanib-N-oxide were low and did not allow the determination of the AUC0-504h. However, compared with vandetanib alone, the AUC determined to a common time t increased by about 100% and Cmax by about 175% when vandetanib was given in combination with rifampicin and the exposure relative to vandetanib showed a small increase from approximately 1.5% to approximately 2%.</p><p>Vandetanib exhibit pH dependent solubility: high solubility at low pH and low solubility at neutral pH.</p><p>At pH 6.8 solubility of vandetanib is 0.35 mg/ml. No further data on vandetanib solubility has been submitted at different pH and notably under a value of 6.8. As proton-pump inhibitors and H2antihistamines increase gastric pH until 5-6, one cannot exclude that this solubility could be affected.</p><p>S-warfarin (the pharmacologically more active enantiomer) is metabolized by CYP2C9 and R-warfarin is metabolized principally by CYP1A2 and to a lesser degree by CYP3A4. Vandetanib has been shown to have a moderate potential to inhibit these iso-enzymes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetics using human biomaterials</head><p>See Non-clinical pharmacokinetic drug interactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3.">Pharmacodynamics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanism of action</head><p>The role of vandetanib as a selective inhibitor of VEGF, EGFR and RET has been described in the nonclinical section of this report. In addition to this, clinical studies supporting the involvement of VEGFR and EGFR in the anti-cancer activity of vandetanib are described in the primary pharmacology section below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary and Secondary Pharmacology</head><p>See Secondary Endpoints, Pharmacodynamic parameters pertinent for activity in the MTC setting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.4.">Discussion on clinical pharmacology</head><p>There is a scientific rationale in MTC for vandetanib which targets two separate aspects of cancer by directly inhibiting EGFR and/or RET dependent tumour growth and indirectly inhibiting tumour growth through antiangiogenic effects on endothelial cell proliferation, migration and survival.</p><p>The long half-life of vandetanib is unfavourable for a drug which is to be dose adjusted based on adverse events, especially with regard to serious concerns about the safety profile, including marked QT prolongation (and clinical consequences) and potential deterioration of renal function, as high concentrations will remain for months after cessation of the drug. Conventional studies and popPK analysis indicated a low intra-and moderate to high inter-subject variability of vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.5.">Conclusions on clinical pharmacology</head><p>Pharmacokinetics of vandetanib and metabolites have been adequately investigated. Following single oral dose of vandetanib absorption appeared to be relatively slow with Cmax achieved at a median Tmax of 6 h and vandetanib is slowly cleared from the plasma (8.7 L/h) and is characterised by a long plasma half-life of 8-18 days. Consistent with the long half-life, once daily oral administration of 100 mg or 300 mg resulted in approximately 10-fold accumulation from single dose to steady-state levels.</p><p>A pharmacokinetic study in volunteers with mild, moderate and severe renal impairment shows that exposure to vandetanib after single dose is increased up to 1.5, 1.6 and 2-fold respectively in patients with mild, moderate (creatinine clearance ≥ 30 to &lt; 50 ml/min) and severe (clearance below 30 l/min) renal impairment at baseline (see section 5.2 of the SmPC). Clinical data suggest that no change in starting dose is required in patients with mild renal impairment. There is limited data with 300 mg in patients with moderate renal impairment: discontinuation for AEs in 5/6 pts. The starting dose could be reduced to 200 mg in patients with moderate renal impairment; safety and efficacy have however not been established with 200 mg (see section 4.4 of the SmPC). Vandetanib is not recommended for use in patients with severe renal impairment since there is limited data in patients with severe renal impairment, and safety and efficacy have not been established.</p><p>Vandetanib is a weak inhibitor of the efflux pump P-gp. The co-administration of vandetanib and drugs excreted by P-gp, such as digoxin, may result in increased plasma concentrations of these drugs.</p><p>Patients receiving digoxin and vandetanib may require increased digoxin blood level monitoring and appropriate dosage adjustments. The applicant has planned to study the interaction between vandetanib and digoxin further.</p><p>Vandetanib is an inhibitor of the OCT2 transporter. Therefore, vandetanib may have the potential to decrease the elimination of drugs known to be excreted by OCT2 and to increase a patient's exposure to these drugs. Metformin is a substrate of OCT2; patients who are receiving vandetanib and metformin (or other substrates of OCT2) may require more careful monitoring and possible dose adjustment of metformin. The applicant has planned to study the interaction between vandetanib and metformin further.</p><p>The effect of proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists on the gastrointestinal absorption of vandetanib has not been determined. Vandetanib demonstrates pH-dependent solubility; therefore, the co-administration of vandetanib with proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists may reduce a patient's exposure to vandetanib. The concomitant use with these therapeutic classes is therefore not recommended (see section 4.4 of the SmPC)</p><p>The co-administration of vandetanib with proton pump inhibitors and H2 antagonists may reduce a patient's exposure to vandetanib. Therefore, the applicant has planned to study this interaction further.</p><p>Vandetanib has the potential to induce the CYP3A4 enzyme system. Co-administration of vandetanib and drugs primarily metabolised by the CYP3A4 enzyme system may result in decreased plasma concentrations of these drugs that could reduce or shorten therapeutic effects. Therefore, appropriate dosage adjustments may be required. The applicant has planned to study the interaction between vandetanib and midazolam further.</p><p>The above mentioned drug-drug interaction studies are covered in the RMP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Clinical efficacy</head><p>The clinical efficacy submission in MTC is based on one pivotal study (Study 58) with vandetanib 300 mg daily and is supported by two phase II uncontrolled studies performed with different dose regimen 100 mg (study 068) and 300 mg daily (study 008) in patients with MTC.  The ORR was 20.0% (6/30) (complete (CR) or partial response (PR) based on primary site-read assessment based on RECIST). By independent assessment there were 5 (16.7%) of patients who had an OR (modified RECIST criteria). Median PFS was 27.9 months. The median duration of response (DOR) from first response until progression or death was 10.2 months, and from first dose until progression or death was 18.5 months. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D4200C00068</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Participants</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Inclusion criteria</head><p>Patients had to fulfil all of the following criteria for inclusion in the study: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample size</head><p>Assuming 2:1 randomisation (vandetanib: placebo), to detect a doubling of PFS at the 2-sided alpha= .050 level with 80% power, at least 90 events were required. Assuming a median PFS of 12 months in the control group, a non-linear recruitment period of 22 months, and a minimum follow-up of 6.7 months, at least 232 patients were to be recruited for the study, i.e., the total length of the study was estimated to be 28.7 months to observe 90 progression events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomisation</head><p>Eligible subjects were to be randomized strictly sequentially in a 2:1 ratio.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blinding (masking)</head><p>The study was double-blind.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary endpoint analysis</head><p>The primary analysis was based on an ITT analysis of PFS data derived from all available modified RECIST assessments, which included any available information on central read RECIST scans performed whilst on randomised treatment, after discontinuation of randomised treatment and after</p><p>first dose of open label treatment.</p><p>A log-rank test was planned for the primary analysis of PFS (unadjusted model with treatment factor only).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant flow</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruitment</head><p>The study <ref type="formula">(</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conduct of the study</head><p>There were 7 amendments of the study protocol that occurred for 5 of them after the last patient was enrolled (data not shown). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numbers analysed</head><p>A total of 331 patients were randomised to receive treatment in this study (231 in the vandetanib arm and 100 in the placebo arm) and were included in the Full Analysis Set. One patient randomised to receive placebo never received any study treatment, therefore, the safety analysis set included 330 patients.  The median PFS in the placebo group was 19.3 months. The median PFS in the vandetanib group could not be calculated (because of an insufficient number of PFS events); a Weibull model was used to estimate the median PFS in the 2 treatment arms: the predicted median PFS for the vandetanib arm is 30.5 months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Kaplan-Meier curves for the comparison of time to PFS</head><p>Sensitivity analyses for PFS Cox proportional hazard regression model is adjusted for treatment and baseline covariates. c Whitehead method used to assess the impact of a differential frequency of assessments in the treatment arms. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subgroup analyses on the primary endpoint</head><p>The following subgroup analyses, pre-specified prior to unblinding, were performed using a log rank test with treatment as the only factor: Forest plots are presented below ( for pre-specified RET mutation status, CTN doubling time, CEA doubling time, p-VEGF at baseline, p-VEGFR2 at baseline and p-bFGF at baseline these primary pharmacology) .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: Subgroup analyses for PFS -Baseline characteristics and disease status (ITT)</head><p>PFS was derived from all available central read RECIST assessments. Prior therapy refers to systemic anti-cancer therapy for MTC taken prior to the first dose of randomised treatment. A response to prior therapy is defined as a BOR of CR or PR to the most recent prior therapy. No response to prior therapy is defined as a BOR of SD or PD to the most recent prior therapy.</p><p>The superiority of vandetanib over placebo is consistent across all pre planned subgroups, even if not significant in all of them. No HR is greater than 1.</p><p>Most patients (all but 18 patients) had either progressive disease or symptoms at baseline (12 patients without progression and without symptoms and 6 patients with unknown progressive status and without symptoms); 25 patients were only symptomatic; 64 patients had only progressive disease; 186 patients had symptomatic and progressive disease. 307 patients were known to be progressive or symptomatic.  There was an improvement in weight in the vandetanib arm compared to the placebo arm [28.6% vs.</p><p>11%, OR 3.24, 95% CI 1.69 to 6.76, p=0.0003].</p><p>Pharmacodynamic parameters pertinent for activity in the MTC setting Data from Study 58 are described in the figure below with regard to effect of vandetanib on biochemical response rate (CTN and CEA), according to RET status and other biomarkers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 5. Study 58/subgroup analyses for PFS -Biomarkers (ITT)</head><p>High p-VEGF &gt; 55.0 pg/ml at baseline. Low p-VEGF &lt;= 55.0 pg/ml at baseline. High p-VEGFR2 &gt; 9.88165 pg/ml at baseline. Low p-VEGFR2 &lt;= 9.88165 pg/ml at baseline. High p-bFGF &gt; 2.10 pg/ml at baseline. Low p-bFGF &lt;= 2.10 pg/ml at baseline.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RET mutation status</head><p>RET mutation status was determined by sequencing the 6 most commonly mutated exons in MTC <ref type="bibr">(10, 11, 13, 14, 15, and 16</ref>) and by evaluating for the M918T mutation using an amplification refractory mutation system (ARMS) analysis as there is no standard or routine practices for how to test for somatic RET mutations in the tumours of patients with advanced MTC.</p><p>A RET positive mutation status was defined as having a mutation either observed from the sequencing or ARMS assay. RET mutation negative status was defined as having the sequencing assay successfully showing wild type sequence at all 6 exons, and the ARMS assay negative for a M918T mutation.</p><p>Unknown RET mutation status was documented when 1 or more sequencing assay was unsuccessful (non-informative), and none of the successful assays demonstrated a mutation.  Following a post-hoc analysis, efficacy endpoints were studied for seventy nine patients. These patients were identified as without M918T mutation and with no other RET mutation (71 patients with sporadic MTC previously classified as RET mutation "unknown" and 8 patients with sporadic MTC previously classified as RET mutation "negative "). Forty six patients were randomised to vandetanib and 33 patients to placebo. CEA and CTN doubling times and tumor size have been linked to the rate of objective progression in MTC. HR for PFS was in favour of vandetanib in patients with tumor size &lt;10 cm and ≥ 10 cm, but seems somewhat better in patients with the largest tumors≥ 10 cm.</p><p>A significant effect on PFS was demonstrated in patients with tumor size ≥ 10 cm at baseline but not in patients with tumor size &lt;10 cm .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of main study</head><p>The following tables summarise the efficacy results from the main studies supporting the present application. These summaries should be read in conjunction with the discussion on clinical efficacy as well as the benefit risk assessment (see later sections). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis performed across trials (pooled analyses and meta-analysis)</head><p>No analyses performed across trials were submitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical studies in special populations</head><p>Preliminary dose-finding and safety results of Study 79 in 6 paediatric patients with hereditary MTC were reported, with objective response in 5 patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supportive studies</head><p>Preliminary results of a phase II, placebo controlled randomised study (study 79) of vandetanib 300 mg in 145 patients with locally advanced or metastatic papillary or follicular thyroid carcinoma failing or unsuitable for radioiodine therapy found a HR of 0.62 (0.43,0.92), p=0.017 on the primary endpoint PFS without any significant difference on the secondary endpoints.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.3.">Discussion on clinical efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design and conduct of clinical studies</head><p>The clinical efficacy in the present submission is based on a pivotal study (Study 58) with vandetanib 300 mg daily. Study 58 was a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study comparing the efficacy and safety of vandetanib versus placebo in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic MTC.</p><p>The primary objective of this study was to demonstrate an improvement in progression-free survival (PFS) with vandetanib as compared to placebo in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic MTC. A total of 331 patients were randomized (2:1) to receive vandetanib 300 mg once daily (231 patients) or placebo (100 patients).</p><p>There was no substantial imbalance between treatment arms with respect to demographic and baseline Following the SAG's advice, the indication was revised to include aggressive and symptomatic disease.</p><p>The choice of 'aggressive' instead of 'progressive' was justified by the fact that the term of "progressive" remains ambiguous (RECIST progression as in the primary criteria or including clinical, RX and biological criteria) and the term "aggressive" is likely to address patients condition with rapid deterioration, for whom an urgent treatment is required.</p><p>Only 6 patients with moderate renal failure were randomised to vandetanib (1 with severe renal impairment, NI criteria). These 6 patients were initially treated with 300 mg but the dose was reduced for AEs in 5/6 patients to 200 mg and further to 100 mg in 1 patients. The safe and effective dose in patients with moderate or severe renal failure has not been established (see sections 4.2 and 4.4 of the SmPC).</p><p>At present optimal duration of treatment remains unclear and should be left to the clinical evaluation and decision of the treating physician. A dose-finding study analyzing the safety and activity of 150mg vs 300mg due to be completed in July 2014 will address this issue (see section on Pharmacovigilance).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RET mutation status</head><p>The activity of vandetanib in RET mutation negative patients is indirectly supported by the activity of the drug observed in the subgroup of 138 patients in Study 58 whose RET status could not be successfully established. In the vandetanib arm, PFS at 12 months for this subgroup of patients was 27.2 % compared to 34.3 % in patients with RET + status.</p><p>In a post-hoc analysis, further data from 71 patients previously classified as RET mutation "unknown"</p><p>and 8 patients previously classified as RET mutation "negative" showed efficacy (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 12</ref>) Therefore, the available evidence suggests but does not fully confirm efficacy of vandetanib in RET negative tumours.</p><p>Moreover, it is not certain that those patients tested RET negative in the post-hoc analysis are not positive for mutation on other exons. It is equally not certain that those patients tested RET negative from old tumour sample were still RET negative at the time of initiation of treatment. Therefore, it is difficult to draw an unequivocal conclusion of the size of the benefit of vandetanib in patients with RET mutation negative tumours.</p><p>Given that the precise mechanism of action of vandetanib in RET remains unclear, the absolute benefit in these patients should be more precisely/directly determined. A conditional marketing authorisation was thus recommended, taking into consideration that the risk-benefit balance of vandetanib, as defined in Article 1(28a) of Directive 2001/83/EC, is positive, to gather the missing information.</p><p>In the framework of the conditional marketing authorisation,, given the need to confirm the benefit risk balance in RET negative patients, the following statements were included in the Product Information: A post-hoc subgroup analysis of RET negative status based on absence of M918T mutation of the pivotal study 58 was performed. A patient was considered to have a RET mutation if either an M918T mutation by the ARMS assay, or a RET mutation in any exons sequenced was present in the tumour. Actually 79 patients were identified by absence of an M918T mutation and no RET mutation identified at any of the other 6 exons tested but in 71 of such patients sequencing of the 6 exons was incomplete. M918T mutation is the most frequent mutation observed inpatients with sporadic MTC; however it cannot be ruled out that some patients tested RET negative for M918T mutation might be positive for mutation on other exons.</p><p>Results according to RET status (positive, unknown and RET M918T mutation negative definition) are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_6">Table 3</ref>, Section 5.1 of the SmPC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>The SmPc and Package Leaflet have also been amended, referring to the medicinal product as having been authorized under the conditional approval scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional expert consultation</head><p>The SAG was requested to define the restricted population of patients in whom the absolute benefit in terms of progression prevention would compensate for the overall safety profile of vandetanib and to comment on whether other possible methods as FISH or RNA studies would be more sensitive and specific to determine RET status.</p><p>In view of the associated risks, the SAG considered that it was important to limit treatment with vandetanib to patients who are in real need for treatment. This can be established based on clinical and biological criteria. From a clinical point of view, this corresponds to patients that can be identified as having a symptomatic-aggressive course of the disease. Either symptomatic disease or progressive disease alone is not enough to prompt the need for treatment with vandetanib. Rate of change in biomarker levels such as of calcitonin and/or CEA as well as the rate of change of tumour volume during watchful waiting might help to identify not only patients in need for treatment but also the optimal moment to commence the treatment. Similarly, imaging data alone is not expected to be useful in identifying patients in need for treatment. From a biological point of view, the efficacy of vandetanib has been established only in patients with RET mutation-positive tumours. The efficacy is unknown in RET mutation-negative tumours. Further studies are needed, using biopsy material in the metastatic setting, to study the effect in RET mutation-negative tumours and to clarify the exact mechanism of action of the drug.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional efficacy data needed in the context of a conditional MA</head><p>Current evidence supports the use of vandetanib in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic medullary thyroid cancer. However, from a quantitative point of view, the specific benefit in RET -MTC patients might be less as compared with what was observed in RET+ MTC tumours.</p><p>Therefore, based on the available evidence, there is a need to further investigate any quantitative differences in terms of efficacy in RET negative patients with vandetanib that are not known at present.</p><p>As a result, the CHMP considered the following measure necessary to address the missing clinical data in the context of a conditional MA:</p><p>A non-randomised study of vandetanib in patients with sporadic medullary thyroid cancer with known RET mutation status to include 60% of patients who receive vandetanib in the CHMP approved indication within the EU. Patients will be followed for 2 years and an interim analysis will be presented 12 months after first inclusion. Data will be collected and analyzed at pre-specified times.</p><p>The inclusion criteria will be based on the SmPC indication, sporadic medullary thyroid cancer and known RET mutation status. RET mutation negative patients who do not receive vandetanib due to RET status or contraindication should also be to enrolled and followed in order to have a control group for patients with RET negative status. Exclusion criteria should be limited as much as possible to contraindications outlined in section 4.3 of the SmPC.</p><p>Patients will not be required to have a fresh tissue biopsy to determine RET status before enrolment.</p><p>However RET status must be determined and a recent determination of such status should be obtained as often as possible even in patients previously tested at an earlier stage of their disease.</p><p>Determination of RET status should be made preferably just prior to the initiation of treatment. Tissue type used for assay, date of tissue biopsy, assay type and definition used for RET mutation positive and negative will be collected.</p><p>Efficacy endpoints will include ORR, DCR and PFS. The main analysis will compare efficacy parameters of vandetanib in RET mutation positive and RET mutation negative patients, with reference to the respective outcomes observed in RET mutation positive and RET mutation negative patients who do not receive treatment. Safety analyses will be determined for the overall population, RET mutation negative and RET mutation positive patients. At each visit, a safety assessment will be conducted including QT prolongation information.</p><p>Efficacy assessments will be performed at 3 month intervals. PFS hazard ratio will be calculated for RET mutation positive versus RET mutation negative patients. The magnitude of the hazard ratio should be interpreted in the context of the non-randomized grouping of patients by RET mutation status.</p><p>The final analysis will be performed when at least 40 patients identified with RET mutation and 40 patients identified without evidence of RET mutation have been enrolled into the study and received vandetanib for 14 months. The total duration of the study is expected to be 38 months.</p><p>The applicant confirmed that it would be able to provide the clinical data requested as part of the specific obligation, set out in section 4 Recommendations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.4.">Conclusions on the clinical efficacy</head><p>A randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study (Study 58) was conducted to demonstrate safety and efficacy of vandetanib 300 mg versus placebo. The result of the primary analysis of PFS showed a statistically significant improvement in PFS for patients randomized to vandetanib compared to placebo (Hazard Ratio (HR) = 0.46; 95% Confidence Interval (CI) = 0.31-0.69; p=0.0001).</p><p>The CHMP considers that an open label trial comparing RET negative and RET positive patients with sporadic medullary thyroid cancer treated with vandetanib, based on a CHMP approved protocol is necessary to address the missing efficacy data in the context of a conditional MA:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Clinical safety</head><p>The safety data submitted corresponds primarily to the safety analysis set in Study 58.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient exposure</head><p>The total estimated exposure to vandetanib (at all doses, and with concomitant chemotherapy as well as monotherapy) from clinical studies in healthy volunteers and patients is approximately 4000 patients. As of the data cut-off date of 19 October 2009, 1839 patients had received 300 mg vandetanib in the pooled monotherapy clinical studies: 274 patients for at least 1 year and 84 patients for at least 2 years.</p><p>In pivotal study 58, patients were randomised to receive vandetanib 300 mg or placebo, continuing on blinded treatment until objective disease progression. A total of 231 patients were treated with vandetanib 300 mg monotherapy and 99 patients received placebo in the randomised phase.</p><p>Upon disease progression, patients were discontinued from blinded study treatment and then  At the date of data cut-off, of the 231 patients randomised in vandetanib 300 mg arm, 162 patients had been treated with vandetanib for at least 12 months, and 51 patients had been treated for at least 24 months. A total of 49.4% had a dose reduction or interruption: while 30.3% remained on 300 mg, 35.1% were reduced to 200 mg, 0.9% reduced directly to 100 mg and 33.7% discontinued (22.0 % due to disease progression; 6.1% due to AE, without having a dose reduction; 5.6% for other reasons).</p><p>The reasons for discontinuation of randomised treatment were:</p><p>-AEs in 12.1% of vandetanib patients and 3.0% of placebo patients.</p><p>-Disease progression in 30.7% vandetanib patients versus 55.0% placebo patients.</p><p>While randomized placebo patients remained on placebo therapy for a median of 265 days:</p><p>-Patients who remained on initial 300 mg dose remained on therapy for a median of 339 days -Patients who had their dose reduced to 200 mg remained on therapy for a median of 502 days -Patients who had their dose reduced to 100 mg remained on therapy for a median of 545.5 days A summary of patients who had dose reductions and/or interruptions whilst on randomised treatment is provided below. Other 9 ( 3.9) 4 ( 4.0) 13 ( 3.9) A patient could have been dose reduced more than once, but was counted only once at each reduced dose. Reasons for dose reduction/interruption are not mutually exclusive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adverse events</head><p>During the randomized treatment phase (study 58), a total of 3149 AEs including 289 grade 3-4 AEs,  As assessed by the Investigator. c Any AE deemed by the sponsor to be significant. AEs that occurred at any time during study, excluding any AEs that occurred during or after open label treatment.</p><p>The following adverse reactions were identified during the randomized treatment phase of study 58  The following adverse reactions were identified in clinical studies with patients receiving vandetanib as treatment for medullary thyroid cancer. Vandetanib at a dose of 300 mg is associated with a substantial and concentration dependent prolongation in QTc (mean 28msec, median 35 msec). First QT prolongations occurred most often in the first 3 months of treatment, but continued to first occur after this time. The effect does not lessen over time. Prolonged QTc≥500msec was more frequent in female patients (75% versus 25% in male), and the frequency of QTc≥500msec was increased in subgroups of patients with hypertension (20%), diarrhoea (&gt;20%), serum Mg&lt;LLN (31.3%) and with baseline cardiac impairment (32.1%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Arrhythmia and QT prolonged AEs</head><p>There were 2 sudden deaths (in patients with QTc &gt;550 ms), and 4 suspected sudden deaths.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cardiac failure</head><p>One vandetanib patient had a Grade 1 AE of cardiac failure (following a grade 3 event of abnormal left ventricular function) and 1 patient had a Grade 5 SAE of cardiac failure acute during the randomised treatment period; no patients in the placebo arm reported these events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ischaemic heart disease</head><p>Ischaemic heart disease grouped events were reported in 2.2% vandetanib patients versus 2.0% in the placebo arm. In the vandetanib arm, 4 patients had events of grade 1 and 1 patient had an event of grade 3. Both patients in the placebo arm had grade 1 events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vascular disorders</head><p>A total of 39.0% vandetanib patients experienced an AE from the SOC Vascular disorders (vs 11.1% placebo patients).</p><p> Hypertension which is a common side effect was reported in 31.6% vandetanib patients (versus 5.1% placebo), including 8.7% patients with Grade ≥3 events of hypertension, hypertensive crisis (1.7%), or accelerated hypertension. Two patients (0.9%) discontinued due to AEs of hypertension (1 patient with Grade 4 and 1 with Grade 2 hypertension). The prevalence of hypertension, hypertensive crisis, or accelerated hypertension was approximately 20% for the vandetanib arm within 3 months of treatment and this appeared to increase slightly over time throughout Study 58. The median duration of hypertension, hypertensive crisis, or accelerated hypertension was 261.5 days for the vandetanib arm and 188 days for placebo. The upper quartile durations were 609.5 and 259 days, respectively.</p><p> Three (1.3%) patients, all in the vandetanib arm, had AEs of ischaemic cerebrovascular conditions, all of which were grade 3, while no patient in the placebo arm had these events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>Thromboembolic events were reported less frequently in the vandetanib arm than in the placebo arm (0.9% vs 4.0%). Both events in the vandetanib arm were grade 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nervous system disorders</head><p>A total of 256 AEs have been reported in 112 (48.5%) vandetanib patients. There were 16 reported AEs grade≥3 (2 headaches, 1 dizziness, 1 tremor, 1 disturbance in attention, 1 hyperesthesia, 1 motor dysfunction) and 9 SAEs: 1 brain edema, 1 cerebral ischemia, 1 peripheral sensorimotor neuropathy, 1 depressed level of consciousness, 2 loss of consciousness, 3 transient ischemic attacks).</p><p>In contrast, 40 AES have been reported in 32 placebo patients (32%): 4 AEs grade 3-4: 2 syncopes and 2 SAEs: 1 neuralgia, 1 hemiparesis. A total of 5 ischemic cerebrovascular events have been reported in vandetanib arm versus none in placebo. Cerebrovascular event is an identified risk in the safety database of vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Peripheral neurotoxicity</head><p>A total of 49 AEs related to paraesthesia, peripheral hypoesthesia, sensory neuropathy, neuropathy peripheral or tremor have been reported in vandetanib arm versus 9 AEs in placebo arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy</head><p>Headache was reported more frequently in 25.5% vandetanib patients compared with 9.1% placebo patients and was subsequent to elevated blood pressure. There were no reported cases of RPLS in patients receiving 300 mg monotherapy. However, a total of 4 cases of RPLS have occurred in the vandetanib programme. One case occurred in Study 32 in a patient who received vandetanib 100 mg daily in combination with chemotherapy for NSCLC. Two cases occurred in paediatric patients with primary brain tumours receiving vandetanib with concomitant radiotherapy in investigator-sponsored (Study IRUSZACT0051). One case occurred in Study IRUSZACT0070 in a patient receiving vandetanib in combination with gemcitabine + oxaliplatin for transitional cell cancer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infections disorders</head><p>In 115 (49.8%) vandetanib patients (23 grade 3-4 AEs and 32 SAEs) versus 54 AEs in 36 (36.4%) placebo patients (5 AEs grade 3-4 and 2 SAEs including one fatal). Among the 32 SAEs reported under the SOC infection in vandetanib patients, there were 3 pneumonitis, 1 chylothorax, 1 pneumomediastinum, 1 pulmonary edema and 11 pneumonia (7 SAEs, one was fatal).</p><p>ILD and Pneumonia are an identified risk in the 3,000-patient vandetanib safety data base. In the monotherapy pool of 1839 patients, the majority of whom have lung cancer, the most common fatal event was pneumonia with 14 deaths. In all there were 110 events of pneumonia with 58 ≥Grade 3 and 73 serious. There were 15 cases of pneumonitis (6 ≥Grade 3, 8 serious, 2 fatal) and 7 cases of interstitial lung disease (1 ≥Grade 3, 6 serious, 2 fatal).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Respiratory disorders</head><p>During the randomized phase study, there were 165 AEs reported in 89 (38.5%) vandetanib patients (including 11 SAEs: 2 dyspnea, 1 hemoptysis, 3 pneumonitis, 1 bronchospasm, 1 respiratory failure, 1 pneumonia aspiration, 1 chylothorax, 1 respiratory arrest,) versus 75 AEs in 33 (33.3%) placebo patients (including 3 SAEs: 1 hemoptysis, 1 pleural effusion, 1 pulmonary thrombosis).</p><p>Globally, the number of AEs and the nature of the most frequent AEs reported in vandetanib arm compare well with those reported in placebo arm. Aspiration pneumonia, hemoptysis were reported by 1 patient in each treatment arm. However, there were 3 pneumonitis, 1 chylothorax, 1 pneumomediastinum, 1 pulmonary edema in vandetanib. Of note, there were only 2 pneumonitis grade ≥3</p><p>reported in the initial submission, while no SAE was mentioned.</p><p>No event of ILD occurred during randomised treatment. However, there was 1 cases of ILD reported in patients taking vandetanib in the open-label phase. No cases have been reported in the placebo arm.</p><p>Although none of these reported cases were considered by the investigator to be related to vandetanib, ILD remains an identified risk in MTC patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Renal disorders</head><p>Overall, 24.7% of patients in the vandetanib arm compared with 10.1% of patients in the placebo arm experienced an AE in the SOC renal disorders.</p><p> AEs of renal failure or renal insufficiency were reported in 5 vandetanib patients versus 1 placebo patient. In all cases an aggravating condition was present: vomiting in the case of the placebo patient; hypercalcaemia, dehydration, diarrhoea or pre-existing moderate renal insufficiency with diabetes in the patients receiving vandetanib.</p><p> Nephrolithiasis was reported in 9 vandetanib patients and 1 placebo patient  One related acute case of interstitial nephritis led to temporary withdrawal and a reduced 200 mg dose after resolving.</p><p> Proteinuria was reported in 10% of vandetanib patients (26 AEs versus 3 in placebo arm).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>During randomised treatment, mean creatinine was consistently higher over time in the vandetanib arm than in the placebo arm. Furthermore, 90.9% vandetanib patients had a proteinuria on dipstick versus 28.3% placebo patients.</p><p>The number of patients who experienced an AE in the renal SOC was significantly higher in the vandetanib arm. Furthermore, during randomised treatment, mean creatinine was consistently higher over time in the vandetanib arm than in the placebo arm, 90.9% vandetanib patients had a proteinuria on dipstick versus 28.3% placebo patients. Based on the 5 narratives of fatal cases provided by the applicant, at least two patients died after a</p><p>Grade 4 anorexia, one of malnutrition and respiratory failure (not documented), and one of pneumonia aspiration (not documented).</p><p>Patients with advanced MTC often have airway and esophageal compromise as a result of bulky disease around the neck-deaths from respiratory arrest and aspiration are not unexpected. However, a causal relationship between treatment with vandetanib and Patients 0009003 and 2801012 deaths cannot be ruled out.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eye disorders</head><p>Abnormalities from visual assessment were more common in the vandetanib arm than the placebo arm, (83.6% versus 61.5%). The most notable difference between treatment arms was in abnormalities of the epithelium, which were observed in 49.7% vandetanib patients compared with 3.8% placebo patients. Vandetanib patients also had a higher frequency of stroma abnormalities (17.6% vs 3.8%) and abnormalities of the conjunctiva (7.5% vs 3.8%). Vandetanib patients had a lower frequency of abnormalities of blood vessels (6.9% vs 11.5%) and colour vision (7.5% vs 17.3%) relative to patients in the placebo arm. Six (5.9%) patients had AEs leading to discontinuation of openlabel treatment, including 1 patient with blurred vision. 30.8% vandetanib patients who underwent ophthalmologic examinations had vortex keratopathy, compared with no patients in the placebo arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug Interactions</head><p>In Study 58, co-administration of drugs known to prolong ECG QT interval, whether or not clearly associated with Torsades de Pointes, was associated with a higher incidence of prolongation of the ECG QTc interval than when vandetanib was given without such drugs.</p><p>The potential for a PD interaction with respect to QTc between vandetanib and ondansetron was assessed in Study 21, a four-way cross-over study. Ondansetron 32 mg iv was administered alone or 6 hours after vandetanib 700 mg was administered. The mean effect of 32 mg ondansetron on QTc interval when given alone was 12.45 ms. The mean effect of 700 mg vandetanib 6 hours after administration was 17.29 ms. The combined effect of ondansetron, infusion 6 hours after 700 mg vandetanib, was 22.3 ms. These results point to an additive or slightly less than additive effect on mean QTc when ondansetron (32 mg) was administered as a 15-minute infusion to healthy volunteers who had received a single oral dose of 700 mg vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety during open-label treatment in Study 58</head><p>A  The increases in serum creatinine were CTCAE grade 1-2, and may be related to inhibition of the human transport protein OCT2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Laboratory findings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Haemoglobin</head><p>Mean values for haemoglobin were consistently higher with vandetanib compared with placebo in both males and females. The differences between treatment arms in mean haemoglobin values were more pronounced in females than males. In males these mean levels were higher by approximately 5 to 10 g/L in the vandetanib arm up to Week 72, when the differences between treatment arms diminished.</p><p>In females the mean levels of haemoglobin were higher in the vandetanib arm by ≥10 g/L at the majority of time points. One (0.4%) patient in the vandetanib arm and 2 (2.0%) patients in the placebo arm had CTCAE Grade 3 reductions in haemoglobin. There were no important differences with respect to mean values over time for haematology parameters other than haemoglobin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ALT</head><p>Mean ALT values increased from baseline to Week 12 during randomised treatment before decreasing to the baseline level by Week 120. Mean ALT values during randomised treatment were consistently higher over time through Week 108 in the vandetanib arm compared with the placebo arm. Similar results were observed for median values. A higher percentage of patients in the vandetanib arm than the placebo arm shifted from baseline to a higher CTCAE grade for ALT during randomised treatment.</p><p>Liver function test (LFT) elevations were reported as an AE more frequently in the vandetanib arm than the placebo arm. These included alanine aminotransferase increased <ref type="formula">(</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Creatinine</head><p>The mean creatinine level increased from 73.6 μmol/L at baseline to 91.6 μmol/L at Week 1 and remained relatively stable through Week 108 before decreasing slightly. Mean creatinine was consistently higher over time in the vandetanib arm than in the placebo arm. A higher percentage of patients in the vandetanib arm than the placebo arm shifted from baseline to a higher CTCAE grade for creatinine during randomised treatment.</p><p>No patient in either treatment arm had laboratory findings for creatinine of CTCAE grade 3 or 4 whilst on randomised treatment. There were 6 CTCAE grade 2 elevations in serum creatinine in the vandetanib arm versus none in the placebo arm. Of these 6 patients, 4 normalised or improved with dose interruption, reduction, or discontinuation, 1 patient had recurrent episodes of nephrolithiasis and pyelonephritis, and 1 patient continued to have elevated creatinine at the date of data cut-off.</p><p>A total of 9 (3.9%) patients in the vandetanib arm had an AE of blood creatinine increased, while no patient in the placebo arm had this AE. Two (0.9%) of these patients discontinued vandetanib treatment due to AEs of blood creatinine increased.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Calcium</head><p>The percentage of patients with laboratory variables for low calcium of CTCAE grade 3 or 4 whilst on randomised treatment was higher for the vandetanib arm than for the placebo arm (5.6% vs 3.0%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sodium</head><p>The percentage of patients with laboratory variables of high sodium for CTCAE grade 3 or 4 whilst on randomised treatment was higher for the vandetanib arm than for the placebo arm (1.7% vs 0%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Thyroid Stimulating Hormone (TSH)</head><p>Median values of TSH during the randomised treatment phase of Study 58 were higher in the vandetanib arm than those in the placebo arm at virtually all time points, with the highest median value for vandetanib occurring at Week 12, after which the median values declined in this treatment arm at all time points except one.</p><p>For patients with normal TSH at baseline, elevated TSH was defined as a TSH value above 3x upper limit of normal (ULN) on at least 2 separate follow-up assessments. For patients with an abnormal TSH value at baseline, elevated TSH was defined as a TSH value above 3x the baseline value on at least 2 separate follow-up assessments. The definition was based on the findings of a study by deGroot et al 2005. By this definition, 43 (18.6%) patients in the vandetanib arm had elevated TSH values during treatment, compared with 1 (1.0%) patient in the placebo group. The median time to TSH elevation in the vandetanib arm was 57 days (range, 14 to 502).</p><p>Hypothyroidism was reported as an AE in 15 (6.5%) patients in the vandetanib arm and no patients in the placebo arm. All of the AEs of hypothyroidism were grade 1 or 2. A total of 114 (49.3%) and 17 (17.2%) of patients on the vandetanib and placebo arms respectively, required an increase in thyroid hormone replacement therapy while on randomised treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Urinalysis</head><p>The percentage of patients with newly developed proteinuria or deterioration of existing proteinuria during randomised treatment was higher in the vandetanib arm <ref type="formula">(</ref> Among the 210 patients in the vandetanib treatment arm who developed proteinuria or had deterioration of existing proteinuria during randomised treatment, 54 (23.4%) patients had a concurrent or subsequent AE of hypertension, compared with 1 (1%) of 28 patients in the placebo arm. None of these same patients in the 2 treatment arms had a concurrent or subsequent elevated blood pressure.</p><p>Among the 79 patients who developed haematuria or had deterioration of existing haematuria during treatment with vandetanib, 16 (6.9%) patients had a concurrent or subsequent AE of hypertension, compared with compared with 1 (1%) of 22 patients in the placebo arm. None of these same patients in the 2 treatment arm had a concurrent or subsequent elevated blood pressure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety in special populations</head><p>Effect of gender 99.3% of males and 100% of females in the vandetanib arm, and 92.7% of males and 88.6% of females in the placebo arm, had an AE. The reported incidences of rash (40.3% versus 51.5%), diarrhoea (53.0% versus 60.8%), hypertension (27.6% versus 37.1%), and fatigue (19.4% versus 29.9%) were higher in females than in males in the vandetanib arm; the incidence of asthenia (17.2% versus 11.3%) was lower. Incidences in the placebo arm were similar between genders. These differences do not significantly change the safety profile.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effect of age</head><p>The safety profile of vandetanib was examined across the following age ranges: &lt;40 years of age, 40</p><p>to &lt;65 years of age; 65 to &lt;75 years of age; and 75 years of age. Elderly patients were defined as those patients 65 years of age. For the first 3 groups, the safety profile was similar except that among skin reactions, acne was reported more frequently in patients &lt;40 years of age. There were too few patients 75 years of age to define a safety profile in that group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Renal impairment</head><p>Patients with severe renal impairment (creatinine clearance &lt;30 ml/min) were excluded from all vandetanib Phase III studies. Mild renal impairment was defined as baseline creatinine clearance values of 50 to 80 ml/min, and moderate impairment was 30 to 50 ml/min. In Study 58, 1 patient had mild renal impairment at baseline and had an event of interstitial nephritis.</p><p>The safety profile of vandetanib in patients with both mild and moderate renal impairment was similar to that of the overall study population. The incidences of the events of rash, diarrhoea, hypertension, fatigue, and asthenia were 45.9%, 58.1%, 34.5%, 23%, and 14.2%, respectively, in patients with mild renal failure, and 46.7%, 40%, 26.7%, 20%, and 13.3%, respectively, in patients with moderate renal failure. These data indicate no adjustment in starting dose is needed in patients with mild-to-moderate renal impairment.</p><p>Clinical data and PK data in healthy subjects suggest that no change in starting dose is required in volunteers with mild or moderate renal impairment; in healthy subjects with severe renal impairment, exposure to vandetanib may be increased up to 2-fold.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hepatic impairment</head><p>There is limited clinical data in patients with hepatic impairment treated with vandetanib for MTC; only 5 such patients were enrolled in Study 58. Clinical data and PK data in healthy subjects suggests that no change in starting dose is required for mild, moderate, or severe hepatic impairment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cardiac impairment</head><p>Thirty-eight (11.5%) patients with cardiac impairment were recruited into Study 58. Patients with previous cardiovascular abnormalities recorded on their medical history CRF were defined as having cardiac impairment. A total of 21.4% of patients in the vandetanib arm with cardiac impairment at baseline had protocol-defined QT prolongation, compared with 14.3% of all patients treated with vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fertility, pregnancy and lactation</head><p>Pregnant or lactating women have been excluded from participation in vandetanib studies. Therefore, there is no adequate clinical information in pregnant women using vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety related to drug-drug interactions and other interactions</head><p>A total of 3 (9.7%) of 31 patients in the vandetanib arm who were treated with a Group 1 concomitant medication had protocol-defined QTc prolongation during randomised treatment and 1 (3.2%) of 4 patients had this event after randomised treatment. Of those taking Group 2 concomitant medications, 5 (8.8%) patients in the vandetanib arm had QTc prolongation during randomised treatment and 2 (3.5%) patients had QTc prolongation after randomised treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discontinuation due to adverse events</head><p>One case of discontinuation was reported in blinded phase of Study 58 for safety reasons, in the vandetanib group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post marketing experience</head><p>N/A</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.1.">Discussion on clinical safety</head><p>Regarding the pro-arrhythmogenic effect of vandetanib, Vandetanib at a dose of 300 mg is associated with a substantial and concentration dependent prolongation in QTc (mean 28msec, median 35 msec).</p><p>First QT prolongations occurred most often in the first 3 months of treatment, but continued to first occur after this time. Actually, this effect does not lessen over time and the half-life of vandetanib (19 days) renders this prolongation in QTc interval particularly problematic. Prolonged QTc≥500msec was more frequent in female patients (75% versus 25% in male). The frequency of QTc≥500msec was particularly increased in subgroups of patients with hypertension (20%), diarrhoea (&gt;20%), serum Mg&lt;LLN (31.3%) and with baseline cardiac impairment (32.1%).</p><p>Overall, 31 (13.4%) vandetanib patients had QTc (Bazett's) ≥500 ms compared with 1.0% placebo patients, and 8 (3.47%) vandetanib patients had QTc ≥550 ms or increase from baseline ≥100 ms, based on a single value during randomised treatment. Globally, there was no difference between the different groups regarding sex ration and median age. However, when it comes up to patients with QTc≥500msec, the sex ratio is different (M/F=0.33) (25% M / 75% F).</p><p>QTc increase is an AE. The mechanism of action and both preclinical and pharmacological studies in humans have shown an explanation for the concentration related increase in QTc. Torsades de Pointes have been observed. Cases of sudden death have also been observed not linked to cases of Torsades de Pointes nor exposure. This risk is of further concern in a drug with a very long half life <ref type="bibr">(19 days)</ref> and as diarrhoea is one of the main disease related symptom and side-effect of the drug. Another additional risk factor is the further risk of dehydration and consequent renal impairment; in addition, vandetanib has also shown a deterioration of renal function (increase in creatinine). Duration of follow up in the pivotal study is quite short with regard to the need for long duration of treatment and therefore the risk of developing further major Cardiac SAEs including Torsades de Pointes. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional expert consultations</head><p>Considering vandetanib induced QTcF-prolongation and the observed cardiac events and sudden deaths in the pivotal study as well as Torsades de Pointes in other indications, the SAG was asked to discuss the importance of QTcF prolongation and its clinical consequences in this clinical setting. The SAG was also asked to discuss specific measures that could be recommended to prevent, limit and control the specific cardiac risk in clinical practice in an oncology unit, and specifically whether such treatment should be administered in relation with specialised cardiological advice/follow-up.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAG's conclusion:</head><p>The QT interval is an important measurement to identify patients at risk of developing ventricular arrhythmias and sudden death. Pharmacological and clinical observations (interference with potassium channels, mechanism of Torsades de Pointes, clinical observation of Torsades de Pointes, and cardiac deaths even if judged as unrelated to the study drug) provide strong evidence of an important association between vandetanib and increased risk of clinically significant cardiac events. Of particular concern are the long half-life of the drug, the drug-related diarrhoea potentially inducing hypokalemia, drug-drug interactions such as with SSRIs, deterioration of renal function, and the long treatment duration, all of which may contribute to increase the risk of arrhythmias and sudden death. Selected patients could a priori have an increased risk, such as those with a genetically determined long QTc interval.</p><p>A prerequisite for commencing treatment with vandetanib is the correct measurement of QT interval, if necessary by experienced cardiologists. The QTcF interval should be &lt;480 msec prior to start. Patients with a QT interval of &gt;480 msec are at increased risk of arrhythmias and sudden death, but the precise magnitude of the risk is unknown. Patients who develop QTcF &gt;480 msec should be referred to a cardiologist for identification of risk factors and follow-up.</p><p>Adequate information should be provided to patients and health care professionals on minimising concomitant risks, such as the need to identify increased diarrhoea and the need to strictly control diarrhoea in view of the risk of developing hypokalemia, monitoring of renal function and serum potassium at appropriate intervals, avoiding adverse drug-drug interactions, prompt referral to a cardiologist in case of patients at increased risk of arrhythmias and sudden death.</p><p>Although it is difficult to try to restrict use of vandetanib to specialised centres, it is important to recommend that treating oncologists should have extensive experience in identifying and managing the risk of ventricular arrhythmias and sudden death associated to vandetanib, and that specialist cardiologic advice be available promptly when needed. Overall, the SAG agreed on the risk minimisation measures presented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.2.">Conclusions on the clinical safety</head><p>To prevent and limit the safety concerns, the following aspects have been reflected into the Product Information:  In addition to this, extensive physician and patient information with regard to the risks of QTc prolongation, Torsades de Pointes, PRES/RPLS and their management will be provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Pharmacovigilance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Detailed description of the pharmacovigilance system</head><p>The CHMP considered that the Pharmacovigilance system as described by the applicant fulfils the legislative requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk Management Plan</head><p>The applicant submitted a risk management plan, which included a risk minimisation plan. Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional)</head><p>Infections Routine pharmacovigilance practices, signal identification, and review Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional)</head><p>Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome</p><p>In addition to routine pharmacovigilance practices, signal identification, and review, HCP contacted and enhanced follow-up conducted using follow-up checklists. Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional)</head><p>Toxic epidermal necrolysis, toxic skin eruption, exfoliative dermatitis, and other skin reactions</p><p>In addition to routine pharmacovigilance practices, signal identification, and review, HCP contacted and enhanced follow-up conducted using follow-up checklists Reproductive toxicity Routine pharmacovigilance practices, signal identification, and review and follow-up on pregnancy outcome for all reports of exposure to vandetanib during pregnancy Information relating to women of childbearing potential, pregnancy, breast-feeding and fertility is provided in the SmPC Section 4.6</p><p>Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Important missing information:</head><p>Long-term use Routine pharmacovigilance practices, signal identification, and review Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional)</head><p>Use in patients with moderate to severe renal impairment Vandetanib coadministered with metformin. Vandetanib is an inhibitor of the organic cation transporter 2 (OCT2). Therefore, vandetanib may have the potential to decrease the elimination of medicinal products known to be excreted by OCT2 and to increase a patient's exposure to these medicinal products. Metformin is a substrate of OCT2; patients who are receiving vandetanib and metformin (or other substrate of OCT2) may require more careful monitoring and possible dose adjustment of metformin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>June 2013</head><p>Vandetanib coadministered with antacids ( omeprazole or ranitidine). The effect of proton pump inhibitors or histamine agonists on the gastrointestinal absorption of vandetanib has not been determined. Vandetanib demonstrates pH-dependent solubility; therefore, the co-administration of vandetanib with proton pump inhibitors or histamine agonists may reduce a patient's exposure to vandetanib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>June 2013</head><p>Vandetanib coadministered with midazolam. Vandetanib has the potential to induce the CYP3A4 enzyme system. Co-administration of vandetanib and medicinal products primarily metabolised by the CYP3A4 enzyme system may result in decreased plasma concentrations of these medicinal products that could reduce or shorten therapeutic effects. Therefore, appropriate dose adjustments may be required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>June 2013</head><p>The following additional risk minimisation activities were required:</p><p> Before and after product launch, the MAH must provide the SmPC, sufficient Patient Alert Cards (see Annex 10) for each prescription, and health care professional (HCP) educational material about the risks of QTc prolongation, Torsades de Pointes and PRES and their management according to the SmPC, to all HCPs who are expected to prescribe the product. The MAH shall agree the educational material with the national competent authority before launch of the product in the authority's state.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">User consultation</head><p>The results of the user consultation with target patient groups on the package leaflet submitted by the applicant show that the package leaflet meets the criteria for readability as set out in the Guideline on the readability of the label and package leaflet of medicinal products for human use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-Risk Balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Beneficial effects</head><p>In the current submission, the Applicant has mainly provided results taken from one pivotal study <ref type="bibr">(Study 58)</ref>. Two supportive studies (Studies 08 and 68) were also submitted, both performed in a limited number of patients with hereditary medullary thyroid cancer.</p><p>Study 58 was a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study comparing the efficacy and safety of vandetanib versus placebo in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic MTC. In the primary analysis, the superiority of vandetanib as compared to placebo was demonstrated, with a 11.2 months increase (19.3 vs 30.5 months) of median PFS (HR=0.46, 95% CI, 0.31 to 0.69, p=0.0001).</p><p>The superiority of vandetanib over placebo is clinically significant and quite consistent across all pre planned subgroups. More benefit from vandetanib was seen in patients with a CTN or CEA doubling time &lt; 24 months compared to patients with a longer doubling time and in patients with symptoms at baseline.</p><p>The terms "symptomatic and aggressive" disease correspond to a rapid deterioration of clinical condition (clinical, biological and radiological signs) i.e., patients at urgent need of treatment Uncertainty in the knowledge about the beneficial effects.</p><p>The activity of vandetanib in RET mutation negative patients is indirectly supported by the activity of the drug observed in the subgroup of patients with RET unknown status. Further data from study 58 provided in the post-hoc analysis of RET negative patients (including those patients classified as RET unknown, with the M918T mutation) showed efficacy. Therefore, the available evidence supports the efficacy of vandetanib in RET negative tumours using the most frequent mutation (80%-92%). . It is not certain however that those patients tested RET negative for M918T mutation are not positive for mutation on other exons. It is equally not certain that those patients tested RET negative from old tumour sample were still RET negative at the time of initiation of treatment. Therefore, it is difficult to draw an unequivocal conclusion of the size of the benefit of vandetanib in patients with RET mutation negative tumours. Given that the precise mechanism of action of vandetanib in RET remains unclear, the absolute benefit in these patients should be more precisely/directly determined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risks</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Unfavourable effects</head><p>The most commonly reported adverse drug reactions have been diarrhoea, rash, nausea, hypertension, and headache. Regarding the pro-arrhythmogenic effect, Vandetanib at a dose of 300 mg is associated with a substantial and concentration dependent prolongation in QTc (mean 28msec, median 35 msec).</p><p>First QT prolongations occurred most often in the first 3 months of treatment, but continued to first occur after this time. This effect does not lessen over time. Prolonged QTc ≥ msec was more frequent in female patients (75% versus 25% in male), Frequency of QTc msec was particularly increased in subgroups of patients with hypertension (20%), diarrhoea (&gt;20%), serum Mg&lt;LLN (31.3%) and with baseline cardiac impairment (32.1%).</p><p>The mechanism of action and both preclinical and pharmacological studies have shown an explanation for the concentration related increase in QTc. Torsades de Pointes have been observed. Cases of sudden death have also been observed not linked to cases of Torsades de Pointes nor exposure. This risk is of further concern in a drug with a very long half life (19 days) and with diarrhoea as one of the main disease related symptoms. Another additional risk factor is the further risk of dehydration and consequent renal impairment; in addition, vandetanib has also shown a deterioration of renal function (increase in creatinine).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uncertainty in the knowledge about the unfavourable effects</head><p>In view of the toxicity profile of vandetanib at the 300 mg dose, at least in some patients the safety of the 300 mg dose may be a concern; there is a need to further study the optimal dose with the aim to maximise the benefit-risk balance, Additional data on safety and activity of a lower dose will be provided through a randomized dose-finding trial looking at safety and activity of 150mg vs 300mg dose of vandetanib (Study D4200C00097), with overall response rate as the primary endpoint. The trial is due to be completed in October 2015. (see Section 2.7 Pharmacovigilance)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-risk balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Importance of favourable and unfavourable effects</head><p>In the overall population, improvement in PFS, ORR and DCR are of importance as well as a positive effect on some PRO. The management of the risk of QT prolongation and associated clinical consequences and renal risks associated with vandetanib are particularly important.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-risk balance</head><p>The restriction of the indication to patients with symptomatic and aggressive disease allows to select patients who are at urgent need of treatment for medullary thyroid cancer. It is in this patient population that the benefits outweigh the important risks outlined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion on the benefit-risk balance</head><p>To prevent and limit the concern on QT prolongation and clinical consequences associated with vandetanib, the following measures have been implemented in the Product Information. :  a statement in section 4.5 of the SmPC noting that Vandetanib has been shown to prolong the ECG QT interval and Torsades de Pointes have been uncommonly reported. Therefore, the concomitant use of vandetanib with drugs known to also prolong the QT interval and / or induce Torsades de Pointes is either contra-indicated or not recommended depending on existing alternative therapies.</p><p>If there is no appropriate alternative therapy, not recommended combinations of such medicinal products with vandetanib may be made with additional ECG monitoring of the QTc interval, evaluation of electrolytes and further control at onset or worsening of diarrhoea.</p><p>In addition to this, extensive physician and patient information with regard to the risks of QTc prolongation, Torsades de Pointes and their management will be provided.</p><p>Although the results of the randomised, placebo controlled, phase III trial fully support the positive balance of benefits and risks, there is still the need to obtain further data to confirm the magnitude of the effect of vandetanib in patients with RET mutation negative tumours. Based on the randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study presented in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic MTC, the superiority of vandetanib was demonstrated compared to placebo, with a 11.2 months increase (19.3 vs 30.5 months) of median PFS (HR=0.46, 95% CI, 0.31 to 0.69, p=0.0001). The benefit risk balance of vandetanib in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic medullary thyroid cancer is therefore considered to be positive.</p><p>From a quantitative viewpoint, the specific benefit in patients with RET -tumours might be less as compared with what was observed in RET+ tumours. There is a need to further confirm such differences in terms of efficacy in RET negative patients with vandetanib,  It is likely that the applicant will in a position to provide comprehensive clinical data</p><p>Comprehensive clinical data will be provided through an open label study of vandetanib in patients with sporadic medullary thyroid cancer with known RET mutation status. Data will be collected and analyzed at pre-specified times. The final analysis will be performed when at least 40 patients identified with RET mutation and 40 patients identified without evidence of RET mutation have been enrolled into the study and received vandetanib for 14 months. This study will include 50 -60% of patients who receive vandetanib within the EU. Patients will be followed for 2 years and an interim analysis will be presented 12 months after first inclusion. The study is considered feasible and it is therefore likely that the applicant will in a position to provide comprehensive clinical data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>Unmet medical needs to be fulfilled Patients with MTC can be cured only by thyroidectomy, performed when the tumour is confined to the thyroid gland. The tumour is relatively unresponsive to conventional doses of radiation therapy and to chemotherapeutic regimens (none of which have been approved in this indication yet). Caprelsa is intended for the treatment of aggressive and symptomatic medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic disease. The CHMP concluded that the product fulfils an unmet medical need due to the lack of available alternative treatments in this population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>The benefits to public health of the immediate availability on the market of the medicinal product concerned outweighs the risk inherent in the fact that additional data are still required</p><p>The CHMP considered that the potential risks inherent in marketing vandetanib for the specific indication while additional, more comprehensive data will be available in the future would be offset by the benefit to patients with aggressive and symptomatic medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic disease. The CHMP agreed that the RMP for vandetanib in the approved indication was adequate to address any identified and unknown risks.</p><p>The CHMP concluded that all the requirements for the granting of a conditional marketing authorisation had been met.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Recommendations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome</head><p>Based on the CHMP review of data on quality, safety and efficacy, the CHMP considers by consensus that the risk-benefit balance of Caprelsa in the treatment of "aggressive and symptomatic medullary thyroid cancer (MTC) in patients with unresectable locally advanced or metastatic disease (For patients win whom Rearranged during Transfection (RET) mutation is not known or is negative, a possible lower benefit should be taken into account before individual treatment decision(see important information in sections 4.4 and 5.1))" is favourable and therefore recommends the granting of the conditional marketing authorisation subject to the following conditions:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions regarding supply and use</head><p>Medicinal product subject to restricted medical prescription (See Annex I: Summary of Product Characteristics, section 4.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions and requirements of the Marketing Authorisation Risk Management System and PSUR cycle</head><p>The MAH must ensure that the system of pharmacovigilance, presented in Module 1.8.1 of the marketing authorisation, is in place and functioning before and whilst the product is on the market.</p><p>The MAH shall perform the pharmacovigilance activities detailed in the Pharmacovigilance Plan, as agreed in version 7 of the Risk Management Plan (RMP) presented in Module 1.8.2 of the marketing authorisation and any subsequent updates of the RMP agreed by the CHMP.</p><p>As per the CHMP Guideline on Risk Management Systems for medicinal products for human use, the updated RMP should be submitted at the same time as the next Periodic Safety Update Report (PSUR).</p><p>In addition, an updated RMP should be submitted:</p><p> When new information is received that may impact on the current Safety Specification, Pharmacovigilance Plan or risk minimisation activities  Within 60 days of an important (pharmacovigilance or risk minimisation) milestone being reached  at the request of the EMA The PSUR cycle for the product will follow a half yearly cycle until otherwise agreed by the CHMP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product</head><p>Prior to launch of the product in each Member State, the Marketing Authorisation Holder shall agree the content and format of the educational material with the national competent authority.</p><p>The Marketing Authorisation Holder (MAH) should ensure that, at launch and thereafter, all Healthcare Professionals who are expected to use and/or prescribe Caprelsa are provided with an Educational pack.</p><p>The educational pack should contain the following: The total duration of the study is expected to be 38 months.</p><p>Analyses:  The study will run for 2 years and at pre-specified times, the data will be collected and analyzed (e.g., 12 months and 24 months)  Objective response rate, progression status and DCR in the overall population, RET mutation negative and RET mutation positive patients  Safety analyses in the overall population, RET mutation negative and RET mutation positive patients</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product to be implemented by the Member States.</head><p>The Member States should ensure that all conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product described below are implemented:</p><p>Prior to launch of the product in each Member State, the Marketing Authorisation Holder shall agree the content and format of the educational material with the national competent authority.</p><p>The Marketing Authorisation Holder (MAH) should ensure that, at launch and thereafter, all Healthcare Professionals who are expected to use and/or prescribe Caprelsa are provided with an Educational pack.</p><p>The educational pack should contain the following: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New Active Substance Status</head><p>Based on the CHMP review of data on the quality, non-clinical and clinical properties of the active substance, the CHMP considers that vandetanib is to be qualified as a new active substance (see Appendix 1).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>and point 3 of Annex of Regulation (EC) No 726/2004. The eligibility to the centralised procedure was initially agreed upon by the EMA/CHMP on 23 March 2010 and subsequently on 20 September 2010. The applicant applied for the following indication: Vandetanib is indicated for the treatment of adult  The procedure started on 22 September 2010.  The Rapporteur's first Assessment Report was circulated to all CHMP members on 14 December 2010. The Co-Rapporteur's first Assessment Report was circulated to all CHMP members on 10 December 2010.  During the meeting on 20 January 2011, the CHMP agreed on the consolidated List of Questions to be sent to the applicant. The final consolidated List of Questions was sent to the applicant on 20 January 2011.  The applicant submitted the responses to the CHMP consolidated List of Questions on 19 April 2011. The summary report of the inspection carried out at the following sites Centre Léon Bérard, Service de Médecine Nucléaire and Hamatologie/Onkologie between 15 March -8 April 2011 was issued on 31 May 2011.  The Rapporteurs circulated the Joint Assessment Report on the applicant's responses to the List of Questions to all CHMP members on 6 June 2011.  During the CHMP meeting on 23 June 2011, the CHMP agreed on a list of outstanding issues to be addressed by the applicant.  During a meeting of a SAG on 8 September 2011, experts were convened to address questions raised by the CHMP.  The applicant submitted the responses to the CHMP List of Outstanding Issues on 19 and 28 September 2011.  The Rapporteurs circulated the Joint Assessment Report on the applicant's responses to the List of Outstanding Issues to all CHMP members on 6 October 2011.  During the CHMP meeting on 20 October 2011, the CHMP agreed on a list of outstanding issues to be addressed by the applicant.  The applicant submitted the responses to the CHMP List of Outstanding Issues on 2 November 2011  The Rapporteurs circulated the Joint Assessment Report on the applicant's responses to the List of Outstanding Issues to all CHMP members on 09 November 2011 recommending the granting of a conditional marketing authorisation.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>A</head><label></label><figDesc>recently completed study (Study D4200C00079 [Study 79]) was performed in patients with differentiated thyroid cancer and the preliminary results are also presented in the Applicant's documentation. A list of clinical efficacy studies submitted is presented in the table below.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>PFS and ORR for 4 Ad Hoc Subgroups based on disease statusSecondary endpointsORR</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In section 4.1 of the SmPC: "'For patients in whom Rearranged during Transfection (RET) mutation is not known or is negative, a possible lower benefit should be taken into account before individual treatment decision (see important information in sections 4.4 and 5.1)In section 4.4 of the SmPC: "Patients without RET mutation may have a decreased benefit from vandetanib treatment and the benefit/risk balance for this group of patients may therefore differ from that of the group with RET mutations. For patients whose RET mutation status could be negative, a possible lower benefit should be taken into account beforeindividual treatment decisions and the use of vandetanib should be carefully considered because of the treatment related risks. Therefore RET mutation testing is recommended. When establishing RET mutation status, tissue samples should be obtained if possible at the time of initiation of treatment rather than at the time of diagnosis (see sections 4.1 and 5.1)  In section 5.1 of the SmPC: "In Study 58, RET mutation testing was performed by using the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) based Amplification Refractory Mutation System (ARMS) assay for the M918T mutation, and direct sequencing of DNA for mutations in exons 10, 11, 13, 14, 15 and 16 (site of M918T mutation) on all sporadic patients where DNA was available (297/298).However, RET status could not be tested in a large proportion of patients (mainly because of unavailable results for direct sequencing of DNA) and response rate was somewhat lower in the patients with unknown RET status compared with RET mutation positive status: 51.8% vs.35.9 % respectively. In the blinded comparison of vandetanib vs. placebo, only 2 patients known to be RET negative at all 6 exons received vandetanib and none demonstrated responses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>unblinded and given the option to receive post-progression open label treatment with vandetanib 300 mg (or receive a permanently reduced dose, if applicable), or enter follow-up for survival status. A total of 58 (58%) of randomised placebo patients and 44 (19%) randomised vandetanib patients received vandetanib during the open label treatment. Overall, there were no substantial imbalance regarding patients characteristics, except in the percentage of patients ≤ 40 y at baseline in the vandetanib arm.The mean duration of exposure was longer for vandetanib 300 mg (75.0 weeks for total exposure and 73.6 weeks for actual exposure) than for placebo (53.9 weeks for total exposure and 53.7 weeks for actual exposure) (SeeFigure X below).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure 6. Percentage of patients by exposure on randomised treatment in Study 58 (safety analysis set)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>from Table 11.3.2.9.1. SOC = System Organ Class, PT = Preferred Term. a Number (%) of patients with AEs, sorted by group, in decreasing order of frequency in the vandetanib arm. Event rate = (No. of pats. with event / total duration of follow-up until 1st event for all pats. in group) x 1000</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>total of 102 patients had received open-label treatment with vandetanib by the data cut-off date of 19 October 2009. A total of 58 placebo patients received vandetanib during the open label study phase, and 42 of them were continuing at the time of the cut-off data. The reported incidence of AEs in the open label phase is similar in number and type to that seen in patients who initially received vandetanib in the randomised phase. There were no fatal cases among the 58 placebo patients while 2 occurred in the vandetanib randomized patients. One patient died of an SAE of pneumonia aspiration during the open-label phase. One additional patient died of a suicide 103 days after receiving his last dose of vandetanib during open-label treatment. The event was not considered related to treatment by the investigator.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>9 [3.9%] vs 1 [1.0%] in the vandetanib and placebo arms, aspartate aminotransferase increased (10 [4.3%] vs 1 [1.0%]), transaminases increased (4 [1.7%] vs 0), and liver function test abnormal (1[0.4%] vs 0 patients). No patient had a concomitant bilirubin elevation.Four (1.7%) patients in the vandetanib arm had laboratory findings for ALT of CTCAE grade 3 or 4 whilst on randomised treatment, compared with no patients in the placebo arm. Of 28 patients in the vandetanib arm who had an ALT elevation of grade 2 or higher, 21 patients returned to normal value (18 patients) or grade 1 ALT elevation (3 patients) without any change in vandetanib dose. In 3 patients ALT normalised (2 patients) or improved to grade 1 (1 patient) after dose reduction or interruption. Four patients still had an ALT of grade 2 at data cut-off. No patient had both an ALT elevation of 3 x ULN and a bilirubin elevation of 2 x ULN. No patient in the vandetanib arm discontinued due to AEs related to LFT elevations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A recommendation in section 4.2 of the SmPC with regards to treatment initiation and supervision by a physician experienced in treatment of MTC and in the use of anticancer medicinal products and experienced in the assessment of ECG.  A contraindication in section 4.3 of the SmPC with regards to congenital long QTc syndrome, patients with an increased QTc interval over 480 msec and the concomitant use of vandetanib with drugs known to also prolong the QT interval and / or induce Torsades de Pointes (arsenic, cisapride, erythromycine IV, toremifene, mizolastine, moxifloxacine, Class IA and III antiarrhythmics</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A recommendation in section 4.2 of the SmPC with regards to treatment initiation and supervision by a physician experienced in treatment of MTC and in the use of anticancer medicinal products and experienced in the assessment of ECG.  A contraindication in section 4.3 of the SmPC with regards to congenital long QTc syndrome, patients with an increased QTc interval over 480 msec and the concomitant use of vandetanib with drugs known to also prolong the QT interval and / or induce Torsades de Pointes (arsenic, cisapride, erythromycine IV, toremifene, mizolastine, moxifloxacine, Class IA and III antiarrhythmics). a precaution in section 4.4 of the SmPC with regards to QTc prolongation. Patients who develop a single value of corrected ECG QTc interval of at least 500 msec should stop taking vandetanib. Dosing can be resumed at a reduced dose after return of the ECG QTc interval to pretreatment status has been confirmed and correction of possible electrolyte imbalance has been made.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Following</head><label></label><figDesc>consultation with the applicant, the CHMP considered the granting of a conditional marketing authorisation vandetanib. Vandetanib aims at the treatment of seriously debilitating diseases or lifethreatening diseases and falls within the scope of Commission Regulation 507/2006 on the conditional marketing authorisation. The Committee found that although comprehensive clinical data referring to the efficacy of the medicinal product had not been supplied, all of the following requirements were met: The risk-benefit balance of the medicinal product, as defined in Article 1(28a) of Directive 2001/83/EC, is positive</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table of contents List of abbreviations</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>PP</cell><cell>Per protocol</cell></row><row><cell>PR</cell><cell>Partial response</cell></row><row><cell>PRO</cell><cell>Patient reported outcome</cell></row><row><cell>PPI</cell><cell>Patient's pain intensity</cell></row><row><cell>PTC</cell><cell>Papillary Thyroid Cancer</cell></row><row><cell>AEs QoL ALT QTcV AST ATP QWBA AUC RECIST bFGF RET BOR BPI RTK BRK SAE CEA SAWP Cmax SCCHN CNS SD CR / PR T1/2 CTN TK CYP TKIs DCR TDPS DOR Tmax EGFR TTC ECOG PS TTOU ELISA TWP EU ULRR FACT-G VDss FGF VEGF FGFR VEGFR FMO VEGFR-2 GCP TTP GLP WHO PS HR ZD6474</cell><cell>Quality of Life Adverse Events Heart rate corrected QT interval (Van der Waters ALanine AminoTransferase correction) ASpartate aminoTransferase Quantitative Whole Body Autoradiography Adenosine TriPhosphate Response Evaluation Criteria in Solid Tumors Area under the plasma concentration time curve Rearranged during Transfection receptor (proto-basic Fibroblast Growth Factor oncogene) Best Objective Response Receptor Tyrosine Kinase Brief Pain Inventory Serious adverse event Breast Tumour Kinase Scientific Advice Working Party CarcinoEmbryonic Antigen Squamous Cell Carcinoma of the Head and Neck Maximum observed plasma concentration Stable disease Central Nervous System Half life Complete response / partial response Tyrosine Kinase Calcitonin Levels Tyrosine Kinase Inhibitors Cytochrome P450 Time to Decline in WHO Performance Status Disease Control Rate Time of maximum observed plasma concentration Duration of response Threshold of Toxicological Concern Epidermal Growth Factor Receptor Time To Opioid analgesic Use Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group performance status Time to Worsening in Pain Enzyme-Linked Immunosorbent Assay upper limit of reference range European Union Volume of Distribution at steady state Functional Assessment of Cancer Therapy General Scale Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor(4 family members: -Fibroblast Growth Factor (bFGF is basic fibroblast growth A, -B, -C and -D) factor) Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor Receptor Fibroblast Growth Factor Receptor (family members (3 family members: -1, -2 and -3) include FGFR-1, -2, -3, -4) Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor Receptor-2 Flavine containing Mono-Oxygenase Time to tumour progression Good clinical practices World Health Organization Performance Status Good Laboratory Practice Hazard ratio vandetanib</cell></row><row><cell>HEK</cell><cell>Human Embryonic Kidney</cell></row><row><cell>hERG</cell><cell>human Ether-a-go-go-Related Gene</cell></row><row><cell>HPAEC</cell><cell>Human Pulmonary Artery Endothelial Cells</cell></row><row><cell>HPLC-MS/MS</cell><cell>High Performance Liquid Chromatography tandem Mass</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Spectrometry</cell></row><row><cell>HPMC</cell><cell>HydroxyPropylMethylCellulose</cell></row><row><cell>HUVEC</cell><cell>Human Umbilical Vein Endothelia Cell</cell></row><row><cell>IC50</cell><cell>Concentration that reduces the effect by 50%</cell></row><row><cell>LC-MS/MS</cell><cell>Liquid Chromatography tandem Mass Spectrometry</cell></row><row><cell>LSC</cell><cell>Liquid Scintillation Counting</cell></row><row><cell>ITT</cell><cell>Intent to treat</cell></row><row><cell>MAA</cell><cell>Marketing Authorisation Application</cell></row><row><cell>MDR1</cell><cell>Multi Drug Resistance 1 transporter</cell></row><row><cell>MEN</cell><cell>Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia</cell></row><row><cell>MLEC</cell><cell>Mouse Lung Endothelial Cells</cell></row><row><cell>MTC</cell><cell>Medullary Thyroid Cancer</cell></row><row><cell>MTD</cell><cell>Maximum Tolerated Dose</cell></row><row><cell>N/A</cell><cell>Not Applicable</cell></row><row><cell>NE</cell><cell>Not evaluable</cell></row><row><cell>NRTK</cell><cell>Non-Receptor Tyrosine Kinase</cell></row><row><cell>NSCLC</cell><cell>Non-small cell lung cancer</cell></row><row><cell>NYHA</cell><cell>New York Heart Association</cell></row><row><cell>ORR</cell><cell>Objective Response Rate</cell></row><row><cell>OS</cell><cell>Overall survival</cell></row><row><cell>PD</cell><cell>Progressive disease</cell></row><row><cell>PFS</cell><cell>Progression free survival</cell></row><row><cell>Pgp</cell><cell>P-glycoprotein</cell></row><row><cell>PK</cell><cell>Pharmacokinetic</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The hereditary form of MTC is a rare disease commonly diagnosed in patients &lt;20 years and characterised by Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia (MEN) with complete penetrance (virtually all patients develop MTC), but variable expressivity: Multiple Endocrine Neoplasia (MEN) type 2a, MEN type 2b, or Familial Medullary Thyroid Carcinoma (FMTC). Only 50% of patients with MEN2a and MEN2b, develop pheochromocytoma and 30% of patients with MEN2a develop parathyroid hyperplasia). All of the patients with MEN2b develop a typical ganglioneuromastosis throughout the aerodigestive tract.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Stability studies support the shelf-life as defined in the SmPC. No special storage conditions are needed.</figDesc><table /><note>The stability studies have been performed according to EU/ICH guidelines on stability. All parameters remained within specification during the stability testing at all storage conditions. Slight increase in water content and decrease of dissolution was observed at accelerated and intermediate conditions; no other trends are detected. No degradation was seen in the samples.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 1 . Summary of main study results Substance (INN/Invented Name): CAS-number (if available): PBT screening Result Conclusionchemical properties and fate Study type Test protocol Results Remarks Adsorption-Desorption OPPTS 835.1110 OECD 121 Adsorption to sludge K oc = 22 700 L/kg Adsorption to soil K oc = 100.000 (pH 11.5)Phase IIa Effect studies Study type Test protocol Endpoint value Unit Remarks</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Bioaccumulation potential-log K ow OECD122</cell><cell cols="2">-0.684 ; 2.21 ; 3.90</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Not &gt; 4.5 ; not PBT</cell></row><row><cell>PBT-assessment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Parameter</cell><cell>Result relevant for</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Conclusion</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>conclusion</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bioaccumulation</cell><cell>log K ow</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BCF</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Persistence</cell><cell>DT50 or ready</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>biodegradability</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Toxicity</cell><cell>NOEC or CMR</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>T/not T</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PBT-statement :</cell><cell cols="4">The compound is not considered as PBT nor vPvB</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">The compound is considered as vPvB</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">The compound is considered as PBT</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Phase I</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Calculation</cell><cell>Value</cell><cell>Unit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Conclusion</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PEC surfacewater , default or refined</cell><cell>0.00001 µg/l then</cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">PEC is &lt; 0.01</cell></row><row><cell>(e.g. prevalence, literature)</cell><cell>&lt; 0.01 µg/l.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">then Phase II is</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">not necessary;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">but the Applicant</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">has chosen to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">conducte Phase</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">II assessment.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Other concerns (e.g. chemical</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>class)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Phase II Physical-Highly absorbed (&gt;</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>10.000 L/kg,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">EMEA/CCCHMP/4447/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>00)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ready Biodegradability Test</cell><cell>OECD 301F</cell><cell cols="3">5% is degraded (after 28</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>days)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Aerobic and Anaerobic</cell><cell>OECD 308</cell><cell>DT 50, water =</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transformation in Aquatic</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">DT 50, sediment =</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sediment systems</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">DT 50, whole system =</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">% shifting to sediment =</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Algae, Growth Inhibition</cell><cell>OECD 201</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell cols="3">freshwater green algae</cell></row><row><cell>Test/Species</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Daphnia sp. Reproduction Test</cell><cell>OECD 211</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>300</cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell cols="2">Daphnia magna</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Fish, Early Life Stage Toxicity</cell><cell>OECD 210</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Test/Species</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Activated Sludge, Respiration</cell><cell>OECD 209</cell><cell>EC</cell><cell></cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Inhibition Test</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Phase IIb Studies</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bioaccumulation</cell><cell>OECD 305</cell><cell>BCF</cell><cell></cell><cell>L/kg</cell><cell>%lipids:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Aerobic and anaerobic</cell><cell>OECD 307</cell><cell cols="6">60.6 -101.6% of the applied radioactivity could be</cell></row><row><cell>transformation in soil</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">recovered In soil.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Soil Micro organisms: Nitrogen</cell><cell>OECD 216</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>56</cell><cell>µg/kg</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transformation Test</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Terrestrial Plants, Growth</cell><cell>OECD 208</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>1000</cell><cell>mg/kg</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Test/Species</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Earthworm, Acute Toxicity Tests</cell><cell>OECD 207</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>1000</cell><cell>mg/kg</cell><cell>Eisenia</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">foetida foetida</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Collembola, Reproduction Test</cell><cell>ISO 11267</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>mg/kg</cell><cell cols="2">Folsomia candida</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sediment dwelling organism</cell><cell>OECD 218</cell><cell>NOEC</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>mg/kg</cell><cell>Toxicity</cell><cell>to</cell><cell>the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">freshwater midge</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Chironomus riparius.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 2 . Summary of the clinical studies contributing PK data of vandetanib Study No. Study detail Dose Number randomized/treated and type of subjects</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Study 01</cell><cell>Rising single dose followed by</cell><cell>ZD6474: 50 mg,</cell><cell>77/77</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>multiple dose tolerability and toxicity study (Western)</cell><cell>100 mg, 200 mg, 300 mg, 500 mg, 600 mg</cell><cell>Patients with malignant solid tumors.</cell></row><row><cell>Study 43</cell><cell>Rising single dose followed by</cell><cell>ZD6474: 100 mg,</cell><cell>0/18</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>multiple dose tolerability and toxicity study (Japanese)</cell><cell>200 mg, 300 mg, 400 mg (single doses)</cell><cell>Japanese patients with malignant solid tumours.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>PK parameters for vandetanib after a single dose and at steady state (day 43) for 100 mg administered every other day) and 100 and 300 mg (administered once daily): Study 04</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Pharmacokinetics of metabolites of vandetanib has been investigated in healthy volunteers, in patients and subjects with renal and hepatic impairment. Due to the low systemic exposure, it is estimated that the active metabolite N-desmethyl-vandetanib contributes only a relatively small proportion (approximately 10%) of the overall pharmacological activity of vandetanib. This proportion may increase up to 43% in patients co-administered CYP inducers such as rifampicin (Study 26), but is not changed in patients with renal impairment (Study 22) and may be decreased in patients with hepatic</figDesc><table /><note>impairment (Study 16).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Summary of secondary pharmacokinetic parameters (median) from MTC patients dosed to steady state (Day 56) with 300 mg daily (study 8, 58) and 100 mg (study 68).</figDesc><table><row><cell>8</cell></row></table><note>Summary of pharmacokinetic parameters estimated by popPK analysis in patients with MTC (studies 8, 58 and 68) and in healthy subject/cancer patients.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 5 : Vandetanib studies in thyroid cancer 2.5.1. Dose response studies D4200C00008 Study</head><label>5</label><figDesc>008 was a single-arm, open-label, uncontrolled, monotherapy Phase II study conducted to evaluate the efficacy and tolerability of vandetanib (300 mg daily) in 30 patients with hereditary locally advanced or metastatic MTC.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>2.5.2. Main study D4200C00058 An</head><label></label><figDesc>Study 068 was a single-arm, open-label, uncontrolled, monotherapy Phase II study conducted to evaluate the efficacy and tolerability of vandetanib (100mg) in 19 patients with hereditary locally advanced or metastatic MTC. The ORR (RECIST criteria, based on site-read assessment) was 15.8% (3/19) with 95% CI [3.4; 39.6]. The median DOR from the onset of response was 5.5 months International, Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled, Multi-Center Study to Assess the Efficacy of ZD6474 versus Placebo in Subjects with Unresectable Locally Advanced or Metastatic Medullary Thyroid Cancer</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A technique providing ≤5mm sections: a sum of diameters ≥2 cm (no target lesions measuring &lt;1 cm and no lymph nodes &lt;1.5 cm) or  A technique providing &gt;5mm sections: a sum of diameters ≥4 cm (no target lesion measuring &lt;2 cm)  CTN ≥500 pg/mL (conventional units) or ≥146.3 pmol/L (international standard units)  All patients (other than those with hereditary MTC who had a documented germline RET mutation) had to submit a suitable archived tumour collection sample. When this sample was not available prior to 2 weeks before randomisation, a fresh tumour sample was obtained. The tumour sample had to be obtained by the investigative site and shipped to its destination prior to randomisation.Any of the following was regarded as a criterion for exclusion from the study: Brain metastases or spinal cord compression, unless treated at least 4 weeks before the first dose, and stable without steroid treatment for 10 days  Any concomitant medications that may have affected QTc or induced CYP3A4 function (with the exception of somatostatin or somatostatin analog) and/or any prohibited medications referenced in Serum bilirubin &gt;1.5 x the upper limit of reference range (ULRR)  Creatinine clearance &lt;30 mL/min (calculated by Cockcroft-Gault formula) Potassium &lt;4.0 mmol/L despite supplementation, or above the Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (CTCAE) grade 1 upper limit. Magnesium below the normal range despite supplementation, or above the CTCAE grade 1 upper limit. Serum calcium above the CTCAE grade 1 upper limit. In instances when the serum calcium was below the normal range, the calcium adjusted for albumin was to be obtained and substituted for the measured serum value. Exclusion was to then be based on the calcium adjusted for albumin values falling below the normal limit. Previous or current malignancies of other histologies within the last 5 years, with the exception of tumours associated with MEN2a and MEN2b, in situ carcinoma of the cervix, or adequately treated basal cell or squamous cell carcinoma of the skin  Any unresolved chronic toxicity greater than CTCAE grade 2 from previous anticancer therapy  Participation in a clinical study and/or receipt of an investigational drug during the last 30 days (participation in the survival follow-up period of a study was not an exclusion criterion)TreatmentsDuring the blinded phase of the study, patients received either:-vandetanib 300 mg once daily oral dose or -placebo 300mg once daily oral dose until they had objective disease progression, provided they did not meet any other withdrawal criteria.Upon disease progression, patients were discontinued from blinded study treatment and given theoption to begin open label treatment with vandetanib 300 mg (or receive a permanently reduced dose, if applicable), or enter follow-up for survival status. To demonstrate an improvement in biochemical response with vandetanib as compared to placebo, as measured by calcitonin (CTN) and carcinoembryonic antigen (CEA)  To demonstrate a delay in time to worsening of pain (TWP) among patients with MTC after treatment with vandetanib as compared to placebo  To determine the pharmacokinetics (PK) of vandetanib in this patient population and investigate any influence of patient demography and pathophysiology on the PK  To assess the relationship between PK and time interval between the start of the Q wave and the end of the T wave, (corrected for heart rate) (QTc), safety, efficacy, and biomarkers To determine the safety and tolerability of vandetanib treatment in MTC patients PFS), defined from the date of randomization to the date of objective progression or death (by any cause in the absence of progression), provided death was within 3 months from the last evaluable RECIST assessment, using data from RECIST assessments performed at baseline, during treatment and during the follow-up period. The PFS assessment was based on an independent radiological review.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3"> Objectives Provision of written informed consent</cell></row><row><cell cols="3"> Primary objective: Female or male aged 18 years and over Corrected Calcium=Ca + 0.8 X (4-serum albumin)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell> </cell><cell>Previously confirmed histological diagnosis of unresectable locally advanced or metastatic Alanine aminotransferase (ALT), aspartate aminotransferase (AST), or alkaline phosphatase (ALP) To demonstrate an improvement in progression-free survival (PFS) with vandetanib as compared hereditary or sporadic MTC. Documentation had to be provided in patient's medical chart. &gt;2.5 × ULRR, or &gt;5.0 × ULRR, if judged by the investigator to be related to liver metastases to placebo in patients with unresectable, locally advanced or metastatic medullary thyroid cancer</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">  Secondary objectives: Life expectancy of 12 weeks or longer (These patients were considered most likely to be able to  (MTC). Significant cardiac event (eg, myocardial infarction), superior vena cava syndrome, New York Heart tolerate study procedures and treatment.) WHO Performance status (PS) 0-2 (These patients were considered most likely to be able to Association (NYHA) classification of heart disease ≥2, within 12 weeks before randomisation, or presence of cardiac disease that in the opinion of the investigator increased the risk of ventricular</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>tolerate study procedures and treatment.) arrhythmia To demonstrate an improvement in the objective response rate (ORR), disease control rate (DCR),</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ability to swallow study medication History of arrhythmia (multifocal premature ventricular contractions, bigeminy, trigeminy, and duration of response (DOR) with vandetanib as compared to placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>  </cell><cell>ventricular tachycardia) that was symptomatic or required treatment (CTCAE grade 3), To demonstrate an improvement in the overall survival (OS) in patients with MTC who have been Presence of a measurable tumour as defined by (a) a solitary lesion measuring ≥2 cm or for symptomatic or uncontrolled atrial fibrillation despite treatment, or asymptomatic sustained treated with vandetanib as compared to placebo multiple lesions, the following criteria applied: ventricular tachycardia. Patients with atrial fibrillation controlled by medication were permitted.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Congenital long QT syndrome or 1st degree relative with unexplained sudden death under 40 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>of age</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>QT prolongation with other medications that required discontinuation of that medication</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Presence of left bundle branch block (LBBB)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>QTc with Bazett's correction unmeasurable or ≥480 ms on screening electrocardiogram (ECG)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Hypertension not controlled by medical therapy (systolic blood pressure&gt;160 millimeter of mercury</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>[mmHg] or diastolic blood pressure &gt;100 mmHg)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Negative pregnancy test for female patients of childbearing potential To determine the mutational status of the rearranged during transfection (RET) proto-oncogene in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) extracted from tumour samples</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Exclusion criteria Outcomes/endpoints</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Primary endpoint</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">the Amended CSP Major surgery within 4 weeks of randomisation The last dose of prior chemotherapy was received less than 4 weeks prior to randomisation Previous exposure to vandetanib Currently pregnant or breast feeding Involvement in the planning and conduct of the study Previous randomisation or treatment in the present study Progression-free survival (Secondary endpoints       </cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Radiation therapy within the last 4 weeks prior to randomisation (with the exception of palliative</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>radiotherapy)</cell></row></table><note> Secondary efficacy endpoints included overall Respose Rate (ORR) by RECIST, overall survival (OS) and biochemical response rate: CTN and CEA.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 6 : Summary of demographic characteristics (ITT Analysis Set)</head><label>6</label><figDesc>of previous thyroidectomy was noted in 90.3% of patients, diarrhoea in 45.0%, and fatigue in 15.4%.RET mutation status was determined to be positive in 187 (56.5%) patients, negative in 8 patients (2.4%), and unknown in 136 (41.1%) patients. Thus, while all but 2 patients provided an archived tumour sample for RET mutation analysis, the complete mutation analysis comprising the ARMS assay for M918T and the 6-exon sequencing was not successful for all patients, suggesting that the quality of the archived samples may have been inadequate for the comprehensive sequencing analyses.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vandetanib 300mg (N=231)</cell><cell>Placebo (N=100/ = 99 for weight)</cell><cell>Total (N=331)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years)</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>50.7</cell><cell>53.4</cell><cell>51.5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>14.1</cell><cell>12.0</cell><cell>13.6</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Median</cell><cell>50.0</cell><cell>52.5</cell><cell>51.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>26</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Max</cell><cell>83</cell><cell>84</cell><cell>84</cell></row><row><cell>Age group</cell><cell>≥18 -&lt;40</cell><cell>50 ( 21.6)</cell><cell>10 ( 10.0)</cell><cell>60 ( 18.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>≥40 -&lt;65</cell><cell>132 ( 57.1)</cell><cell>70 ( 70.0)</cell><cell>202 ( 61.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>≥65 -&lt;75</cell><cell>42 ( 18.2)</cell><cell>17 ( 17.0)</cell><cell>59 ( 17.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>≥75</cell><cell>7 ( 3.0)</cell><cell>3 ( 3.0)</cell><cell>10 ( 3.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Sex n (%)</cell><cell>Male</cell><cell>134 ( 58.0)</cell><cell>56 ( 56.0)</cell><cell>190 ( 57.4)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Female</cell><cell>97 ( 42.0)</cell><cell>44 ( 44.0)</cell><cell>141 ( 42.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Race n (%)</cell><cell>Black</cell><cell>1 ( 0.4)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>2 ( 0.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Caucasian</cell><cell>218 ( 94.4)</cell><cell>97 ( 97.0)</cell><cell>315 ( 95.2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Oriental</cell><cell>8 ( 3.5)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>9 ( 2.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Other</cell><cell>4 ( 1.7)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>5 ( 1.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Weight (kg)</cell><cell>Mean</cell><cell>70.4</cell><cell>70.2</cell><cell>70.3</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SD</cell><cell>17.3</cell><cell>16.8</cell><cell>17.2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Median</cell><cell>68.0</cell><cell>69.0</cell><cell>68.0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Min</cell><cell>38</cell><cell>36</cell><cell>36</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Max</cell><cell>125</cell><cell>115</cell><cell>125</cell></row><row><cell>A medical history</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 7 . Number analysed Number of patients Vandetanib 300 mg Placebo Total</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Patients randomised</cell><cell>231</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>331</cell></row><row><cell>Patients included in Safety Analysis Set</cell><cell>231</cell><cell>99</cell><cell>330</cell></row><row><cell>Patients excluded from Safety Analysis Set</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Randomised but not received blinded treatment 0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Patients included in Full Analysis Set</cell><cell>231</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>331</cell></row><row><cell>Patients included in Per-Protocol Analysis Set</cell><cell>215</cell><cell>91</cell><cell>307</cell></row><row><cell>Patients excluded from Per-Protocol Analysis Set</cell><cell>16</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>25</cell></row><row><cell>Patients included in PK Analysis Set</cell><cell>231</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>231</cell></row><row><cell>Patients excluded from PK Analysis Set</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>No evaluable PK sample</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>Outcomes and estimation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Primary endpoint</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Treatment effect</cell></row><row><cell>(vandetanib:placebo)</cell></row></table><note>Primary analysis of PFS (ITT)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 9 . Sensitivity analyses of PFS /analysis methods</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Treatment effect</cell></row><row><cell>(vandetanib:placebo)</cell></row><row><cell>--</cell></row></table><note>a Log rank test with treatment as the only factor in the PP analysis set.b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 10 . Sensitivity analyses of PFS -derivations of PFS (ITT)</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Treatment effect</cell></row><row><cell>(vandetanib:placebo)</cell></row><row><cell>--</cell></row></table><note>a PFS was imputed for patients who took open label treatment in the absence of progression based on changes in TL size whilst on randomized treatment.b PFS derivation used site read RECIST assessments, excluding any assessments of scans performed whilst on open label treatment.c PFS derivation treated 1st appearance of hypointense or hypodense lesions in the 1st 2 follow-up scans as PD on that scan date.d PFS derivation did not use the correction for calcified lesions. log rank test with treatment as the only factor.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 11 . ORR (ITT Set)</head><label>11</label><figDesc>ORR by site read assessment (excluding the open label period) was respectively 39% vs. 2.0%. None of the patients had complete response; the absence of response was due to stable disease in respectively 49.4% and 70% of the patients and disease progression 3.9% and 13.0% of the patients in the vandetanib and placebo treatment groups.Median DOR could not be calculated for either group.There was an improvement in TWP (derived using the worst pain score from BPI and patient reported analgesic use) for vandetanib compared with placebo: HR 0.61, 95% CI (0.43, 0.87), p=0.0062; this was confirmed by sensitivity analyses that used the Cox proportional hazards. The median time to deterioration in worsening of pain was 7.85 months vs. 3.25 months in the placebo arm.There were no observed differences between treatment groups for most exploratory variables such as time to deterioration in WHO PS [32.5 % vs. 34.0 %, HR 0.74, 95% CI (0.48, 1.14), p=0.1654, stool frequency, FACT_G score, or opioid analgesic medication use [OR 2.78, 95% CI 0.77 to 10.80, p=0.1193].</figDesc><table><row><cell>Treatment effect</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(vandetanib:placebo)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Randomised treatment</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>Number (%) of responses</cell><cell>Odds ratio</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>2-sided p-value</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">(a) primary analysis using a logistic regression model with treatment as the only factor.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Vandetanib 300mg</cell><cell cols="2">231 104 (45.0)</cell><cell>5.48</cell><cell>(2.99, 10.79)</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001</cell></row><row><cell>Placebo</cell><cell cols="2">100 13 ( 13.0)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>OS Figure 4: Kaplan-Meier plot of OS (ITT) No significant positive effect of vandetanib over placebo has been demonstrated on OS: HR of 0.89 (0.28, 2.85). In MTC setting, even at metastatic stage, OS is fair; one should also note that open label use of vandetanib was allowed after progression and cross-over from placebo (randomised treatment) to open label vandetanib was chosen in 58 of the 100 ITT placebo patients.Time to worsening of pain (Patient reported outcome) and other secondary endpoints</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>All patients included in the phase II supportive trials (Studies 08 and 68) had hereditary MTC, documented as RET positive in all patients in study 08 and RET positive in 17/19 and unknown in 2/19 in study 68. Patients included in the pivotal phase III trial (Study 58) had either sporadic or hereditary MTC. Out of 331 patients, 287 (86.7%) had sporadic MTC, 33 (10.0%) patients had hereditary MTC (more, n=28 in the vandetanib vs. n=5 in the placebo group), and 11 (3.3%) patients had unknown status. Diagnosis of hereditary MTC was based on family history if RET mutation status was unavailable. Patients with hereditary MTC who had a documented germline mutation in RET were not required to provide a mandatory tumour collection sample. All patients with sporadic MTC had to submit a suitable archived tumour sample before randomisation. Measurement of RET mutation status in the RET proto-oncogene was (after amendment) a secondary objective and was performed on a tumour samples from all patients who did not have a documented germline RET mutation. RET mutation was positive in 187 (56.5%) patients, unknown in 138 (41.1%), and shown negative in only 8 patients (2.4%), including 2 patients in the vandetanib group. At 12 months, the progression rate (vandetanib vs. placebo) was 34.3 % (47/137) vs. 54.0 % (27/50) in patients with RET + status, Correlation between RET mutation status and clinical outcome could not be clearly evaluated in study 58 because in 41.1%% of patients in study 58 RET mutation status was unknown.</figDesc><table><row><cell>27.2 % (25/92) vs. 43.2 % (19/44) in patients with RET unknown status and 50.0 % (1/2) vs. 83.3 %</cell></row><row><cell>(5/6) in patients with RET -status, respectively.</cell></row></table><note>Study 058 initially had a co-primary analysis population to evaluate the efficacy of vandetanib in patients with a RET mutation as well as in the overall population which was removed when the RET could not be determined for a major proportion of patients after completion of recruitment.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>Table 12 . Efficacy endpoints in RET mutation positive patients and the 79 patients proven without M918T mutation and with no other RET mutation identified.</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Efficacy Endpoint</cell><cell>RET Mutation Positive (n=187) a</cell><cell>Patients with No M918T Mutation and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No Other Identified</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Mutation (n=79)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">PFS HR (95% confidence interval)</cell><cell>0.45 (0.26, 0.78)</cell><cell>0.57 (0.29, 1.13)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Predicted median PFS (months)</cell><cell>29 vs. 18</cell><cell>28 vs. 18</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(vandetanib vs. placebo)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Objective response rate (vandetanib arm) 52%</cell><cell>35%</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Duration of response (months)</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>a</cell><cell cols="2">RET mutation positive hereditary and sporadic MTC patients</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head>Table 12</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Absolute difference was 17%, and relative difference was 33%. Vandetanib is suggested to prolong PFS compared to placebo in that subgroup, with a HR for PFS of 0.57 [95% CI 0.29-1.13]. The results are not significant in the RET negative patients as the higher bound of the 95% CI is over 1 (1.13) and the HR for PFS is lower in RET mutation negative' patients as defined above as compared with RET positive patients [HR for PFS =0.45 95% CI 0.26-0.78]. Duration of response is 18 months instead of 22 months (absolute difference 4 months, relative difference 18 % shorter).Predicted mean PFS is similar (29 vs. 28) and longer than placebo (18 months). 4 weeks later. PR was define as decrease in the CTN/CEA level of at least 50% from baseline confirmed by a repeat assessment &gt; 4 weeks later.In the phase II study (Study 08) with vandetanib 300 mg, CTN response was observed in 80% (24/30) of patients and CEA response in 53% (16/30) of patients. In the phase II study with vandetanib 100 mg (68), CTN response was observed in 15.8% of patients (3/19 patients) who experienced a reduction in CTN of at least 50% that was sustained for at least 4 weeks; 5.3 % of patients (1/19 patients) experienced a reduction in CEA of at least 50% from baseline that was sustained for at least</figDesc><table><row><cell>Biochemical</cell></row></table><note>compares the efficacy analysis observed in RET mutation positive patients versus RET mutation negative patients (defined as having no mutation at the most common site of RET mutation (M918T) and no other RET mutation identified) For vandetanib in 'RET mutation negative' patients, the ORR was 35% [16 /46,] versus 52%.response rate: CTN and CEA Biochemical response rate (CTN and CEA), markers of activity of vandetanib in MTC, were evaluated as secondary efficacy endpoints in the 3 clinical studies in MTC, the open phase II (Study 08 and 68) and in the pivotal phase II-III study vs. placebo (Study 58) as percentage of patients with a best biochemical response (respectively CTN / CEA) of CR or PR. CR was defined as complete normalization of the CTN level (≤10 pg/ml for men and ≤5 pg/ml for women) /CEA level (2.5 pg/ml) confirmed by a repeat assessment &gt;CTN doubling time ≤ 24 months and CEA doubling time ≤24 months are known to be markers of poor prognosis and more aggressive disease. In study 58, the efficacy of vandetanib on PFS was more marked in comparison with placebo in patients with CTN doubling time ≤ 24 months and CEA doubling time ≤24 months (statistically significant difference versus placebo in these subgroups). Forest plots of subgroup analyses for PFS (according to baseline characteristics, disease status and biomarkers) have been submitted. As the global interaction test was not statistically significant at the 1% level (p=0.177), unplanned post hoc individual interaction tests were performed with a 10% significance level for all factors included in the forest plots. The percentage of patients with ORR was higher in patients with CEA doubling time ≤24 months at baseline compared with CEA doubling time &gt;24 months: 53.6% versus 37 % respectively. The percentage of patients with ORR was higher in patients with CTN doubling time ≤24 months at baseline compared with CTN doubling time &gt;24 months: 46.8% vs. 39.8 % respectively.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 13 . Summary of Efficacy for pivotal Study 058 Title</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Locally</cell></row></table><note>: An International, Phase III, Randomized, Double-Blinded, Placebo-Controlled, Multi-Centre Study To Assess the Efficacy of ZD6474 versus Placebo in Subjects with Unresectable</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>with the 19.3 months median PFS in the placebo arm. The gain in PFS was maintained over time. Post-hoc sensitivity analysis of PFS adjusting for CTN and for CEA at baseline were performed and did not show any influence of baseline imbalance in CTN values and CEA values. Except for response in terms of CEA doubling time, the superiority of vandetanib over placebo on PFS was consistent across all pre planned subgroups, even if not significant in all of them.</figDesc><table><row><cell>The results observed on PFS were supported by results on some secondary endpoints such as ORR (45</cell></row><row><cell>% vs. 13.0 %, OR 5.48 (2.99, 10.79), &lt;0.0001 for the primary analysis). The results on biochemical</cell></row><row><cell>response also supported the primary endpoint. For CTN OR = 72.86, 95% CI of 26.22, 303.2;</cell></row><row><cell>p&lt;0.0001 and for CEA OR = 52.03; 95% CI of 15.95, 320.3; p&lt;0.0001 with more marked effect of</cell></row><row><cell>vandetanib on PFS in patients with more aggressive stage of the disease characterised by CTN</cell></row><row><cell>doubling time ≤ 24 months and CEA doubling time ≤24 months. No significant positive effect of</cell></row><row><cell>vandetanib over placebo has been demonstrated on OS: HR of 0.89 (0.28, 2.85). It is likely that it will</cell></row><row><cell>not be possible (even with more mature data) to establish a long term survival outcome from the</cell></row><row><cell>pivotal study and this could be in part caused by the open label use of vandetanib after progression on</cell></row><row><cell>randomised treatment. Because of the proposed cross-over at progression, the OS comparison in fact</cell></row><row><cell>compares populations that differ mainly by the fact that vandetanib has been proposed early</cell></row><row><cell>(experimental group) or later on, at progression (placebo arm).</cell></row><row><cell>characteristics, with the exception of age. Of 331 patients, 287 (86.7%) had sporadic MTC, 33 (10.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>patients had hereditary MTC, and 11 (3.3%) patients had unknown status. The patients who</cell></row><row><cell>participated in this study were generally representative of a population of patients with unresectable</cell></row><row><cell>locally advanced or metastatic MTC population, and their demographic and baseline characteristics</cell></row><row><cell>generally resembled those in the target population. There was a statistically significant difference at</cell></row><row><cell>baseline in the % of patients &lt;40 years of age in the vandetanib and placebo group, p=0.02. Age was</cell></row><row><cell>not a pre-planned subgroup analysis for efficacy data.</cell></row></table><note>A significant increase in PFS versus placebo on the primary analysis (HR=0.46, 95% CI, 0.31 to 0.69, p=0.0001) was observed. The predicted median PFS (Weibull model) for the vandetanib arm was 30.5 months, which is approximately an 11-month delay for the vandetanib arm when compared95% of the study population had metastases at baseline. Because of the very small number of patients without metastasis treated with vandetanib (14 patients only), no firm conclusion can be made about efficacy and B/R in patients without metastasis.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head>Table 14 . Summary of patients who had dose reductions and/or interruptions whilst on randomised treatment (Safety Analysis Set)</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Actual dose</cell><cell>Reason for dose</cell><cell>Vandetanib</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>level</cell><cell>change</cell><cell>N=231 (%)</cell><cell>N=99 (%)</cell><cell>N=330 (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Original dose level</cell><cell>300 mg /day</cell><cell></cell><cell>231 (100.0)</cell><cell>99 (100.0)</cell><cell>330 (100.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Dose reduction or dose</cell><cell></cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>114 ( 49.4)</cell><cell>15 ( 15.2)</cell><cell>129 ( 39.1)</cell></row><row><cell>interruption</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dose reductions</cell><cell>200 mg /day</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>81 ( 35.1)</cell><cell>3 ( 3.0)</cell><cell>84 ( 25.5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>19 ( 8.2)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>20 ( 6.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>19 ( 8.2)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>19 ( 5.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>5 ( 2.2)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>5 ( 1.5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>5 ( 2.2)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>6 ( 1.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>QTc Prolongation</cell><cell>16 ( 6.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>16 ( 4.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>9 ( 3.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>9 ( 2.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>6 ( 2.6)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>6 ( 1.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Other</cell><cell>9 ( 3.9)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>10 ( 3.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>200 mg every</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>1 ( 0.4)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>1 ( 0.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>other day</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>1 ( 0.4)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>1 ( 0.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>100 mg /</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>32 ( 13.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>32 ( 9.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>day</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>9 ( 3.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>9 ( 2.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>6 ( 2.6)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>6 ( 1.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>1 ( 0.4)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>1 ( 0.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>4 ( 1.7)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>4 ( 1.2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>QTc Prolongation</cell><cell>8 ( 3.5)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>8 ( 2.4)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>3 ( 1.3)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>3 ( 0.9)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>2 ( 0.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>2 ( 0.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Other</cell><cell>2 ( 0.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>2 ( 0.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Dose interruptions</cell><cell>0 mg</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>109 ( 47.2)</cell><cell>15 ( 15.2)</cell><cell>124 ( 37.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>33 ( 14.3)</cell><cell>7 ( 7.1)</cell><cell>40 ( 12.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>46 ( 19.9)</cell><cell>4 ( 4.0)</cell><cell>50 ( 15.2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea &lt;grade 3</cell><cell>7 ( 3.0)</cell><cell>2 ( 2.0)</cell><cell>9 ( 2.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>10 ( 4.3)</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>11 ( 3.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Non-compliance</cell><cell>2 ( 0.9)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>2 ( 0.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>QTc Prolongation</cell><cell>19 ( 8.2)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>19 ( 5.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash &lt; grade 3</cell><cell>3 ( 1.3)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>3 ( 0.9)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rash ≥ grade 3</cell><cell>12 ( 5.2)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>12 ( 3.6)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>141 SAEs and 6 fatal SAEs have been reported in 99.6% vandetanib patients. In placebo arm: 666 AEs including 46 grade 3-4 AEs, 19 SAEs and 2 fatal SAEs have been reported in 90.9% patients. The same pattern of AEs events identified during the clinical development of vandetanib is retrieved in study 58. The 5 most frequently reported AEs were diarrhoea, rash, nausea, hypertension, and headache. The percentage of patients with grade ≥ 3 AEs was 2.3 fold higher in vandetanib than in placebo arms: 55.4% vs 24.2%. (See table below).</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 15 . Summary of patients who had at least 1 AE in any category whilst on randomized treatment (Safety analysis set)</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>AE category</cell><cell>Vandetanib 300mg (N=231) (%) a</cell><cell>Placebo (N=99) (%) a</cell><cell>Total number (%) of patients (N=330)</cell></row><row><cell>Any AEs</cell><cell>230 ( 99.6)</cell><cell>90 ( 90.9)</cell><cell>320 ( 97.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Any vandetanib causally b related AE</cell><cell>222 ( 96.1)</cell><cell>59 ( 59.6)</cell><cell>281 ( 85.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Any AEs of grade 3 and higher</cell><cell>128 ( 55.4)</cell><cell>24 ( 24.2)</cell><cell>152 ( 46.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Any SAEs (including events with outcome = death)</cell><cell>71 ( 30.7)</cell><cell>13 ( 13.1)</cell><cell>84 ( 25.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Any SAEs with outcome = death</cell><cell>5 ( 2.2)</cell><cell>2 ( 2.0)</cell><cell>7 ( 2.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Any AEs leading to discontinuation of vandetanib</cell><cell>28 ( 12.1)</cell><cell>3 ( 3.0)</cell><cell>31 ( 9.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Any other significant AEs c</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell></row></table><note>a Patients with multiple events in the same category are counted only once in that category.b</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Table 16 .Summary of grouped AEs whilst on randomized treatment -based on MedDRA groupings (Safety analysis set)</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">__Vandetanib 300mg (N=231)__</cell><cell cols="2">__Placebo (N=99)__</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Grouped event type</cell><cell>Maximum CTCAE Grade</cell><cell>Number (%) of patients a</cell><cell>Event rate (per 1000 pt years)</cell><cell>Number (%) of patients a</cell><cell>Event rate (per 1000 pt years)</cell><cell>Total number (%) of patients (N=330)</cell></row><row><cell>Rash</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>205 ( 88.7)</cell><cell>3942.9</cell><cell>23 ( 23.2)</cell><cell>279.5</cell><cell>228 ( 69.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 1</cell><cell>112 ( 48.5)</cell><cell>591.3</cell><cell>22 ( 22.2)</cell><cell>265.8</cell><cell>134 ( 40.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 2</cell><cell>77 ( 33.3)</cell><cell>346.3</cell><cell>1 ( 1.0)</cell><cell>9.8</cell><cell>78 ( 23.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 3</cell><cell>15 ( 6.5)</cell><cell>48.1</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell>15 ( 4.5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 4</cell><cell>1 ( 0.4)</cell><cell>3.0</cell><cell>0 ( 0.0)</cell><cell>0.0</cell><cell>1 ( 0.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhoea</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>131 ( 56.7)</cell><cell>845.4</cell><cell>27 ( 27.3)</cell><cell>334.5</cell><cell>158 ( 47.9)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 1</cell><cell>60 ( 26.0)</cell><cell>237.3</cell><cell>17 ( 17.2)</cell><cell>194.1</cell><cell>77 ( 23.3)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 17 . Adverse drug reactions and system organ class</head><label>17</label><figDesc>In contrast, in Placebo arm, there were 2 deaths related to gastrointestinal SAE, 5 deaths with objective progression, and 4 deaths that would be due to MTC (no objective progression). Diarrhoea, which is one of the frequent symptoms of MTC, especially in patients with high CTN levels, was reported in 56% of vandetanib patients at all grades in study 58, i.e. a 2-fold increased percentage compared with placebo. It was the most common grade ≥3 AE reported in vandetanib patients (# 11%), with a time to onset of 151 days (range 9 to 415). At least, two patients experienced a SAE. Overall, the prevalence of diarrhea reaches approximately 40% at 3 months for all grades and does not increase after the first 3 months. The median duration was 267.5 days for the vandetanib arm and 49.5 days for the placebo arm. The management of diarrhea and vomiting which should include the monitoring of electrolytes is a major concern because of the increased risk of QTc prolongation. A bowel perforation occurred in a patient with a history of diverticulosis, 16 months after the start of vandetanib. Intestinal perforation is a identified risk in MTC patients receiving vandetanib.  3 cases of pancreatitis have been reported with vandetanib during the study: one in the randomised phase and 2 during the open label phase.</figDesc><table><row><cell>System Organ</cell><cell>Very commom</cell><cell>Common</cell><cell>Uncommon</cell></row><row><cell>Class</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Infection and</cell><cell>Nasopharyngitis</cell><cell>Pneumonia, sepsis, influenza,</cell><cell>Appendicitis,</cell></row><row><cell>infestation</cell><cell>bronchitis, upper</cell><cell>cystitis, sinusitis, laryngitis,</cell><cell>staphloccocal</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell>respiratory tract</cell><cell>folliculitis, furuncle, fungal</cell><cell>infection,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>infections, urinary tract</cell><cell>infection, pyelonephritis</cell><cell>diverticulitis,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>infections</cell><cell></cell><cell>cellulitis, abdominal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>wall abscess</cell></row><row><cell>Endocrine</cell><cell></cell><cell>Hypothyroidism</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Metabolism and nutrition disorders</cell><cell>Appetite decreased, Hypocalcaemia</cell><cell>Hypokalaemia, hypercalcaemia,</cell><cell>Malnutrition</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>hyperglycemia, dehydration,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>hyponatremia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Psychiatric disorders</cell><cell>Insomnia, Depression</cell><cell>Anxiety</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Nervous sytem</cell><cell>Headache, parasthesia,</cell><cell>Tremor, lethargy, loss of</cell><cell>Convulsion, clonus,</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell>dysaesthesia, dizziness</cell><cell>consciousness, balance</cell><cell>brain oedema</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>disorders, dysgeusia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Eye disorders</cell><cell>Vision blurred, corneal</cell><cell>Visual impairment, halo</cell><cell>Cataract,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>structural change</cell><cell>vision, photopsia, glaucoma,</cell><cell>accomodation</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(including corneal</cell><cell>conjunctivitis, dry eye,</cell><cell>disorders</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>deposits and corneal</cell><cell>keratopathy</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>opacity)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cardiac disorders</cell><cell>Prolongation of ECG QT</cell><cell></cell><cell>Heart failure, acute</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>interval(*)(**)</cell><cell></cell><cell>heart failure, rate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and rhythm</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>disorders, cardiac</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>conduction</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>disorders,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>ventricular</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>arrhythmia and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cardiac arrest</cell></row><row><cell>Vascular disorders</cell><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell>Hypertensive crisis, ischemic</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>cerebrovascular conditions</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal</cell><cell></cell><cell>Epistaxis, hemoptysis, pneumonitis</cell><cell>Respiratory failure, pneumonia aspiration</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gastrointestinal</cell><cell>Abdominal pain,</cell><cell>Colitis, dry mouth, stomatitis,</cell><cell>Pancreatitis,</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell>diarrhoea, nausea,</cell><cell>dysphagia, constipation,</cell><cell>peritonitis, ileus,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>vomiting, dyspepsia</cell><cell>gastritis, gastrointestinal</cell><cell>intestinal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>haemorrhage</cell><cell>perforation, faecal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>incontinence</cell></row><row><cell>Hepatobiliary</cell><cell></cell><cell>Cholelithiasis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Skin and</cell><cell>Photosensitivity reaction,</cell><cell>Palmar-plantar</cell><cell>Bullous dermatitis</cell></row><row><cell>subcutaneous</cell><cell>rash and other skin</cell><cell>erythrodysaesthiesia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>tissue disorders</cell><cell>rections (including acne,</cell><cell>syndrome, alopecia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dry skin, dermatitis,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pruritis), nail disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Renal and urinary disorders</cell><cell>Proteinuria, nephrolithiasis</cell><cell>Dysuria, hematuria, renal failure, pollakiuria,</cell><cell>Chromaturia, anuria</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>micturition urgency</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_31"><head>Table 18 . Shift table of creatinine clearance at baseline against maximum percentage decrease in creatinine clearance whilst on randomised treatment (Study 48)</head><label>18</label><figDesc>Reported incidences of insomnia and depression were more frequently reported in vandetanib patients than in placebo arm. Importantly, one patient died of a suicide 103 days after receiving his last dose of vandetanib during open-label treatment.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Based on the table above, 21% patients with a normal renal function had a decreased creatinine</cell></row><row><cell>clearance &gt; 20% (decrease&gt;30% in 9% patients). Furthermore, 51.5% mild renal impaired patients</cell></row><row><cell>had a decreased creatinine clearance &gt; 20% (decrease&gt; 30% in 28.6% patients). These figures show</cell></row><row><cell>evidence of the vandetanib nephrotoxicity.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_32"><head>Table 19 . Laboratory findings Laboratory finding</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Protein in urine by dipstick 1</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Blood in urine by dipstick 1</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Increased serum TSH</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Increased serum amylase</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Increased serum lipase</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Increased haemoglobin</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Increased serum creatinine 2</cell><cell>Very common</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell cols="2">Incidence of laboratory findings in a randomised clinical trial in medullary thyroid cancer, not of reported</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>adverse events.</cell></row></table><note>2</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Combinations not recommended: methadone, haloperidol, amisulpride, chlorpromazine, sulpiride, and zuclopenthixol), halofantrine, pentamidine and lumefantrine.If there is no appropriate alternative therapy, not recommended combinations of such medicinal products with vandetanib may be made with additional ECG monitoring of the QTc interval, evaluation of electrolytes and further control at onset or worsening of diarrhoea.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">a statement in section 4.5 of the SmPC noting that Posterior reversible encephalopathy</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">syndrome, PRES (Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome-RPLS) has been</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">observed infrequently with vandetanib treatment in combination with chemotherapy. PRES has</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">also been observed in patients receiving vandetanib as monotherapy. This syndrome should be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">considered in any patient presenting with seizures, headache, visual disturbances, confusion or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">altered mental function. Brain MRI should be performed in any patient presenting with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">seizures, confusion or altered mental status.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>).</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">a precaution in section 4.4 of the SmPC with regards to QTc prolongation. Patients who</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">develop a single value of a QTc interval of greater than 500 msec should stop taking</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">vandetanib. Dosing can be resumed at a reduced dose after return of the QTc interval to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">pretreatment status has been confirmed and correction of possible electrolyte imbalance has</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">been made.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">a statement in section 4.5 of the SmPC noting that Vandetanib has been shown to prolong the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ECG QT interval and Torsades de Pointes have been uncommonly reported. Therefore, the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">concomitant use of vandetanib with drugs known to also prolong the QT interval and / or</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">induce Torsades de Pointes is either contra-indicated or not recommended depending on</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">existing alternative therapies:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Combinations contraindicated: cisapride, erythromycine IV, toremifen, mizolastine,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>moxifloxacine, arsenic, ,Class I A and III antiarrhythmics</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_36"><head>Table 20 . Summary of the risk management plan Safety concern/missing information Proposed pharmacovigilance activities (routine and additional) Proposed risk minimisation activities (routine and additional</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-glycoprotein (P-gp). The co-administration of vandetanib and medicinal products excreted by P-gp, such as dabigatran or digoxin, may result in increased plasma concentrations of these medicinal products. Patients receiving dabigatran or digoxin and vandetanib may require increased clinical and biological surveillance and appropriate dose adjustments, if needed.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Description</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Due date</cell></row><row><cell>efflux pump P</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Routine pharmacovigilance practices,</cell><cell cols="2">Section 4.2 of the SmPC</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>signal identification, and review</cell><cell cols="2">states: Clinical data suggest</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">that no change in starting dose</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">is required in patients with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">mild renal impairment. There</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">is limited data with 300 mg in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">patients with moderate renal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">impairment: the dose needed</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">to be lowered to 200 mg in 5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">out of 6 patients. The starting</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">dose could be reduced to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">200 mg in patients with</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">moderate (creatinine clearance</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">≥30 and &lt;50 ml/min) renal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">impairment; safety and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">efficacy have however not</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">been established with 200 mg.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Vandetanib is not</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">recommended for use in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">patients with severe</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(creatinine clearance below</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">30 ml/min) renal impairment</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">since there is limited data in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">patients with severe renal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">impairment, and safety and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">efficacy have not been</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">established.</cell></row><row><cell>Use in paediatric patient population</cell><cell>Routine pharmacovigilance practices,</cell><cell cols="2">The safety and efficacy in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>signal identification, and review</cell><cell cols="2">children has not been</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Two paediatric studies (IRUZACT0004, and IRUZACT0098) are ongoing.</cell><cell cols="2">established. Therefore vandetanib is not indicated for use in paediatric patients.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">HCP Healthcare professional; ILD Interstitial lung disease; PRES Posterior Reversible Encephalopathy Syndrome.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">The below pharmacovigilance activities in addition to the use of routine pharmacovigilance are needed</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">to investigate further some of the safety concerns:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Description</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Due date</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Study D4200C00097, an international, double-blind, two-arm study to evaluate the safety and efficacy of vandetanib 150mg and 300mg/day in patients with</cell><cell>October 2015</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">unresectable locally advanced or metastatic medullary thyroid carcinoma with</cell></row><row><cell>progressive or symptomatic disease.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Study IRUZACT0004, a Phase I Study of the Combination of Vandetanib and</cell><cell></cell><cell>July 2013</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Dasatinib Administered During and After Radiation Therapy in Children with Diffuse</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Intrinsic Pontine Glioma is being conducted in patients between the ages of 18 and</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">24 who will be dosed with vandetanib 50 to 110 mg/m 2 /d.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Study IRUZACT0098, a Phase I/II Trial of Vandetanib in Children and Adolescents</cell><cell>May 2015</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">with Hereditary Medullary Thyroid Cancer recruits patients between the ages of 5</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">to 18 years. Patients will begin on vandetanib 100 mg/m 2 /d, and will be escalated</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">to vandetanib 150 mg/m 2 /d if the lower dose is tolerated</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Vandetanib coadministered with digoxin. Vandetanib is a weak inhibitor of the</cell><cell>June 2013</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Summary of Product Characteristics and Package Leaflet  Educational material for Healthcare Professionals  Patient Alert Cards (text as agreed by the CHMP) The educational material for Healthcare Professionals should contain the following key elements:  Vandetanib prolongs the QTc interval and can cause Torsades de Pointes and sudden death Who have a history of Torsades de Pointes unless all risk factors that contributed to Torsades have been corrected.  The need for an ECG, and serum levels of potassium, calcium and magnesium and thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and the times and situations when it should be performed  Patients who develop a single value of corrected ECG QTc interval of at least 500 msec should stop taking vandetanib. Dosing can be resumed at a reduced dose after return of the ECG QTc interval to pretreatment status has been confirmed and correction of possible electrolyte imbalance has been made.  If QTc increases markedly but stays below 500 msec, the advice of a cardiologist should be sought.  Details of medicinal products where the co-administration of vandetanib is either contraindicated or not recommended.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Vandetanib treatment must not be started in patients:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>whose ECG QTc interval is greater than 480 msec</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Who have congenital long QTc syndrome</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note> That vandetanib may cause Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES) also known as Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Summary of Product Characteristics and Package Leaflet  Educational material for Healthcare Professionals  Patient Alert Cards (text as agreed by the CHMP) The educational material for Healthcare Professionals should contain the following key elements:  Vandetanib prolongs the QTc interval and can cause Torsades de Pointes and sudden death  Vandetanib treatment must not be started in patients:  whose ECG QTc interval is greater than 480 msec  Who have congenital long QTc syndrome  Who have a history of Torsades de Pointes unless all risk factors that contributed to Torsades have been corrected.  The need for an ECG, and serum levels of potassium, calcium and magnesium and thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) and the times and situations when it should be performed  Patients who develop a single value of corrected ECG QTc interval of at least 500 msec should stop taking vandetanib. Dosing can be resumed at a reduced dose after return of the ECG QTc interval to pretreatment status has been confirmed and correction of possible electrolyte imbalance has been made.  If QTc increases markedly but stays below 500 msec, the advice of a cardiologist should be sought.  Details of medicinal products where the co-administration of vandetanib is either contraindicated or not recommended.  That vandetanib may cause Posterior reversible encephalopathy syndrome (PRES) also known as Reversible posterior leukoencephalopathy syndrome (RPLS)  PRES should be considered in any patient presenting with seizures, headache, visual disturbances, confusion or altered mental function. Brain MRI should be performed in any patient presenting with seizures, confusion or altered mental status.  The need to counsel patients about the risk of prolonged QTc and PRES and inform them of what symptoms and signs to be aware of and the actions to take  The role and use of the Patient Alert Card</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">December 2015Assessment report Page 86/88</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p> PRES should be considered in any patient presenting with seizures, headache, visual disturbances, confusion or altered mental function. Brain MRI should be performed in any patient presenting with seizures, confusion or altered mental status.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><p>The need to counsel patients about the risk of prolonged QTc and PRES and inform them of what symptoms and signs to be aware of and the actions to take  The role and use of the Patient Alert Card</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Specific Obligation to complete post-authorisation measures for the conditional marketing authorisation</head><p>This being a conditional marketing authorisation and pursuant to Article 14(7) of Regulation (EC) No 726/2004, the MAH shall complete, within the stated timeframe, the following measures:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Description</head><p>Due date An open label trial based on a CHMP approved protocol, comparing RET negative and RET positive patients with sporadic medullary thyroid cancer treated with vandetanib. The study will include approximately 60 % of patients who receive vandetanib within the EU.</p><p>Inclusion criteria: to meet criteria based on SmPC indication. In addition, RET mutation negative patients who do not receive vandetanib due to RET status or contraindication will be allowed to enrol and followed.</p><p>Exclusion Criteria: limited to contraindications outlined in section 4.3 of the SmPC Data to be collected on study:  History and physical examination  RET mutation status </p><p>Patients not required to have tissue biopsy to determine RET status for enrolment RET mutation status: Patients will not be required to have a fresh tissue biopsy to determine RET status before enrolment. However investigator should be strongly requested to obtain a recent sample for determination of the RET status as often as possible, even in patients previously tested at an earlier stage of their disease. Determination of RET status should be made preferably just prior to the initiation of treatment. Tissue type used for assay, date of tissue biopsy, assay type and definition used for RET mutation positive and negative will be collected.</p><p>RET mutation negative patients who do not receive vandetanib due to RET status or contraindication will be allowed to enrol and followed.</p><p>RET mutation status should be assessed according to pre-defined mutational analysis, where type of test and exons to be analyzed are protocol pre-specified.</p><p> Safety Assessments at each visit including QT prolongation information. </p><p>Objective tumour responses / duration of response progression  Assessed in accordance with study physicians normal medical practice  Within a centre, patients will be assessed for efficacy in a consistent manner, irrespective of their RET status at pre-defined time points  Method used for assessment (e.g. CT, MRI)  Disease status at each efficacy visit: objective response, stable disease or progressive disease. </p><p>The final analysis will be performed when at least 40 patients identified with RET mutation and 40 patients identified without evidence of RET mutation have been enrolled into the study and received vandetanib for 14 months.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
