<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report 3. Benefit-Risk Balance............................................................................ 113 4. Recommendations ............................................................................... 117</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-04-01">1 April 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Churchill Place • Canary Wharf</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E14 5EU</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">European Union</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report 3. Benefit-Risk Balance............................................................................ 113 4. Recommendations ............................................................................... 117</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-04-01">1 April 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Darzalex International non-proprietary name: daratumumab Procedure No. EMEA/H/C/004077/0000 Note Assessment report as adopted by the CHMP with all information of a commercially confidential nature deleted. Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 2/119 Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 3/119 Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 4/119 Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 5/119 Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 6/119</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T03:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Telephone +44 (0)20 3660 6000 Facsimile +44 (0)20 3660 5555 Send a question via our website www.ema.europa.eu/contact</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Scientific discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.">Introduction</head><p>Multiple myeloma, which is a malignant disorder of the plasma cells, is diagnosed in approximately 114,000 patients per year worldwide, which includes over 33,000 patients from the European Union. The median age of patients at diagnosis is 65 years and the disease has a typical course characterized by a chronic phase and several relapses leading to an aggressive terminal phase. Progress, such that survival of patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma has increased from approximately 3 years with no improvement from the years <ref type="bibr">1985</ref><ref type="bibr">to 1998</ref><ref type="bibr">(Kyle 2003</ref> to 6 to 10 years today <ref type="bibr">(Moreau 2015)</ref>.</p><p>Despite these advances, multiple myeloma remains incurable. All patients eventually relapse. With each successive relapse, the chance of response and duration of response typically decreases. After relapse from PIs and IMiDs, patients are often retreated with drugs that have the same mechanism of action.</p><p>Ultimately, the disease becomes refractory. Patients who are heavily pretreated and/or refractory to both a PI and IMiD have a dismal prognosis, are difficult to get back into a durable remission, and median survival is only between 8 to 9 months <ref type="bibr">(Kumar 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Usmani 2015</ref><ref type="bibr">, Verelst 2015</ref>. The relapsed and refractory setting represents a serious and life threatening disease with an unmet medical need.</p><p>First line treatment options contain at least one of the novel therapies, i.e. proteasome inhibitors and/or immunostimulatory drugs, followed by autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT), if indicated. In Europe, bortezomib, thalidomide (as first line treatment) and lenalidomide are approved in combination regimens for the treatment of multiple myeloma.</p><p>Relapsed and/or refractory patients typically receive salvage therapy (if possible, this could include (2nd) autologous or allogeneic hematopoietic stem cell transplantation) until relapse or toxicity and then go onto the next salvage option. In this setting, for patients who have received at least 2 prior therapies, including bortezomib and an IMiD, and have shown relapsed or refractory disease, pomalidomide (in combination with dexamethasone) and panobinostat (in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone) are approved agents in the EU. The proteasome inhibitor carfilzomib and the monoclonal antibody elotuzumab both in combination with lenalidomide and dexamethasone were approved in the EU for the treatment of adult patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least one prior therapy.</p><p>In patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy there are not any treatment options, other than the physician's best choice and palliative care.</p><p>Daratumumab is an IgG1κ human monoclonal antibody (mAb) that binds to the CD38 protein expressed at a high level on the surface of multiple myeloma tumour cells, as well as other cell types and tissues at various levels. CD38 protein has multiple functions such as receptor mediated adhesion, signalling and enzymatic activity (SmPC section 5.1).</p><p>Daratumumab has been shown to potently inhibit the in vivo growth of CD38-expressing tumour cells.</p><p>Based on in vitro studies, daratumumab may utilize multiple effector functions, resulting in immune mediated tumour cell death. These studies suggest that daratumumab can induce tumour cell lysis through complement-dependent cytotoxicity, antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity (ADCC), and antibody-dependent cellular phagocytosis (ADCP) in malignancies expressing CD38. A subset of myeloid derived suppressor cells (CD38+MDSCs), regulatory T cells (CD38+Tregs) and B cells (CD38+Bregs) are susceptible to daratumumab mediated cell lysis (SmPC section 5.1).</p><p>Daratumumab induced apoptosis in vitro after Fc mediated cross linking. In addition, daratumumab modulated CD38 enzymatic activity, inhibiting the cyclase enzyme activity and stimulating the hydrolase activity. The significance of these in vitro effects in a clinical setting, and the implications on tumour growth, are not well-understood (SmPC section 5.1).</p><p>The sponsor applied for the following indication: Daratumumab Janssen-Cilag is indicated for the treatment of patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy.</p><p>The recommended indication for approval is: DARZALEX as monotherapy is indicated for the treatment of adult patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy (SmPC section 4.1)</p><p>The recommended dose is Daratumumab Janssen-Cilag 16 mg/kg body weight administered as an intravenous infusion weekly (weeks 1 to 8) then once every two weeks (weeks 9 to 24) and once every four weeks from week 25 onwards until disease progression (SmPC section 4.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Quality aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1.">Introduction</head><p>Daratumumab is a fully human immunoglobulin G1κ (IgG1κ) monoclonal antibody that binds to the extracellular domain of human CD38, a transmembrane glycoprotein.</p><p>The daratumumab finished product is supplied as a sterile 20 mg/mL liquid concentrate for solution for infusion in a Type I glass vial. After dilution in commercially available 0.9% sodium chloride, the product is intended for intravenous infusion. Two presentations are proposed for marketing authorisation: packs of 5 mL and 20 mL vials (one vial each).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Active Substance General Information</head><p>Daratumumab is a human monoclonal immunoglobulin G1 (IgG1). The intact molecule contains 2 identical heavy chains (HC) of 452 amino acids (approximately 51 kDa each) and 2 identical kappa light chains (LC) of 214 amino acids (approximately 24 kDa each). The 4 chains are linked together by covalent disulfide bonds and non-covalent protein-protein interactions.</p><p>The amino acid sequences were deduced by the Applicant from the complementary deoxyribonucleic acid (cDNA) sequence and confirmed by peptide mapping. The disulfide bonds were predicted from the expected pairings for a human IgG1 antibody and confirmed by peptide mapping. The N-linked glycans (glycosylation site located at HC Asn302) were shown to be bi-antennary structures typical for an IgG1 antibody expressed in CHO cells by oligosaccharide mapping with mass spectrometry analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture, characterisation and process controls</head><p>A concentrated viral inactivation and neutralisation (VIN) intermediate is manufactured by Biogen Inc. in Research Triangle Park, NC, USA. The daratumumab active substance is manufactured by Janssen Biologics (Ireland) in Cork, Ireland, and is designated as active substance.</p><p>Daratumumab active substance is manufactured in an 11-stage process consisting of fed batch cell culture followed by purification with a series of chromatography, viral inactivation and filtration steps.</p><p>Formulation also takes place at the active substance level. The concentrated viral inactivation and neutralisation (VIN) intermediate is obtained at Stage 5b.</p><p>There are 2 types of in-process controls (IPCs) in the daratumumab active substance process: (1) an IPC with an Acceptance Criterion, and (2) an IPC with a Predefined Instruction.</p><p>A list of IPCs with acceptance criteria used in the daratumumab active substance manufacturing process is provided. It includes a list of the process step in which the IPC test is performed, the test, and the associated acceptance criterion. Acceptance criteria that are exceeded must be investigated and may result in batch rejection. IPC tests for bioburden also have associated action limits that when exceeded, require response, investigation, and correction.</p><p>After Stage 5b, the concentrated VIN material is frozen at for up to and transported from Biogen Inc.</p><p>(BIIB), USA to Janssen Biologics, Ireland for further processing. Release and stability acceptance criteria are established for the stored VIN intermediate and cover testing of relevant quality attributes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Process Validation and/or Evaluation</head><p>Consideration of the process validation and process evaluation efforts began during development. The daratumumab active substance manufacture is developed by QbD concepts. Daratumumab critical quality attributes (CQAs) have been identified based on the quality target product profile (QTPP) for the finished product and scientific knowledge of the monoclonal antibodies. Based on process development and clinical manufacturing experience, criticality assessments were performed and critical quality attributes (CQAs), critical process parameters (CPPs), in-process controls (IPCs), and process monitoring tests (PMTs) were identified. Process parameter control ranges and acceptance criteria were established for CPPs and IPCs, respectively, to control CQAs according to predetermined CQA specifications, and were the basis of a high level process validation master plan and validation acceptance criteria in subordinate protocols. The identified CQAs represent the focal point for the subsequent control strategy development.</p><p>Process validation and evaluation studies were executed at both manufacturing and reduced scales according to the process validation master plan. Process intermediate hold times, chromatography resin lifetimes, and reprocessing steps at specific stages of the active substance process were validated in studies according to subordinate protocols. Resin lifetime limits will be verified during commercial processing until the maximum number of cycles or total contact time validated using reduced scale cycling studies is reached.</p><p>Following process validation, criticality assessments were repeated as part of the lifecycle management of the active substance manufacturing process. Reduced scale models were employed to evaluate and establish proven acceptable ranges (PARs) for parameters that were not challenged at manufacturing scale. Results from clinical manufacturing, process validation, and reduced scale studies were assessed to establish the final list of CPPs for the commercial-scale active substance manufacturing process.</p><p>An integrated control strategy for each stage of the daratumumab active substance manufacturing process as well as the control strategy for each of the identified CQAs are outlined. The overall control strategy includes relevant elements such as control of process parameters and process monitoring tests <ref type="bibr">(PMT)</ref>, which are established to ensure consistent process stage performance. Control of material attributes that enter the manufacturing process like e.g. raw materials, culture media and buffers, WCB</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3.">Finished Medicinal Product</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Description of the product and Pharmaceutical Development</head><p>The nominal composition of the finished product along with the function and grade of the excipients used in preparation of the finished product (glacial acetic acid, sodium acetate trihydrate, sodium chloride, mannitol, polysorbate 20 and water for injection) are provided for each presentation.</p><p>Based on the results from the process development studies, the commercial finished product manufacturing process was established at Cilag for the 100 mg/vial daratumumab finished product and at</p><p>Vetter for 100 and 400 mg/vial daratumumab finished product.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture of the product and process controls</head><p>Manufacture of the finished product is performed at the following facilities:</p><p>100 mg 100 mg and 400 mg Cilag A.G.</p><p>Vetter Pharma Fertigung GmbH &amp; Co. KG Hochstrasse 201</p><p>Mooswiesen 2 8200 Schaffhausen 88214 Ravensburg, Switzerland Germany</p><p>Batch release of the finished product is performed at the following facilities: Janssen Biologics B.V. Einsteinweg 101 2333 CB Leiden The Netherlands</p><p>An overview of the finished product manufacturing process and in-process controls is presented below.</p><p>The process consists of thawing active substance, pooling and mixings, prefiltration, sterile filtration, aseptic filling, stoppering and capping, inspection, secondary packaging, and finally storage at 2-8ºC.</p><p>CPPs and pCPPs were identified.</p><p>Process validation was performed in order to demonstrate the ability of the daratumumab finished product manufacturing process to consistently yield a final finished product meeting its predetermined specifications and quality attributes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Product specification</head><p>The release specification of the finished product includes control of identity, charge heterogeneity, purity, potency and other general tests.</p><p>Batches have been analysed and all results met the predetermined release acceptance criteria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stability of the product</head><p>Finished product batches were manufactured and placed in the stability-monitoring programs.</p><p>Based on the data provided a shelf life of 18 months for the finished product (unopened vials) when stored at the recommended temperature of 2-8 ºC and protected from light is considered acceptable.</p><p>Regarding in-use stability, from a microbiological point of view, unless the method of opening/ dilution precludes the risk of microbial contamination, the product should be used immediately. If not used immediately, in-use storage times and conditions are the responsibility of the user and should be no more than 24 hours at refrigerated conditions (2 °C -8 °C) protected from light, followed by 15 hours (including infusion time) at room temperature (15°C -25°C) and room light.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adventitious agents</head><p>During cell line development, rabbit serum and fetal bovine serum have been used. No animal-derived materials, however, have been used to prepare the master cell bank or working cell banks.</p><p>Mycoplasma and microbial bioburden are controlled through use of a sanitary process design and appropriate testing. Bioburden and endotoxin contamination is also evaluated as part of routine testing.</p><p>Manufacturing procedures and 0.2-µm filtration steps throughout the process minimize the risk of microbial contamination. Viral clearance is achieved through different steps in the purification process.</p><p>A viral safety factor for retrovirus-like particles (RVLP) in the manufacturing process was calculated from viral clearance values using xenotropic murine leukaemia virus (XMuLV), a specific model virus for the RVLP in the production CHO cell line used for clinical and commercial manufacturing.</p><p>The manufacturing process provides sufficient removal capacity.</p><p>With regard to non-specific model virus studies, cumulative minimum clearances were demonstrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4.">Discussion on chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>Overall, the Quality dossier is of high quality. No major issues were identified during the review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Active substance</head><p>The preparation of the MCB, WCB and Extended End of production cell bank (EEPCB) are described. These cell banks were characterised according to current guidelines to show their identity and freedom from adventitious agents. On request the generation and use of the, in total, three WCBs, has been described.</p><p>The first WCB generated was only used for the manufacture of the very early clinical material. The second WCB is currently used for production. A third WCB has been generated and will replace the second one, once it has depleted. A clear procedure to prepare future WCBs has been presented on request. Finally, EEPCB preparation has been described in sufficient detail. Careful product-and process development has been done with the use of all elements of QbD. CQAs has been identified. Most of the manufacturing process development work is described at high level, e.g. DoE's are described and results summarised but only very limited real data is presented. A reasonable and expected number and type of critical process parameters has been identified and no broad production or control flexibility is requested. Some steps of the process have, on a risk-based level, been chosen (production bioreactor, VIN intermediate and CEX) for more detailed review. A number of issues, for these steps needed further justification and/or clarification. This has been provided and do not call for comments.</p><p>Based on updated active substance stability data, the claimed shelf-life for active substance when stored at is accepted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Finished product</head><p>The use of tolerance intervals, as a statistical tool to set finished product (and active substance) specification acceptance criteria, called for concern but a justification was provided and the issue was considered resolved.</p><p>On request the Applicant has discussed the proposed acceptance criteria for all methods included in the finished product specification, taking into account the clinically qualified levels. The specification for potency (CDC and ADCC) and charge heterogeneity has been revised and is considered acceptable.</p><p>Acceptance criteria in the active substance specification have been revised accordingly.</p><p>Altogether, the data presented support the Daratumumab finished product shelf life claim of 18 months when stored at 2-8 ºC and protected from light. However, the Applicant is recommended to continue the stability studies on two 400 mg/vial finished product batches (engineering and clinical) and finished product 400 mg/vial process validation batches () stored at 2-8 ºC in order to confirm the stability profiles of these batches. Should any unexpected issues arise during the studies it is recommended that it is reported to the Rapporteur and the Agency immediately.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adventitious agents</head><p>Two minor issues needed to be solved: the Applicant was asked to provide i) retrovirus-like particles estimation for three unprocessed cell culture supernatant; and ii) raw data for Adventitious agents safety evaluation. These data were provided and the issues were considered resolved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5.">Conclusions on the chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>Overall, the quality of Darzalex is considered to be in line with the quality of other approved monoclonal antibodies. The different aspects of the chemical, pharmaceutical and biological documentation comply with existing guidelines. The fermentation and purification of the active substance are adequately described, controlled and validated. The active substance is well characterised with regard to its physicochemical and biological characteristics, using state-of-the-art methods, and appropriate specifications are set. The manufacturing process of the finished product has been satisfactorily described and validated. The quality of the finished product is controlled by adequate test methods and specifications.</p><p>Viral safety and the safety concerning other adventitious agents including TSE have been sufficiently assured.</p><p>The overall quality of Darzalex is considered acceptable when used in accordance with the conditions defined in the SmPC. However, a quality Recommendation has been made.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.6.">Recommendation for future quality development</head><p>In the context of the obligation of the MAHs to take due account of technical and scientific progress, the CHMP recommended a point for investigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Non-clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Introduction</head><p>Pivotal nonclinical safety studies were conducted in conformance with Good Laboratory Practice (GLP).</p><p>Daratumumab binds to human and chimpanzee CD38, but not to CD38 of species typically used for nonclinical toxicology testing, ie, mouse, rat, rabbit, pig, and cynomolgus and rhesus monkey. Therefore, another anti-CD38 mAb, HuMab-CD38, that binds human and cynomolgus monkey CD38 was also characterized and used in some exploratory studies. Normal human cells, cell lines expressing human CD38, and patient derived cells were used in vitro or in immunosuppressed mouse models for the pivotal pharmacology studies. Cynomolgus monkeys were used in pilot studies of HuMab-CD38.</p><p>Nonclinical PK of daratumumab was evaluated in the 6-week repeat-dose chimpanzee toxicology study.</p><p>PK of HuMab-CD38 was evaluated in the 2-week repeat-dose pilot cynomolgus monkey toxicology study.</p><p>The toxicology program for daratumumab consisted of a GLP 6-week repeat-dose toxicity study in chimpanzees, and in vitro tissue cross-reactivity studies using chimpanzee and human tissues. Additional supportive studies were conducted with HuMab-CD38, a mAb that binds cynomolgus CD38, and included a pilot, non-GLP 2-week repeat-dose toxicity study in cynomolgus monkeys, and an in vitro tissue cross-reactivity study with cynomolgus monkey tissues. Both in vivo repeat-dose studies utilized the intended clinical route of administration (ie, intravenous infusion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacodynamic studies</head><p>Binding characterization to human CD38</p><p>The CD38 epitope for binding of daratumumab was determined using the PEPSCAN method which showed that daratumumab bound to the C-terminal region of human CD38, amino acid [aa] 267 to 280) in combination with region aa 233 to 246. In addition, epitope mapping was done by site-directed mutagenesis which showed that the binding of daratumumab to CD38 is sensitive to mutations at positions 272 and 274 in the CD38 protein (Study GMB 3003-008).</p><p>The kinetics of daratumumab interaction with human CD38 were investigated by Biacore analysis, which revealed specific, saturable, and high-affinity binding, with a KD of 4.36x10 -9 M (Study GMB 3003-002).</p><p>HuMab-CD38 interaction with human CD38 showed a KD of 8.18 x10 -10 M.</p><p>ELISA analysis confirmed that daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 bind to hCD38 in a similar, concentration-dependent manner. EC 50 of daratumumab binding to hCD38 was achieved at 55.2 ng/mL (GMB 3003-002).</p><p>The binding of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 to cell surface-expressed CD38 was characterized by flow cytometry using Daudi cells, CHO transfected cells (CHO-CD38 cells), MM-derived cell lines and freshly isolated MM tumour cells. Daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 bound in a specific, dose-dependent manner.</p><p>The EC 50 values for binding to Daudi and CHO-CD38 cells were 0.26 and 0.47 μg/mL for daratumumab, and 0.99 and 0.96 μg/mL for HuMab-CD38, respectively (GMB 3003-002).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanism of action</head><p>The binding of daratumumab to CD38 on the surface of tumour cells and engagement/ligation of the Fc domains of bound antibodies leads to multiple biologic effects, including CDC, ADCC, ADCP, tumour cell apoptosis, and modulation of CD38 enzymatic activity in patient derived cells and cell lines expressing human CD38.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of Complement-Dependent Cytotoxicity</head><p>The capacity of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 to induce CDC was studied in vitro using several cell types and cell lines (GMB 3003-003):</p><p>Lysis of Daudi-luc cells: Daratumumab induced CDC with maximum lysis of 60%, whereas the surrogate antibody HuMab-CD38 was inefficient in inducing lysis, and did so only at very high concentrations.  Lysis of freshly-isolated MM cells: In 8 out of 12 evaluable tumour cell samples, daratumumab-induced lysis was greater than 48%. In the remaining four tumour cell samples, poor lysis was observed (&lt;23%).</p><p>With HuMab-CD38 (all forms), only two patients responded at the level of approximately 30% lysis. The mechanism underlying the differences in cell lysis among the patient-derived cells is not known, as levels of CD38 expression were not characterized.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of Antibody-Dependent Cell-Mediated Cytotoxicity</head><p>Target cells were loaded with 51 Cr, incubated with antibody and effector cells, and lysis was determined by measuring 51 Cr release (GMB 3003-004). In studies using the Daudi cell line, daratumumab induced ADCC with an average EC 50 of 20.9 ng/mL, compared to HuMab-CD38 (52.5 ng/mL) and rituximab (55.3 ng/mL). Similar results were seen in assays using MM-derived cell lines.</p><p>In freshly isolated myeloma cells, both CD38 Ab induced ADCC, although the extent of maximal lysis differed per tumour sample and was influenced by the origin of effector cell (PBMC from healthy volunteers). In a subcutaneous (SC) mouse model using Daudi-luc tumour cells, DARA-K322A provided stronger inhibition of tumour growth than the DARA-IgG2-K322A isoform, which has impaired phagocytosis-stimulatory capacity. Furthermore, in the IV leukemic Daudi-luc xenograft model, in which mice were treated at the time of tumour challenge, DARA-K322A also showed stronger tumour growth inhibition compared to DARA-IgG2-K322A</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of Antibody-Dependent Cellular Phagocytosis</head><p>To translate these observations from the mouse to a human setting, daratumumab -dependent phagocytosis by human monocyte-derived macrophages was demonstrated ex vivo in 11 out of 12</p><p>patient-derived MM cells tested, even at low CD38 expression level (35,000 molecules/cell) . Although a clear relationship between expression levels of CD38 and susceptibility to phagocytosis was not evident, MM cells from one patient with very low CD38 expression (~10,000 molecules/cell) were not susceptible to daratumumab-dependent phagocytosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Induction of patient myeloma cell phagocytosis by human macrophages</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effects on CD38 Enzymatic Activity</head><p>The effect on the ADP-ribosyl cyclase activity of CD38 was evaluated by three methods, either by incubation with recombinant CD38 (figure 2.1.5 A) or cellular CD38 (figure 2.1.5 B) in assays using nicotinamide guanine dinucleotide (NGD) or 8NH2-cADPR as substrate. In studies using NGD as a substrate, daratumumab, but not HuMab-CD38, induced a concentration-dependent inhibition of cyclase activity. Daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 inhibited 8NH2-cADPR production in a concentration dependent manner.</p><p>The effect of daratumumab on cADPR hydrolase activity of CD38 was measured by HPLC to determine the amount of ADPR produced from cADPR, or by measuring the amount of 32P-ADPR produced from 32P-cADPR by thin layer chromatography. Results suggest that daratumumab stimulated cADPR hydrolysis (EC 50 of 1.2 µg/ml).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Induction of Apoptosis</head><p>The capacity of daratumumab to directly induce apoptosis of CD38-expressing cells was studied in a series of experiments employing either Ramos or luciferase-transfected Daudi (Daudi-luc) cells (Study GMB3003-011). Results of these initial studies suggest that daratumumab (1 µg/mL) is able to induce target cell apoptosis upon binding to cell-surface CD38, and that this effect requires cross-linking of the induced an increase in Annexin-V positive cells and significantly increased the number of 7-AAD positive cells following 4 h incubation in the FcRγ-/-mice. This indicates that DARA-K322A crosslinking via the inhibitory FcγRIIb was sufficient to induce tumour cell apoptosis in vivo. In NOTAM mice, DARA-K322A treatment also significantly increased the number of Annexin-V positive and 7-AAD positive cells.</p><p>The inhibitory FcγRIIb and also the activating murine FcγRs, FγRI, FcγRIII and FcγRIV, can mediate daratumumab crosslinking in vivo, leading to apoptosis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>In Vivo Anti-Tumour Effects of Daratumumab</head><p>The effect of daratumumab on the growth of human lymphoma cells in vivo was investigated by engrafting luciferase-transfected Daudi cells (Daudi-luc, originated from Burkitt's lymphoma) into SCID mice by IV injection, followed by treatment with daratumumab, HuMab-CD38, or controls (GMB 3003-007). In the first study, antibodies (300 μg per mouse, n = 4 or 5) were administered one week after IV inoculation of Daudi-luc tumour cells, and tumour burden was followed by optical imaging. Both daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 significantly reduced tumour growth compared to control treatment on Days 28 and 34 (P &lt;0.001). On Day 55 after inoculation, tumour burden after treatment with HuMab-CD38 was slightly lower than after treatment with daratumumab (P &lt;0.01); however, values for neither the daratumumab nor the HuMab-CD38 group were different from the rituximab control group.</p><p>In the second therapeutic study, antibodies (10 μg per mouse, 0.5 mg/kg body weight, n = 6) were administered 14 days after IV inoculation of Daudi-luc tumour cells. At the end of the study (Day 49), tumour burden in both the daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 groups was reduced compared to control (P &lt;0.05; and was not different from the rituximab control group. To support nonclinical studies, the binding of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 (a human IgG1 mAb that specifically binds human and cynomolgus monkey CD38, also referred as HuMab-3003-003) to human and animal tissues and cells was characterized by flow cytometry, ELISA and IHC. Daratumumab binds to human and chimpanzee CD38, but not to CD38 of species typically used for nonclinical testing, (mouse, rat, rabbit, pig, and cynomolgus and rhesus monkey). HuMab-CD38 functional activity was also characterized in some exploratory studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Species selection</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Binding to human lymphoid and non-lymphoid tissues</head><p>Daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 were characterized with respect to their specific cellular staining of lymphoid and non-lymphoid human tissue (Study GMB 3003-006). Results of immunohistochemical analyses showed that both antibodies bound to lymphocytes (T-and B-lymphocytes, plasma B cells), macrophages and lymphatic endothelium as expected. Both antibodies also bound to CD38 on myocytes (in striated muscle) and a subset of differentiated epithelium in lung; HuMab-CD38 was also shown to bind to differentiated epithelium in prostate and fallopian tube.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reactivity to human and Cynomolgus blood cells</head><p>The binding of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 to individual cell types in human and cynomolgus monkey blood was studied in vitro by flow cytometry (Study SR3003-06-31 to cynomolgus monkey blood cells was seen and it may suggest higher levels of CD38 expression in monkey vs. human peripheral blood cells, which could be an important consideration in interpreting results of nonclinical studies in cynomolgus monkeys.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison of Daratumumab interaction with human and chimpanzee CD38 and with blood cells</head><p>The coding sequence of chimpanzee CD38 was determined and compared to hCD38. The cDNA of chimpanzee and human CD38 was highly similar, without insertions and with only 4 AA differences (not within the daratumumab binding epitope). Daratumumab was found to bind equally well to chimpanzee and human CD38 in vitro, when assessed using purified CD38 protein (ELISA) and using Pan EBV3 cells and human B cells (flow cytometry). Furthermore, by means of surface plasmon resonance (Biacore), the affinities of daratumumab for hCD38 (KD = 3.50 x 10-9 M + 1.66 x 10-9 M) and for chimpanzee CD38 (KD = 4.46 x 10-9 M + 1.66 x 10-9 M) were found not to be significantly different. Daratumumab was found to inhibit the enzyme activity of both chimpanzee and hCD38 to the same extent (Study GMB 3003-014).</p><p>The binding of daratumumab to chimpanzee CD38 was further characterized by flow cytometric analysis of chimpanzee PBMCs (BKV00001). Daratumumab binding was identified on CD4, CD8 or CD56-positive lymphocytes in both human and chimpanzee PBMCs. The percentages of positive cells for each of these lymphocyte subsets were comparable between human and chimpanzee, indicating that daratumumab is able to bind to naturally-occurring chimpanzee CD38.</p><p>Furthermore, binding of daratumumab to human and chimpanzee platelets was characterized by flow cytometry (BKV00013 and BKV00015). The binding experiments revealed that chimpanzee platelets express a daratumumab binding site with an affinity (EC 50 value) of approximately 1 µg/mL, which is not expressed on human platelets. The binding affinity on human platelets could not be determined in the tested concentration range, since a maximal binding plateau was not reached. It is assumed that the binding affinity of daratumumab to human platelets is at least 15-fold lower than to chimpanzee platelets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anti-tumour effects of Daratumumab in combination with other therapeutic agents</head><p>The effects of combining daratumumab with other therapeutic agents that are currently used for the treatment of MM were evaluated in two ex vivo studies. Daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide (Study GMB 3003-069): a synergistic interaction was identified between lenalidomide and daratumumab-induced tumour cell lysis in treated samples of bone marrow mononuclear cells from MM patients.</p><p>Addition of daratumumab to lenalidomide and/or bortezomib increased MM cell lysis by more than two-fold in all combinations (p &lt; 0.001). Combination of daratumumab with either lenalidomide/ bortezomib/ dexamethasone cocktail or melphalan/ prednisone/ bortezomib cocktail resulted in significantly increased tumour cell lysis compared to cocktail alone (Study GMB 3003-070).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary pharmacodynamic studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anti-tumour effects of daratumumab in combination with other therapeutic agents ex vivo</head><p>The effects of combining daratumumab with other therapeutic agents that are currently used for the treatment of MM were evaluated in two ex vivo studies. The first study addressed the activity of daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide, an immune modulatory drug, against MM cells (Study GMB 3003-069). Daratumumab-dependent killing of purified primary MM cells and the UM-9 myeloma cell line by ADCC was significantly augmented (approximately two-fold) by lenalidomide pre-treatment of effector PBMCs. Furthermore, a synergistic interaction was identified between lenalidomide and daratumumab-induced tumour cell lysis in treated samples of bone marrow mononuclear cells from MM patients. In addition, the capacity to mediate daratumumab-induced ADCC against UM-9 target cells was significantly up-regulated in PBMC derived from three MM patients during lenalidomide treatment.</p><p>In a second study, the potential benefit of combining daratumumab with multi-drug chemotherapy regimens was evaluated in fresh tumour cells from MM patients (Study GMB 3003-070). Lysis of primary tumour cells was measured directly in bone marrow mononuclear cell isolates obtained from MM patients.</p><p>Addition of daratumumab to lenalidomide and/or bortezomib increased MM cell lysis by more than two-fold in all combinations (p &lt; 0.001), even in samples from patients that were refractory to lenalidomide and bortezomib treatment. Furthermore, combination of daratumumab with either lenalidomide/bortezomib/ dexamethasone cocktail or melphalan/ prednisone/ bortezomib cocktail resulted in increased tumour cell lysis compared to cocktail alone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety pharmacology programme</head><p>No safety pharmacology studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacodynamic drug interactions</head><p>No pharmacodynamic drug interactions studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>The nonclinical PK of daratumumab was evaluated in the 6-week repeat-dose toxicology study in chimpanzees administered weekly as an IV infusion, and followed by a 91 to 105-day recovery period. PK of HuMab-CD38 was evaluated in the repeat-dose pilot toxicology study conducted in cynomolgus monkeys via weekly IV infusion for 2-weeks, and followed by a 2-month recovery period. Serum concentrations of daratumumab in chimpanzees and HuMab-CD38 in cynomolgus monkeys were determined using validated GLP-compliant ELISA bioanalytical methods. The lower limit of quantification (LLOQ) was determined to be 21.538 ng/mL in a 1% chimpanzee serum matrix and 22.973 ng/mL in a 2.5% chimpanzee serum matrix. The LLOQ of the cynomolgus assay was determined to be 3.13 ng/mL in 10% serum.</p><p>Serum ADA of daratumumab in chimpanzees and HuMab-CD38 in cynomolgus monkeys were determined using validated GLP-compliant ELISA bioanalytical methods. Data obtained from the validation demonstrated that the ELISA-based methods for the detection of antibodies were suitable for use.</p><p>However, a greater than 30% reduction in ADAs detection signal was observed for concentrations of daratumumab greater than 10 μg/mL in chimpanzee (Study BKV00005)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6-week study in chimpanzees (Study 8754-0701, GLP)</head><p>Two chimpanzees (1/sex) received 30 min. IV infusions of 5 mg/kg daratumumab. The male received weekly infusions for 6 consecutive weeks. The female was injured and only received 2 weekly infusions.</p><p>An additional female died from an IRR shortly after the first infusion and was excluded from PK analysis.</p><p>Two chimpanzees (1/sex) received IV infusions of 25 mg/kg daratumumab for 6 consecutive weeks. The first infusion of 25 mg/kg infusion was given over 1 h and was preceded by an IV injection of 10 mg daratumumab 24 h before the infusion. Subsequent 25 mg/kg infusions were given over 30 min without a pre-dose. Individual animal data are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table 11</ref>. <ref type="table">Table 3</ref>: Serum PK parameters in chimpanzees following weekly IV administration of</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Daratumumab</head><p>No daratumumab anti-drug antibodies (ADAs) were detected during the study. <ref type="bibr">(Study No. 509809,</ref> The study consisted of six male and six female cynomolgus monkeys randomized into 3 dose groups of 2  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2-week study in Cynomolgus Monkeys</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4.">Toxicology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single dose toxicity</head><p>No single-dose toxicity studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repeat dose toxicity</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Genotoxicity</head><p>No genotoxicity studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carcinogenicity</head><p>No carcinogenicity studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reproduction Toxicity</head><p>No reproduction toxicity studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicokinetic data</head><p>Toxicokinetic data are presented under section ''2.3.3. Pharmacokinetics''.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Local Tolerance</head><p>No local tolerance studies have been conducted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other toxicity studies</head><p>Tissue Cross-Reactivity of FITC-Labeled Daratumumab With Chimpanzee Tissues Ex Vivo (Report</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>BKV00003)</head><p>This study was conducted to determine the tissue binding specificity of FITC-labeled daratumumab in normal chimpanzee tissue specimens. The following tissues were evaluated: adrenal gland, bone marrow, binding was also detected in the cytoplasm of multiple chimpanzee tissues (adrenal gland, bone marrow, brain, colon, fallopian tube, GI tract, heart, kidney, liver, lymph node, mesenteric lymph node, pancreas, pituitary, skin, spinal cord, spleen, striated muscle, testes, and tonsil). The only tissue examined that showed no binding was lung.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Daratumumab-FITC: An Immunohistochemical Investigation of Cross-Reactivity in a Range of Human</head><p>Tissues (Report 28118)</p><p>This study was conducted to determine the tissue binding specificity of FITC-labeled daratumumab on normal, adult human tissue specimens. The tissue panel was based on the "suggested list of human tissues to be used for immunohistochemical investigations of cross reactivity" in Annex II of the 1995 European Medicines Evaluation Agency Guideline. All tissues selected for inclusion in this study were stained with hematoxylin and eosin, or giemsa (for blood and bone marrow) and an appropriate antigen marker before acceptance to the study.</p><p>Sections of each sample of tissue were treated with FITC-labeled daratumumab at concentrations of 0, 0.5, 1, and 2 µg/mL. Examination of the positive and negative controls showed the validity of the test system. Specific daratumumab-FITC staining occurred in the lymphoid cells in the spleen, tonsil, lymph nodes, and thymus. Specific daratumumab binding was also detected in the cytoplasm of multiple human tissues, ie, capillaries of the pituitary gland, vascular endothelial cells of the fallopian tube, lymphocytes in the ileum serosa, parathyroid, lymph node, spleen, thymus and tonsil, kidney, testis, and thyroid interstitial cells, epithelial cells of the fallopian tube, and the prostate. The subcellular location of staining in vascular endothelial cells of the pituitary gland and fallopian tube could not be determined.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HuMab-CD38-FITC: An Immunohistochemical Investigation of Cross-Reactivity in a Range of Cynomolgus Monkey Tissues (Study 510547)</head><p>This study was conducted to determine the tissue binding specificity of the FITC-conjugated HuMab-CD38, which binds to cynomolgus monkey CD38, in a panel of 35 normal cynomolgus monkey tissues: adrenal gland, brain (cerebellum and cerebrum), breast, eye (with retina), fallopian tube, GI tract (stomach, small intestine and large intestine), heart, kidney, liver,lung, lymph node, ovary, pancreas, peripheral nerve, pituitary gland, prostate, parotid salivary gland, skin, spinal cord, spleen, striated muscle, testis, thymus, thyroid and parathyroid gland, tonsil, urinary bladder, ureter, uterus (cervix and endometrium), and vascular endothelium. Haematological samples (blood and bone marrow) prepared as smears or cytospins were also evaluated.</p><p>All tissues selected for inclusion in this study were stained with hematoxylin and eosin, or giemsa (for blood and bone marrow) and an appropriate antigen marker before acceptance to the study.</p><p>Acetone-fixed cryosections of each sample of tissue were treated with FITC-labeled HuMab-CD38 at concentrations of 0, 0.2, 0.5, and 1 µg/mL.</p><p>Staining was observed in the cytoplasm of blood vessels, bone marrow lymphocytes, cerebellum white matter, cerebrum white matter, cervix, colon lamina propria, fallopian tube interstitium, ileum lamina propria, lung alveolar cells, lymph node T-cells, peripheral nerve myelin, retina/choroidea glassy membrane, spinal cord white matter, spleen T-cell zone, stomach, striated muscle fibers, thymus T-cells in medulla and cortex, and tonsil T-cell zone. It was not possible to determine the subcellular location of specific staining in endothelial (capillary) cells, whose cytoplasm is particularly thin, or in the interstitium of glomeruli in the kidney or the sinusoids of the liver. In the kidney and liver, staining in the interstitium/sinusoids may reflect staining of endothelial cells. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.5.">Ecotoxicity/environmental risk assessment</head><p>No ERA studies were submitted (see discussion on non-clinical aspects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.6.">Discussion on non-clinical aspects</head><p>The Applicant has addressed the structural and functional properties of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 in a comprehensive array of non-clinical in vitro and in vivo pharmacology studies in support of the use of daratumumab in the proposed indication.</p><p>Daratumumab binding to CD38 leads to multiple biologic effects on tumour cells. As an IgG1 antibody, daratumumab has the potential to bind to all FcγRs inducing ADCC, CDC and ADCP. These effector functions were assessed in cell-based studies, showing high tumour cell lysis, though with high variability.</p><p>The mechanism underlying differences in cell lysis are unknown and could be attribute to effector cells (NK and macrophages) and/or to differences in CD38 expression.</p><p>Binding of daratumumab to CD38 also mediated cell apoptosis and to modulate enzymatic activities of CD38, blunting cyclase activity and enhancing hydrolase activity, although the underlying cellular mechanism and the contribution to the overall anti-tumour effect are not clearly understood.</p><p>Treatment with daratumumab effectively reduced growth of human lymphoma cells in SCID mice, both in the preventive and therapeutic settings. When administered to mice bearing established disease, therapeutic activity was observed at a dose as low as 10 μg per mouse, corresponding to approximately 0.5 mg/kg body weight. Pharmacological effects other than the primary therapeutic activity (secondary pharmacodynamics) could derive from IgG1 isotype effector functions such as cytokine release and complement-mediated lysis of erythrocytes. Daratumumab has a low level of binding to human erythrocytes but did not induce specific complement-mediated lysis of erythrocytes, however a risk of interference with blood typing may exist (see Clinical safety discussion and RMP). Cytokine release observed with daratumumab was similar to other marketed therapeutic antibodies and it was consistent with adverse effects observed in toxicology studies. Overall, results of these studies support the hypothesis that daratumumab does not exert target-specific agonistic activity, and that the cytokine release observed is mainly caused by the Fc-portion of IgG1.</p><p>Distinct differences in the binding of daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 to human and cynomolgus B and T lymphocytes were identified. Daratumumab did not demonstrate specific binding to any cynomolgus monkey cell types while both daratumumab and HuMab-CD38 bound weakly to human B and T cells. In contrast, HuMab-CD38 bound strongly to cynomolgus monkey B and T lymphocytes. HuMab-CD38 bound to cynomolgus monkey erythrocytes at concentrations &gt; 3 µg/mL, which may suggest higher levels of CD38 expression in monkey vs. human peripheral blood cells. No binding to human erythrocytes was seen. The results support the use of HuMab-CD38 as a surrogate antibody for nonclinical studies involving cynomolgus or rhesus monkeys and indeed, the higher binding of HuMab-CD38 to cynomolgus monkey blood cells may suggest higher levels of CD38 expression in monkey vs. human peripheral blood cells, which could be an important consideration in interpreting results of nonclinical studies in cynomolgus monkeys.</p><p>Systemic exposure (Cmax and AUC) of daratumumab increased in a greater than dose-proportional manner with increasing dose. Daratumumab t1/2 values generally increased and CL values generally decreased after repeated administration and with increasing dose, which suggested saturation of elimination mechanisms at elevated serum drug concentrations.</p><p>No consistent gender differences were observed for any of the PK parameters estimated in the 2-week study with HuMab-CD38 in cynomolgus monkeys. High drug substance concentrations are considered to interfere with the detection of ADA's and therefore, ADA presence cannot be completely excluded.</p><p>Collectively, the non-clinical pharmacokinetic data of daratumumab derived from repeat dose toxicology studies is considered limited (as chimpanzees is the only relevant species), however, adequate for the characterization of the pharmacokinetics of daratumumab and the anti-CD38 mAb, HuMab-CD38 after single dose and repeated administration.</p><p>No stand-alone safety pharmacology studies were conducted with either daratumumab or HuMab-CD38.</p><p>Safety pharmacology endpoints were incorporated into the design of the repeat-dose toxicology studies as suggested in ICH S6(R1) and this approach is endorsed. There were no treatment-related adverse effects on cardiovascular, respiratory, or central nervous system parameters in the 6-and 2-week IV repeat-dose toxicology studies in chimpanzees and cynomolgus monkeys administered daratumumab or HuMab-CD38, respectively.</p><p>The two primary toxicities in the pivotal chimpanzee study were infusion-related reactions (IRRs) and</p><p>thrombocytopenia. Measures were taken to avoid the IRRs in the subsequent dosing of high-dose animals, i.e. a pre-dose of 10 mg daratumumab was administered i.v. 24 h before dosing, and infusion time was lengthened to 1 h, resulting in milder IRRs. In the clinical setting, IRRs are one of the safety issues, and measures are addressed accordingly in relevant sections of the SmPC (see discussion on clinical safety).</p><p>At the histopathologic examination, thymic atrophy was observed in animals from the main study groups.</p><p>Lymphoid atrophy or depletion was also observed in the mandibular and mesenteric lymph nodes and spleen in animals that received 20 or 100 mg/kg. Following the recovery period, there was minimal thymic atrophy in the 100 mg/kg-dosed female and minimal lymphoid depletion in the mesenteric lymph node in the 100 mg/kg-dosed male. A NOAEL was not established in this study.</p><p>ADAs to HuMab-CD38 were detected in both monkeys in the 20 mg/kg recovery group. The development of ADA in non-clinical species is not necessarily predictive of potential immunogenicity in humans, however, positive Coombs' tests have been observed in patients, and methods to ameliorate the interference of daratumumab in the assay have been developed and this has been addressed in the SmPC (see discussion on clinical safety).</p><p>No developmental and reproductive toxicity studies were performed. Developmental and reproductive toxicity testing is not feasible in chimpanzees. The use of a surrogate antibody in cynomolgus monkeys was considered, but anaemia and formation of ADAs limit the dosages and duration of any additional studies in this species. In addition, as the majority of patient population is beyond reproductive age it is therefore acknowledged that such studies are not deemed necessary for marketing authorisation however in order to address the whole population studied, reproductive and developmental toxicity is included as missing information in the RMP (see discussion on clinical safety). The lack of such data is addressed in the SmPC as follows: ''There are no human or animal data to assess the risk of daratumumab use during pregnancy. IgG1 monoclonal antibodies are known to cross the placenta after the first trimester of pregnancy. Therefore daratumumab should not be used during pregnancy unless the benefit of treatment to the woman is considered to outweigh the potential risks to the fetus. If the patient becomes pregnant while taking this medicine, the patient should be informed of the potential risk to the fetus'' (see SmPC section 4.6).</p><p>No genotoxicity and carcinogenicity studies are required for daratumumab.</p><p>Local tolerance assessment was incorporated into repeat-dose studies with no relevant findings suggesting local toxicity.</p><p>Tissue cross-reactivity studies were conducted using FITC-labeled daratumumab and normal chimpanzee and human tissue specimens. In addition, a tissue cross-reactivity study was conducted with FITC-labeled Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 28/119</p><p>HuMab-CD38 and normal cynomolgus monkey tissue samples. Specific binding was observed in most lymphoid tissues which confirmed that HuMab-CD38 and daratumumab binds to target sites of the lymphoid tissues in all species. Furthermore, binding was observed in the cytoplasm in multiple tissues in all three species. However, cytoplasmic binding is generally not relevant for mAbs as they do not diffuse into cells and do not have access to the cytoplasm.</p><p>The justification provided by the Applicant for not performing environmental risk assessment studies was considered acceptable since daratumumab is a protein therefore, unlikely to result in significant risk to the environment. This is in accordance with the "Guideline on Environmental Risk Assessment of Medicinal Products for Human Use (EMEA/CHMP/SWP/4447/00 corr 21*).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.7.">Conclusion on the non-clinical aspects</head><p>Overall, the non-clinical pharmacology data for daratumumab and HuMab-CD38, is considered sufficient for the proposed cancer indication. The relevant information has been included in the SmPC (sections 4.6, 5.1 and 5.3).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1.">Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GCP</head><p>The Clinical trials were performed in accordance with GCP as claimed by the applicant.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>The pharmacokinetics (PK) of daratumumab following intravenous administration were evaluated in patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma at dose levels from 0.1 mg/kg to 24 mg/kg. A population PK model of daratumumab was developed to describe the PK characteristics of daratumumab and to evaluate the influence of covariates on the disposition of daratumumab in patients with multiple myeloma. The population PK analysis included 223 patients receiving daratumumab in two clinical trials (150 subjects received 16 mg/kg) (SmPC section 5.2).</p><p>The exposure-response analyses were performed on the combined data from studies GEN501 (N=104) and MMY2002 (N=124) as well as the data from Study MMY1002.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Absorption</head><p>No bioavailability studies were performed. As daratumumab is administered intravenously, bioavailability is 100%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution</head><p>The volume of distribution (Vd) was investigated in the Phase I Study GEN501 (Part 1 and Part 2), in the The population PK estimate for the central volume of distribution is 56.98±18.07 mL/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Elimination</head><p>As observed in the Phase I GEN501 study (Part 1), clearance decreased with multiple doses, particularly in the dose groups receiving at least 2 mg/kg daratumumab: In the 2 mg/kg group, mean clearance decreased from 1.06 mL/h/kg after the first full infusion to 0.59 mL/h/kg after the seventh (last) full infusion. In the 24 mg/kg group, mean clearance decreased from 0.29 mL/h/kg after the first full infusion to 0.16 mL/h/kg after the seventh (last) full infusion.</p><p>The elimination halftime (T½) increased with multiple doses: from 25.62±5.61 hours for 2 mg/kg to 154.65±36.48 hours for 24 mg/kg. In the 16 mg/kg group, mean T½ increased from 109.9±42.05 hours after the first full infusion to 586.56±486.89 hours after the seventh (last) full infusion (Study GEN501, Part 1).</p><p>In the population PK analysis, the model-derived half-life (mean±standard deviation) associated with linear elimination was approximately 18±9 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose proportionality and time dependencies</head><p>Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 31/119  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infusion: Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set (Study GEN501 Part 1)</head><p>Terminal half-life increases with increasing dose and with repeated dosing. The mean (standard deviation</p><p>[SD]) estimated terminal half-life of daratumumab following the first 16 mg/kg dose was 9 (4.3) days.</p><p>Based on population PK analysis, the mean (SD) half-life associated with non-specific linear elimination was approximately 18 (9) days (SmPC section 5.2).</p><p>At the end of weekly dosing for the recommended schedule and dose of 16 mg/kg, the mean (SD) serum Cmax value was 915 (410.3) micrograms/mL, approximately 2.9-fold higher than following the first infusion. The mean (SD) predose (trough) serum concentration at the end of weekly dosing was 573 (331.5) micrograms/mL (SmPC section 5.2).</p><p>Based on the population PK analysis, daratumumab steady state is achieved approximately 5 months into the every 4-week dosing period (by the 21st infusion), and the mean (SD) ratio of Cmax at steady-state to Cmax after the first dose was 1.6 (0.5) (SmPC section 5.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Special populations</head><p>Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 33/119 Based on population PK analysis, age (range: 31-84 years) had no clinically important effect on the PK of daratumumab, and the exposure of daratumumab was similar between younger (aged &lt; 65 years, n = 127) and older (aged ≥ 65 years, n = 96; aged ≥ 75years, n = 18; aged ≥ 85 years, n = 0) patients. Based on the population PK analysis the exposure to daratumumab was similar between white (n = 197) and non-white (n = 26) subjects (SmPC section 5.2).</p><p>Based on population PK analysis body weight was identified as a statistically significant covariate for daratumumab clearance. Therefore, body weight based dosing is an appropriate dosing strategy for the multiple myeloma patients (SmPC section 5.2).</p><p>Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 34/119</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetic interaction studies</head><p>No in vitro or in vivo studies on pharmacokinetic drug interactions have been submitted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3.">Pharmacodynamics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanism of action</head><p>Daratumumab is an IgG1κ human monoclonal antibody (mAb) that binds to the CD38 protein expressed at a high level on the surface of multiple myeloma tumour cells, as well as other cell types and tissues at various levels. CD38 protein has multiple functions such as receptor mediated adhesion, signalling and enzymatic activity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary and Secondary pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacology</head><p>In Study GEN501, peripheral blood samples were immunophenotyped to track specific immune cell subtypes (NK cells, T cells, and B cells), which may act as effector cells to induce tumour cell death with daratumumab. Decreases in NK cells were observed post-treatment in all treatment groups and were most pronounced in all treatment groups ≥2 mg/kg in both peripheral blood and bone marrow. In Part 2, the change in total NK cells (as a percentage of lymphocytes in bone marrow) decreased from a median of 14.50% at baseline to 2.80% on treatment in the 8 mg/kg group and from a median of 19.90% at baseline to 5.90% on treatment in the 16 mg/kg group; these changes were statistically significant (p=0.0468 in 8 mg/kg group; p&lt;0.0001 in the 16 mg/kg group).</p><p>Baseline absolute counts of total NK cells and post-baseline changes in NK cells were compared between responders and non-responders for 8 mg/kg and 16 mg/kg groups in Study GEN501 Part 2. A decrease in total NK cells was observed in both responders and non-responders and there was no association observed between the percentage of NK cell decrease and clinical response in either blood or bone marrow.</p><p>In addition to NK cells, other lymphocytes known to express CD38 such as B cells and T cells were measured at baseline and following daratumumab treatment. B cells (CD19+) were maintained in the peripheral blood and bone marrow following daratumumab treatment. T cells, both CD3+CD4+ and CD3+CD8+, were noted to increase over time with daratumumab treatment both in the periphery and the bone marrow (absolute counts as well as percentage of lymphocytes).</p><p>In study MMY2002, total NK cells (CD45+CD3-CD16+CD56+) were evaluated as a possible pharmacodynamic biomarker for daratumumab. A decrease in absolute counts (cells/µL) of total NK cells in peripheral blood was observed following daratumumab treatment in both the 8 mg/kg and 16 mg/kg groups. In the 8 mg/kg group with monthly dosing of daratumumab, total NK cells were reduced by Cycle Baseline absolute counts of total NK cells were also compared between responders and non-responders for the 8 mg/kg and 16 mg/kg groups. The baseline total NK cells counts in blood or bone marrow did not show any difference between responders and non-responders. There was also no association observed between the percentage of NK cell decrease and clinical response.</p><p>Daratumumab treatment-associated changes were also observed in other immune cells. Evaluation of T cells indicated a significant increase of CD3+CD4+ and CD3+CD8+ T-cells over time with daratumumab treatment in the peripheral blood and bone marrow (both absolute counts and percentage of lymphocytes).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>QTc interval</head><p>The effect of daratumumab on the QTc interval was evaluated in an open-label study for 83 patients (Study GEN501) with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma following daratumumab infusions (4 to 24 mg/kg) (SmPC section 5.1).</p><p>Pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic analyses was performed using a linear mixed effects modeling approach to examine the relationship between the baseline-adjusted/corrected change in QTcF intervals and time-matched (within 3 hours) serum concentrations of daratumumab.</p><p>In GEN501 Part 1, no statistically significant or clinically relevant change in QTcF vs. daratumumab serum concentrations was observed <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 18</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunogenicity</head><p>The immunogenicity of daratumumab has been evaluated in 2 monotherapy daratumumab studies (GEN501 and MMY2002) using validated ECLIA methods.</p><p>Patients (n = 199) were evaluated for anti-therapeutic antibody responses to daratumumab at multiple time points during treatment and up to 8 weeks following the end of treatment. Following the start of daratumumab treatment, none of the patients tested positive for anti-daratumumab antibodies (SmPC section 5.1).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Relationship between plasma concentration and effect</head><p>The exposure-response analyses were performed on the combined data from studies GEN501 (N=104) and MMY2002 (N=124) as well as the data from study MMY2002 alone. Different exposure metrics were predicted and derived using estimated individual PK parameters based on the population PK model and actual dosing information for each subject. The exposure metrics included (1) maximal pre-infusion (trough) concentration (Cpre-infusion,max), (2) maximal end-of-infusion concentration (Cpost-infusion,max), (3) pre-infusion concentration before the last dose received, (4) end-of-infusion concentration after the last dose received, and (5) average concentration during the treatment. For the 5 subjects without measurable concentrations and excluded from the population PK analyses, the exposures (ie, concentrations) were set to half of the lower limit of the quantification (ie, 0.1 μg/mL).</p><p>The exposure-efficacy analyses were performed for ORR, the primary efficacy endpoint in study MMY2002, and other secondary endpoints (DOR, TTP, TTR, OS, PFS, and maximal reduction in paraprotein <ref type="bibr">[MRPP]</ref>). For study GEN501, the response and progression data were based on a computerised algorithm since IRC data were not available from the study. The clinical relevance of significant covariates identified from the population PK analyses (ie, body weight, albumin, gender, drug product, and type of myeloma) was evaluated using ORR in the exposure-efficacy analyses.</p><p>Overall response rate significantly increased with daratumumab systemic exposure, and there was a maximum effect (Emax) relationship between daratumumab exposure and ORR . Among the tested exposure metrics, Cpre-infusion,max had the strongest correlation with ORR as it best described the data and provided the lowest Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) value. The estimated half maximal effect Cpre-infusion,max was 261 μg/mL, and the slope factor was approximately 45. Therefore, the 90% maximal effect on ORR may be achieved when Cpre-infusion,max = 274 μg/mL ( ), and limited additional benefit in ORR could be obtained when Cpre-infusion,max was above the predicted .</p><p>Sensitivity analyses were conducted based on <ref type="formula">(1)</ref>  The figure below shows an apparent separation in the observed trough concentration over time between responders and non-responders, and maximum separation was observed around the maximal trough concentrations for both groups. The mean maximum trough concentration in non-responders appears below the , while it is well above the threshold in responders. In Study GEN501, assessment of NK cells in peripheral blood was performed for the following dosing groups: ≤1 mg/kg, 2 mg/kg, 4 mg/kg, 8 mg/kg, 16 mg/kg and 24 mg/kg. Decreases in NK cells were observed post-treatment in all treatment groups and were most pronounced in treatment groups ≥2 mg/kg in both peripheral blood and bone marrow.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2: Comparison of Observed Pre-infusion (Trough) Concentration Over Time Between</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Responders and Non-responders</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dosing regimen</head><p>The total clearance of daratumumab decreased over time, possibly due to the depletion of the target (CD38). The intensive weekly dosing at the beginning of the treatment was therefore helpful to overcome the high clearance initially, and rapidly establish the efficacious concentration. Thereafter, the every 2</p><p>week and every 4 week dosing at 16 mg/kg appeared to be adequate to saturate the target and maintain the total clearance close to the non-specific linear clearance. The reduction in daratumumab concentration over time during less frequent dosing was not associated with either shorter duration of response or higher risk of disease progression. This result corroborates the finding based on the clinical analysis in which the rate of subjects who had disease progression was consistent in every 2 week and every 4 week dosing periods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exposure-safety</head><p>Exposure-safety analyses were conducted for selected AEs, including infusion-related reactions (IRRs), </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacodynamic interactions</head><p>There is no information available regarding pharmacodynamic interactions with other medicinal products or substances. A decrease in total NK cells in peripheral blood and bone marrow aspirates was observed following daratumumab treatment with lenalidomide/dexamethasone in all cohorts (Phase 1 and Phase 2</p><p>of Study GEN503). The NK cell decrease observed in this combination study was comparable to that observed with daratumumab monotherapy treatment in earlier studies (Studies MMY2002 and GEN501).</p><p>In vitro studies have shown that glucocorticoid inhibits CD38 expression in human airway smooth muscle In vitro studies have also shown that novobiocin increases CD38 expression <ref type="bibr">(Thiele A et al. Biochimica Biophysica Acta, 2002:32-40</ref>). An analysis of baseline CD38 expression between responders and non-responders in studies GEN501 and MMY2002 shown that the baseline median expression levels of CD38 in bone marrow multiple myeloma cells (CD138+) were lower in non-responders compared to responders, but a substantial overlap of the CD38 level between the two response groups were observed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.4.">Discussion on clinical pharmacology</head><p>The PK of daratumumab has been reasonably well investigated and generally in accordance with the current guideline on the clinical investigation of pharmacokinetics of therapeutic proteins (CHMP/EWP/89249/2004) and scientific advice provided by EMA/CHMP/SAWP (EMA/CHMP/SAWP/69790/2013). The overall approach of combined phase I/II trials and additional population PK-and exposure-response analyses can be supported. Of note, all pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic investigations were performed on target population namely patients with multiple myeloma relapsed from or refractory to 2 or more different prior therapies and therefore no extrapolation from e.g. healthy volunteers is necessary.</p><p>The primary PK of daratumumab is well characterised and is in accordance with the expected for an analyses and thus is expected to be for the doses of the pooled dataset however, data for patients treated with the recommended dose of 16 mg/kg and in steady state (i.e. after the last full infusion) is limited to less than 10 patients and therefore, the model-derived mean half-life is based on the population PK analyses is considered to be most representative.</p><p>Inter-individual variability has not been specifically addressed but generally, the inter-individual variability in PK parameters was moderate to high (25-50%). As expected also the intra-individual variability was moderate (32.7%).</p><p>The PPK analysis was overall performed using well recognised model building techniques.</p><p>Limited data were available for the following categories of the covariates, limiting the possibility for a robust assessment of the PK in these patients: age (≥ 75 years: n=18); races (White, Hispanic or Latino: 3% n=7; Asian: 2% n=4; other: 2% n=5); creatinine clearance category (≥15-≤29 ml/min: 2%, n=5;</p><p>&lt;15 ml/min: 0%, n=1); hepatic dysfunction (mild dysfunction: 15% n=34); baseline ECOG score (2: 6%, n=14); refractory status (None: 10%, n=23; PI only: 4%, n=8; IMiD only: 6%, n=14  were evaluated for anti therapeutic antibody responses to daratumumab at multiple time points during treatment and up to 8 weeks following the end of treatment. Following the start of daratumumab treatment, none of the patients tested positive for anti-daratumumab antibodies. However, the employed assay has limitations in detecting anti-daratumumab antibodies in the presence of high concentrations of daratumumab. Therefore, the incidence of antibody development might not have been reliably determined".</p><p>The optimised method JRD, which was used in studies MMY2002, had a sufficient drug tolerance up to 31,250 ng/mL (without dilution 625 µg/mL). According to protocol, immunogenicity was tested on C1D1 pre, C3D1 pre, C6D1 pre, C12D1 pre and after the end of treatment. It should be noted that the mean ± SD through concentration at the end of weekly dosing (Cycle 3 Day 1 predose) was 573.49±331.49 µg/mL. Consequently, the presence of anti-daratumumab antibodies in studies MMY2002 may have been underestimated because observed concentration could be higher than drug tolerance at some time points.</p><p>Exposure-response analyses have demonstrated that the response rate significantly increased with daratumumab systemic exposure. The choice of 16 mg/kg rather than 8 mg/kg has been sufficiently justified as the recommended dose however, considered the seriousness of the disease and the poor prognosis for this group of patients, it was questioned if additional treatment response can be obtained by increasing the percentage of patients reaching a Cpre-infusion,max above the estimated. However a dose of 24 mg/kg compared with the recommended dose of 16 mg/kg, will only result in approximately 10% more subjects with a a Cpre-infusion,max above the estimated. It is acknowledged that most of the patients (i.e. the approximately 80% with a 99% predicted target saturation after weekly dosing) will not benefit from a higher dose but considering the seriousness of the disease and the dismissing prognosis for the patients not responding to daratumumab treatment, an increase of 10% patients with a clinically relevant increase in effect appears compelling. In addition, the experience with 24 mg/kg is indeed very limited (3 patients) thus naturally insufficient for a benefit-risk assessment. Therefore, 24 mg/kg is not a realistic alternative to 16 mg/kg, which remains the recommended dose. The results from the analyses of ORR in the IgG and the ORR in the non-IgG groups are almost similar supporting the fact that the decreased estimated in patients with IgG multiple myeloma is counter-balanced by an increased sensitivity. Thus, the difference in drug exposure in the IgG and the non-IgG groups seems not to be clinically relevant and despite the fact that an increase in treatment dose can be expected to increase efficacy (including ORR, PFS and DoR), this is expected to be of similar magnitude for both IgG and non-IgG patients. Therefore, there is no apparent reason for different dosing regimen depending on IgG-status.</p><p>No interaction studies have been performed. As an IgG1қ monoclonal antibody, renal excretion and hepatic enzyme-mediated metabolism of intact daratumumab are unlikely to represent major elimination routes. As such, variations in drug-metabolising enzymes are not expected to affect the elimination of daratumumab. Due to the high affinity to a unique epitope on CD38, daratumumab is not anticipated to alter drug-metabolising enzymes (SmPC section 5.1). and CHF did not find an association between any of these subgroups and QTc prolongation either. Thus, taken together, no plausible cause for the findings of the statistically significant QTc prolongation in Study GEN501 Part 2 has been identified.</p><p>Linear mixed PK-PD analyses indicated no large increase in mean QTcF interval (i.e., greater than 20ms) at daratumumab C max (SmPC section 5.1).</p><p>A thorough QTc study is not feasible but the Applicant will incorporate well-controlled data collection in a substudy of the ongoing Study SMM2001 to further evaluate a relationship between datatumumab concentration and QTc. QTc prolongation has been classified as an important potential risk in the RMP (See Clinical Safety discussion and RMP).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.5.">Conclusions on clinical pharmacology</head><p>Overall, the clinical pharmacology of daratumumab has been reasonably well investigated and generally in accordance with the current guideline (CHMP/EWP/89249/2004). Study GEN501 was a Phase 1/2, open-label, non-randomized, first-in-human study in subjects with multiple myeloma whose disease was relapsed or refractory to at least 2 prior lines of therapies.</p><p>In Part 1 of Study GEN501 (the First-in-Human dose escalation study), escalating doses of daratumumab were administered (0.005, 0.05, 0.10, 0.50, 1, 2, 4, 8, 16, and 24 mg/kg) as a single dose, followed by a 3 week resting period, followed by 6 weekly doses for a total of 7 doses. The subjects in the 4 mg/kg, 8 mg/kg, 16 mg/kg and 24 mg/kg were included in the Part 1 efficacy analysis (n=3 subjects at each dose level). The best response at any dose level in this 8 week treatment period of Part 1 was a partial rtesponse (PR). A maximum tolerated dose (MTD) was not identified. An IDMC determined that, based on data from Part 1, the study could move forward with daratumumab doses ≥ 8 mg/kg. Based on the PK and efficacy data in Part 1, the 8 mg/kg dose was chosen as the Part 2 dose. However, during Part 2, it was identified that the 8 mg/kg dose may not saturate a majority of the target (CD38) throughout dosing, as indicated by the high inter-subject variability in pharmacokinetics. Therefore, the 8 mg/kg dose in Part 2 was changed to 16 mg/kg (Protocol Amendment 13) to assess whether high-dose intensity (leading to higher levels of systemic exposure and consistent saturation of the CD38 target), was needed to optimize the efficacy of daratumumab.</p><p>In Part 2 of Study GEN501, daratumumab 16 mg/kg was administered as a single dose, followed by a 3</p><p>week resting period, followed by weekly doses for 7 weeks, then every other week for an additional 14 weeks, and every 4 weeks thereafter for up to 96 weeks. In Part 2, the 16 mg/kg dose level (n=42, ORR of 36%) had an acceptable safety profile and resulted in higher and deeper response rates as compared to the 8 mg/kg dose level (n=30, ORR of 10%).   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.2.">Main studies MMY2002</head><p>Study MMY2002 was an open-label, multicentre, phase 2 trial investigating the efficacy and safety of daratumumab in subjects with multiple myeloma who have received at least 3 prior lines of therapy (including a proteasome inhibitor and IMiD) or are double refractory to a proteasome inhibitor and an IMiD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Participants</head><p>Patients ≥ 18 years of age with documented multiple myeloma, were eligible to enter the study.</p><p>The key inclusion criteria were the following:</p><p>• Documented multiple myeloma as defined by the criteria below and evidence of disease progression on the most recent prior treatment regimen based on IMWG criteria: • Evidence of response (ie, achieved ≥ 25% reduction in M-protein for ≥ 6 weeks [MR]) to at least 1 of their prior treatment regimens.</p><p>• Received an alkylating agent (≥ 2 cycles or 2 months) either alone or in combination with other myeloma treatments. One course of an alkylating agent for autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) alone or in combination was acceptable. A list of alkylating agents is provided in the National Cancer Comprehensive Network (NCCN) Guidelines (NCCN 2013).</p><p>• Received at least 3 prior lines of therapy (definition below) including a PI (≥ 2 cycles or 2 months of treatment) and an IMiD (≥ 2 cycles or 2 months of treatment) in any order during the course of treatment (except for patients who discontinued either of these treatments due to a severe allergic reaction within the first 2 cycles/months).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>OR</head><p>Disease was double refractory to a PI and an IMiD. For patients who received more than 1 type of PI or IMID, their disease was to be refractory to the most recent one of them.</p><p>• ECOG performance status score of 0, 1, or 2.</p><p>The key exclusion criteria were the following:</p><p>• Previously received daratumumab or other anti-CD38 therapies.</p><p>• Received anti-myeloma treatment within 2 weeks before Cycle 1, Day 1.</p><p>• Nonsecretory multiple myeloma based upon standard M-component criteria (ie, measurable serum/urine M-component) unless the baseline serum FLC level was elevated.</p><p>• Previously received an allogeneic stem cell transplant or ASCT within 12 weeks before Cycle 1, Day 1.</p><p>• Received a cumulative dose of corticosteroids more than the equivalent of ≥ 140 mg of prednisone within the 2-week period before Cycle 1, Day 1.</p><p>• History of malignancy (other than multiple myeloma) within 5 years before Cycle 1, Day 1 (exceptions were squamous and basal cell carcinomas of the skin and carcinoma in situ of the cervix, or malignancy that in the opinion of the investigator, with concurrence with the sponsor's medical monitor, was considered cured with minimal risk of recurrence).</p><p>• Exhibited clinical signs of meningeal involvement of multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatments</head><p>Daratumumab was administered as an IV infusion in 28-day cycles until disease progression, unacceptable toxicity, or other reasons as listed in the CSR.</p><p>In Part 1, patients received 1 of the following 2 treatment regimens:</p><p>• </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 3: Design of Study MMY2002</head><p>All subjects received pre-infusion medication as shown in the following table: For the prevention of delayed IRRs, all subjects were to receive corticosteroid orally (20 mg methylprednisolone or equivalent in accordance with local standards) on the 2 days following all daratumumab infusions (beginning the day after the infusion). For subjects with a higher risk of respiratory complications (eg, subjects who had a forced expiratory volume in 1 second (FEV1) % from predicted &lt;75%), the following post-infusion medications should have been considered:</p><p>• Antihistamine (diphenhydramine or equivalent) on the first and second days after all infusions • Short-acting β2 adrenergic receptor agonist such as salbutamol aerosol</p><p>• Control medications for lung disease (eg, inhaled corticosteroids ± long-acting β2 adrenergic receptor agonists for subjects with asthma; long-acting bronchodilators such as tiotropium or salmeterol ±inhaled corticosteroids for subjects with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The primary objective was to evaluate the efficacy of 2 treatment regimens of daratumumab, as measured by the ORR (PR or better) in patients with MM who had received at least 3 prior lines of therapy including a PI and an IMiD or whose disease was double refractory to both a PI and an IMiD agent. The secondary objectives were:</p><p>• To assess the safety and tolerability of daratumumab.</p><p>• To assess the pharmacokinetics of Phase 2 drug product and Phase 3 drug product.</p><p>• To evaluate duration of and time to response to daratumumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To determine the clinical benefit (minimal response <ref type="bibr">[MR]</ref> or better) rate following treatment with daratumumab.</p><p>• To evaluate clinical outcomes including time to disease progression (TTP), progression-free survival (PFS), and overall survival (OS).</p><p>• To assess the pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and generation of antibodies to daratumumab (immunogenicity).</p><p>• To explore biomarkers predictive of response to daratumumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes/endpoints</head><p>The primary endpoint was the overall response rate (ORR), which was defined as the proportion of subjects who achieved PR or better according to the IMWG criteria (Durie 2007, Rajkumar 2011).</p><p>The secondary efficacy endpoints included:</p><p>• Duration of response, defined as the time from the date of initial response (PR or better) to the date of first documented evidence of progressive disease, according to IMWG criteria.</p><p>• Overall survival (OS), defined as the time from the date of first dose of daratumumab to the date of death from any cause.</p><p>• Clinical benefit rate (MR or better), defined as the proportion of subjects with best response of MR or better (including PR, very good partial response (VGPR), CR, and sCR).</p><p>• Time to response, defined as the time from the date of first dose of daratumumab to the date of initial documentation of a response (PR or better).</p><p>• Progression-free survival (PFS), defined as the time between the date of first dose of daratumumab and either disease progression or death, whichever occurred first.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 24</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample size</head><p>Up to 90 subjects were to be enrolled in Part 1, in which Phase 2 drug product was to be used. This part utilized a Simon's randomized 2-stage Phase 2 design to identify the treatment group for Part 2, in which Phase 3 drug product was used. Within each randomized treatment group, a 2-stage design was employed. The null hypothesis was that the ORR was at most 15%, and the alternative hypothesis was that the ORR was at least 40%. With a one-sided α of 2.5%, and a power of 85%, the total sample size within each randomized treatment group in Part 1 was 36 response-evaluable subjects. Assuming a non-evaluable rate of 10%, up to 40 subjects were to be enrolled within each randomized treatment group. The Stage 1 analysis was to be performed when approximately 15 subjects were enrolled in each treatment group and had sufficient data (i.e. up to 8 weeks of treatment) to be evaluable for response.</p><p>Future enrolment into each treatment group was to be terminated if it was determined during the first stage that the treatment group was considered as ineffective or not well-tolerated. If a treatment group proceeded to the second stage with a total of 36 evaluable subjects with 2 stages combined, the null hypothesis was to be rejected if 11 or more responses were observed.</p><p>If it was determined at the end of Part 1 that a treatment group was to be further evaluated in Part 2, then up to an additional 60 subjects were to be enrolled in Part 2 and treated with Phase 3 drug product. This would bring the total number of subjects treated during the study up to approximately 100 for the selected treatment group. The purpose of Part 2 was to characterize the 2 different drug products with respect to pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, efficacy, and safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomisation</head><p>Central randomization was implemented in Part 1 Stage 1 using an interactive web response system (IWRS).</p><p>Patients were randomly assigned to one of two treatment groups (daratumumab dosed at 8 mg/kg or 16 mg/kg). The randomization was stratified by International Staging System (I, II, or III) and refractory status (none, refractory to either a PI or IMiD, or refractory to both a PI and IMiD). This was an open-label study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blinding (masking)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject Populations Analyzed</head><p>All treated Analysis Set: All subjects who received at least 1 dose of daratumumab were used for all efficacy and safety analyses.</p><p>Per-Protocol Analysis Set: The per-protocol analysis set excluded all treated subjects who have had major protocol deviations due to not meeting all inclusion/exclusion criteria.</p><p>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set: All treated subjects with at least 1 post-infusion sample were used for all pharmacokinetic analyses.</p><p>Immunogenicity Analysis Set: All treated subjects with appropriate samples for detection of antibodies to daratumumab.</p><p>No formal statistical hypothesis testing was planned. For each observed response category, a 2-sided 95% exact confidence interval (CI) was presented. For the calculation of ORR, those patients who were not evaluable for response, were to be considered non-responders.</p><p>No statistical comparison was performed. The Kaplan-Meier curve was provided for subjects in the 16 mg/kg group only and by responder vs. non-responder based on computerized IMWG algorithm.</p><p>As an exploratory analysis, the same PFS analyses were repeated based on investigator assessment, where progressive disease was determined by study investigators.</p><p>Additionally, in Part 2, descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation, median, and range) were provided to summarize time to first response and time to best response for responders in each treatment group. A waterfall plot was generated for maximum percent reduction from baseline in serum/urine M-protein or FLC, based on the measurable type at baseline. Among responders, a shift table of bone marrow percent plasma cells from baseline value to first value post-baseline was provided and a figure was generated to display the percent change from baseline. No inferential analysis was performed.</p><p>The primary analysis sets for efficacy results were all treated patients. Two interim analyses were performed as specified in the protocol.</p><p>The first interim analysis also referred to as a futility analysis, occurred in March 2014, with a data cut-off 8 weeks after the last patient in Part 1 Stage 1 was dosed. Thirty-four (34) patients who were treated in Three subjects crossed over during the study from the 8 mg/kg to 16 mg/kg but were included in the 8 mg/kg group in all analyses, unless otherwise specified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 51/119</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant flow</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruitment</head><p>The study was conducted at 26 sites in 3 countries (Canada, Spain, and the United States). Most of the subjects (72%) were enrolled at sites in the United States (16 sites), 18% in Canada (6 sites), and 10%</p><p>in Spain (4 sites).</p><p>The first subject started treatment on 08 October 2013, and the last subject started treatment on 20 May 2014.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conduct of the study</head><p>The original protocol, dated 11 July 2013, was amended 3 times. The original platelet count criteria was &lt;75 x109/L for subjects in whom &lt;50% of bone marrow nucleated cells are plasma cells; otherwise platelet count &lt;50 x109/L. and/or not well tolerated. The platelet count criteria was revised to &lt;75 x10 9 /L for subjects in whom &gt;50% of bone marrow nucleated cells are plasma cells; otherwise platelet count &lt;50 x10 9 /L in subjects with bone marrow plasma cells ≤ 50%.</p><p>• Amendment INT-2 (07 February 2014): included the following changes: following the discontinuation of the dose schedule of 8 mg/kg every 4 weeks (Treatment Group B) at the end of Stage 1, the number of subjects in Part 2 was increased to approximately 60 subjects, biomarker sampling time points were modified, and subjects in Group B were allowed to crossover to Group A. The platelet count criteria was modified to &lt;50 x10 9 /L (transfusion support within 7 days before the laboratory test is not permitted).</p><p>• Amendment INT-3 (09 July 2014): changed the timing of the on treatment bone marrow biopsy. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline data</head><p>The demographic and baseline disease characteristics are presented in the following tables:  Previous multiple myeloma treatments and refractory status in the study population are summarized in the tables below:  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes and estimation</head><p>As of a 30 June 2015 clinical cut-off date, the median duration of follow-up, based on Kaplan-Meier estimate, was 19.1 months for the 8 mg/kg group and 14.7 months for the 16 mg/kg group.    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary endpoint -ORR</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical benefit rate (MR or better)</head><p>The clinical benefit rate for the 16 mg/kg group, by IRC assessment, was 34% (95% CI: 25%, 44%).</p><p>Based on the IRC assessment for the per-protocol analysis set, the clinical benefit rate was 35% (95% CI:</p><p>26%, 45%) for the 16 mg/kg group (data not shown).   Overall survival (OS)   Among 12 subjects in the 16 mg/kg group with baseline bone marrow plasma cell involvement greater than 30%, 5 patients (42%) had post baseline bone marrow plasma cell involvement normalized to less than 5%, and an additional 4 patients (33%) had post-baseline bone marrow plasma cell involvement improved to between 5 to 10% (data not shown).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Time to disease progression</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ancillary analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of study MMY2002</head><p>The following tables summarise the efficacy results from the main studies supporting the present application. These summaries should be read in conjunction with the discussion on clinical efficacy as well as the benefit risk assessment (see later sections).</p><p>Title: An open-label, multicentre, phase 2 trial investigating the efficacy and safety of daratumumab in subjects with multiple myeloma who have received at least 3 prior lines of therapy (including a proteasome inhibitor and IMiD) or are double refractory to a proteasome inhibitor and an IMiD </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GEN 501</head><p>Study GEN501 was a Phase 1/2, open-label, multicentre, safety study divided into 2 parts. Part 1 was a dose-escalation phase; Part 2 was a single-arm phase with multiple cohorts, based on the dose levels established in Part 1. Part 2 was one of the main studies described below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Participants</head><p>The key inclusion criteria were the following: The key exclusion criteria were the following:</p><p>1. Other chemotherapy that is or may be active against multiple myeloma </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatments</head><p>The summary of the study design is presented in the figure below:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 7: Schematic overview of Study GEN501</head><p>During Part 2 of the study, 4 additional amendments (11-14) were issued. Based on pharmacokinetic and efficacy data, the 8 mg/kg dose was chosen as the Part 2 dose (Amendment 11). Additionally, to minimize IRRs, particularly at the first full-dose infusion, different combinations of predose infusions, infusion volumes, and infusion rates were evaluated (Amendment 12). During Part 2, it was determined that the The dosing schedule used in the study is summarized in the following figure: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pre-infusion medication</head><p>In Parts 1 and 2, subjects were to receive:</p><p>• 1 g paracetamol (acetaminophen) PO</p><p>• antihistamine (clemastine 1 mg IV, cetirizine 10 mg PO, or equivalent)</p><p>• glucocorticoids (methylprednisolone 100mg IV before the first 2 pre-doses and before the first 2 full daratumumab infusions and since amendment 4 (April 2010) before every subsequent infusion. The dose could be decreased to 50 mg following Visit 4 in Part 2 of the study if no significant infusion reactions were noted)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post-infusion medication</head><p>In Part 2, all subjects were to receive 20 to 25 mg methylprednisolone PO, or equivalent, on the first and second days after all full-dose infusions. For subjects with a higher risk of respiratory complications (eg, subjects with FEV1 &lt;75%), the following post-infusion medications were permitted:</p><p>• antihistamine (clemastine 1 mg IV, cetirizine 10 mg PO, or equivalent) on the first and second days after all full-dose infusions</p><p>• salbutamol aerosol</p><p>• controller medications (eg, inhaled corticosteroids ± long-acting beta agonists for subjects with asthma; long-acting bronchodilators such as tiotropium or salmeterol ± inhaled corticosteroids for subjects with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The primary objective of this study was to establish the safety profile of daratumumab given as monotherapy in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma to at least 2 different cytoreductive therapies and without further established treatment options.</p><p>The secondary objectives were:</p><p>• To establish the pharmacokinetic profile of daratumumab after single and multiple infusions for both phase 2 and phase 3 drug products.</p><p>• To evaluate the efficacy of monotherapy daratumumab in the proposed patient population.</p><p>• To establish safe dose levels for future studies with daratumumab.</p><p>• To optimize pre-infusion medication and infusion parameters for daratumumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To evaluate the immunogenicity of the drug and biomarkers of daratumumab's mechanism of action, infusion reactions and clinical response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes/endpoints</head><p>The primary efficacy endpoint was overall response rate (ORR), which was defined as the proportion of patients who achieved a partial response (PR) or better. Objective response evaluations were made based on assessments from a computerized algorithm using the International Multiple Myeloma Working Group • Change in bone marrow % plasma cells, based on results from either biopsy or aspirate.</p><p>• Clinical benefit rate, defined as the proportion of patients with best response of minor response (MR) or better (including PR, VGPR, CR and sCR).</p><p>• Time to progression (TTP), defined as the number of days from the date of the first infusion to the date of the first record of disease progression (IMWG criteria), confirmed by 2 consecutive assessments.</p><p>• Progression-free survival (PFS), defined as the time between the date of first dose of daratumumab and either disease progression or death, whichever occurred first.</p><p>• Duration of response (DOR), calculated from the date of the initial documentation of a response (PR or better) to the date of first documented evidence of progressive disease (IMWG criteria).</p><p>• Overall survival (OS), defined as the number of days from administration of the first infusion (day 1) to the date of death.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample size</head><p>For Part 2, up to 80 subjects could be enrolled, for a maximum of 112 subjects enrolled across both parts.</p><p>With the descriptive statistics methodology for the primary endpoint in mind, the impact of different sample sizes on the descriptive statistics is presented by the probability of making at least one observation of an event with rare incidence.</p><p>In addition, 2 sets of safety stopping rules were defined for Part 2: a set defined per cohort (N ≤30) and</p><p>another set for all cohorts combined (N ≤80). A stopping rule was triggered if the number of subjects experiencing a CAE (critical adverse event) was greater than or equal to the number shown in the Study Protocol for the indicated number of subjects enrolled. A CAE was defined as s study drug-related serious TEAEs with an onset within 48 hours after the start of the daratumumab infusion that corresponded to CTCAE Grade 3 or higher, did not respond to symptomatic therapy, and did not resolve within 6 hours from onset of the event.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomisation</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blinding (masking)</head><p>This was an open label study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical methods</head><p>No formal statistical hypothesis testing was planned. For each observed response category, a 2-sided 95% exact confidence interval (CI) was presented. For the calculation of ORR, those patients who were not evaluable for response were to be considered non-responders. The clinical benefit rate would be analysed similarly to the primary endpoint.</p><p>Additionally, in Part 2, descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation, median, and range) were provided to summarize time to first response and time to best response for responders in each treatment group. No inferential analysis was performed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant flow Recruitment</head><p>A total of 72 patients participated in the study. The study sites for Part 2 were in Denmark (2 sites), Sweden (2 sites), Netherlands (1 site), and the United States (1 site).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conduct of the study</head><p>The original protocol was amended 14 times, this included change of pre-and post-infusion medication, predose and infusion rate. The key amendments were the following:</p><p>• 9 th amendment (27 June 2011): the dosing period was expanded to 8 weeks with weekly infusions followed by bi-weekly infusions for additional 16 weeks.</p><p>• 11 th amendment (19 October 2012): the dose chosen for Part 2 was 8 mg/kg, and the treatment duration was increased up to 96 weeks or until disease progression or unmanageable toxicity.</p><p>• 13 th amendment (28 June 2013): schedule D changes to 16 mg/kg daratumumab to assess whether high levels of systemic exposure and consistent saturation of the CD38 target was needed to optimize efficacy of daratumumab.</p><p>• 14 th amendment (02-dec-2013): the study design was changed to include Schedule E to evaluate the Phase 3 drug product.</p><p>The major protocol violations in the study are summarized in the tables below.    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Numbers analysed</head><p>The following populations were:</p><p>• All-Treated Analysis Set included all enrolled subjects who received at least 1 dose of study drug. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes and estimation</head><p>Primary endpoint -ORR</p><p>The efficacy results in terms of the primary endpoint of ORR (cut-off date 09 January 2015) are summarized in the tables below.     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of main study</head><p>The following tables summarise the efficacy results from the main studies supporting the present application. These summaries should be read in conjunction with the discussion on clinical efficacy as well as the benefit risk assessment (see later sections).   In the subset of subjects who were refractory to pomalidomide or carfilzomib, or both, the median OS were 15.2 to 16.5 months (data not shown).</p><p>Tables 47 and 48 summarize previously published data for newer anti-MM drugs. .0 g/dL ≥8.0 g/dL NR Platelet count &gt;50x10 9 /L &gt;75x10 9 /L &gt;75x10 9 /L &gt;75x10 9 /L &gt;75x10 9 /L ≥50x10 9 /L ≥30x10 9 /L ANC &gt;1.0x10 9 /L ≥1.0x10 9 /L &gt;1.0x10 9 /L &gt;1.0x10 9 /L &gt;1.0x10 9 /L ≥1.0x10 9 /L NR Prior Therapy Prior lines of therapy, median  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supportive studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study GEN503</head><p>Study GEN503 was an open label, international, multicenter, dose escalating phase 1/2 trial investigating the safety of daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide (25 mg orally on Days 1 through 21 of each 28 day cycle) and dexamethasone (total dose of approximately 40 mg weekly) in patients with relapsed or relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma. The design of the study is presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">Table 50</ref>. The first subject started treatment on 17 March 2014, and the last subject started treatment on 13 August 2014. As of the clinical cutoff date 4 subjects from Phase 1 (n=13) and 6 subjects from Phase 2 (n=32) had discontinued treatment.</p><p>In Phase 2, 32 subjects were treated with 16 mg/kg daratumumab in combination with LEN/Dex. At the time of clinical cutoff, 81% of subjects received at least 7 treatment cycles (26 of 32 subjects). The median number of treatment cycles was 8 cycles (range of 1.0; 11.0). Twenty-six (26) of 32 subjects were continuing treatment.</p><p>The majority of subjects (81%) in Phase 2 were male and all subjects were White. In Phase 2, 66% (21/32 subjects) had received a prior PI and IMiD, and 22% (7/32) were double refractory to the most recent PI and IMiD.</p><p>Efficacy analyses from Phase 2 (16 mg/kg daratumumab) showed the following:</p><p>-Twenty-eight (28) of 32 subjects (88%) had an ORR of PR or better; 7 subjects had a stringent CR, 1 subject had a CR, and 9 subjects had a VGPR.</p><p>-Response to 16 mg/kg daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide/dexamethasone was rapid and durable. The median time to response was approximately 1 month. A median duration of response was not reached at the time of clinical cutoff; however, 93% of responders remained progression-free and alive after 6 months on treatment.</p><p>-At the time of clinical cutoff, disease progression had occurred in 5 subjects (16%). The median time to progression and a median PFS rate were not reached; however, 84% of subjects remained progression-free after 6 months.</p><p>-All subjects had substantial reductions in paraprotein from baseline; 31 subjects had at least a 50% reduction in paraprotein from baseline and 22 subjects had at least a 90% reduction in paraprotein from baseline.</p><p>-All responders who had bone marrow plasma cell data at baseline and first post-baseline measurement (20 subjects) had complete or near complete clearance of malignant plasma cells from their bone marrow (ie, &lt;5% plasma cells remaining). The study population included patients who were heavily pre-treated and highly refractory, thus standard treatment options such as alkylating agents, ASCT, bortezomib and lenalidomide were exhausted. The patient population was not only refractory to bortezomib and lenalidomide, but 95% of the study population in the MMY2002study was refractory towards the newer drugs, pomalidomide and carfilzomib.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.3.">Discussion on clinical efficacy Design and conduct of clinical studies</head><p>Patients with poor renal function and compromised haematology parameters were allowed to be included in the studies.</p><p>The recommended dose of 16 mg/kg was selected on the basis of the part 1 of Study GEN501 and study MMY2002. The dose of 16 mg/kg seems to offer a better antitumor activity than 8 mg/kg with an acceptable safety profile and to some extent comparable toxicity showed by the dose 8 mg/kg. Taking into account the PK data and the target saturation threshold for CD38, the selection of 16 mg/kg appears reasonable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy data and additional analyses</head><p>The GEN501 and MMY2002 studies showed that the 16 mg/kg dose met the protocol-specified criteria for continuation of an ORR of 15%. At 16 mg/kg, daratumumab, the response was rapid and durable, a total of 31 patients achieved response of PR or better based on IRC assessment; the ORR was 29% (95% CI:</p><p>21%, 39%). The responses were rapid with a median time to response of 1 month and the median duration of response was 7.4 months. The ORR was consistent across different clinically relevant subgroups, including those refractory to newer drugs, such as pomalidomide or carfilzomib. The ORRs of daratumumab in these populations (28% to 33%) were similar to the overall population (29% to 36%).</p><p>The data also demonstrated that 3 patients (3%) achieved stringent CR and 13 patients (12%) achieved VGPR or better in the MMY2002 study, while 5% had stringent CR in the GEN501 study. This depth of response, a combined VGPR or better rate of 11% is high for a single-agent therapy, when compared with other recently approved therapies, especially given the refractoriness of the study population. The median OS was 17.5 months for patients who received 16 mg/kg daratumumab. All patients with stringent CR/CR are still on treatment, with longest follow-up of 21.4 months.</p><p>Whether daratumumab can change the response of subsequent therapies due to its novel mechanism of action or whether it will be possible to identify potential predictors of response and resistance remains to be elucidated. In the ongoing and future studies as MMY3003 and MMY3004, the Applicant is planning to perform translational biomarker studies, analysis of CD38 expression, subsets of CD38+Tregs and CD38+ Bregs, enzymatic activity of CD38 and T cell clonality, genome sequencing and mRNA sequencing of CD38+ MM cell, and correlate this with clinical response/progression. The CHMP recommended the applicant to provide these data once available.</p><p>The Applicant has initiated an Early Access Programme in the U.S. which is being conducted under a clinical trial protocol (54767414MMY3010), this programme will also be expanded to include European countries. The objective of this programme is to provide early access to single agent daratumumab and collect additional data while the medication is not commercially available. By this program, over 600 patients will receive daratumumab. Multiple myeloma patients who have received at least 3 prior lines of therapy including a proteasome inhibitor (PI) and an immunomodulatory agent (IMiD) or whose disease is double refractory to both a PI and an IMiD will be eligible for the programme, thus the patient population is similar to the present study group. The CHMP recommended the applicant to provide the results of the US (?) Early Access Programme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional efficacy data needed in the context of a conditional MA</head><p>The absence of a control arm and the small number of patients treated with daratumumab in studies MMY2002 and GEN501 impacts on the interpretation of the clinical benefit of daratumumab in the treatment of adult patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 88/119 a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy.</p><p>To further support the results obtained in studies MMY2002 and GEN501, the Applicant provided historical previously published data. Although such a comparison should be done cautiously, an ORR of 29%-36% is quite high for monotherapy in this clinical setting and a clinical benefit for daratumumab, can be considered established, but a confirmation from phase III comparative studies is needed in order to better quantify the magnitude of the effect.</p><p>The Applicant has proposed to submit the final CSR for Phase 3 studies of daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide/low-dose dexamethasone (MMY3003) and of daratumumab in combination with bortezomib/low dose dexamethasone (MMY3004) in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma which are currently ongoing to meet this requirement. These studies are expected to generate comprehensive data to confirm the benefit-risk balance in the proposed indication.</p><p>Therefore, the CHMP has recommended imposing specific obligations in Annex II to the marketing authorization for the submission of the final results of ongoing Phase 3 studies MMY3003 and MMY3004.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.4.">Conclusions on the clinical efficacy</head><p>The clinical efficacy data available are adequate to support the efficacy of daratumumab in the treatment of adult patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy.</p><p>The CHMP considers the following measures necessary to address the missing efficacy data in the context of a conditional MA:</p><p>In order to address the uncertainties related to the single arm design of the pivotal study supporting the approval of Darzalex, the MAH should submit the results of study MMY3003, a phase III randomised study investigating lenalidomide and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously treated multiple myeloma.</p><p>In order to address the uncertainties related to the single arm design of the pivotal study supporting the approval of Darzalex, the MAH should submit the results of study MMY3004, a phase III randomised study investigating bortezomib and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously treated multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Clinical safety</head><p>The clinical studies that support the safety of daratumumab are presented in the figure below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 14: Overview of clinical studies supporting safety for daratumumab</head><p>The overview of these clinical studies is presented in the tables below.     </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adverse events</head><p>An overview of treatment emergent adverse events (TEAEs) observed in daratumumab monotherapy studies is provided in the tables below: The most common TEAEs are summarized in the table below:   Infusion-related reaction includes terms determined by investigators to be related to infusion, see below</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adverse events of special interest</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infusion-related reactions</head><p>Infusion-related reactions include but are not limited to the following multiple adverse reaction terms: nasal congestion, cough, chills, allergic rhinitis, throat irritation, dyspnoea, nausea (all ≥ 5%), bronchospasm (2.6%), hypertension (1.3%) and hypoxia (1.3%). The median time to onset of a reaction was 1.5 hours (range: 0.02 to 9.3 hours). Median durations of infusion for the first, second and subsequent infusions were 7.0, 4.6 and 3.4 hours respectively (SmPC section 4.8).   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><p>Of particular clinical concern were IRRs of bronchospasm, which are summarized in the next table:  One subject on daratumumab monotherapy developed a skin cancer (basal cell carcinoma) during the course of treatment (Study GEN501).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infections and Infestations</head><p>One subject on daratumumab monotherapy was diagnosed with adenocarcinoma with metastases (origin most likely the colon) and was withdrawn from the study (Study GEN501, Part 2).</p><p>One subject in combination therapy with daratumumab was reported to have gastric adenocarcinoma (Study GEN503).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Serious adverse event/deaths/other significant events</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Serious adverse event</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg monotherapy group, 50 subjects (32%) experienced treatment-emergent SAEs. The most common were pneumonia in 9 subjects (6%), general physical health deterioration, pyrexia (each in 5 subjects [3%]), and hypercalcemia in 4 subjects (3%). All other SAEs occurred in 3 or fewer subjects <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 65</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deaths</head><p>Fifteen deaths occurred within 30 days of last dose <ref type="table" target="#tab_17">(Table 66</ref>).</p><p>In the 16 mg/kg monotherapy group, 11 subjects died within 30 days of the last dose of study drug due to progressive disease, and 3 subjects died due to TEAEs not considered related to daratumumab <ref type="table" target="#tab_19">(Table   7)</ref>. One additional subject (in the 8 mg/kg group) died within 30 days of the last dose of study drug due to progressive disease <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 10</ref>).</p><p>In the total population, 15 subjects (6%) died within 30 days of the last dose of study drug. No TEAE with a fatal outcome (in 3 subjects [2%]) was considered by the investigator to be related to daratumumab Across all dose groups, 11 subjects (5%) experienced a Grade 5 TEAE. Ten of these were in the 16 mg/kg group; these were general physical health deterioration in 5 subjects; respiratory failure, pneumonia, cardiorespiratory arrest, hepatic failure, and hypercalcemia (each in 1 subject).</p><p>A total of 56 deaths were recorded (24% of the integrated safety population); of these, 46/56 deaths (82%) were due to progression of disease.</p><p>Three subjects in the 16 mg/kg group who died due to a TEAE. One subject from Study MMY2002 died of cardiorespiratory arrest due to H1N1 influenza. One subject from Study MMY2002 died due to general physical health deterioration secondary to aspiration pneumonia, and a second subject from Study GEN501 (Part 2) died due to pneumonia. None of the fatal TEAEs were considered related to study drug. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leukopenia/Neutropenia</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, of 154 of subjects with Grade 0-2 leukopenia at baseline, 26% (17%) worsened to Grade 3 and 3 (2%) worsened to Grade 4 during treatment. This pattern was similar to that observed across groups.</p><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, of 155 subjects with Grade 0-2 neutropenia at baseline, 25 (16%) worsened to Grade 3 and 6 (4%) worsened to Grade 4 during treatment. Treatment-emergent AEs of neutropenia were reported in 34 (22%) of these subjects, 19 (12%) of which were considered Grade 3-4. This was slightly higher than across dosing groups where treatment-emergent AEs of neutropenia were reported in 38 (16%), 21 (9%) of which were considered Grade 3-4.</p><p>No statistically significant trend in the TEAE rate of neutropenia or of neutropenic fever was found with increasing exposure, and no patients discontinued daratumumab due to neutropenia in any of the treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lymphopenia</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, of 138 subjects with baseline Grade 0-2 lymphocyte count, 46 (33%) worsened to Grade 3 and 6 (4%) worsened to Grade 4 during treatment. This was similar to the findings across dosing groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Natural Killer Cells</head><p>Natural Killer Cells counts decreased or remained low in the majority of subjects treated in the daratumumab monotherapy studies. the incidence of TEAEs of infection and infestation did not increase over time (ie, the incidence was 50% during the first 6 months of treatment and 38% after 6 months of treatment.</p><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, of 111 subjects with normal NK cell counts at baseline, 108 were low at some time during the study, and 3 remained normal. All of the subjects with low or high NK cells at baseline had low NK cells at some time during the study.</p><p>In the total population, 137 of 143 subjects with normal NK cell counts at baseline were low at some time during the study, and 6 remained normal. All of the subjects with low or high NK cell counts at baseline had low NK cell counts during the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemistry</head><p>Chemistry laboratory abnormalities generally occurred with a low incidence, most were grade 1-2 and most were related to underlying Multiple Myeloma. Grade 3-4 changes were infrequent. Across dosing groups, the most common Grade 3-4 chemistry laboratory abnormalities were hypercalcemia (15 subjects (6%), Grade 4 in 7 subjects), and hyponatremia (13 subjects (6%), Grade 4 in 1 subject).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electrocardiogram Assessment</head><p>The clinical and pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic data demonstrate that daratumumab does not cause clinically relevant QT prolongation. There were no subjects with QTcF values &gt;500 ms or changes from baseline of &gt;60 ms, and no TEAE of cardiac arrhythmia associated with QT prolongation was reported.</p><p>In   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sex</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, 84 (54%) of the subjects were male while 72 (46%) were female. No differences in the rate of AEs between males and females were observed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Race</head><p>There was an overrepresentation of White study participants (76%) in the 16 mg/kg group. No differences in the rate of AEs between races were observed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline Renal Function</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, 95 (61%) of subjects had baseline CrCl ≥60 mL/min, 56 (36%) had baseline CrCl between 30 to &lt;60 mL/min while 5 (3%) had baseline CrCl &lt;30 mL/min. In the latter group there were too few subjects to make meaningful comparisons. In the two former groups, the incidences of AEs were similar.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline Hepatic Function</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, 134 (86%) subjects had normal hepatic function at baseline while 21 (13%) had mildly impaired hepatic function at baseline. Overall, the incidence of AEs by baseline hepatic function was similar to the total 16 mg/kg group. When comparing subjects with mildly impaired hepatic function with all subjects, there was a higher incidence of SAEs (9 subjects (43%) vs. 50 subjects (32%)), Grade ≥3 AEs (15 subjects (71%) vs. 88 subjects (56%)) and AEs leading to treatment discontinuation (4 subjects (19%) vs. 6 subjects (4%)).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety related to drug-drug interactions and other interactions</head><p>No formal drug-drug interaction studies have been performed with daratumumab (see discussion on clinical safety).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discontinuation due to adverse events</head><p>In the 16 mg/kg group in the monotherapy studies, a total of 6 patients discontinued treatment due to AEs. None of these AEs were related to daratumumab as determined by the investigator. Across all treatment groups, a total of 11 subjects discontinued due to AEs. Five were considered drug related. Four of the 5 occurred in the ≤4 mg/kg group and 1 occurred in the 24 mg/kg group. Two of the patients in the ≤4 mg/kg group who discontinued due to AEs did not receive prophylactic post-infusion steroids, as the protocol did not call for it at the time.</p><p>In one of the 5 patients who discontinued treatment due to AEs this was due to hepatic function abnormal.</p><p>The remaining 4 patients discontinued due to infusion related reactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post marketing experience</head><p>N/A</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.1.">Discussion on clinical safety</head><p>Safety data from a total of 331 subjects treated with daratumumab (237 as monotherapy, 94 as part of a combination therapy regimen) is considered sufficient to evaluate the safety profile of daratumumab under conditional approval.</p><p>The proposed treatment dose applied for (16 mg/kg) corresponds to the treatment dose of the majority of subjects included in the clinical studies (240/331). Long term data (exposure ≥6 months) has been obtained from 52 subjects however, there is limited data on the long term use &gt;2 years of daratumumab.</p><p>Long term extension trials are ongoing, and will provide additional safety information when completed.</p><p>Long term use (&gt;2 years) is included in the RMP under missing information.</p><p>The majority of subjects (99%) in the 3 pivotal studies experienced AEs. Most notably, infusion related reactions were common which also justifies the recommendation of both pre-and post-infusion steroid treatment. Other frequently occurring AEs were fatigue, nausea, anaemia, neutropenia, back pain, cough and thrombocytopenia.</p><p>In the 16 mg/kg group, the most common infections were upper respiratory tract infections, However, there was no reported interference with the clinical decision to administer blood transfusions.</p><p>Moreover, no AEs were reported in relation to blood transfusions.</p><p>In the event of a planned transfusion blood transfusion centres should be notified of this interference with indirect antiglobulin tests. If an emergency transfusion is required, non-cross-matched ABO/RhD-compatible RBCs can be given per local blood bank practices (SmPC sections 4.4 and 4.5).</p><p>An additional risk minimisation measure is considered to be needed to address this safety concern. To make HCPs and Blood banks aware of the risk associated with blood typing, educational materials will be distributed that include an HCP and blood bank brochure and a patient alert card. Survey tools will be used to measure (and increase) the awareness of the risk of interference of blood typing associated with daratumumab. Final results will be presented in the next PSUR/PBRER after the survey has been concluded (see RMP). Daratumumab targets CD38 which is expressed on NK cells. This is evidenced by an expected decrease in the number of NK cells. However, this was not accompanied by an overall increase in infections or infestations and infections did not become more frequent with time on treatment. Prolonged decrease in NK cells has been classified as an important potential risk in the RMP.</p><p>There is a theoretical risk of haemolysis. Continuous monitoring for this safety signal will be performed in clinical studies and post-marketing safety data (SmPC section 4.8). Intravascular haemolysis has been classified as an important potential risk in the RMP. The immunogenicity of daratumumab has been evaluated in 2 monotherapy daratumumab studies (GEN501 and MMY2002) using validated Charles River ECLIA methods. Limitations in detecting anti-daratumumab antibodies in the presence of high concentrations of daratumumab cannot be ruled out. Therefore, the Applicant will develop a new method for detecting ADAs (See RMP). Immunogenicity has been classified as an important potential risk in the RMP however until further information are available, the following text is included in section 5.1 of the SmPC: ''Patients (n = 199) were evaluated for anti -therapeutic antibody responses to daratumumab at multiple time points during treatment and up to 8 weeks following the end of treatment. Following the start of daratumumab treatment, none of the patients tested positive for anti-daratumumab antibodies. However, the employed assay has limitations in detecting anti-daratumumab antibodies in the presence of high concentrations of daratumumab.</p><p>Therefore, the incidence of antibody development might not have been reliably determined".</p><p>Among AEs of higher grades, haematologic AEs were common, but no clear dose-dependency was noted for grade 5 TEAEs. In the 16 mg/kg group, 6% of the patients had grade 5 TEAEs, 4% of the patients in the &lt; 4 mg/kg group, and none in either the 8 or 24 mg/kg groups. The incidence of grade 3 or 4 TEAE were similar across all dose groups.</p><p>Apart from pneumonia, common SAEs were general physical health deterioration, pyrexia and hypercalcemia. Three deaths occurred within 30 days of the last dose of study drug which were caused by adverse events but none were considered related to study drug.</p><p>Anaemia and/or thrombocytopenia were experienced by many study subjects. However, anaemia and thrombocytopenia are frequently associated with Multiple Myeloma. It was apparent that higher incidences of anaemia and thrombocytopenia were observed among non-responders to daratumumab as compared with responders, therefore they are more likely due to the underlying disease than to the daratumumab treatment.</p><p>Leukopenia and neutropenia were also observed, No statistically significant trend in the TEAE rate of neutropenia or of neutropenic fever was found with increasing exposure, and no patients discontinued daratumumab due to neutropenia in any of the treatment.</p><p>Most chemistry laboratory abnormalities occurred with a low incidence, were of low grade and most were related to underlying Multiple Myeloma. There were no safety signals identified in a review of vital signs.</p><p>No formal QT studies of daratumumab were conducted, but ECGs were systematically collected and reviewed. Although few ECG abnormalities were detected, in Study GEN501 Part 2 a statistically significant QT-prolongation was indeed observed. Although this was not observed in Part 1 of the study and may in part be attributable to an observed increase in heart rate, however, as discussed in Clinical Pharmacology, conflicting results were observed in Study GEN501 Part 1 and Part 2.</p><p>No differences in the incidence of AEs were observed with regard to age groups, sex, race, baseline renal or hepatic function, geographical area or drug product. For renal and hepatic function it is noted that some groups contain only few subjects.</p><p>Due to the large, overlapping CIs, no statistically significant trend in the TEAE rate was found with increasing drug exposure. IRRs were the most frequently observed TEAEs in all treatment groups, but most of them were grade 1 or 2. In the 16 mg/kg group, IRRs were reported in 48% of the patients and 55% in the 8 mg/kg group; 3% and 4% of patients, respectively, had Grade 3 IRRs, but no grade 4 IRR was noted in the two dose groups. All IRRs were well-managed, and none resulted in discontinuation from treatment.</p><p>Women of child-bearing potential should use effective contraception during, and for 3 months after cessation of daratumumab treatment (SmPC section 4.6).</p><p>There are no human or animal data to assess the risk of daratumumab use during pregnancy. IgG1 monoclonal antibodies are known to cross the placenta after the first trimester of pregnancy. Therefore daratumumab should not be used during pregnancy unless the benefit of treatment to the woman is considered to outweigh the potential risks to the fetus. If the patient becomes pregnant while taking this medicine, the patient should be informed of the potential risk to the fetus (SmPC section 4.6).</p><p>It is not known whether daratumumab is excreted into human or animal milk. Maternal IgG is excreted in human milk, but does not enter the neonatal and infant circulations in substantial amounts as they are degraded in the gastrointestinal tract and not absorbed. The effect of daratumumab on newborns/infants is unknown. A decision should be made whether to discontinue breast-feeding or to discontinue daratumumab therapy taking into account the benefit of breast feeding for the child and the benefit of therapy for the woman (SmPC section 4.6). Use in pregnancy and lactation is included in the RMP under missing information.</p><p>Due to the small population of patients ≥75 years (n=18), ''Use in the elderly over 75 years'' is added as missing information in the RMP until Phase 3 trials are completed. Additional analyses of covariates (including age ≥75 years) will be done with larger sample sizes as current Phase 3 trials reach maturation (see discussion on clinical pharmacology).</p><p>There has been no experience of overdosage in clinical studies. Doses up to 24 mg/kg have been administered intravenously in a clinical study. There is no known specific antidote for daratumumab overdose. In the event of an overdose, the patient should be monitored for any signs or symptoms of adverse effects and appropriate symptomatic treatment should be instituted immediately. Daratumumab is not expected to have a potential for abuse (SmPC section 4.9).</p><p>Daratumumab has no or negligible influence on the ability to drive and use machines. However fatigue has been reported in patients taking daratumumab and this should be taken into account when driving or using machines (SmPC section 4.7).</p><p>No drug-drug interaction studies have been performed. However, as daratumumab is an IgG, renal excretion and hepatic enzyme-mediated metabolism is considered unlikely.</p><p>In the group treated with the proposed dose of 16 mg/kg, a total of 6 subjects discontinued treatment due to AEs. None of these were related to daratumumab as determined by the investigator. Across all treatment groups, additionally 5 subjects discontinued treatment due to AEs which were indeed related to daratumumab as determined by the investigator. Four of the 5 AEs were IRRs but 2 of these occurred before the protocol was amended to include post-treatment administration of steroids.</p><p>From the safety database all the adverse reactions reported in clinical trials have been included in the Summary of Product Characteristics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.2.">Conclusions on the clinical safety</head><p>The overall safety profile of daratumumab 16 mg/kg dosing regimen is considered acceptable for use in the treatment of adult patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy and appears favourable. The adverse events appeared manageable.</p><p>The CHMP also considers the following measure necessary to address the missing safety data in the context of a conditional MA:</p><p>The safety data provided based on a single-arm, open-label pivotal study was quite limited. Additional safety data from the ongoing comparative phase III studies assessing lenalidomide and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab (study MMY3003) and bortezomib and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (study MMY3004), will be provided to further establish the safety profile of daratumumab. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Risk Management Plan</head><p>The CHMP received the following PRAC advice on the submitted RMP.</p><p>The PRAC considered that the RMP version 1.0 (dated 03 September 2015) could be acceptable if the applicant implements the changes to the RMP as described in the PRAC endorsed PRAC Rapporteur Updated assessment report.</p><p>The CHMP endorsed the PRAC advice with changes.</p><p>The applicant implemented the changes in the RMP as requested by PRAC and CHMP.</p><p>The CHMP endorsed the RMP version 1.2 (dated 30 March 2016) with the following content:  Therefore the summary of product characteristics and the package leaflet includes a statement that this medicinal product is subject to additional monitoring and that this will allow quick identification of new safety information. The statement is preceded by an inverted equilateral black triangle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Benefit-Risk Balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Beneficial effects</head><p>Daratumumab monotherapy at 16 mg/kg achieved an ORR of 29% in this studied population. The response data were supported by the GEN501 study, which had an ORR of 36% among patients treated with 16 mg/kg daratumumab. The ORR was consistent across different clinically relevant subgroups, such as number of prior lines of therapy, type of myeloma (IgG, non IgG), baseline renal function, refractory status including those refractory to newer drugs, such as pomalidomide or carfilzomib. The ORRs of daratumumab in these populations (28% to 33%) were similar to the overall population (29% to 36%).</p><p>The responses were rapid with a median time to response of 1 month and the median duration of response was 7.4 months.</p><p>A response of VGPR or better rate of 12% in the MMY2002 study was demonstrated. In the MMY2002 and GEN501, 3% and 5% of the patients respectively achieved stringent CR/CR.</p><p>For the combined studies, the median OS was 20.1 months after a median duration of follow-up of 20.77 months. Percentages of events in the MMY2002 and GEN501 were 53.8% and 38.1% respectively, with a 24-month OS rate of 41.3% and 57.4% respectively. The median OS for patients in the MMY2002 study who were refractory to pomalidomide was 13.8 months and 18.7 months in the GEN501 study. For patients refractory to carfilzomib, the median OS in study MMY2002 was 15.2 months and NE in the GEN501. Finally, the median OS in the MMY2002 study who were refractory to both pomalidomide and carfilzomib was 13.8 months and 16.5 months in the GEN501 study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uncertainty in the knowledge about the beneficial effects</head><p>The design of the study with no comparative arm is of concern because the ORR, PFS, and OS data cannot be directly compared to other treatment results in the same population. To further support the results obtained in studies MMY2002 and GEN501, the Applicant will submit the final CSR for study MMY3003 an ongoing phase 3, two arm, randomized, parallel-group study designed to compare the efficacy of daratumumab when combined with lenalidomide and dexamethasone (DRd) to that of lenalidomide and dexamethasone (Rd) in subjects with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma and also for study MMY3004, phase 3, two arm, randomized, parallel-group study designed to compare the efficacy of daratumumab when combined with bortezomib and dexamethasone (DVd) to that of bortezomib and dexamethasone (Vd) in subjects with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma.</p><p>Therefore, the CHMP has recommended two specific obligations in Annex II to the marketing authorization for the submission of the final results of ongoing studies MMY3003 and MMY3004.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risks</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Unfavourable effects</head><p>The most frequently reported adverse reactions were IRRs (48%); see section 4.4. Other frequently reported adverse reactions (≥ 20%) were fatigue (39%), pyrexia (21%), cough (21%), nausea (27%), back pain (23%), upper respiratory tract infection (20%), anaemia (27%), neutropenia (22%) and thrombocytopenia (20%).</p><p>Most AEs were of lower grades. Daratumumab targets CD38 which is expressed on NK cells and consequently the majority of subjects experienced a temporal decrease or had continually low measurements of NK cells. However, the overall incidence of infections and infestations remained comparable to the total population and consistent with underlying Multiple Myeloma. Notably, the incidence of opportunistic infections was low (2%).</p><p>While 15% of study subjects experienced AEs leading to infusion delays and 40% of subjects experienced AEs leading to infusion interruptions, the number of patients who permanently discontinued treatment due to AEs was low.</p><p>The incidence of death within 30 days of the last dose of study drug was relatively low. While 15 subjects in total died within this period, only 3 of the deaths were caused by AEs and none were considered related to study drug.</p><p>In study MMY1002, all 9 subjects experienced a positive result in indirect Coomb's Test after treatment with daratumumab. However, there was no reported interference with the clinical decision to administer blood transfusions and no AEs were reported in relation to blood transfusions.</p><p>Uncertainty in the knowledge about the unfavourable effects</p><p>The safety data provided based on a single-arm, open-label pivotal study was quite limited. Additional safety data from the ongoing comparative phase III studies assessing daratumumab versus lenalidomide and dexamethasone (study MMY3003) and versus bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma (study MMY3004), will be provided to further establish the safety profile of daratumumab.</p><p>No plausible cause for the findings of the statistically significant QTc prolongation in Study GEN501 Part 2 has been identified. A (thorough) QTc study is not feasible but the Applicant will incorporate more well-controlled data collection in a substudy of the ongoing Study SMM2001 to further evaluate a relationship between daratumumab concentration and QTc (see RMP).</p><p>Finally, only 11% of the patients treated with the dose of 16 mg/kg were older than 75 years, though the ORR was in line with the overall population (31% vs 25%). Use in the elderly ≥ 75 years is included in the RMP under missing information (see RMP).</p><p>Limitations in detecting anti-daratumumab antibodies in the presence of high concentrations of daratumumab cannot be ruled out (see discussion on clinical pharamacology). Therefore, the Applicant will develop a new method for detecting ADAs (see RMP).</p><p>In study MMY1002, all 9 subjects experienced a positive result in indirect Coomb's Test after treatment with daratumumab. However, there was no reported interference with the clinical decision to administer blood transfusions and no AEs were reported in relation to blood transfusions. An additional risk minimisation measure is considered to be needed to address this safety concern (see RMP and Annex II).</p><p>Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 115/119 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Effects Table</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-risk balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Importance of favourable and unfavourable effects</head><p>A positive effect on ORR has been demonstrated for daratumumab monotherapy. Furthermore, the safety profile can be acceptable in the context of the stage of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-risk balance</head><p>Based on the positive clinical effect of daratumumab as a single agent drug that has been demonstrated in a highly refractory/relapsed patient population and that the safety profile is acceptable and manageable, the benefit/risk balance is positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion on the benefit-risk balance</head><p>Daratumumab, a novel monoclonal antibody that specifically binds to the cell surface molecule CD38, has shown a durable response rate in a heavily pre-treated population with limited treatment options. Given the limitations in the number of patients treated and the design of the studies the applicant has applied for a conditional approval.</p><p>The CHMP considered that DARZALEX falls under the scope of Article 2 of Commission Regulation (EC) No. a) The benefit/risk balance of the product is positive.</p><p>The ORR of 29% obtained with daratumumab in pivotal study MT103-211 is significant and clinically relevant in patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy despite the absence of confirmatory controlled data. Patients were heavily pretreated, and 79.8% and 69.4% had received more than 3 lines of prior therapy in the MMY2002 and GEN501 studies respectively, further 95% and 95.8% respectively were refractory to both PI's and IMiD's.</p><p>Together with an acceptable safety-profile in patients in the proposed indication, the benefit-risk balance is considered positive.</p><p>b) It is likely that the Applicant will be able to provide comprehensive data</p><p>The applicant will provide further comprehensive clinical data to confirm efficacy and safety of daratumumab in the proposed indication. More specifically the Applicant will provide:</p><p>-Study MMY 3003 a phase 3, two arm, randomized, parallel-group trial of lenalidomide and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously-treated multiple myeloma.</p><p>-Study MMY 3004, a Phase 3, two arm, randomized, parallel-group trial of bortezomib and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously-treated multiple myeloma.</p><p>These phase 3 studies of daratumumab in combination with lenalidomide/low-dose dexamethasone (MMY3003) and bortezomib/low dose dexamethasone (MMY3004) in patients with relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma are currently ongoing. A total of 560 and 480 patients respectively are planning to be randomized in these studies. These phase III studies are not in the exact same setting where daratumumab is authorised. It is anticipated that approximately 240 subjects across both studies enrolled will have received 3 or more prior lines of therapy. These studies will therefore provide comparative efficacy and safety data for daratumumab in combination with standard backbone therapies in a population that overlaps that enrolled in MMY2002 and GEN501. In the absence of controlled single-agent data in patients who have exhausted all standard treatments as in MMY2002 and GEN501, these studies can provide controlled data in a larger target population within the same condition which will further define the benefit-risk of daratumumab in the proposed indication. Both studies are ongoing and Assessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 117/119 the data will be provided by the applicant for study MMY3003 by the September 2017 and for study MMY3004 by December 2016.</p><p>c) The product fulfils an unmet medical need.</p><p>Daratumumab fulfils an unmet medical need for patients with poor long-term prognosis and limited treatment alternatives. Daratumumab has a new mechanism of action, a manageable safety profile, and treatment with daratumumab was associated with durable response, which provides a major therapeutic advantage.</p><p>d) The benefits to the public health of the immediate availability of the product outweigh the risks inherent in the fact that additional data are still required</p><p>In view of the high ORR compared to available treatment options, the immediate availability of DARZALEX on the market outweighs the risk inherent in the fact that additional data are still required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Recommendations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Similarity with authorised orphan medicinal products</head><p>The CHMP by consensus is of the opinion that Darzalex is not similar to Thalidomide Celgene, Revlimid, Imnovid, Farydak and Kyprolis within the meaning of Article 3 of Commission Regulation (EC) No.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>847/200. See appendix 1.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome</head><p>Based on the CHMP review of data on quality, safety and efficacy, the CHMP considers by consensus that the risk-benefit balance of Darzalex in the treatment of adult patients with relapsed and refractory multiple myeloma, whose prior therapy included a proteasome inhibitor and an immunomodulatory agent and who have demonstrated disease progression on the last therapy is favourable and therefore recommends the granting of the conditional marketing authorisation subject to the following conditions:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions regarding supply and use</head><p>Medicinal product subject to restricted medical prescription (see Annex I: Summary of Product Characteristics, section 4.2).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions and requirements of the Marketing Authorisation</head><p>•</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Periodic Safety Update Reports</head><p>The requirements for submission of periodic safety update reports for this medicinal product are set out in the list of Union reference dates (EURD list) provided for under Article 107c <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> of Directive 2001/83/EC and any subsequent updates published on the European medicines web-portal.</p><p>The marketing authorisation holder shall submit the first periodic safety update report for this product within 6 months following authorisation. An updated RMP should be submitted:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product</head><p>• At the request of the European Medicines Agency;</p><p>• Whenever the risk management system is modified, especially as the result of new information being received that may lead to a significant change to the benefit/risk profile or as the result of an important (pharmacovigilance or risk minimisation) milestone being reached.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional risk minimisation measures</head><p>Prior to the launch of DARZALEX (daratumumab) in each Member State (MS) the Marketing Authorisation Holder (MAH) must agree about the content and format of the educational materials, aiming at increasing awareness about the Important Identified Risk of "Interference for blood typing (minor antigen) (Positive Indirect Coombs' test)" and providing guidance on how to manage it.</p><p>The MAH shall ensure that in each MS where DARZALEX (daratumumab) is marketed, all HCPs and patients who are expected to prescribe, dispense and receive this product have access to/are provided with the below.</p><p>The HCPs and Blood Banks educational materials shall contain the following key elements:</p><p>o The guide for HCPs and Blood Banks, to advice about the risk of interference for blood typing and how to minimise it;</p><p>o The Patient Alert Card.</p><p>The Guide for HCP and Blood Banks shall contain the following key elements:</p><p>o All patients should be typed and screened prior to start treatment with daratumumab; alternatively, phenotyping may also be considered;</p><p>o Daratumumab-mediated positive indirect Coombs test (interfering with cross-matching of blood) may persist for up to 6 months after the last product's infusion; therefore, the HCP should advise the patient to carry the Patient Alert Card until 6 months after the treatment has ended;</p><p>o Daratumumab bound to Red Blood Cells (RBCs) may mask the detection of antibodies to minor antigens in the patient's serum;</p><p>o The determination of a patient's ABO and Rh blood type are not impacted;</p><p>o The interference mitigation methods include treating reagent RBCs with dithiothreitol (DTT) to disrupt daratumumab binding or other locally validated methods. Since the Kell Blood group system is also sensitive to DTT treatment, Kell-negative units should be supplied after ruling out or identifying alloantibodies using DTT-treated RBCs. Alternatively, genotyping may also be considered;</p><p>o In case of urgent need for transfusion, non-cross matched ABO/RhD compatible RBC units can be administered as per local bank practices;</p><p>o In the event of a planned transfusion, the HCPs should notify blood transfusion centres about the interference with indirect antiglobulin tests;</p><p>o Reference to the need to consult the Summary of Product Characteristics (SmPC);</p><p>o Reference to the need of giving the Patient Alert Card to the patients and to advise them to consult the Package Leaflet (PL).</p><p>The Patient Alert Card shall contain the following key elements:</p><p>o A warning message for HCPs treating the patient at any time, including in conditions of emergency, that the patient is using DARZALEX (daratumumab), and that this treatment is associated with the Important Identified Risk of Interference for blood typing (minor antigen) (Positive Indirect Coombs' test), which might persist for up to 6 months after the last product's infusion; and a clear reference that the patient should continue to carry this card until 6 months after the treatment has ended;</p><p>o Contact details of the DARZALEX (daratumumab) prescriber;</p><p>o Reference to the need to consult the Package Leaflet (PL).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Obligation to complete post-authorisation measures for the conditional marketing authorisation</head><p>This being a conditional marketing authorisation and pursuant to Article 14 <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> of Regulation (EC) No 726/2004, the MAH shall complete, within the stated timeframe, the following measures:</p><p>Description Due date In order to address the uncertainties related to the single arm design of the pivotal study supporting the approval of Darzalex, the MAH should submit the results of study MMY3003, a phase III randomised study investigating lenalidomide and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously treated multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="30">September 2017</head><p>In order to address the uncertainties related to the single arm design of the pivotal study supporting the approval of Darzalex, the MAH should submit the results of study MMY3004, a phase III randomised study investigating bortezomib and dexamethasone with or without daratumumab in patients with previously treated multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="31">December 2016</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product to be implemented by the Member States.</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New Active Substance Status</head><p>Based on the CHMP review of data on the quality properties of the active substance, the CHMP considers that daratumumab is qualified as a new active substance.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>SmPC section 5.2).Gender [female (n = 91), male (n = 132)] did not affect exposure of daratumumab to a clinically relevant degree (SmPC section 5.2).No formal studies of daratumumab in patients with renal impairment have been conducted. A population PK analysis was performed based on pre-existing renal function data in patients receiving daratumumab, including 71 with normal renal function (creatinine clearance [CRCL] ≥ 90 mL/min), 78 with mild renal impairment (CRCL &lt; 90 and ≥ 60 mL/min), 68 with moderate renal impairment (CRCL &lt; 60 and ≥ 30 mL/min), and 6 with severe renal impairment or end stage renal disease (CRCL&lt; 30 mL/min). No clinically important differences in exposure to daratumumab were observed between patients with renal impairment and those with normal renal function (SmPC section 5.2).No formal studies of daratumumab in patients with hepatic impairment have been conducted. Changes in hepatic function are unlikely to have any effect on the elimination of daratumumab since IgG1 molecules such as daratumumab are not metabolised through hepatic pathways. A population PK analysis was performed to evaluate the effect of hepatic impairment as defined using the National Cancer Institute (NCI) criteria of hepatic dysfunction on the clearance of daratumumab based on pre existing hepatic function data in 223 patients. No clinically important differences in the exposure to daratumumab were observed between patients with mild hepatic impairment (TB 1.0 x to 1.5 x ULN or AST &gt; ULN; n = 34) and those with normal hepatic function (TB and AST ≤ ULN; n = 189). Daratumumab has not been studied in patients with moderate (TB &gt; 1.5 x to 3 x ULN and any AST) or severe (TB &gt; 3 x ULN and any AST) hepatic impairment (SmPC section 5.2).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>HASM) cells (Kang BN et al. The FASEB Journ, 2006 May, vol 20: 1000-2 [E170-8], Tirumurugaan KG et al. Resp Research2008,9:26-40). No significant difference in median steroid dose between responders and non-responders though no statistical analyses have been observed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>n=127). Hepatic impairment may also have impact on levels of albumin or indirect pathway of elimination of daratumumab. This was evaluated by studying albumin's (&lt;35 g/L vs. ≥ 35 g/L) effect on overall response rate (ORR) before and after adjusting for drug exposure. The effect of albumin (&lt;35 g/L vs. ≥ 35 g/L) on ORR before and after adjusting for daratumumab exposure is similar and these results are in line with the results of the analysis performed with albumin as a continuous variable supporting that albumin does not affect the effect of daratumumab. The CHMP recommended that the impact of baseline Assessment report EMA/278085/2016Page 40/119 hepatic impairment on safety and efficacy of daratumumab should be further characterized through the collection and analysis of additional PK data from the ongoing clinical studies.NK cells are known to express high levels of CD38 and are susceptible to daratumumab mediated cell lysis. Decreases in absolute counts and percentages of total NK cells (CD16+CD56+) and activated (CD16+CD56dim) NK cells in peripheral whole blood and bone marrow were observed with daratumumab treatment. However, baseline levels of NK cells or kinetics of NK cell decrease did not show an association with clinical response (SmPC section 5.1).T cells (CD3+, CD4+, and CD8+) are also known to express CD38 depending on the stage of development and the level of activation. Significant increases in CD4+ and CD8+ T cell absolute counts, and percentages of lymphocytes, were observed with daratumumab treatment in peripheral whole blood and bone marrow. In addition, T-cell receptor DNA sequencing verified that T-cell clonality was increased with daratumumab treatment, indicating immune modulatory effects that may contribute to clinical response (SmPC section 5.1).The immunogenicity of daratumumab has been evaluated in 2 monotherapy daratumumab studies (GEN501 and MMY2002) using validated Charles River ECLIA methods. Limitations in detecting anti-daratumumab antibodies in the presence of high concentrations of daratumumab cannot be ruled out. Therefore, the Applicant should develop a new method for detecting ADAs. Immunogenicity has been classified as an important potential risk in the Risk Management Plan (RMP) however until further information are available, the following text is included in section 5.1 of the SmPC:''Patients (n = 199)    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Prior documentation of monoclonal plasma cells in the bone marrow ≥ 10% or presence of a biopsy-proven plasmacytoma. -Presence of measurable disease at baseline as defined by any of the following: serum M-protein level ≥ 1.0 g/dL or urine M-protein level ≥ 200 mg/24 hours; or IgA multiple myeloma: Serum M-protein level ≥ 0.5 g/dL or urine M-protein level 200 mg/24 hours; or light chain multiple myeloma: Serum immunoglobulin free light chain (FLC) 10 mg/dL and abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa lambda FLC ratio.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Time to disease progression (TTP), defined as the number of days from the date of first dose of daratumumab to the date of first record of disease progression. Disease evaluations were to be performed by a central laboratory (unless otherwise specified) according to the Time and Events Schedule in the protocol until disease progression. The study used the IMWG consensus recommendation for multiple myeloma treatment response criteria (Durie 2007, Rajkumar 2011)4,13 presented in</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Part 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Stage 1 (18 from the 8 mg/kg group and 16 from the 16 mg/kg group), were included in the first interim analysis. The second interim analysis had a data cut-off 8 weeks after the last patient in Part 1 Stage 2 was dosed, and occurred in June and July 2014. An additional 25 patients were treated in the 16 mg/kg group in Part 1 Stage 2. Based on the cumulative response data observed in Part 1, 11 patients (27%) achieved response in the 16 mg/kg group and this group was further expanded in Part 2.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Figure 4 :</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Forest plot of subgroup analyses on overall best response on IRC Assessment (All treated -16 mg/kg group -Study MMY2002) based on IRC assessment (median duration of follow-up of 9.3 months) is summarized below:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Kaplan-Meier plot of PFS based on IRC assessment (All treated analysis set -Study MMY2002)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Kaplan-Meier plot of OS (All treated analysis set -Study MMY2002), Data cut-off 30 June 2015</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>1.</head><label></label><figDesc>Documented diagnosis of multiple myeloma requiring systemic therapy. Diagnosis of myeloma must have been made following the established criteria at the time of diagnosis (Durie 2006): • Presence of a measurable M-protein in serum and/or urine. Measurable M-protein was defined as: -Serum M-protein level ≥1.0 g/dL or urine M-protein level ≥200 mg/24 hours; or -Light chain multiple myeloma: Serum immunoglobulin free light chain (FLC) ≥10 mg/dL and abnormal serum immunoglobulin kappa lambda free light chain ratio. • and clonal plasma cells in the bone marrow or &gt;1 clonal plasmacytoma, but no bone marrow involvement • and at time of diagnosis, 1 or more of the following (attributable to underlying plasma cell disorder): -Calcium elevation (&gt;11.5 mg/dL [&gt;2.65 mmol/L]) -Renal insufficiency (creatinine &gt;2 mg/dL [177 µmol/L or more]) -Anaemia (hemoglobin &lt;10 g/dL [&lt;6.2 mmol/L] or 2 g/dL [1.25 mmol/L] &lt;normal) -Bone disease (lytic lesions or osteopenia) 2. Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) Performance Status Score of 0, 1, 2 3. Life expectancy &gt;3 months 4. Relapsed from or refractory to 2 or more different prior therapies, including IMiDs (eg, thalidomide, lenalidomide) and proteasome inhibitors, chemotherapy-based regimens, or autologous stem cell transplantation (ASCT) and without further established treatment options</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Dosing schedules: Study GEN501 (Part 1 and Part 2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>IMWG) Response Criteria for Multiple Myeloma (Durie 2006, Rajkumar 2011). The secondary endpoints were: • Time to response, defined as the time from the date of first dose of daratumumab to the date of initial documentation of a response (PR or better) • Time to best response, defined as the time between the date of first dose of daratumumab and the date of the initial evaluation of the best response (PR or better) to treatment • Reduction of serum/urine M-protein or free light-chain reduction, defined as the percent change from baseline at each post-baseline assessment visit in the quantification of the corresponding serum/urine M-protein or FLC, according to the measurable type at baseline.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>: 36: Summary of OS (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Figure 11 :</head><label>11</label><figDesc>Forest Plot of Subgroup Analyses on Overall Best Response; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002 and GEN501 Part 2)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>507/2006 as eligible for a Conditional Marketing Authorisation as it belongs to: a) Medicinal products designated as orphan medicinal products in accordance with Article 3 of Regulation (EC) No 141/2000; b) Medicinal products which aim at the treatment, the prevention or the medical diagnosis of seriously debilitating diseases or life-threatening diseases. Furthermore, the requirements listed in Article 4 of Commission Regulation No 507/2006 apply to daratuzumab on the basis of the following reasons:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Risk Management Plan (RMP)The MAH shall perform the required pharmacovigilance activities and interventions detailed in the agreedAssessment report EMA/278085/2016 Page 118/119 RMP presented in Module 1.8.2 of the Marketing Authorisation and any agreed subsequent updates of the RMP.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table of contents 1. Background information on the procedure</head><label></label><figDesc>.............................................. 6 1.1. Submission of the dossier ...................................................................................... 6 The CHMP adopted a report on similarity with Revlimid, Thalidomide Celgene, Imnovid, Farydak and Kyprolis on 1 April 2016.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">List of abbreviations kg kilogram LC light chain •</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ADA LEN ADCC LLOQ ADCP LMW ADR mAb ALKY mg ANC min ASCT mL AST MM AUC MR BORT MS CAE MVM CARF MRPP CCO NE CDC NGD cDNA NK CEX NR CHMP ORR CHO OS CI PAR cADPR PBMCs cIEF PFS Cmax PI CL PK CPP PL CQA PMT CR PO CRCL POM cSDS Pom+LD-dex pomalidomide plus low dose dexamethasone lenalidomide Anti-drug antibody Lower Limit of Quantification antibody-dependent cell-mediated cytotoxicity Low molecular weight antibody-dependent cell phagocytosis monoclonal antibody adverse drug reaction milligram alkylating agent minute absolute neutrophil count milliliter autologous stem cell transplant Multiple myeloma aspartate aminotransferase minimal response Area under the curve Mass spectrometry bortezomib minute virus of mice Critical adverse event Maximal reduction in paraprotein carfilzomib not evaluable Clinical cutoff date nicotinamide guanine dinucleotide complement-dependent toxicity natural killer complementary deoxyribonucleic acid Not reported Cation Exchange Chromatography overall response rate Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use overall survival Chinese hamster ovary proven acceptable ranges confidence interval peripheral blood mononuclear cells Cyclic ADP Ribose progression free survival capillary isoelectric focusing proteasome inhibitor Maximum serum concentration pharmacokinetic Total body clearance Package leaflet Critical process parameters Process monitoring test Critical quality attributes orally complete response pomalidomide creatinine clearance Capillary sodium dodecyl sulfate CSR PR partial response Clinical study report DBL PRAC Pharmacovigilance Risk Assessment Committee Database lock date DOR PRV pseudorabies virus duration of response DSC RBC Red blood cell differential scanning calorimetry EC REO reovirus type 3 European Commission EC 50 RMP Risk management plan half maximal effective concentration ECD RP-HPLC reversed phase high performance liquid chromatography Equivalent circular diameter ECG RP-UPLC reversed phase ultra performance liquid chromatography electrocardiogram ECLIA RVLP retrovirus-like particles electrochemiluminescent immunoassay ECOG SAE Serious adverse events Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group ELISA SCID severe combined immune deficiency enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay Emax SCT Stem cell transplant maximum effect ERA SmPC Summary of Product Characteristics Environmental risk assessment EURD SPE serum protein electrophoresis EU reference dates FDA SV-AUC sedimentation velocity analytical ultracentrifugation Food and Drug Administration FLC t 1/2 Terminal elimination half-life Free light chain FITC TEAE treatment emergent adverse event fluorescein isothiocyanate GCP t max Time for occurrence of C max Good Clinical Practice GLP THAL thalidomide Good Laboratory Practice HCP TTP time to progression Host cell protein HMW TTR time to response High molecular weight HPLC UV Ultraviolet High Performance Liquid Chromatography HuMab VGPR very good partial response Humanized monoclonal antibody IFE VIN viral inactivation and neutralisation immunofixation IgG1κ V z Volume of distribution during the elimination phase immunoglobulin G1 kappa IHC Immunohistochemistry XMuLV xenotropic murine leukemia virus</cell></row><row><cell>IMiD</cell><cell>immunomodulatory agent</cell></row><row><cell>IMWG</cell><cell>International Myeloma Working Group</cell></row><row><cell>IPC</cell><cell>In-process controls</cell></row><row><cell>IRC</cell><cell>Independent Review Committee</cell></row><row><cell>IRR</cell><cell>infusion related reaction</cell></row><row><cell>IV</cell><cell>intravenous</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>On request a protocol for the VIN intermediate stability has been presented, which includes release and shelf-life acceptance criteria.The Applicant agreed to introduce a test for protein concentration to the VIN intermediate release specification, and a measure for fragments into the stability specification for the VIN intermediate.</figDesc><table /><note>Several concerns were raised in relation to the Viral Inactivation and Neutralisation (VIN) intermediate in the active substance manufacturing process. Pooling of VIN intermediates thawed and pooled for further processing into active substance has been addressed. The strategy for VIN intermediate selection has been described. The acceptance criteria for the VIN intermediate have been aligned with manufacturing experience.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 : Maximal lysis and mean EC 50 values against Daudi-luc cells</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Lysis of CD38-Transfected CHO Cells:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2 :</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Maximal lysis and mean EC50 values against CD38-expressing CHO cellsa Max lysis expressed as %. EC50 values expressed as µg/ml</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>To evaluate the capacity of daratumumab to stimulate tumour cell phagocytosis in vivo, variant forms of daratumumab were created to either eliminate complement-activating function by altering a residue in the Fc domain (DARA-K322A), or to reduce phagocytosis-stimulatory function through isotype switching to the IgG2 equivalent (DARA-IgG2-K322A).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 17/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 4 : Serum PK parameters in Cynomolgus Monkeys following weekly IV administration of HuMab-CD38</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 5 : Repeated-dose toxicity studies Study ID Species/Sex/ Number/ Group Dose/Route Duration</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>NOEL/NOAE</cell><cell>Major findings</cell></row><row><cell>L</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(mg/kg/day</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 6 : Overview of clinical studies</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Study</cell><cell>No. of</cell><cell>Design</cell><cell>Study Posology</cell><cell>Patient characteristics</cell><cell>Total No of</cell></row><row><cell>ID</cell><cell>study</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Patients</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>centres /</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Enrolled</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>locations</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GEN501</cell><cell>Part1: 4</cell><cell>Phase 1/2</cell><cell>Part 1,</cell><cell>MM patients relapsed from</cell><cell>104</cell></row><row><cell>Key</cell><cell>sites in</cell><cell>Monotherapy</cell><cell>0.005-24mg/kg:n=32</cell><cell>or refractory to at least 2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>study</cell><cell>Denmark,</cell><cell></cell><cell>Part 2, 16mg/kg: n=42</cell><cell>different cytoreductive</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Netherlands</cell><cell></cell><cell>Part 2, 8mg/kg: n=30</cell><cell>therapies and without</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>further treatment options.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Sweden.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Part 2: 6</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>sites in Part</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1 countries</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and USA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MMY2002</cell><cell>26 sites in</cell><cell>Phase 2</cell><cell>16mg/kg: n= 106</cell><cell>MM patients who have</cell><cell>124</cell></row><row><cell>Key</cell><cell>USA,</cell><cell>Monotherapy</cell><cell>8mg/kg :n= 18</cell><cell>received at least 3 prior</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>study</cell><cell>Canada and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>lines of therapy (incl. PI</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Spain</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>and IMiD) or double</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>refractory to PI and IMiD</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">MMY1001 21 sites in</cell><cell>Phase 1/2 +</cell><cell>16 mg/kg: n=49</cell><cell>MM patients who received</cell><cell>49</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>USA, France</cell><cell>various</cell><cell></cell><cell>various chemotherapy,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and Spain</cell><cell>chemotherapy</cell><cell></cell><cell>usually a combination incl.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Velcade</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GEN503</cell><cell>11 sites in</cell><cell>Phase 1/2</cell><cell>16mg/kg: n=32</cell><cell>MM patients who had</cell><cell>45</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>France,</cell><cell>+len/dex</cell><cell>2-16mg/kg: n=13</cell><cell>relapsed or were refractory</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Italy,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>to at least 1 prior regimen</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Denmark,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Netherlands,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>UK, and USA</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">MMY1002 2 sites in</cell><cell>Phase 1</cell><cell>16mg/kg: n=5</cell><cell>MM patients with relapsed</cell><cell>9</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Japan</cell><cell>Monotherapy</cell><cell>8mg/kg: n=4</cell><cell>or refractory disease</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Part 1), following the first IV administration of daratumumab, the mean Vz across dose levels (0.1-24 mg/kg) ranged from 38.24 to 58.94 mL/kg, and the mean values across the same dose range following the last infusion ranged from 31.90 to 104.77 mL/kg . In the larger sample of 42 subjects administered the recommended dose of 16 mg/kg (Study GEN501, Part 2), Vd was 90.19±43.40 mL/kg after the first dose and 59.51±54.68 mL/kg following the last dose.The values volumes observed in subjects receiving 8 mg/kg in Study MMY2002 were mean Vd: 61.99±18.43 mL/kg), and in Japanese subjects participating in Study MMY1002: Mean Vd in subjects receiving 8 mg/kg was 66.94±30.89 mL/kg and mean Vd in subjects receiving 16 mg/kg was 57.97±3.29 mL/kg.</figDesc><table><row><cell>In GEN501 (</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 30/119</cell></row></table><note>Japanese Phase I Study MMY1002 and in the Phase II Study MMY2002.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Summary of Daratumumab Pharmacokinetic Parameters for the First Full Infusion: Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set (Study GEN501 Part 1)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Summary of Daratumumab Pharmacokinetic Parameters for the Last (7th) Full</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 9 : Number of subjects in different age groups</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Age 65-74</cell><cell>Age 75-84</cell><cell>Age 85+</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(Older subjects number</cell><cell>(Older subjects number</cell><cell>(Older subjects number</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>/total number)</cell><cell>/total number)</cell><cell>/total number)</cell></row><row><cell>Controlled Trials</cell><cell>0/237</cell><cell>0/237</cell><cell>0/237</cell></row><row><cell>Non Controlled Trials</cell><cell>84/237</cell><cell>20/237</cell><cell>0/237</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>1</head><label></label><figDesc>Day 2, but started to recover by Cycle 1 Day 4. Absolute counts of total NK cells increased until the next dose of daratumumab at Cycle 2, after which total NK cells decreased and did not recover during the treatment period.In the 16 mg/kg group (daratumumab dosing weekly for 8 weeks, every 2 weeks for 16 weeks, and every 4 weeks thereafter), reduced absolute cell counts of total NK cells were observed by Cycle 1 Day 8 and remained at low levels during daratumumab treatment. In addition, activated NK cells (CD16+CD56dim) in blood also decreased following daratumumab dosing similar to total NK cells, and remained low while on treatment. The change in total NK cells (as a percentage of lymphocytes in bone marrow) decreased from a median of 14.80% at baseline to 8.00% on treatment in the 8 mg/kg group and from a median of 19.80% at baseline to 4.60% on treatment in the 16 mg/kg group; these changes were statistically significant (p=0.0039 in 8 mg/kg; p&lt;0.0001 in 16 mg/kg group).</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head>Table 10 : Change from Baseline Versus the Daratumumab Serum Concentration -Estimates</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Pharmacokinetic-and pharmacodynamic analysis was performed using a linear mixed effects modeling approach to examine the relationship between the baseline-adjusted/corrected change in QTcF intervals and time-matched (within 3 hours) serum concentrations of daratumumab. The primary QT correction method was the Fridericia corrected QT (QTcF) because the Bazett correction is often less reliable. A statistically significant and borderline clinically relevant change in QTcF vs. daratumumab serum concentrations was observed with a ΔQTc of 12.34 msec at average daratumumab Cmax of 700</figDesc><table><row><cell>From Linear Mixed Model [1,2] QTc Fridericia Interval (msec) (Part 1, Pharmacokinetic-</cell></row><row><cell>Pharmacodynamic Population)</cell></row><row><cell>A separate analysis was performed for 72 subjects (8 mg/kg n=30; 16 mg/kg n=42) in Study GEN501</cell></row><row><cell>Part 2.</cell></row></table><note>µg/mL (p&lt;0.0001) (Table 19). No QTcF increase &gt;60 ms, no new QTcF &gt;500 ms, and no new abnormal U waves were observed.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 11 : Change from Baseline Versus the Daratumumab Serum Concentration -Estimates From Linear Mixed Model [1,2] QTc Fridericia Interval (msec) (Part 2 Pharmacokinetic- Pharmacodynamic Population)</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>subjects who completed at least 8 doses in the pooled MMY2002 dataset, (2) data from Study MMY2002 alone, and (3) subjects who completed at least 8 doses in Study MMY2002 alone. Both predicted and observed concentration data showed that approximately 80% of the subjects who were in the 16 mg/kg dose group and completed at least 8 infusions had Cpre-infusion,max above the estimated .</figDesc><table><row><cell>GEN501/</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 37/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Comparison of Daratumumab 8 mg/kg and 16 mg/kgSimulations were conducted to compare the trough concentrations for 8 mg/kg and 16 mg/kg dose levels under the recommended dosing schedule (ie, QW for 8 weeks, Q2W for 16 weeks, and then Q4W [8 doses for the current simulation] thereafter). Individual post hoc PK parameters based on the final population PK model for the 223 subjects from Studies GEN501 and MMY2002 were used.The percentage of subjects that would achieve 90% and 99% target saturation at the end of the QW and Q4W dosing period was calculated. The simulations showed that the majority of subjects (ie, &gt;80%) may achieve the 99% predicted target saturations after weekly dosing, and 90% predicted target saturations after Q4W (ie, at steady state) dosing at 16 mg/kg. However, in comparison, only approximately 50% of subjects may achieve 99% predicted target saturation after the QW dosing of 8 mg/kg daratumumab, and approximately 70% of subjects may achieve 90% target saturation at 8 mg/kg daratumumab after the Q4W dosing(Figure 8).Conclusively, the response rates were consistently and significantly higher and deeper at the 16 mg/kg dose level as compared to various schedules at the 8 mg/kg dose level.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 38/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>thrombocytopenia, anaemia, neutropenia, lymphopenia, and infections. Both treatment-emergent and drug-related adverse events (AEs) were investigated. The predicted end-of-infusion concentration after the first infusion (ie, Cmax after first dose, Cmax,1st) was explored for IRRs because the majority of IRRs occurred after the first dose, while the predicted maximal end-of-infusion concentration (ie, multiple-dose Cmax, Cpost-infusion,max) was investigated for the other AEs. Safety data were based on either the data from Study GEN501 and Study MMY2002 combined (n=228) or Study MMY2002 alone (n=124). No apparent relationship between the drug exposure and IRR, thrombocytopenia, anaemia, neutropenia, and lymphopenia was identified. Although the overall event rate of infection appeared to numerically increase with drug exposure, this trend was not observed for infections Grade 3 or higher. Further analysis showed that there was no significant difference in the rate of infections/infestations between IgG and non-IgG multiple myeloma subjects, although higher exposure was observed in non-IgG multiple myeloma subjects.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>immunoglobulin(IgG). PK data demonstrated a model-derived mean half-life of approximately 18±9 days, which is approximate to the half-life of endogenous IgG (reported to be approximately 21 days[Keizer et al. 2010]). The model-derived mean half-life is based on data included in the population PK</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Additionally, the low limit of the 95%CI of mild hepatic impairment (235.77 μg/mL) is under 274 μg/mL (EC90 ORR) which may have impact on efficacy. It is reassuring that mild hepatic impairment was not a significant covariate based on the model-based covariate analyses.Moreover, an analysis of the response-rate between patients with normal and mild hepatic function revealed no clinically relevant difference: The overall response rate (ORR) for patients treated with 16 mg/kg and with mild hepatic impairment (n=24) was 33% (95%CI: 16.9%-53.2%) compared with 31% (95%CI: 23.1%-39.1%) in the patients treated with at 16 mg/kg and with normal hepatic function</figDesc><table /><note>). The CHMP recommended the Applicant to perform additional analyses of the age, gender, renal impairment, hepatic impairment, ECOG score and refractory status with larger sample sizes as current Phase 3 studies reach maturation. With reference to hepatic impairment, changes in hepatic function are unlikely to have a direct effect on the elimination of daratumumab since IgG1 molecules are not metabolised through hepatic pathways. Nevertheless, relevance of mild hepatic impairment on PK exposure cannot be completely ruled out since number of patients with mild hepatic impairment patients are limited (n=34) although the 95%CIs (normal and mild) are overlapped.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_33"><head>Table 12 :</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Study MMY2002was an open-label, 2-part, multicentre, Phase 2 study in subjects with multiple myeloma who received at least 3 prior lines of therapy including a PI and an IMiD or whose disease was double refractory to both a PI and an IMiD. The purpose of Part 1 was to select the optimal dose and schedule with a higher overall response rate (ORR) using Phase 1/2 pre-change drug product. Within each randomized treatment group in Part 1, a 2-stage design was utilized to allow an inefficacious dose schedule to be terminated early for futility. The purpose of Part 2 was to evaluate the efficacy of the selected dosing regimen identified in Part 1 in a population using Phase 3 (large scale production) drug product.Part 1 of Study MMY2002 began at approximately the same time as the implementation of Protocol Amendment 13 in Study GEN501 (i.e., amendment to allow for administration of 16 mg/kg in Part 2). In Part 1 of Study MMY2002, 2 dosing regimens were evaluated in a randomized fashion (8 mg/kg every 4 weeks and 16 mg/kg weekly for 8 weeks, then every other week for 16 weeks, then every 4 weeks thereafter). It was expected that the 16 mg/kg dose would result in complete saturation of the target for all time points in the majority of subjects. The ORR for subjects treated with 8 mg/kg (n=18) in Part 1 was 11% as compared to 32% for subjects in Part 1 treated with 16 mg/kg (n=41). Furthermore, the VGPR or</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note>Overview of treatment-related AEs (All treated analysis set; Study GEN501 Part 2) Study MMY2002better rate for the 16 mg/kg group in Part 1 was 20% (8 of 41 subjects) as compared to 6% (1 of 18 subjects) at the 8 mg/kg dose level. The observed ORR at the 8 mg/kg dose level did not meet the protocol-specified criteria for continuation. Based on the totality of the data including efficacy, safety, and pharmacokinetics, the 8 mg/kg dose schedule was discontinued.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 13 :</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note>Overall best response based on IRC assessment (All Treated Analysis Set; Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>Table 14 :</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Overview of treatment-related AEs (All Treated Analysis Set; Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_37"><head>Table 15 :</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Pre-infusion medication (Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_39"><head>Table 16 : International Uniform Response Criteria Consensus Recommendations</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>were made for clarification throughout the protocol. An alternative treatment group (Group C; at the discretion of the Sponsor) was permitted to be added in Part 1, Stage 2, if either or both of the existing Treatment Groups A or B were considered as ineffective</figDesc><table><row><cell>minor additional changes</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 52/119</cell></row></table><note>• Amendment INT-1 (26 November 2013): included the following changes: the sample size was increased to approximately 20 subjects per treatment group in Part 1 Stage 1 from an original 15 subjects, the study agent administration guidelines were changed from mg/hr to mL/hr, and</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head>Table 17 :</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Subjects with major protocol deviations (All treated analysis set; Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head>Table 18 : Demographic characteristics (All Treated Analysis Set; Study MMY2002)</head><label>18</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_44"><head>Table 19 : Baseline disease characteristics (All Treated Analysis Set; Study MMY2002)</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_45"><head>Table 20 : Type of prior multiple myeloma therapy (All treated analysis set; Study MMY2002)</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_46"><head>Table 21 : Refractory status to prior multiple myeloma therapy (All treated analysis set; Study MMY2002) Numbers analysed</head><label>21</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>All treated Analysis Set: 124 patients</cell></row><row><cell>Per-Protocol Analysis Set: 101 patients</cell></row><row><cell>Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set: 123 subjects (18 subjects who received 8 mg/kg and 105 subjects who</cell></row><row><cell>received 16 mg/kg)</cell></row><row><cell>Immunogenicity Analysis Set: 111 patients (16 patients who received 8 mg/kg and 95 patients who</cell></row><row><cell>received 16 mg/kg).</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_47"><head>Table 22 : Overall best response based on IRC assessment (All treated analysis set; Study MMY2002)</head><label>22</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Subgroup analysis results are provided in the figure below:</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_48"><head>Table 23 : Duration of response based on IRC assessment (Responders in all treated analysis set -Study MMY2002)</head><label>23</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Time to response</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_49"><head>Table 24 :</head><label>24</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Time to response based on IRC assessment (Responders in all treated analysis set - Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_50"><head>Table 25 : Time to disease progression based on IRC assessment (All treated analysis set - Study MMY2002)</head><label>25</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Progression free survival (PFS)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_51"><head>Table 26 :</head><label>26</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note>PFS based on IRC assessment (All treated analysis set -Study MMY2002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_52"><head>Table 27 : OS (All treated analysis set -Study MMY2002), Data cut-off 30 June 2015</head><label>27</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_53"><head>Table 28 : Overall Survival; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002 and GEN501 Part 2) Data cut-off 31 December 2015</head><label>28</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note>Other efficacy analyses reported that 40 patients (38%) had a &gt;50% reduction in paraprotein from baseline, and 17 (16%) patients having &gt; 90% reduction (data not shown).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_55"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Laboratory values: absolute neutrophil counts &lt;1000/mm3; platelet count &lt;75x109/L; serum creatinine &gt;2x the upper limit of normal (ULN) hemoglobin &lt;7.5 g/dL (4.7 mmol/L); alanine aminotransferase (ALT) &gt;3.5 times the ULN; alkaline phosphatase &gt;3.5xULN; bilirubin</figDesc><table><row><cell>2. Previously received an allogeneic stem cell transplant</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. &gt;2.5xULN; hypokalemia (serum potassium &lt;3.0 mEq/L)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Concomitant corticosteroid use of &gt;10 mg prednisone or equivalent</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">5. Past or current malignancy, except for cervical carcinoma Stage 1B or less; noninvasive basal cell</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">and squamous cell skin carcinoma; malignant melanoma with a complete response (CR) of a</cell></row><row><cell>duration of &gt;10 years; curable cancer diagnosis with a CR of a duration of &gt;5 years</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6. Clinical signs of meningeal involvement of multiple myeloma; history of significant</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>cerebrovascular disease</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7. Known severe chronic obstructive pulmonary disease or asthma (forced expiratory volume in 1</cell></row><row><cell>second [FEV1] &lt;60% of expected); sensory or motor neuropathy of ≥ Grade 3</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">8. Chronic or ongoing active infectious disease; positive serology for hepatitis B; known human</cell></row><row><cell>immunodeficiency virus seropositivity</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">9. Clinically significant cardiac disease; baseline QTcF &gt;470 msec (women) or &gt;450 msec (men) or</cell></row><row><cell>complete left bundle branch block (LBBB) (QRS interval ≥120 msec)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 65/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_56"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>kg dose might not saturate a majority of the target (CD38) throughout dosing, as indicated by the high intersubject variability in pharmacokinetic parameters. Therefore, the 8 mg/kg dose in Cohort D was changed to 16 mg/kg to assess whether high-dose intensity, leading to high levels of systemic exposure and consistent saturation of the CD38 target, was needed to optimize the efficacy of daratumumab (Amendment 13). Further, Amendment 14 made a change in the study design to include Cohort E to evaluate a Phase 3 drug product (commercial product) that is produced with a larger scale manufacturing process.</figDesc><table><row><cell>8 mg/</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 67/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_57"><head>Table 29 : Subjects with major protocol violations (Study GEN501 Part 2) Baseline data</head><label>29</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_58"><head>Table 30 : Demographics (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>30</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_59"><head>Table 31 : Baseline Disease Characteristics (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>31</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_60"><head>Table 32 : Prior Multiple Myeloma Therapy (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>32</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_61"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This population was used for all efficacy and safety analyses. For Part 1, only subjects treated with ≥4 mg/kg daratumumab were used for all efficacy analyses since the other doses in Part 1 were under the therapeutic level (12 patients in Part 1 and 72 patients in Part 2, 84 patients in total). Immunogenicity Analysis Set consisted of all treated subjects with at least 1 baseline and 1 post-baseline immunogenicity assessment: 22 patients in Part 1 and 66 patients in Part 2 (88 patients in total).</figDesc><table><row><cell>•</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell cols="2">Pharmacokinetic Analysis Set consisted of all treated subjects with at least 1 baseline and 1</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">post-baseline pharmacokinetic assessment: 32 patients in Part 1 and 72 patients in Part 2 (104</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>patients in total)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 75/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_62"><head>Table 33 : Overall Best Response based on Computerized Algorithm (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>33</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_63"><head>Table 34 : Subgroup Analysis on Overall Best Response based on Computerized Algorithm (All Treated -16 mg/kg Group; Study GEN501 Part 2) Figure 9: Forest Plot of Subgroup Analysis on Overall Best Response based on Computerized Algorithm Assessment (All Treated -16 mg/kg Group; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>34</label><figDesc>The table below summarizes the efficacy results regarding the secondary endpoint (DOR) in Part 2 of the study (cut-off date 09 January 2015).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Secondary endpoint -duration of response (DOR)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_64"><head>Table 35 : Duration of Response (All Treated Analysis Set; Study GEN501 Part 2)</head><label>35</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Secondary endpoint -overall survival (OS)</cell></row><row><cell>The applicant submitted an updated OS analysis for Part 2 of the study with a data cut-off of 30 June</cell></row><row><cell>2015, corresponding to a follow-up time of 15.2 months for the 16 mg/kg group and 27.6 months for the</cell></row><row><cell>8 mg/kg group.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_65"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_66"><head>Table 37 : Summary of Efficacy for trial GEN501 Title: Daratumumab (HuMax-CD38) safety study in multiple myeloma -open-label</head><label>37</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>,</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_67"><head>Table 39 :</head><label>39</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note>Overall Survival; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002 and GEN501 Part 2)- Data cut-off 31 December 2015</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_68"><head>Table 40 : Patient Population Characteristics for Daratumumab, Pomalidomide, and</head><label>40</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Carfilzomib Studies</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Dara</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dara</cell><cell>(n=42)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=106)</cell><cell>(16</cell><cell>POM</cell><cell>POM+</cell><cell>POM+</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(16 mg/kg) Phase 2 MMY2002</cell><cell>mg/kg) Phase 1/2 GEN501</cell><cell>alone (n=108) Phase 2 MM-002 c</cell><cell>LD-dex (n=113) Phase 2 MM-002 c</cell><cell>LD-dex (n=302) Phase 3 MM-003 d</cell><cell>Carfilzomib (n=266) Phase 2 PX171-003-A1 e</cell><cell>Carfilzomib (n=157) Phase 3 FOCUS f</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Eligibility criteria</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Median age (yrs)</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>61</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>64</cell><cell>63</cell><cell>63</cell></row><row><cell>Creatinine</cell><cell>CrCl&gt; 20mL/min /1.73m 2</cell><cell>serum creatinine ≤2xULN</cell><cell>serum creatinine ≤3.0mg/dL</cell><cell>serum creatinine ≤3.0mg/dL</cell><cell>CrCl&gt; 45mL/min</cell><cell>CrCl&gt; 30mL/min</cell><cell>CrCl≥ 15mL/min</cell></row><row><cell>Hemoglobin</cell><cell>&gt;7.5g/dL</cell><cell>&gt;7.5g/dL</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>≥8</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_70"><head>Table 41 : Response Categories for Daratumumab, Pomalidomide, and CarfilzomibClinical studies in special populations Age 65-74 (Older subjects number /total number) Age 75-84 (Older subjects number /total number) Age 85+ (Older subjects number /total number)</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Based on n=64 subjects who were refractory to BORT and LEN g Based on n=69 subjects who were refractory to BORT and LEN h Based on n=225 subjects who were refractory to BORT and LEN i Based on n=169 subjects who were refractory to BORT and LEN</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Dara</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dara</cell><cell>(n=42)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=106)</cell><cell>(16</cell><cell>POM</cell><cell>POM+</cell><cell>POM+</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(16 mg/kg)</cell><cell>mg/kg) Phase</cell><cell>alone (n=108)</cell><cell>LD-dex (n=113)</cell><cell>LD-dex (n=302)</cell><cell>Carfilzomib (n=257)</cell><cell>Carfilzomib (n=157)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Phase 2 MMY2002 a</cell><cell>1/2 GEN501 a</cell><cell>Phase 2 MM-002 b</cell><cell>Phase 2 MM-002 b</cell><cell>Phase 3 MM-003 c</cell><cell>Phase 2 PX171-003-A1 d</cell><cell>Phase 3 FOCUS e</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Response Rate (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ORR</cell><cell>29%</cell><cell>36%</cell><cell>7%</cell><cell>29%</cell><cell>31%</cell><cell>24%</cell><cell>19%</cell></row><row><cell>sCR/CR</cell><cell>3%</cell><cell>5%</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0.9%</cell><cell>1%</cell><cell>0.4%</cell><cell>NR</cell></row><row><cell>VGPR or better</cell><cell>12%</cell><cell>10%</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>6%</cell><cell>5%</cell><cell>4%</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">ORR in Subgroups (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Refractory to PI/IMiD</cell><cell>30%</cell><cell>33%</cell><cell>6% f</cell><cell>28% g</cell><cell>28% h</cell><cell>15% i</cell><cell>NR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>No</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Refractory to POM</cell><cell>28%</cell><cell>33%</cell><cell>patient with prior</cell><cell>patient with prior</cell><cell>patient with prior</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>NR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>POM</cell><cell>POM</cell><cell>POM</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Refractory to CARF</cell><cell>29%</cell><cell>29%</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>NR</cell><cell>No patient with prior CARF</cell><cell>No patient with prior CARF</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">Abbreviations: BORT=bortezomib; CARF=carfilzomib; CR=complete response; LD-dex=low-dose</cell></row><row><cell cols="8">dexamethasone; LEN=lenalidomide; NR=not reported; ORR=overall response rate; POM=pomalidomide;</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">sCR=stringent complete response; VGPR=very good partial response b FDA Medical Review</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">c San Miguel 2013</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">d Siegel 2012, response evaluable population</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>e Ludwig 2014</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Controlled Trials</cell><cell cols="2">0/237</cell><cell></cell><cell>0/237</cell><cell></cell><cell>0/237</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Non Controlled Trials</cell><cell cols="2">84/237</cell><cell></cell><cell>20/237</cell><cell></cell><cell>0/237</cell></row></table><note>f</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_71"><head>Table 42 : Design of study GEN503</head><label>42</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_73"><head>Table 43 : Overview of daratumumab monotherapy clinical studies</head><label>43</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_74"><head>Table 44 : Overview of daratumumab combination clinical studies</head><label>44</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_75"><head>Table 45 : Total Exposure to Daratumumab in Integrated Monotherapy Studies (N=237)</head><label>45</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_76"><head>Table 46 :</head><label>46</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Total Exposure to Daratumumab in Combination Therapy Studies (N=94)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_77"><head>Table 47 : Daratumumab Infusions; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><label>47</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_78"><head>Table 48 : Overview of TEAEs; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><label>48</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_79"><head>Table 49 : Most Common (At least 10%) TEAEs by System Organ Class, Preferred Term and Grade 3/4; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><label>49</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">The most commonly reported TEAEs in the 16 mg/kg group (daratumumab monotherapy) were:</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>fatigue: 59 subjects (38%)</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>nausea: 40 subjects (26%)</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>anaemia: 39 subjects (25%)</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>neutropenia: 34 subjects (22%)</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>back pain: 33 subjects (21%)</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>cough and thrombocytopenia: each in 31 subjects (20%)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Adverse Reactions</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_80"><head>Table 50 : Adverse Drug Reactions in Patients With Multiple Myeloma Treated With Daratumumab 16 mg/kg (Cut-off date 9 January 2015)</head><label>50</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_81"><head>Table 51 : Adverse reactions in multiple myeloma patients treated with DARZALEX 16 mg/kg (Cut-off date 30 June 2015)</head><label>51</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>System Organ Class</cell><cell>Adverse reaction</cell><cell>Frequency (All</cell><cell cols="2">Incidence (%)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>grades)</cell><cell>All grades</cell><cell>Grade 3-4</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Infections and infestations Pneumonia**</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>6*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Upper respiratory tract</cell><cell></cell><cell>20</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nasopharyngitis</cell><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Blood and lymphatic system</cell><cell>Anaemia</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>17*</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell>Neutropenia</cell><cell></cell><cell>22</cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Thrombocytopenia</cell><cell></cell><cell>20</cell><cell>14</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Lymphopenia</cell><cell>Common</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>6*</cell></row><row><cell>Metabolism and nutrition</cell><cell>Decreased appetite</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell>disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Nervous system disorders</cell><cell>Headache</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell>Vascular disorders</cell><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>4*</cell></row><row><cell>Respiratory, thoracic and</cell><cell>Cough</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>mediastinal disorders</cell><cell>Nasal Congestion</cell><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dyspnoea</cell><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell>Gastrointestinal disorders</cell><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>27</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Diarrhoea</cell><cell></cell><cell>16</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Constipation</cell><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell></cell><cell>13</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Musculoskeletal and</cell><cell>Back pain</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>23</cell><cell>2*</cell></row><row><cell>connective tissue disorders</cell><cell>Arthralgia</cell><cell></cell><cell>17</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pain in extremity</cell><cell></cell><cell>15</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Musculoskeletal chest</cell><cell></cell><cell>12</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>pain</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>General disorders and</cell><cell>Fatigue</cell><cell>Very common</cell><cell>39</cell><cell>2*</cell></row><row><cell>administration site</cell><cell>Pyrexia</cell><cell></cell><cell>21</cell><cell>1*</cell></row><row><cell>conditions</cell><cell>Chills</cell><cell></cell><cell>10</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_82"><head>Table 52 : Infusion Related Reactions by System Organ Class, Preferred Term and Toxicity Grade</head><label>52</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_83"><head>Table 53 : Time to Onset of Infusion Related Reaction; All Treated Analysis Set -16 mg/kg Group (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><label>53</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_84"><head>Table 54 :</head><label>54</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Duration of Daratumumab Infusions; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002,</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_85"><head>Table 55 : Summary of Subjects who Experienced Bronchospasm IRRs (Studies: MMY2002 and GEN501)</head><label>55</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_86"><head>Table 56 : Exposure-Adjusted Incidence Rate of Infections/Infestations; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</head><label>56</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Second Primary Malignancies</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_87"><head>Table 57 :</head><label>57</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Most Common (At Least 1%) Treatment-Emergent Serious Adverse Events by System Organ Class and Preferred Term; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_89"><head>Table 58 : Death and Primary Causes of Death; All Treated Analysis Set</head><label>58</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(Studies: MMY2002,</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_90"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) that resolved; and no event resulted in clinically meaningful decreases in haemoglobin (&gt;1 g/dL decrease in haemoglobin during a daratumumab dosing window pre-dose to 12 hours post dose). One subject had only a decrease in haptoglobin without a concomitant increase in free haemoglobin or elevation of LDH, and 2 subjects had elevations of free haemoglobin without concomitant decreases in haptoglobin or elevations of LDH. Analysis of all laboratory values of free haemoglobin, haptoglobin, LDH, total bilirubin, and haemoglobin in all subjects in Study GEN501 Part 1 showed no consistent pattern of haemolysis.</figDesc><table><row><cell>free haemoglobin presentDirect and Indirect Coomb's Test</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">The binding of daratumumab to CD38 on RBCs triggers a positive readout on indirect Coombs testing,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">which interferes with the ability to detect red cell alloantibodies. CD38 is expressed at very low levels on</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">erythrocytes. Data indicate that daratumumab interferes with indirect Coombs testing and will make</cell></row><row><cell>complete blood typing difficult for subjects receiving treatment.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transfusion Usage and Red Blood Cell Transfusion-related Reactions</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">In the 16 mg/kg group, 48 subjects received 208 transfusions; 29% of subjects received RBC</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">transfusions. This was similar to the incidence in the total population; 65 subjects received 270</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">transfusions (24% of subjects received RBC transfusions). A summary of blood transfusions is presented</cell></row><row><cell>in Table 67. No TEAEs related to RBC transfusions were reported.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Study GEN501 Part 1, no new QTcF above 500 msec, no change from baseline &gt;60 msec, and no TEAEs</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">of QT prolongation were reported at doses at 2 mg/kg or higher. No subject had an abnormal U wave or</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">a new QTcF &gt;500 ms. No subject had a &gt;60 ms change from baseline for QTcF. In Study GEN501 Part 2,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">no subject had an abnormal, clinically significant ECG, based on investigator's overall interpretation, at</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">baseline or at any timepoint during treatment. Based on central review of ECG data, no subject had a</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">QTcF &gt;500 ms or a &gt;60 ms change from baseline. No TEAEs of QT prolongation were reported.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">In Study MMY1002, 12-lead triplicate ECGs were digitally recorded at the sites and then transmitted to a</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">central laboratory for measurement of cardiac intervals and morphologic assessment by a central</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">cardiologist. There were no clinically significant changes in ECG data observed in either the 8 mg/kg or 16</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">mg/kg group during the study (See discussion on clinical pharmacology). Based on central ECG review, no</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">subject had a QTcF value &gt;500 msec or an increase of &gt;60 msec from baseline. No TEAEs of QT</cell></row><row><cell>prolongation were reported.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Haemolysis Analysis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>No subjects in the 16 mg/kg group experienced TEAEs of hemolysis.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">In Study GEN501, free haemoglobin, haptoglobin, lactic acid dehydrogenase (LDH), total bilirubin, and</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">haemoglobin levels were performed and analysed at a central laboratory to evaluate haemolysis. In the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">32 subjects in Part 1, 3 subjects had TEAEs of haemolysis, 5 subjects had TEAEs of free haemoglobin</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">present, and 1 subject had a TEAE of haptoglobin decreased; all of which were reported in subjects</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">receiving ≤1 mg/kg of daratumumab. All events were Grade 1, events (with the exception of a Grade 2</cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/278085/2016</cell><cell>Page 102/119</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_91"><head>Table 59 : Transfusions During Treatment; All Treated Analysis Set (Studies: MMY2002, GEN501 and MMY1002) Safety in special populations Age</head><label>59</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_92"><head>Table 60 : Treatment-emergent Adverse Events By Age Group; All Treated Analysis Set</head><label>60</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>-16</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_94"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>nasopharyngitis, pneumonia and sinusitis. Infections were most frequent within the first 6 months of treatment. The most common serious infection was pneumonia. No subjects had febrile neutropenia. The overall incidence of infections and infestations was similar to the total population and consistent with underlying Multiple Myeloma. Of note, the incidence of opportunistic infections was low (2% per specified opportunistic infection). No AEs of reactivated HBV or HCV were reported. Infections have been classified as an important potential risk in the RMP. IRRs) were reported in approximately half of all patients treated with daratumumab. Monitor such patients throughout the infusion and the post-infusion period. The majority (95%) of IRRs occurred at the first infusion. Five percent of all patients had an IRR at more than one infusion. Symptoms predominantly included (≥5%) nasal congestion, chills, cough, allergic rhinitis, throat irritation, dyspnoea, and nausea, and were mild to moderate in severity. Severe IRRs (3%) Daratumumab binds to CD38 found at low levels on red blood cells (RBCs) and mayresult in a positive indirect Coombs test. Daratumumab-mediated positive indirect Coombs test may persist for up to 6 months after the last daratumumab infusion. It should be recognised that daratumumab bound to RBCs may mask detection of antibodies to minor antigens in the patient's serum. The determination of a patient's ABO and Rh blood type are not impacted. Patients should be typed and screened prior to starting daratumumab treatment (SmPC section 4.4).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Infusion-related reactions (including bronchospasm (1.3%), hypertension (0.6%), and hypoxia (0.6%) were also reported (SmPC</cell></row><row><cell>section 4.4).</cell></row><row><cell>Patients should be pre-medicated with antihistamines, antipyretics and corticosteroids to reduce the risk</cell></row><row><cell>of IRRs prior to treatment with daratumumab. Daratumumab infusion should be interrupted for IRRs of</cell></row><row><cell>any severity. Medical management/supportive treatment for IRRs should be instituted as needed. The</cell></row><row><cell>infusion rate should be reduced when re-starting the infusion. For the prevention of delayed IRRs, oral</cell></row><row><cell>corticosteroids should be administered to all patients the first and second day after all infusions.</cell></row><row><cell>Additionally the use of post-infusion medications (e.g. inhaled corticosteroids, short and long acting</cell></row><row><cell>bronchodilators) should be considered for patients with a history of obstructive pulmonary disorder to</cell></row><row><cell>manage respiratory complications should they occur (SmPC sections 4.2 and 4.8). Infusion Related</cell></row><row><cell>Reactions have been classified as an important identified risk in the RMP.</cell></row><row><cell>In study MMY1002, all nine subjects experienced a positive result in indirect Coomb's Test after treatment</cell></row><row><cell>with daratumumab.</cell></row><row><cell>The most frequently reported adverse reactions were IRRs (48%); see section 4.4. Other frequently</cell></row><row><cell>reported adverse reactions (≥ 20%) were fatigue (39%), pyrexia (21%), cough (21%), nausea (27%),</cell></row><row><cell>back pain (23%), upper respiratory tract infection (20%), anaemia (27%), neutropenia (22%) and</cell></row><row><cell>thrombocytopenia (20%) (SmPC section 4.8).</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_95"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Daratumumab interference mitigation methods include treating reagent RBCs with dithiothreitol (DTT) to disrupt daratumumab binding or genotyping. Since the Kell blood group system is also sensitive to DTT treatment, Kell-negative units should be supplied after ruling out or identifying alloantibodies using DTT-treated RBCs (SmPC section 4.5). Interference for blood typing (minor antigen) (Positive Indirect Coombs' test) has been classified as an important identified risk in the RMP.</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_99"><head>Table 61 : Summary of the Safety concerns Important Identified Risks</head><label>61</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Infusion Related Reactions (IRRs)</cell></row><row><cell>Interference for blood typing (minor antigen) (Positive</cell></row><row><cell>Indirect Coombs' test)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_100"><head>Table 62 : Table of Ongoing and Planned Additional Pharmacovigilance Studies/Activities in the Pharmacovigilance Plan</head><label>62</label><figDesc>Pursuant to Article 23(1) of Regulation No (EU)726/2004, Darzalex (daratumumab)  is included in the additional monitoring list as it contains a new active substance which, on 1 January 2011, was not contained in any medicinal product authorised in the EU, and is to be approved under conditional marketing authorisation.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Date for</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>submission of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>interim or final</cell></row><row><cell>Study/activity type,</cell><cell></cell><cell>Safety</cell><cell>Status</cell><cell>reports</cell></row><row><cell>title and category</cell><cell></cell><cell>concerns</cell><cell>(planned,</cell><cell>(planned or</cell></row><row><cell>(1-3)</cell><cell>Objectives</cell><cell>addressed</cell><cell>started)</cell><cell>actual)</cell></row><row><cell>Trial MMY 3003 a Phase</cell><cell>To compare the safety and efficacy</cell><cell>Overall Safety</cell><cell>Ongoing</cell><cell>30 September</cell></row><row><cell>3, two arm, Randomised,</cell><cell>of daratumumab when combined</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2017</cell></row><row><cell>Parallel-group Trial of</cell><cell>with lenalidomide and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lenalidomide and</cell><cell>dexamethasone to that of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dexamethasone with or</cell><cell>lenalidomide and dexamethasone in</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>without Daratumumab in</cell><cell>subjects with relapsed or refractory</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Patients with</cell><cell>multiple myeloma.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Previously-treated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multiple Myeloma</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(category 2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Trial MMY 3004, a Phase</cell><cell>To compare the safety and efficacy</cell><cell>Overall Safety</cell><cell>Ongoing</cell><cell>31 December</cell></row><row><cell>3, two arm, Randomised,</cell><cell>of daratumumab when combined</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2016</cell></row><row><cell>Parallel-group Trial of</cell><cell>with VELCADE and dexamethasone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bortezomib and</cell><cell>to that of VELCADE and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dexamethasone with or</cell><cell>dexamethasone, in subjects with</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>without Daratumumab in</cell><cell>relapsed or refractory multiple</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Patients with</cell><cell>myeloma.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Previously-treated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Multiple Myeloma.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(category 2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Survey of additional risk</cell><cell>To measure awareness of blood</cell><cell>Interference for</cell><cell>Protocol to</cell><cell>3 months after</cell></row><row><cell>minimisation measures</cell><cell>banks and HCPs on the interference</cell><cell>blood typing</cell><cell>be</cell><cell>EC decision</cell></row><row><cell>for interference of blood</cell><cell>of blood typing</cell><cell>(minor antigen)</cell><cell>submitted</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>typing</cell><cell></cell><cell>(Positive</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(category 3)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Indirect Coombs' test)</cell><cell>Initial</cell><cell>18 months following the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>evaluation</cell><cell>launch of the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>product.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Final Report</cell><cell>Final results will be presented in the next</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PSUR/PBRER</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>after the survey</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>has been</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>concluded</cell></row><row><cell>Trial SMM2001: A</cell><cell>As a secondary objective to</cell><cell>Effect of</cell><cell>Started</cell><cell>31 December</cell></row><row><cell>randomised Phase 2 trial</cell><cell>determine if daratumumab has an</cell><cell>daratumumab</cell><cell></cell><cell>2018</cell></row><row><cell>to evaluate 3</cell><cell>effect on QT interval.</cell><cell>on QT interval.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>daratumumab dose</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>schedules in smouldering</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>multiple myeloma.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(category 3)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Investigate new method</cell><cell>Improve the immunogenicity</cell><cell cols="2">Immunogenicity Planned</cell><cell>31 December</cell></row><row><cell>for detecting antidrug</cell><cell>method's ability to detect</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2018</cell></row><row><cell>antibodies</cell><cell>anti-daratumumab antibodies in the</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(category 3)</cell><cell>presence of high trough levels of daratumumab</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_101"><head>Table 64 : Effects Table for Daratumumab Effect Short Description</head><label>64</label><figDesc>AE: adverse event, AR: Assessment Report, CI: confidence interval, CR: complete response, DOR: duration of response, IRR: infusion-related reaction, KM: Kaplan Meier, NE: not estimated, ORR: overall response rate, OS: overall survival, PR: partial response, pts: patients, SAE: serious adverse event, sCR/CR: stringent complete remission/ complete remission.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Unit</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Treatment</cell><cell>Control</cell><cell>Uncertainties/Stre</cell><cell>References</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>MMY2002:d</cell><cell>None</cell><cell>ngth of evidence</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>GEN501:d</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Favourable Effects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ORR</cell><cell>Overall</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Percentage</cell><cell cols="2">MMY2002: 29%</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>See clinical</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">response</cell><cell>(KM</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(21%; 39%)</cell><cell>Lack of comparator</cell><cell>efficacy AR</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>rate</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">median;</cell><cell cols="2">GEN501:36%</cell><cell>arm</cell><cell>and discussion</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95% CI)</cell><cell cols="2">(22%; 52%)</cell></row><row><cell>DOR</cell><cell cols="2">Duration of</cell><cell>Months</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">MMY2002: 7.4</cell><cell>Lack of comparator</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">response</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">GEN501:NE</cell><cell>arm</cell></row><row><cell>sCR/CR</cell><cell cols="2">Stringent</cell><cell cols="4">Percentage MMY2002: 3%</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Complete</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">GEN501: 5%</cell><cell>Lack of comparator</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">remission/C</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>arm</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>R</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>OS</cell><cell>Overall</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Months (KM</cell><cell cols="2">MMY2002:17.5</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>survival</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">median;</cell><cell cols="2">(13.7; NE)</cell><cell>Lack of comparator</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">95% CI)</cell><cell></cell><cell>arm</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">Unfavourable Effects (MMY2002, GEN501, MMY1002)</cell></row><row><cell>AEs (e.g.</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Incidence as</cell><cell cols="2">Percent</cell><cell>99%,</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>See clinical</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">fatigue, nausea,</cell><cell cols="2">percentage</cell><cell>age</cell><cell></cell><cell>grade</cell><cell>-Use in the elderly</cell><cell>safety AR and</cell></row><row><cell>anaemia,</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">of patients</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>3-4:56%</cell><cell>≥75 years</cell><cell>discussion</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">neutropenia,</cell><cell cols="2">involved</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>AE leading to</cell><cell>-Immunogenicity</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">back pain, cough</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>discontinuatio</cell><cell>-QTc prolongation</cell></row><row><cell>and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>n: 4%</cell><cell>-limited data</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">thrombocytopeni</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>a)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>SAEs (e.g.</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Incidence as</cell><cell cols="2">Percent</cell><cell>32</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Infection and</cell><cell cols="2">percentage</cell><cell>age</cell><cell></cell><cell>Grade 5 AEs:</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">infestations,</cell><cell cols="2">of patients</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>10/11 pts</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">pneumonia,deteri</cell><cell cols="2">involved</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">oration, pyrexia,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">hypercalcemia)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IRR</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Incidence as</cell><cell cols="2">Percent</cell><cell>51, 2 pts</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">percentage</cell><cell>age</cell><cell></cell><cell>discontinued</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">of patients</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">involved</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Abbreviations:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Assessment report EMA/278085/2016Page 24/119</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk minimisation measures</head><p>Educational materials will be distributed to HCPs and blood banks to advice regarding the risk of and solutions for interference for blood typing.</p><p>Additionally, patient alert cards will be distributed to increase awareness to patients about the interference of blood typing occurring with daratumumab. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Important potential risks</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The CHMP and PRAC considered that the RMP version 1.2 (dated 30 March 2016) is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">Pharmacovigilance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacovigilance system</head><p>The CHMP considered that the pharmacovigilance system summary submitted by the applicant fulfils the requirements of Article 8(3) of Directive 2001/83/EC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.">Product information</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.1.">User consultation</head><p>The results of the user consultation with target patient groups on the package leaflet submitted by the applicant show that the package leaflet meets the criteria for readability as set out in the Guideline on the readability of the label and package leaflet of medicinal products for human use.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
