<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report elmiron List of abbreviations AE Adverse event API active pharmaceutical ingredient aPTT activated partial thromboplastin time ASMF Active Substance Master File ATUn Autorisation Temporaire d&apos;Utilisation nominative AUA American urology association BC maximal bladder capacity BCS Biopharmaceutics Classification System BPS bladder pain syndrome CEP Certificate of Suitability of the EP CFU Colony forming units CI 95 % confidence interval DDD defined daily doses DDI Drug drug interaction DMSO Dimethyl sulfoxide EAU European Association of Urology EC European Commission ESSIC International Society for the Study of Bladder Pain Syndrome EU European Union FDA Food and Drug Administration FT-IR Fourrier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy GAG Glycosaminoglycan GPC Gel permeation chromatography GRA global response assessment GTI gastrointestinal HDPE High Density Polyethylene HPLC high performance liquid chromatography HSCIC Health and Social Care Information Centre IC Interstitial Cystitis ICH International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Registration of ICPI O&apos;Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Problem Index</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2016-03-23">23 March 2016</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="institution">Churchill Place • Canary Wharf</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>E14 5EU</postCode>
									<settlement>London</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="institution">European Union</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Committee for Medicinal Products for Human Use (CHMP) Assessment report elmiron List of abbreviations AE Adverse event API active pharmaceutical ingredient aPTT activated partial thromboplastin time ASMF Active Substance Master File ATUn Autorisation Temporaire d&apos;Utilisation nominative AUA American urology association BC maximal bladder capacity BCS Biopharmaceutics Classification System BPS bladder pain syndrome CEP Certificate of Suitability of the EP CFU Colony forming units CI 95 % confidence interval DDD defined daily doses DDI Drug drug interaction DMSO Dimethyl sulfoxide EAU European Association of Urology EC European Commission ESSIC International Society for the Study of Bladder Pain Syndrome EU European Union FDA Food and Drug Administration FT-IR Fourrier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy GAG Glycosaminoglycan GPC Gel permeation chromatography GRA global response assessment GTI gastrointestinal HDPE High Density Polyethylene HPLC high performance liquid chromatography HSCIC Health and Social Care Information Centre IC Interstitial Cystitis ICH International Conference on Harmonisation of Technical Requirements for Registration of ICPI O&apos;Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Problem Index</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2016-03-23">23 March 2016</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>International non-proprietary name: pentosan polysulfate sodium Procedure No. EMEA/H/C/004246/0000 Note Assessment report as adopted by the CHMP with all information of a commercially confidential nature deleted. Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 2/115 Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 4/115 Page 5/115 ICSI O&apos;Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Symptom Index lgG Immunoglobulin G INR International Normalized Ratio IRA investigator RA IR Infrared ITT Intention to Treat IV, i.v. Intravenous LIVIVO German National Library of Medicine LOCF last-observation-carried forward LoD loss of drying MAA Marketing Authorisation Application/Marketing Authorisation Applicant MCC Microcrystalline Cellulose MO Major Objection MOA Mechanism of action MTD Maximum Tolerated Dose N/A not applicable/ available NIDDK National Institute of Arthritis, Diabetes, Digestive and Kidney Diseases (USA) NLT not less than NMR Nuclear Magnetic Resonance NMT not more than NS not significant</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T03:24+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract xml:lang="fr">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Telephone +44 (0)20 3660 6000 Facsimile +44 (0)20 3660 5520 Send a question via our website www.ema.europa.eu/contact</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Steps taken for the assessment of the product</head><p>The Rapporteur and Co-Rapporteur appointed by the CHMP were:</p><p>Rapporteur: Joseph Emmerich Co-Rapporteur: Romaldas Mačiulaitis • The application was received by the EMA on 4 February 2016.</p><p>• The procedure started on 25 February 2016.</p><p>• The Rapporteur's first Assessment Report was circulated to all CHMP members on 13 May 2016.</p><p>The Co-Rapporteur's first Assessment Report was circulated to all CHMP members on 13 May 2016.</p><p>• The PRAC Rapporteur's first Assessment Report was circulated to all PRAC members on 27 May 2016. • During the CHMP meeting on 10 November 2016, the CHMP agreed on a list of outstanding issues to be addressed in writing and/or in an oral explanation by the applicant.</p><p>• The applicant submitted the responses to the CHMP List of Outstanding Issues on 19 January 2017.</p><p>• The Rapporteurs circulated the Joint Assessment Report on the applicant's responses to the List of Outstanding Issues to all CHMP members on 8 February 2017.</p><p>• During a meeting of an ad hoc Expert group on 30 January 2017, experts were convened to address questions raised by the CHMP.</p><p>• During the CHMP meeting on 20 February 2017, outstanding issues were addressed by the applicant during an oral explanation before the CHMP.</p><p>• During the meeting on 23 March 2017, the CHMP, in the light of the overall data submitted and the scientific discussion within the Committee, issued a positive opinion for granting a marketing authorisation to elmiron.</p><p>The aetiology is unknown but some triggering factors such as certain acid foods (coffee or citrus products), bacterial cystitis, pelvic surgery, delivery are hypothesised.</p><p>Other pathologies can be associated such as fibromyalgia, chronic fatigue syndrome, irritable bowel syndrome, vulvodynia, depression, panic disorders, migraine, sicca syndrome, temporomandibular joint disorder, allergy, asthma and systemic lupus erythematosus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.4.">Clinical presentation, diagnosis</head><p>The diagnosis of IC / BPS is primarily one of exclusion, using symptoms, examination, urine analysis and urine culture (to rule out a urinary tract infection), cystoscopy with hydrodistension (to rule out bladder cancer, vesical stones, urethral diverticula and intravesical foreign bodies), and biopsy (to exclude other pathologies).</p><p>Differentiation is reflected in the standardised scheme for the classification of BPS Types as published by the European Society for the Study of IC/PBS (ESSIC) (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_1">Table 1</ref>). Cases meeting the ESSIC classification 2X to 3C would meet the NIDDK criteria for IC. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1.5.">Management</head><p>There is no consensus regarding the optimal treatment approach for this condition. The difficulty in treating IC/BPS derives from several factors, including (i) the lack of a clear understanding of the aetiology of the disorder. This precludes development of therapies targeted at the underlying pathophysiology; (ii) the symptoms of IC/BPS vary considerably across patients; (iii) the definitions of the condition and of measure of therapeutic outcomes vary; (iv) there are few high quality data (e.g., randomized trials) regarding the efficacy and safety of IC/BPS treatments. No treatment is consistently effective in providing relief for all patients.</p><p>All available treatment options thus far are purely symptomatic. There are no medicinal products approved for the treatment of IC in Europe. Current treatment options include: In the respective US treatment guideline (AUA guideline, 2014), PPS is recommended as second-line treatment (Grade B recommendation) after patient education, self-care practices and behavioural modifications or stress management practices, which are recommended as first-line treatment for IC in the US <ref type="bibr">(Hanno et al.,2014)</ref>.</p><p>Indeed, there are many therapeutic approaches for IC/BPS and none are proven to be helpful for all patients with IC/BPS. One of the standards of care is to treat IC/BPS with a stepwise approach (therapies for IC/BPS vary by the risk of adverse effects and the invasiveness of the treatment). 1st line: self-care and behaviour modification (local heat or cold over the bladder or perineum, avoidance of activities or food or beverages that exacerbate symptoms, fluid management, Bladder training with urge suppression); 2nd line: physical therapy (treatment of the pelvic muscle tender points, trigger points, connective tissue restrictions, and muscular abnormalities of the soft tissues by a physical therapist) and oral medications (amitriptyline, pentosan polysulfate sodium (PPS), antihistamines (eg, hydroxyzine); 3rd line: bladder hydrodistention, treatment of Hunner lesions (by resection, electrical cauterization, or injection of these lesions with a corticosteroid), and intravesical dimethyl sulfoxide;</p><p>4th line: intradetrusor botulinum toxin and sacral neuromodulation; 5th line: Cyclosporine A; 6th line: urinary diversion (removing the ureters from the bladder and diverting the urine into an incontinent urostomy or a continent catheterizable urine pouch). An alternative approach is an individualized treatment plan tailored to the patient's primary symptoms.</p><p>The most recent version of the European Guidelines on Chronic Pelvic Pain <ref type="bibr">(Engeler et al., 2015)</ref> recommend to always consider multimodal behavioural, physical and psychological techniques alongside oral or invasive treatments. For patients with BPS Type 3C, who have Hunner's lesions at cystoscopy, treatment with Transurethral resection (TUR) or laser was recommended if the patient is eligible. In case the patient is not eligible or the response is inadequate for these interventional treatments initiation of treatment with oral agents is recommended.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>About the product</head><p>The active substance pentosan polysulfate sodium (PPS) is a semi-synthetically produced heparin-like macromolecular carbohydrate derivative, which chemically and structurally resembles glycosaminoglycans.</p><p>Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 12/115 PPS is a low molecular weight heparin-like compound. It has anticoagulant, fibrinolytic, and antiinflammatory effects. The exact mechanism of action of PPS in the treatment of IC/BPS is unknown. It is hypothesized, that a potential barrier function of PPS instead of the damaged urothelial mucus might play a role as well the anti-inflammatory activity of PPS.</p><p>Indication elmiron is indicated for the treatment of bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions in adults with moderate to severe pain, urgency and frequency of micturition</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Posology</head><p>The recommended dose of pentosan polysulfate sodium is 300 mg/day taken as one 100 mg capsule orally three times daily. In the Guidelines on Chronic Pelvic Pain, which are released by the European Association of Urology since <ref type="bibr">2004</ref><ref type="bibr">(Fall et al. 2004</ref>, the oral usage of PPS is recommended as standard treatment for IC already in the first version of these guidelines from 2004. PPS was recommended as standard treatment in this indication in all following updates of this European Guidance up to today <ref type="bibr">(Fall et al., 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fall et al., 2010;</ref><ref type="bibr">Engeler et al., 2012;</ref><ref type="bibr">Engeler et al., 2014;</ref><ref type="bibr">Engeler et al., 2015)</ref>. In addition, a review article on treatment guidelines for classic and non-ulcer IC from the year 2000 lists oral treatment with PPS as an established treatment option for IC <ref type="bibr">(Peeker et al., 2000)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Type of Application and aspects on development</head><p>Several national European patient associations confirmed relevant usage of PPS for the treatment of IC at least since 1996. Respective statements are provided by e.g. the German IC associations and the multinational IC Association covering France, Germany, Belgium, The Netherlands and Austria.</p><p>In Germany Pentosan-polysulfat SP54 <ref type="formula">(25 mg</ref>  <ref type="bibr">2004, 43, 1135-1146.</ref> Further evidence on the systematic and continuous use of PPS for the treatment of Interstitial Cystitis (IC would, as per todays classification, fall under BPS 2X-3C i.e. bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions) over at least one decade were provided via documented compassionate use usage in France, Norway and the UK (see quantitative aspects of the use of PPS below).</p><p>(2) The quantitative aspects of the use of PPS:</p><p>For an estimation of the past and current quantitative use in Europe, the Applicant provided the following information about the use of PPS throughout Europe:</p><p>• Germany:</p><p>According to a survey of the health care situation of patients with interstitial cystitis and bladder pain syndrome in Germany conducted in 2010 <ref type="bibr">(Jocham et al 2013)</ref> which was based on 270 questionnaires returned by the patients. 42.22% of these patients mentioned that they have been treated with oral PPS.</p><p>Another survey conducted by the Market research made by Medimed GmbH revealed relevant off-label use of Pentosanpolysulfat SP54 in 2013-2015: ~4000 prescriptions, assuming 185 treatment courses/12 months, or 1.3% of the potential IC patients in Germany. These prescriptions clearly refer to the diagnostic code ICD N30.1 (chronic Interstitial Cystitis). The diagnostic code, which is used in clinical practice for BPS is R10.2 (Pelvic and perineal pain). The latest data received from IMS Health supplement the data collected by MediMed (MediMed belongs to IMS Health) and confirm a constant off-label use of approximately 2000 prescriptions per year for the treatment of IC (ICD N30.1) (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 2</ref>). Based on the fact that the recommendation to use PPS for the treatment of IC did not change over the last 15 years as demonstrated above by listing different articles and treatment guidelines from 2000 to today, it can be assumed, that comparable off label use of Pentosanpolysulfat SP54 also appeared in the previous years, although the conducted survey just covered the last four years.</p><p>•</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>UK:</head><p>Prescription cost analysis conducted by HSCIC for the years 2003 to 2014 for the treatment of IC (that is not reimbursed), provided information on prescriptions of Elmiron authorised outside the EU for the treatment of IC and PPS 100 mg capsules assuming from 97 to 209 treatment courses of 3 month duration annually, or ~2 to 3% of the potential IC patients in UK. The NHS prescription cost analysis for England 2013 reports that approximately 400 community prescriptions for pentosan were dispensed in 2013. There is information about Elmiron prescriptions in Norway as provided by IMS Health. IMS Health data provided information about Elmiron prescriptions in the treatment of IC, assuming from 56 to 110 treatment courses of 3 month duration annually, or 7 to 12% of the potential IC patients in Norway.</p><p>Next to the use in Germany, UK, France, and Norway, limited information from further European countries documenting the use of PPS for the treatment of IC was found for Poland, Italy and Sweden.</p><p>In addition, the Applicant provided the quantity of PPS bene pharmaChem GmbH delivered to pharmacies for magistral preparation of PPS in Germany, in Austria and Netherlands from 2003 to 2014. The major part of the supplied drug substance was used as oral preparations for the treatment of IC.</p><p>The applicant provided information regarding the dose regimens used in the different European countries. Taking into account treatment recommendations over the last 15 years as demonstrated above by listing different articles and treatment guidelines from 2000 it can be assumed that at least a significant part of the Elmiron prescription was in line with the respective label of the imported products.</p><p>Taking into account the rarity of the condition the Applicant has provided sufficient evidence supporting extensive and continued usage of PPS either as Pentosanpolysulfat SP54 or via the US-medicinal product Elmiron for the treatment of IC (bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions) over more than 10 years in Europe in the claimed indication.</p><p>(3) The degree of scientific interest in the use of PPS (as it is reflected in the published scientific literature):</p><p>Publications in peer-reviewed journals concerning the epidemiology of Interstitial Cystitis were collected by extensive use of PubMed Central archive at the U.S. National Institutes of Health's National Library of Medicine (NIH/NLM).</p><p>To identify relevant studies, the following control terms were used:</p><p>-"cystitis, interstitial" OR ("cystitis" AND "interstitial") OR "interstitial cystitis" AND -"pentosan sulfuric polyester" OR ("pentosan" AND "sulfuric" AND "polyester") OR ("pentosan" AND "polysulfate") OR "pentosan polysulfate".</p><p>Relevant publications identified after first review of the abstracts were studied in more detail to extract the required information. In addition, relevant references cited in publications identified above were hand searched and evaluated.</p><p>The continuous scientific interest in PPS for the treatment of IC is documented by the number of publications over time available on this topic: A review of <ref type="bibr">Pubmed (26.5.2015)</ref> identified 2,857 documents found for "Cystitis, Interstitial" <ref type="bibr">[mesh]</ref>, and 154 adding "Pentosan Sulfuric</p><p>Polyester" <ref type="bibr">[mesh]</ref>. In the following figure GoPubMed (www.gopubmed.org, Transinsight GmbH, Germany) was used to provide chronological information on the occurrence of publications on PPS for the treatment of IC in the MEDLINE database. Overall, the submitted EU references are considered sufficient evidence of scientific interest in the EU.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(4) The coherence of scientific assessments:</head><p>In addition to the efficacy and safety data from the 6 pivotal studies, the meta-analysis, the 9 supportive studies and the safety review from a total of more than 4700 patients which are submitted for evaluation in this application, the Applicant provided all the European recommendations:</p><p>• • Four clinical trials conducted in Europe <ref type="bibr">(Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fritjofsson et al., 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sairanen et al., 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">and van Ophoven et al., 2005)</ref> are not directly comparable but efficacy is consistent with the observations in the studies conducted in the US. and safe treatment since more than 10 years.</p><p>For conclusion on the scientific assessment please refer to the Benefit / Risk discussion at the end of this report.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(5) The similarity of the claimed formulation to the formulations examined in the literature</head><p>The applicant has developed a medicinal product:</p><p>-with an active substance quality identical to US Elmiron <ref type="table">(same manufacturer)</ref> -with a quantitative composition, with the exception of the capsule shell, identical to the US Elmiron on which are based the clinical studies described in EU (and non-EU) literature.</p><p>Formulation and manufacturing process are simple and standard: excipients used are typical for the dosage form, drug substance represents approx. 44% w/w of the total capsule filling weight.</p><p>In vitro dissolution results at pH 1.0 4.5 and 6.8 are similar for the PPS drug product and the product used in the literature, both products show a very rapid dissolution &gt;85% within 15 min. Therefore, the profiles can be considered similar in accordance with appendix I of the Guideline on the Investigation of Bioequivalence. The results support the proof of bioequivalence between the medicinal product under application and the product Elmiron used in the literature and fulfil the requirements for a BCSbiowaiver approach for class III drug substances in accordance with appendix III.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion on the well-established use</head><p>As a conclusion of the assessment of the above criteria, the CHMP is of the view that the applicant provides sufficient evidence to establish that the elements related to the quantitative aspects of the use of the substance, the time over which the substance has been used, the degree of scientific interest in the use of the substance in the EU and the coherence of the scientific assessments are fulfilled. Documentation presented can be considered adequate to show similarity of the drug product with the product used in the publications.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Quality aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.1.">Introduction</head><p>The finished product is presented as hard capsules containing 100 mg of pentosan polysulfate sodium as active substance.</p><p>Other ingredients of the capsule contents are microcrystalline cellulose and magnesium stearate.</p><p>Ingredients of the capsule shell are gelatin and titanium dioxide (E171).</p><p>The product is available in HDPE bottle with a tamper-evident PP child resistant closure and PVC/Aclar-Aluminium blisters, as described in section 6.5 of the SmPC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.2.">Active Substance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>General information</head><p>The information on pentosan polysulfate sodium is provided according to the Active Substance Master File (ASMF) procedure.</p><p>The chemical name of pentosan polysulfate sodium is (1→4)-β-D-xylan 2,3-bis (hydrogen sulfate) sodium salt corresponding to the molecular formula (C 5 H 6 Na 2 O 10 S 2 ) n and has weight average molecular weight (obtained by light scattering and gel chromatography) of approximately 5760 g/mol and number average molecular weight (the ordinary arithmetic mean or average of the molecular masses of the individual macromolecules) of approximately 3863 g/mol. The polydispersity index is approximately 1.49. Pentosan polysulfate sodium is a semi-synthetic polymer -a heparin-like macromolecular carbohydrate derivative -sulfated polyxylose which chemically and structurally resembles glycosaminoglycans. It has the following structure: The structure of pentosan polysulfate sodium was confirmed using a combination of FTIR spectroscopy, XRD, 1 H-NMR and 13 C-NMR spectroscopy. The molecular weight distribution data was obtained using a combination of light scattering and gel chromatography. Chiral centres of the active substance originate in the pentosan starting material which is extracted from beech wood. Enantiomeric purity is controlled routinely by optical rotation.</p><p>The active substance is a hygroscopic, faintly yellow powder, very soluble in water and insoluble in most organic solvents. Due to very high solubility in aqueous media, control of the active substance particle size is not critical to ensure a consistent performance in vivo. Due to low permeability, pentosan polysulfate sodium is classified as BCS-class III substance.</p><p>There is no monograph of pentosan polysulfate sodium in the European Pharmacopoeia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture, characterisation and process controls</head><p>Detailed information on the manufacturing of the active substance has been provided in the restricted part of the ASMF and it was considered satisfactory.</p><p>A single manufacturer carries out the entire process. The active substance is synthesized in 10 main steps using a commercially available well defined starting material with acceptable specifications. At the request of CHMP, additional information about the beech tree plant material used for production of the regulatory starting material was provided, in line with the EMA quality Q&amp;A on semi-synthetic active substances from herbal origin and the relevant Ph. Eur. monographs, thereby ensuring the quality of the active substance. Reprocessing can be performed by repetition of purification steps according to the established manufacturing process in accordance with ICH guideline Q7A.</p><p>Adequate in-process controls are applied during the synthesis. The specifications and control methods for starting material and reagents have been presented. There are no intermediates in the manufacturing process of the active substance.</p><p>The characterisation of the active substance and its impurities are in accordance with the EU guideline on chemistry of new active substances.</p><p>Potential and actual impurities were well discussed with regards to their origin and characterised.</p><p>The proposed packaging materials comply with all applicable requirements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Specification</head><p>The active substance specification includes tests for properties (visual inspection), identity (TLC, visible spectrum spectrophotometry, a further chromatographic method, IR), optical rotation <ref type="formula">(</ref> The acceptance criteria of the related substances are in accordance with the ICH Q3A guideline and appropriate specifications have been set.</p><p>The analytical methods used have been adequately described and appropriately validated in accordance with the ICH guidelines. Satisfactory information regarding the reference standards used for assay and identity testing has been presented.</p><p>Batch analysis data from 11 commercial scale batches of the active substance were provided. The results are within the specifications and consistent from batch to batch.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stability</head><p>Stability data on three commercial scale batches of active substance from the proposed manufacturer stored in a container closure system representative of that intended for the market under long term conditions at 25 ºC / 60% RH and under accelerated conditions at 40 ºC / 75% RH according to the ICH guidelines were provided.</p><p>All stability indicating parameters were tested. The analytical methods used were the same as for release.</p><p>All tested parameters were within the specifications. No significant changes or trends were observed in any of the parameters tested through storage compared to the initial values.</p><p>Photostability testing following the ICH guideline Q1B was performed on one batch. The study confirmed that the active substance is not sensitive to light.</p><p>Results under stressed conditions including acidic and alkaline media and heat were provided and it was shown that the methods of analysis used are appropriate to detect the degradation of the active substance, i.e. they are stability indicating. The degradation pathways of the active substance are described and well understood.</p><p>The stability results indicate that the active substance manufactured by the proposed supplier is sufficiently stable. The stability results justify the proposed retest period in the proposed container.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.3.">Finished Medicinal Product</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Description of the product and Pharmaceutical development</head><p>The finished product is presented as immediate release white hard-gelatine capsules (size 2), each containing 100 mg of pentosan polysulfate sodium.</p><p>The aim of pharmaceutical development was to develop a product which is essentially similar to the US product Elmiron, described in scientific literature.</p><p>As mentioned above, pentosan polysulfate sodium is a BCS Class III substance exhibiting very high solubility in aqueous media across the physiological pH range and low permeability.</p><p>All excipients are well known pharmaceutical ingredients and their quality is compliant with Ph. Eur.</p><p>standards. There are no novel excipients used in the finished product formulation. The list of excipients is included in section 6.1 of the SmPC and in paragraph 2.2.1 of this report. The compatibility of the active substance and excipients has been demonstrated.</p><p>No clinical studies have been submitted. In support of the BCS-based biowaiver approach, the finished product has been compared to the product described in scientific literature by in vitro dissolution according to Appendix III of the "Guideline on the Investigation of Bioequivalence"</p><p>(CPMP/EWP/QWP/1401/98 Rev. 1). Comparative dissolution profiles in three different media have been provided and the products are considered similar. The developed dissolution method is in line with Ph.</p><p>Eur. requirements.</p><p>The manufacturing process development is based on blending a powder mixture followed by filling into hard gelatine capsules. The manufacturing process is well known and standard.</p><p>The primary packaging is either PVC/Aclar/Aluminium blisters or an HDPE container with child- The choice of the container closure system has been validated by stability data and is adequate for the intended use of the product.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Manufacture of the product and process controls</head><p>The manufacturing process consists of three main steps: preparation of powder blend, encapsulation and packaging. Conventional pharmaceutical manufacturing equipment is used. The process is considered to be a standard manufacturing process.</p><p>Major steps of the manufacturing process have been validated on 3 consecutive commercial scale batches by a number of studies. It has been demonstrated that the manufacturing process is capable of producing the finished product of intended quality in a reproducible manner. The in-process controls are adequate for this type of manufacturing process and pharmaceutical form.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Product specification</head><p>The Eur.), microbiological quality (Ph. Eur.), impurities (chromatographic method) and assay (chromatographic method).</p><p>The analytical methods used have been adequately described and appropriately validated in accordance with the ICH guidelines. Satisfactory information regarding the reference standards used for assay and identity testing has been presented.</p><p>Batch analysis results were provided for three commercial scale batches confirming the consistency of the manufacturing process and its ability to manufacture to the intended product specification.</p><p>The finished product is released on the market through traditional final product release testing. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stability of the product</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adventitious agents</head><p>Gelatine obtained from bovine sources is used in the product. Valid TSE CEP from the suppliers of the gelatine used in the manufacture is provided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.4.">Discussion on chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>Information on development, manufacture and control of the active substance and finished product has been presented in a satisfactory manner. The results of tests carried out indicate consistency and uniformity of important product quality characteristics, and these in turn lead to the conclusion that the product should have a satisfactory and uniform performance in clinical use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.5.">Conclusions on the chemical, pharmaceutical and biological aspects</head><p>The quality of this product is considered to be acceptable when used in accordance with the conditions defined in the SmPC. Physicochemical and biological aspects relevant to the uniform clinical performance of the product have been investigated and are controlled in a satisfactory way. Data has been presented to give reassurance on TSE safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.6.">Recommendations for future quality development</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.">Non-clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Introduction</head><p>No pharmacology studies have been submitted and the Applicant presented literature data. Likewise, pharmacokinetic data are based on 3 main articles dated from 1984 to 2005.</p><p>The pharmacological profile of elmiron in the treatment of IC (BPS 2X-3C) is unknown. It is hypothesized, that a potential barrier function of PPS instead of the damaged urothelial mucus might play a role as well the anti-inflammatory activity of PPS. This activity is considered as the likely mechanism of action for the proposed indication.</p><p>PPS shows some similarities in its chemical structure as well as in its mechanism(s) of action with unfractionated heparin (UFH), characterized as a sulfated glycosaminoglycan with a mean molecular weight (MW) of about 15-20 kDa (range 2-40 kDa), as well as with low molecular weight heparin derivatives (LMWHs) which are produced by partial depolymerization of UFH exhibiting an average MW of 3-7 kDa. Like heparin, PPS is a mixture of macromolecules but with a higher degree of sulfation and, thus, a higher charge density than UFH. The mean MW of Na-PPS of about 4.7 kDa (80% of the molecules have a MW between 1.8 and 9.0 kDa) is similar to commercially available LMWHs. However, there are important differences in the structure between PPS, UFH and LMWH resulting in different pharmacodynamic properties.</p><p>Parsons showed that PPS resembles the glycosaminoglycans (GAGs) produced by cells in the body, including those lining the bladder (Parsons 1994). Sadhukhan showed a cytoprotective effects resulting in a reduction in the inflammation of the bladder mucosa <ref type="bibr">(Sadhukhan et al. 2002)</ref>. Chiang et al.</p><p>demonstrated that PPS appears to inhibit in a dose-dependent manner the stimulation of connective tissue mast cells and mucosal mast cells <ref type="bibr">(Chiang et al. 2000</ref><ref type="bibr">, Chiang et al. 2003</ref> and activated bladder mast cells are reported in patients with <ref type="bibr">IC (Sant et al. 2007</ref>).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary pharmacodynamic studies</head><p>In Primary Pharmacology part of the dossier, the Applicant presented data from six sources that used studies in vitro and in vivo (with rats and rabbits treating interstitial cystitis by measuring the activity of the nuclear transcription factor nuclear κBfactor, which is thought to have a role in mediating the urothelial inflammatory response of interstitial cystitis. Authors concluded that PPS might have a nonspecific effect against the viral (dsRNA) and bacterial (LPS) activation of nuclear κB -factor and the observed clinical effect of PPS may be mediated by nonspecific binding of PPS molecules and the inflammatory stimulants of urothelial activation. These findings suggest a mechanism of action for PPS that occurs in the urine rather than at the mucosal membrane by direct interaction of the drug with potential interstitial cystitis inducing inflammatory agents. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary pharmacodynamic studies</head><p>In the PD Secondary pharmacology section the Applicant overview the historical development of the PPS activity upon blood coagulation, fibrinolysis and lipid metabolism. <ref type="bibr">Barrowcliffe et al. (1986)</ref> demonstrated after subcutaneous injection of 50mg PPS in humans an enhanced anti·Xa clotting activity and inhibition of the lipid peroxide induced thrombin generation. An increase in plasminogen activator levels after PPS due to the release of endothelial t-PA into the bloodstream was described by <ref type="bibr">Gaffney et al. 1986</ref><ref type="bibr">. Marsh et al. 1986</ref> reproduced the results in men by evaluating the thrombolytic effect of s.c., i.m. or i.v. injection of 2 -10 mg/kg PPS in experimental rats. The thrombolytic effect on freshly formed thrombi was demonstrated in the inferior vena cava thrombosis model; the effect was more pronounced in animals allowed to survive for 24 or 48 h.</p><p>The anticoagulant and fibrinolytic properties are characteristic of PPS, although its anticoagulant activity is clearly less than that of heparin <ref type="bibr">(Soria et al. 1980</ref><ref type="bibr">, Fischer et al. 1982</ref>. The anticoagulant efficacy of PPS in vivo <ref type="bibr">(Giedrojc et al. 1999</ref><ref type="bibr">, Barrowcliffe et al. 1988</ref><ref type="bibr">, Doctor et al. 1991</ref><ref type="bibr">, Ofosu et al. 1988</ref>) was studied in ex vivo samples after s.c., i.v. and i.m. administration into various species such as rats, rabbits and humans. Ex vivo the same inhibitory effects of PPS especially on thrombin and FXa generation can be observed as that seen in vitro, the effects are maintained in AT-deficient plasma. Significant anticoagulant effects in rats can be observed at parenteral doses of 10 mg/kg and higher, in humans a strong anticoagulant action of PPS is measured in the aPTT assay after  While heparin markedly suppressed thrombin and collagen aggregation and LMWHs suppressed thrombin-induced aggregation to a modest degree in parallel to their antithrombinactivity, PPS showed no significant inhibition. The collagen-induced aggregation was inhibited by heparin but at only minor degrees by PPS. At very high heparin concentrations (100 units or 600 μg/ml) ADP-induced aggregation was inhibited, PPS and other heparinoids at the same concentrations did not inhibit aggregation by ADP. Ristocetin-induced aggregation was inhibited by heparin and only slightly at high concentrations by LMWHs and PPS. When the aggregation in normal platelet-rich plasma was induced with the serum of patients with heparin-induced thrombocytopenia in the presence of the different compounds studied, besides heparin and LMWHs also PPS at low concentrations of 6 μg/ml showed a positive aggregation effect, whereas at a high concentration of 600 μg/ml the effect became negative.</p><p>Platelet adhesion to collagen was clearly inhibited by heparin, while PPS was less effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety pharmacology programme</head><p>No safety pharmacology studies with PPS are reported in scientific literature. The available non-clinical and clinical data do not provide any indication of adverse pharmacodynamics effects of PPS on the central nervous system, cardiovascular system or respiratory system.</p><p>Since medicinal products based on PPS have been marketed in the USA and in Europe the lack of nonclinical literature in this field is acceptable as superseded by clinical data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacodynamic drug interactions</head><p>No information on preclinical drug interaction studies conducted with PPS was found in scientific literature.</p><p>Since medicinal products based on PPS have been marketed in the USA and in Europe the lack of nonclinical literature in this field is acceptable as superseded by clinical data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.3.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>Several studies have been conducted to evaluate the pharmacokinetics of PPS in humans in healthy volunteers <ref type="bibr">(Fellström et al. 1986</ref><ref type="bibr">, Faaij et al. 1999</ref><ref type="bibr">, Simon et al. 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">, Danielson et al. 1991</ref>. Cadroy et al. <ref type="bibr">(Cadroy et al. 1987</ref>) determined the pharmacokinetic parameters of PPS in the rabbit from the time course of the plasma TRA concentrations after intravenous injection of 125I-Na-PPS. 5 µCi of 125I-Na-PPS as a marker was injected simultaneously with increasing doses (~ 6 -12,600 µg/kg) of unlabelled Na-PPS to groups of 2 -3 animals. The disappearance of the TRA from the plasma of rabbits was triphasic. The half-lives t1/2α (1.8 -6.8 min) and t1/2γ (3.1 -5.2 h) as well as the total volume of distribution Vd (180 -372 ml) were independent of the dose administered. However, there was a highly significant correlation between the dose and the clearance (r = 0.91), and between the dose and the half-life t1/2,β (r = 0.81). The results show that the TRA clearance (Cltot) is reduced (from 17.4 to 4.8 ml/min) and the half-life t1/2β is prolonged (from 15.1 to 41.5 min) with increasing doses. Over the dose range investigated, the clearance varied by a factor of three in the rabbits. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.4.">Toxicology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Single dose toxicity</head><p>No single dose toxicity studies with PPS are reported in scientific literature which was considered acceptable by the CHMP. The available non-clinical and clinical data do not provide indication of acute toxicity of PPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Repeat dose toxicity</head><p>In 2-week repeat-dose toxicity studies (no GLP compliance) in mice and rats PPS concentrations of 0, 33, 111, 333, 1000 and 3000 mg/kg were applied via oral gavage once daily for 5 days per week for up to 2 consecutive weeks (National Toxicology Program (NTP) <ref type="bibr">2004</ref><ref type="bibr">, Nyska et al. 2002</ref>. No drugrelated mortality was observed. In clinical observations and necropsy: no abnormalities were detected.</p><p>Some changes were observed in the organ weights. Based on these findings the no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL) was determined: 333 mg/kg body weight for mice males and 1000 mg/kg body weight for females. The NOAEL in 2-week toxicity studies in rats was considered to be 333 mg/kg body weight.</p><p>13-week gavage toxicity studies with PPS were conducted in rats and mice. Concentrations of 0, 63, 125, 250, 500 and 1000 mg/kg were applied via oral gavage once daily for 5 days per week for up to 13 consecutive weeks. No drug-related mortality was observed. In these studies were observed increase of body weight in male rats treated with 500 mg/kg. There was also observed an increase in: a) liver weight (in male rats treated with 250 mg/kg or 1000 mg/kg and 500 mg/kg, female rats treated with all dose groups (63-1000 mg/kg), male mice treated with 500 mg/kg, female mice treated with 250 or 1000 mg/kg or 500 mg/kg); b) kidney weight (female rats treated with 1000 mg/kg); c) spleen weight (male rats treated with 125 mg/kg to 1000 mg/kg and 63 mg/kg (absolute), female rats treated with 1000 mg/kg , male mice treated with 1000 mg/kg (absolute and relative) or 125 mg/kg (absolute), female mice treated with 1000 mg/kg); d) lung weight (female rats treated with 1000 mg/kg (absolute and relative) or 125 mg/kg (absolute), female mice treated with 125 or 1000 mg/kg). The observed organ weight increases were associated with the following histopathological observations:</p><p>Liver: In both species, hepatocytic vacuolisation was observed in both sexes in the highest dose group and in males in the 500 mg/kg dose group. The characteristic of the vacuolisation was mainly indicative of fat. Inflammation was also observed in male rats treated with 500 and 1000 mg/kg and in nearly all dose groups of mice.</p><p>Kidney: In rats, tubular epithelial vacuolisation was observed in both species treated with 1000 mg/kg. Spleen: In mice histiocytic infiltration was observed in female mice treated with 500 or 1000 mg/kg and in male mice treated with 1000 mg/kg.</p><p>Lung: In rats, alveolar histiocytic infiltration was observed in all dose-groups treated with PPS and appeared more severe in the higher dose-groups. Chronic interstitial inflammation occurred in both sexes treated with 500 or 1000 mg/kg and also in females treated with 250 mg/kg.</p><p>Rectum: In both species, treatment-related changes consisted of histiocytic infiltration, chronic active inflammation, and chronic ulcers. All observations started with the application of 125 mg/kg to male rats. In female rats, histiocytic infiltration started with the low dose of 63 mg/kg while ulcers and infiltration started with the application of 500 mg/kg only. In male mice, histiocyte infiltration started with 250 mg/kg and ulcer and inflammation started with the highest dose. In female mice, histiocyte infiltration and inflammation started with doses of 500 mg/kg while no ulcers were seen in female mice.</p><p>Overall, lesions consisted mainly of infiltration into multiple tissues of vacuolated histiocytes, which, by histochemical investigation, indicated the presence of neutral and acidic mucins and lipidic material within the vacuoles. Transmission electron microscopy identified these vacuoles as lysosomal structures that exhibited a variety of contents. On the basis of these findings, it was concluded, that PPS was absorbed through the focally disrupted rectal mucosa, was deposited in the lamina propria, accumulated within macrophages, and then was distributed by these cells or as a free chemical via the lymphatics and blood, to the various organ sites manifesting histiocytic infiltration. The cytoplasmic membrane bound structures within macrophages were lysosomes containing membranous material of cellular origin and, perhaps, remnants of the deposited test material.</p><p>Haematological analysis indicated increases for both species in the white blood cells and lymphocyte counts in those animals treated with higher doses of PPS. In both species WBC and lymphocytes were significantly increased in animals treated with 1000 mg/kg.</p><p>According results of the studies the no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL) was considered to be: 250 (males) -500 (females) mg PPS / kg body weight for mice and 125 (males) -250 (females) mg PPS/kg body weight for rates.    With respect to the question whether the absence of findings in the NTP micronucleus studies could be related to the fact that PPS is poorly absorbed, it can be demonstrated that the animals were maximally exposed to the test substance, because the doses administered were selected on the basis of 13-week maximum tolerated dosage (MTD) studies, in which doses up to 1,000 mg/kg bw were administered. At dose levels of 250 mg/kg and above (rat) and at 1,000 mg/kg (mouse), animals of the 13 week studies developed rectal lesions consisting of chronic ulcers and/or chronic inflammation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Genotoxicity</head><p>In addition to the outcome of the MTD study, which indicates that PPS is absorbed after oral administration, <ref type="bibr">Abdo et al., 2003</ref> demonstrate that tritiated PPS upon oral administration to Sprague-Dawley rats is absorbed from the gastrointestinal tract and becomes distributed throughout the body <ref type="bibr">(Dencker et al., 1985;</ref><ref type="bibr">Odlind et al., 1987)</ref>.</p><p>Thus, although no toxicokinetic investigations were performed in parallel to the genotoxicity (and carcinogenicity) NTP studies, it can be concluded that the animals were exposed to the test compound.</p><p>In agreement with the final conclusion drawn in the NTP-Report, the results of the mutagenicity tests can be summarized as follows: PPS was not mutagenic in S. typhimurium strains TA97, TA98, TA100, or TA1535 with or without induced hamster or rat liver S9 enzymes. No increases in the frequency of micronucleated polychromatic erythrocytes were seen in bone marrow cells of rats or mice administered PPS by gavage three times at 24-hour intervals. No significant alterations in the frequency of micronucleated normochromatic erythrocytes were seen in peripheral blood samples from male or female mice administered PPS for 3 months by gavage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Carcinogenicity</head><p>Data presented by the Applicant relied on results obtained after oral administration of the US product.Elmiron and are summarized in Table  The potential reproductive toxicity of PPS was assessed in Sprague-Dawley rats <ref type="bibr">(NTP, 1997</ref> Data from other repeated dose toxicity studies were evaluated concerning findings which could give any indication for potential effects on male or female fertility. In none of the subchronic or chronic studies in rats and mice an influence on weight development, morphology or functionality of male or female sexual organs could be observed.</p><p>Published reproduction toxicity studies are rare. In reproduction toxicity studies in rats which were treated with doses up to 1,000 mg PPS/kg there were no effects on reproductive, breeding, or fertility parameters. Spermatological investigation or evaluation of the oestrus cycles did not reveal any effects of the test compound. Data from other toxicity studies (weights or histologic findings of reproductive organs in males or females) did not give any indication for potential effects on male or female reproduction.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Toxicokinetic data</head><p>No toxicokinetic data were not submitted this was considered acceptable by the CHMP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Local Tolerance</head><p>No specific non-clinical local tolerance studies were submitted. This was considered acceptable by the CHMP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other toxicity studies</head><p>A 28-day repeat dose study to evaluate the potential immunotoxicity of PPS was conducted by NTP <ref type="bibr">(Thakur et al. 2014)</ref>. Eight female B6C3F1/N mice each were orally administered with PPS at doses of 63, 125, 250, 500 or 1000 mg/kg. For the B16F10 host resistance study, doses administered were 0, 250, 500 or 1000 mg/kg. Each treatment group consisted of 12 animals. The doses, vehicle, and the route of exposure were selected based on the dose levels of the 3-month NTP toxicity studies and to minimize the potential for overt toxicity that could confound immunologic evaluation.</p><p>No signs of overt toxicity were observed in the PPS-treated animals. No significant treatment-related effects were observed in mice with respect to body weights except a significant increase (40%) in body weight gain in the 250 mg/kg dose group. The absolute liver weights were increased at the 500 and 1000 mg/kg doses (13% and 23%, respectively) and the relative liver weight was increased at 1000 mg/kg (17%). Treatment-related effects on absolute or relative weights of thymus, spleen, lung or kidney were not observed. PPS treatment resulted in statistically significant increases in the percentage of reticulocytes in the peripheral blood in the 125, 500, and 1000 mg/kg treatment groups (23%, 19% and 29%, respectively). Erythrocyte numbers, differential leukocyte counts, hemoglobin, hematocrit, MCV, and platelet concentration were not affected.</p><p>Mice treated with PPS had a significant increase in absolute numbers of splenic macrophages (63, 500 and 1000 mg/kg) and natural killer (NK) cells (250 and 1000 mg/kg). PPS treatment did not affect the humoral immune response or T cell proliferative response. However, innate immune responses such as phagocytosis by liver macrophages (1000 mg/ kg) and NK cell activity were enhanced (500 and 1000 mg/kg). Further analysis using a disease resistance model showed that PPS-treated mice demonstrated significantly increased anti-tumor activity against B16F10 melanoma cells at the 500 and 1000 mg/kg doses.</p><p>The authors conclude, that the current study demonstrated that 28-day PPS treatment enhances the innate immune responses in healthy female B6C3F1/N mice by specifically increasing macrophage and NK cell number, NK cell activity and macrophage phagocytosis.</p><p>Consistent with their reported function in host defense, the increases in NK cell and macrophage activity appeared to increase resistance to B16F10 tumor development in mice.</p><p>Furthermore, the identified immune potentiating properties of PPS indicates that long term PPS treatment should be used with caution in patients with genetic disposition to development of inflammatory disorders such as autoimmune diseases due to potential exacerbation of innate immune responses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.5.">Ecotoxicity/environmental risk assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PBT screening Result Conclusion</head><p>Bioaccumulation potential-log Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 35/115</p><p>Overall, PPS is not expected to pose a risk to the environment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.1.">Discussion on non-clinical aspects</head><p>Demonstration of pharmacological activity of PPS in the treatment of IC (BPS 2X-3C) relies on a review of the literature. Although the mechanism of action remains unknown, PPS has shown to be able to bind to bladder epithelium; restore epithelial barrier integrity in bladders with permeability disorders and has anti-inflammatory properties. Moreover, PPS is a low molecular-weight heparin like compound with anticoagulant and fibrinolytic effects. Overall, non-clinical pharmacokinetic data is sparse which is acceptable and evaluation relies on literature and clinical experience.</p><p>After I.V. administration of radiolabelled PPS in rabbits clearance of PPS decreased with the doseincrease and this was correlated with a half-life increase. Distribution of radioactivity appeared to be in the whole body after I.V administration in rats with the highest detected radioactivity observed in the urinary tract. Odlind et al. have reported that there were no qualitative differences (only quantitative differences) in distribution in the urinary tract after oral or I.V. administration.</p><p>Bioavailability of PPS is weak and absorbed fraction is metabolized in the liver and spleen.</p><p>Transformation of PPS relies on desulfation process occurring in the liver and the spleen and depolymerisation in the kidney.</p><p>As reported by Fellström et al., less than 0.1% of PPS is recovered unchanged in the urine after oral administration in Human, fraction found in the urine are mainly metabolites. PPS is mostly excreted in the faeces (54-84%) as unchanged drug. Overall, pharmacokinetic data regarding the non-clinical field are seldom and assessment should rely on clinical experience.</p><p>According to the Applicant, LMWHs and certain heparinoids may be less likely to cause bleeding because they do not interfere with collagen-mediated aggregation and adhesion to a significant degree.</p><p>However, PPS did show slight inhibitory activity against collagen aggregation and adhesion and it also interacts with the antibody induced by heparin therapy. In accordance with the abovementioned a warning statement on the anticoagulant effects of elmiron was included in Section 4.4 of the SmPC which was considered acceptable by the CHMP.</p><p>The toxicological program presented by the Applicant relies on literature review including studies conducted by the NTP on Elmiron. No dedicated acute toxicity study with PPS has been reported in the literature but repeated-dose toxicity studies in rodents have highlighted toxicity localized in lymph nodes (mesenteric and mandibular), liver, lung (only rats), rectum and spleen (only mice).</p><p>Elmiron-related increases in organ weight-were observed: lung (rats), liver, kidney (female rats) and spleen (male mice); this in correlation with macrophage infiltration, vacuolization observed in these organs. Ulceration and inflammation localized at the rectum level, is the result of high exposure of this tissue to the drug due to poor absorption after oral administration.</p><p>According results of the studies the no observed adverse effect level (NOAEL) was considered to be: 250 (males) -500 (females) mg PPS / kg body weight for mice and 125 (males) -250 (females) mg PPS/kg body weight for rates.</p><p>Regarding the 2-year carcinogenicity studies, mice are more sensitive towards Elmiron treatment.</p><p>Increase incidence of neoplastic lesions, with statistical significance, were observed in the liver, malignant lymphoma in the spleen, of B6CF3F1 mouse. Under the conditions of these 2-year studies, PPS was carcinogenic to mice but not to rats. In the rat carcinogenicity study, there was no substance related increase in the incidence of neoplasms. In the mouse study, increased incidences of liver hemangiosarcoma were related to the administration of the test material (medium and high dose groups males, high dose group females).</p><p>Additionally, the incidence of liver adenoma was increased (high dose group females). The dosages tested were up to 60 times the maximum recommended human dose (MRHD) in rats, and up to 117 times the MRHD in mice, on a mg/kg basis.</p><p>Due to the relevance of the neoplastic findings from the mouse long term study genotoxicity studies have been performed by the National Toxicology Program (NTP) to develop a comprehensive database permitting a critical anticipation of a chemical`s carcinogenicity and are reported in the NTP Technical Report on the Toxicology and Carcinogenesis studies of Elmiron. Results obtained from in vivo genotoxic studies are considered sufficient by the CHMP to demonstrate that PPS is not susceptible of genotoxic damage. Results indicate no mutagenic effect in the Ames Test (in accordance with the OECD guideline number 471) and no consistent increase in the frequency of micro-nucleated polychromatic erythrocytes revealing a mutagenic potential was induced by PPS. Thus, it can be concluded that the findings in the mouse study are not associated with a genotoxic potential and are not applicable to the circumstances in clinical therapy.</p><p>Evaluation of PPS impact over the immune system was tested in 28-day repeat dose study and was conducted by the National Toxicology Program (NTP) <ref type="bibr">(Thakur et al. 2014</ref>). The doses, vehicle, and the route of exposure were selected based on the dose levels of the 3-month NTP toxicity studies and to minimize the potential for overt toxicity that could confound immunologic evaluation. Treatmentrelated effects on absolute or relative weights of thymus, spleen, lung or kidney were not observed.</p><p>PPS treatment resulted in statistically significant increases in the percentage of reticulocytes in the peripheral blood. Mice treated with PPS had a significant increase in absolute numbers of splenic macrophages (63, 500 and 1000 mg/kg) and natural killer (NK) cells (250 and 1000 mg/kg). PPS treatment did not affect the humoral immune response or T cell proliferative response. However, innate immune responses such as phagocytosis by liver macrophages (1000 mg/ kg) and NK cell activity were enhanced (500 and 1000 mg/kg). PPS treatment enhances the innate immune responses in healthy female B6C3F1/N mice by specifically increasing macrophage and NK cell number, NK cell activity and macrophage phagocytosis.</p><p>No embryofetal toxicity studies are published for PPS, but indirect evidence of the lack of transplacental passage of PPS was generated via a clinical study published by Forestier <ref type="bibr">(Forestier et al. 1986</ref>). Reproduction studies have been performed in mice and rats with intravenous daily doses of 15 mg/kg, and in rabbits with 7.5 mg/kg. These doses are 0.42 and 0.14 times the daily oral human doses of Elmiron when normalized to body surface area. These studies did not reveal evidence of impaired fertility or harm to the foetus from Elmiron. Direct in vitro bathing of cultured mouse embryos with pentosan polysulfate sodium (PPS) at a concentration of 1 mg/mL may cause reversible limb bud abnormalities. Adequate and well-controlled studies have not been performed in pregnant women. The applicant has stated in the proposed SmPC that it is preferable to avoid the use of PPS during pregnancy and should not be used during breast-feeding which is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3.2.">Conclusion on the non-clinical aspects</head><p>The Applicant submitted an application for a well-established use product, and as such submitted no new non-clinical data. The scientific literature review of the non-clinical data on pharmacology, pharmacokinetics and toxicology of pentosan polysulfate sodium is considered appropriate to support the proposed clinical use for the treatment of Interstitial Cystitis/ bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions in adults.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.">Clinical aspects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.1.">Introduction</head><p>According To identify all relevant studies a literature search using the control terms "cystitis" AND "pentosan" was conducted in DIMDI, MedPilot, and PubMed. Relevant publications identified after a first review of abstracts were studied in more detail to extract the required information. In addition, relevant references cited in the publications identified as described were hand searched and evaluated.</p><p>First scientific articles describing the efficacy of PPS in this indication were published in 1983.</p><p>Treatment with PPS is defined as standard of care for the treatment of bladder pain syndrome or Interstitial Cystitis in European treatment Guidelines since the year 2004.</p><p>The efficacy of PPS capsules is supported by six placebo-controlled clinical studies as pivotal data. Five of these studies were double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical studies. In addition one 2x2</p><p>factorial study was conducted with PPS and hydroxyzine in a placebo-controlled design (see <ref type="table">table   "</ref>main clinical studies").</p><p>Supportive data on the efficacy and safety of PPS capsules are also provided from uncontrolled studies conducted with PPS capsules as well as from active controlled studies.</p><p>Interstitial cystitis / BPS is a disease primarily defined by the symptoms experienced by the patients.</p><p>There are no established pharmacodynamics biomarkers or histopathological indicators for the severity of the disease. All 6 placebo-controlled studies evaluated efficacy via patient-reported outcome measures as key evaluation tools.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GCP</head><p>As this application was submitted under Article 10a (well-established use) it is based on literature.</p><p>Based on literature only, it is not possible to confirm with certainty whether the studies were performed in accordance with the guidelines and principles of Good Clinical Practices (GCP). Still, some limited information about GCP could be retrieved for the following studies:</p><p>Holm-Bentzen 1987: the Helsinki-II declaration was used.</p><p>Nickel at al 2015: the study was done in accordance with the ethical principles originating in the Declaration of Helsinki, consistent with Good Clinical Practices and applicable regulatory requirements.</p><p>All patients provided written informed consent before study participation. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.2.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>The composition of the product under application and the product Elmiron authorised in the US for relief of bladder pain or discomfort associated with IC since September 1996 which was used in the literature references is qualitatively and quantitatively identical.</p><p>The three studies with PK data are presented below: Approximately 6.30% ± 1.11% (4.78-7.97%) was excreted in the urine and 84.13% ± 7.71% (68.45-91.56%) was recovered in the faeces (see <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>). Thus, the applicant notes that percentage of PPS absorbed was very low. Radioactivity counts in plasma samples were insignificant and variable with median (CV%) peak plasma PPS concentrations of 250 (25) ng-eq/ml and 358 (9.3) ng-eq/ml for lower and higher dose groups, respectively. The peak plasma concentrations were seen at similar time points (~2 h). The Applicant explained that despite that, the fact that about 6% of the administered dose of radiolabelled PPS were excreted via urine shows that absorption takes place and that PPS localizes in the urinary tract after oral administration. This preferential localization was also reported in respective studies conducted in rats <ref type="bibr">(Odlind et al., 1987)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MacGregor et al., 1984</head><p>Five healthy volunteers (52 to 77 kg, 28 to 44 years old) were included in the study for this paper.</p><p>Four subjects received either 0, 0.1, 1, 7 or 50 mg PPS iv with an iode-based radioactive tracer.</p><p>Radioactivity was cleared from the blood with a half-live between 13-28 minutes in the lower doses and 45 minutes for the 50 mg dose. Most radioactivity was cleared in a second phase over the next 24-96 hours.</p><p>Images taken at 5 minutes interval from 7.5 to 47.5 minutes showed progressive uptake by the liver and spleen. At three hour a profile scan showed 60% of the activity in the liver and spleen, and 13% in the bladder.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Forestier et al., 1986</head><p>In the study described by the article, eight women who were going to have an abortion received 50 mg PPS IV. Clinical data (change of coagulation parameters in foetus plasma) provided no indication of transplacental PPS. A potential transplacental passage was evaluated by measuring maternal and foetal coagulation parameters. While in the maternal plasma aPTT was prolonged, factor Xa generation was impaired and factor V level was deeply decreased 30 minutes after intravenous administration of 50 mg PPS, the respective parameters were unchanged in the plasma of the foetuses of the exposed mothers compared to plasma obtained from control foetuses at the same stage of gestation. The data generated in this study provide no indication of transplacental passage of PPS.</p><p>Since no further data from clinical studies with PPS in pregnant or nursing women are available, the Summary of Product Characteristics (SmPC) states that PPS capsules should not be used during pregnancy or lactation unless clearly necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Elimination</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Excretion</head><p>Data generated by Simon et al., 2005 indicated that the majority of orally administered PPS (84.13% ± 7.71% after 120 h) remained unabsorbed and was excreted predominantly unchanged in the faeces.</p><p>Radioactivity in the urine consisted mostly of components of lower molecular weight and lower degrees of sulfation than PPS. 6.30% ± 1.11% of the administered dose of radiolabelled PPS were excreted via urine during 120 h after application.</p><p>Urine In the study conducted by Simon et al., 2005 a metabolic profiling analysis was conducted in the urine, faeces and plasma samples obtained from three of the high dose subjects. As specific assays for PPS do not exist, metabolic profiling was accomplished through multiple fraction collections and radiochromatographic techniques. The metabolic profiling with urine indicates that PPS was metabolized extensively by desulfation and depolymerisation. The HPLC profiling undertaken with urine samples from selected time-points showed similar HPLC profiles, indicating the metabolic profile did not change appreciably with time. Faeces samples analysed indicated that mainly unchanged PPS is contained in faeces representing PPS amounts that were not absorbed from the GI tract.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose proportionality and time dependencies</head><p>In Simon et al 2005, after 200 and 300 mg PPS per os, Cmax and AUC were proportional between the two doses. However, as the sample size was small, and no other dose proportionality data are presented, no firm conclusion on dose linearity can be made.</p><p>In Marshall et al 1997, after oral administration of PPS three times daily, Cmax increased nearly 7 fold and AUCtau increased nearly 8 fold between D1 and D15. An 8-fold increase in Cmax and AUCtau is consistent with a terminal elimination half-live of 20 hours, which is consistent with the 20 to 24 hours half-live.</p><p>According to the accumulation factor R which describes the ratio of Cmax (as well as AUC0-tau, where tau is the dosing interval) between a single dose administration and at steady state, i.e. after multiple administrations, linear pharmacokinetics were assumed. Calculated half-life was 34 hours and the accumulation factor R of 5 to 6.7 must be expected upon repeated dosing of PPS at 8-hours intervals, considering the half-life to be in range between 24 and 34 hours. Oral administration of pentosan polysulfate sodium 3-times daily is expected to lead to accumulation of pentosan polysulfate sodium over the first 7 days of administration (accumulation factor 5-6.7).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Special populations</head><p>PK has not been studied in special populations (elderly patients, hepatically or renally impaired patients, paediatric patients, pregnant and breast feeding women), this was considered acceptable with the relevant information included into the SmPC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetic interaction studies</head><p>No drug-drug interaction study was performed with PPS by the Applicant. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.3.">Pharmacodynamics</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mechanism of action</head><p>The hypothetic mechanism of action of pentosan polysulfate sodium includes a local effect in the bladder after systemic administration and excretion into the urine by binding of glycosaminoglycans to the deficient mucous of the bladder. This binding of glycosaminoglycans to the bladder mucous bacterial adherence to the cells is reduced by pentosan polysulfate sodium and in consequence the incidence of infections is reduced as well. It is hypothesized, that a potential barrier function of pentosan polysulfate sodium instead of the damaged urothelial mucus might play a role as well the anti-inflammatory activity of pentosan polysulfate sodium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary and Secondary pharmacology</head><p>Mainly two potential mechanisms of action are discussed in scientific literature, a repair of defects in the glycosaminoglycan layer and an anti-inflammatory effect of PPS. Respective assumptions on the mode of action are also reflected in the publications on the pivotal studies <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland, 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mullholland et al., 1990</ref>. No clinical studies explicitly evaluating potential pharmacodynamics of PPS for the treatment of Interstitial Cystitis were reported in scientific literature, but relevant in vitro data with human cells have been generated, which, together with supportive evidence from non-clinical studies reported in scientific literature for the respective hypothesis clearly support the two potential mechanisms of action (please refer to chapter on primary pharmacodynamic studies in the non-clinical part of this report).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary pharmacology</head><p>No dedicated studies were performed. The publication of a small PD study on 18 healthy volunteers after administration of oral doses was submitted which evaluated the impact of orally administered PPS on the coagulation system <ref type="bibr">(Faaij et al., 1999)</ref>. Because no specific assays were available to measure PPS directly during the conduct of the study, indirect measures were used to evaluate the amount of The study was carried out as a three-way cross-over bioavailability design, in which 18 non-smoking, normotensive male healthy volunteers received an intravenous bolus injection of 50 mg PPS, and oral dose of 1500 mg PPS or an oral placebo. The wash-out period between the study days was 2 weeks.</p><p>While the intravenous application of PPS lead to relevant effects on APTT, Anti-Xa activity, t-PA activity and fibrin plate lysis, no such effects were detected after oral administration of the very high dose of 1500 mg PPS applied orally to the subjects.</p><p>However as Elmiron post-marketing experience with humans and <ref type="bibr">Nickel et al. (2005)</ref> data indicate that most common reported AEs were diarrhoea, rectal bleeding and abdominal pain the Applicant was asked to clarify PPS action on GIT providing clear explanation of possible action mechanism, may be related with anticoagulant and fibrinolytic or local irritative properties.</p><p>Firstly, the Applicant stated causal relationship of GITs and the administration of PPS is not obvious.</p><p>GITs are equally reported as associated with the underlying disease and independent of any treatment.</p><p>According to Van de Merwe, 2006, many patients with IC also have gastrointestinal disorders. A survey in the US in which more than 6.000 IC patients were asked what disorders they had in association with their IC showed following prevalence of associated disorders: The PPS dose is estimated to be 3-6 times higher than the recommended dose of PPS used for the treatment of IC. Account should be taken of the fact that the reported gastrointestinal symptoms could likewise be the result of the underlying cancer disease (among others 6 patients with sarcoma, 5 patients with colon carcinoma). It is reported that 14 of the treated patients had completed at least two other treatment attempts before. Possible adequate therapies include radiation therapies which can likewise cause a proctitis with progressive mucosal atrophy from injured micro-vascularisation in the mucosa and submucosal stroma. Furthermore the irradiation of colonic mucosa might decrease prostaglandin production and affect the mucosal permeability to some bile acids causing further destruction and/or alteration of the mucosa eliminating the natural protective barrier of the lower gastrointestinal tract. Thus, the diarrhoea reported might be seen as an attending symptom of the proctitis rather than a side effect of PPS. Further data allowing an assessment of a potential effect of a concomitant therapy as well as to the immunological status are missing.</p><p>On the other hand Grigsby et al., 1990 reports of 13 patients, who were treated because of chronic radiation induced proctitis including tenesmus orally with 150 mg up to 300 mg PPS TID. Notably there was no severe acute or chronic toxicity reported in this study, especially no hint on GIT.</p><p>Secondly, the Applicant states PK data show that the uptake of PPS following oral administration is low.</p><p>The impact of orally administered PPS in man on the coagulation system was studied systematically in a bioavailability study by <ref type="bibr">Faaij et al., 1999</ref> proving that the oral administration of 1500 mg PPS (5 times the recommended daily intake) showed no systemic effects on the coagulation system. Thus the Applicant considers it highly unlikely that there is any causal relationship due to the anticoagulant and fibrinolytic properties of PPS.</p><p>Thirdly, the Applicant states causal relationship of PPS regarding GITs based on pharmacodynamics and pharmacokinetics is not reported in literature. Therefore, the Applicant presented following reflections:</p><p>• Diarrhoea, nausea, dyspepsia and abdominal pain could be due to an osmotic load effect of the PPS created by undigested and/or unabsorbed PPS as well as the cellulose as part of the capsule.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>The degree of sulfatation of PPS might interact with the mucin production GIT causing irritant effects. The gastrointestinal tract is coated by a thick layer of mucus that forms the front line of innate host defence. The mucus consists of high molecular weight glycoproteins called mucins that are synthesized and secreted by goblet cells and functions primarily to lubricate the epithelium and protect it from damage by noxious substances. High degrees of sulfatation of PPS may led to a higher degree of sulfatation in the high molecular weight mucin form and a disturbances in mucin sulfatation process could be detrimental to the maintenance of gastric mucus coat integrity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.4.">Discussion on clinical pharmacology</head><p>Absorption Fellström and al and Simon and al. both showed a very low bioavailability, around or less than 1%.</p><p>According to <ref type="bibr">Fellström et al., 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Marshall et al., 1997</ref><ref type="bibr">and Simon et al 2005</ref>-7% of the administered radioactivity is excreted with the urine and the fraction of unchanged PPS (compared to total radioactivity) is about 1-2% in urine compared to 10-15% in plasma. Therefore, it can be extrapolated that about 1% of the orally administered PPS finally binds to the GAG layer of the urothelium. Considering these pharmacokinetics data, about 3 mg of the unchanged product will reach its target (bladder epithelium) in the urinary tract following a daily oral dose of 300 mg PPS.</p><p>The applicant justifies recommending using PPS capsules with water at least 1 hour before meals or 2 hours after meals based on the use the pivotal studies and the efficacy and safety being established for the respective dosing schedule. This was considered acceptable by the CHMP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Distribution</head><p>The The applicant highlights two studies <ref type="bibr">(Mac Gregor et al., 1984 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Simon et al 2005)</ref> that details metabolic pathways. The studies suggest that metabolism take place in liver, spleen and kidneys via desulfation (assumed to be in liver and spleen, which are rich sources of sulfatases) and depolymerisation (concluded as taking place in kidneys, as depolymerised species were found not in plasma but in urine only). This is summarized in SmPC (section 5.2). No specific proportions for metabolism are given which is acceptable, considering rather limited extent of absorption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose linearity and time dependency</head><p>In Simon et al 2005, after 200 and 300 mg PPS per os, C max and AUC were proportional between the two doses. However, as the sample size was small, and no other dose proportionality data are presented, no firm conclusion on dose linearity can be made.</p><p>In Marshall et al, after oral administration of PPS three times daily, Cmax increased nearly 7 fold and AUCtau increased nearly 8 fold between D1 and D15. An 8-fold increase in Cmax and AUCtau is consistent with a terminal elimination half-live of 20 hours, which is consistent with the 20 to 24 hours half-live. According to the accumulation factor R which describes the ratio of Cmax (as well as AUC0tau, where tau is the dosing interval) between a single dose administration and at steady state, i.e. after multiple administrations, linear pharmacokinetics was assumed. Calculated half-life was 34 hours and the accumulation factor R of 5 to 6.7 must be expected upon repeated dosing of PPS at 8-hours intervals, considering the half-life to be in range between 24 and 34 hours. The calculation is appropriate and this information was reflected in the SmPC.</p><p>In PK has not been studied in some of the special populations (elderly patients, hepatically or renally impaired patients, paediatric patients, pregnant and breast feeding women) the lack of this data and precautionary statement are reflected in the SmPC which was considered acceptable by the CHMP. However, taking into consideration that rectal bleeding is a clinically significant AR and the pharmacological class precautions and warnings referring to a weak anticoagulant effect of PPS were included in the proposed SmPC for PPS and respective information on potential interactions in case of concomitant administration of anticoagulant medicinal products is provided.</p><p>No PK/PD profiles of PPS have been investigated by the applicant which is acceptable in this rare indication. Likewise, no clinical pharmacology studies were performed with PPS. Thus, the mechanism of action of PPS is currently not completely understood. It is hypothesized, that a potential barrier function of PPS instead of the damaged urothelial mucus might play a role in the bladder endothelium as well the anti-inflammatory activity of PPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4.5.">Conclusions on clinical pharmacology</head><p>A potential weak anticoagulant effect of PPS in patients especially "in patients with an increased risk of bleeding due to concomitant treatments with anticoagulants, heparin derivatives, thrombolytic or antiplatelet agents including acetylsalicylic acid, or non-steroidal anti-inflammatory medicinal products" was adequately reflected in the SmPC.</p><p>Regarding the pharmacodynamics, mainly two potential mechanisms of action are discussed in scientific literature, a repair of defects in the glycosaminoglycan layer and an anti-inflammatory effects of PPS. Overall, the studies conducted in vitro in human cells supported by relevant non-clinical in vivo studies described above provide solid evidence for both mechanisms of action.</p><p>However, Pharmacological data of PPS are still lacking in human to better understand the real mechanism of action of PPS in IC / bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or</p><p>Hunner's lesions in adults. The assessment relies therefore on the evaluation of efficacy in the pivotal trials.</p><p>Overall the clinical pharmacology of this product can be considered sufficiently described for the purpose of the marketing authorisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.">Clinical efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.1.">Dose response study(ies)</head><p>In the two provided supportive dose range evaluations for potential dose-response relationship <ref type="bibr">(Nickel et al., 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">, Nickel et al., 2015</ref> neither 1x100 mg of PPS /day versus 3x100 mg or 2x300 mg, 3x300 mg versus 3x 100 mg of PPS per day leads to statistically significant differences in terms of efficacy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.2.">Main studies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Title of studies</head><p>The efficacy of PPS capsules was supported by six placebo-controlled clinical studies as pivotal data.</p><p>Five of these studies were double-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled clinical studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Participants</head><p>The enrolled patient population differed between the studies, reflecting understanding and definition of IC at the time, when the study was planned and conducted. In particular, ESSIC classification 2X and 3C would meet the NIDDK criteria for IC.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatments</head><p>The main studies were performed with Elmiron capsules, which is the identical medicinal product authorised in the US as the product being applied for in the context of the current application.</p><p>The majority of patients in the pivotal studies as well as in the supportive studies were treated with the established dose of 3x100 mg PPS per day and few patients received a dose of 2x200 mg PPS per day.</p><p>The treatment duration varied from 3 months, 4 months or 6 months.</p><p>An overview of the dose-regimens used in the 6 pivotal studies is provided below: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The study objectives of the pivotal studies focused either on IC or IC/BPS treatments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes/endpoints</head><p>Key study endpoints/outcomes in all 6 pivotal studies were patient-reported outcomes via patient responder analysis. As the definitions for responder analyses were rather heterogeneous, the applicant provided an overview of efficacy endpoints used in the six pivotal studies.  subjects per group (total of 645) would provide 90% power to detect a 15% difference in the proportion of responders based on ICSI, assuming 30% responders in the active treatment groups and 15% responders in the placebo group.</p><p>In <ref type="bibr">Parsons 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mulholland 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">, Parsons 1993</ref>, the sample size determination was not mentioned.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomisation</head><p>In Holm-Bentzen 1987, in both protocols patients were randomized after fulfilling the inclusion criteria and pre-trial investigations to receive either 200 mg sodium pentosan polysulfate or placebo capsules twice daily for 4 months. The interval from cystoscopy to randomization varied but it was not allowed to exceed 4 months. Some patients benefited from dilatation during cystoscopy for 1 to 3 months and they did not start the medication before recurrence of symptoms. The pre-trial symptom score values date from the day the patient began medication.</p><p>In Parsons 1987, the patients were randomized to drug or placebo groups by the pharmacy to begin therapy (treatment A). Therapy was begun with 100 mg pentosan polysulfate (or a look-alike placebo)</p><p>3 times daily or 200 mg twice daily, depending on institution they attended. At the end of 3 months, if the patient failed to respond to therapy, cross-over to treatment B was begun (from drug placebo or vice versa). If the patient responded to treatment A, he or she returned in 3 more months, and if there still was a positive response cross-over to treatment B was instituted.</p><p>In Mulholland 1990, the patients were randomly assigned to PPS or placebo group in accordance with a computer-generated random code providing two parallel groups of patients for comparison.</p><p>In Parsons 1993, patients were randomly assigned to receive pentosan polysulfate or placebo in accordance with a computer generated random code providing 2 parallel groups for comparison.</p><p>In Sant 2003, 121 participants were randomized by the 7 participating institutions (representing 89% of the goal) over 18 months in equal proportions to the 4 treatment arms using a randomized block design stratified by clinical site.</p><p>In Nickel 2015, eligible patients were randomized to PPS 100 mg QD, PPS 100 mg TID (the FDA approved dose) or matching placebo in a 1:1:1 ratio based on a computer generated randomization schedule. Randomization was balanced using randomly permuted blocks and stratified by whether patients had or had not ever been treated with PPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blinding (masking)</head><p>All pivotal studies were randomized double-blind according to the authors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical methods</head><p>All six pivotal clinical studies provided a statistical analysis of the efficacy results generated in the respective study:</p><p>The efficacy endpoints evaluated in the pivotal placebo-controlled studies were all based on a patientreported outcome of rather subjective symptoms. In such analyses, the placebo effects are usually rather high. Each of the studies enrolled a very limited number of patients based on the rarity of the disease. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Participant flow</head><p>1) In Holm-Bentzen 1987, of the 43 patients in protocol A, 39 completed the study (19 received sodium pentosan polysulfate and 20 received placebo). 4 patients did not complete the protocol A: 2 stopped the medication because of headache, nausea, and dizziness after 1 month and 5 days respectively, 1 was included by mistake and 1 refused to participate. Of the 72 patients in protocol B, 66 completed the study (33 received sodium pentosan polysulfate and 33 received placebo). 6 patients did not complete protocol B: 1 stopped the medication because of a skin rash after 2 weeks, 1 stopped because aggravation of bladder symptoms, 2 refused to participate, 1 was included by mistake and 1 was not followed.</p><p>2) In Parsons and Mulholland 1987, of 75 patients randomized into the study, 4 withdrew before they received medication, 9 failed to return to complete the study. Not all patients completed evaluation sheets properly, such that there was no-post-treatment report on urgency in 2 and on frequency in 7.</p><p>62 patients completed the study.</p><p>3) In Mulholland et al 1990, 110 patients with documented IC with a duration of one year or more enrolled in the study. Of these, 56 patients were treated with placebo, and 54 were treated with PPS.</p><p>Twelve patients (3 treated with PPS and 9 treated with placebo) failed to complete the 3 month study.</p><p>Of these 12, 8 were in the group of patients classified as having severe disease, 1 (3%) receiving PPS and 7 (21%) receiving placebo. Most of these patients were lost to follow-up and it is likely that lack of efficacy was responsible for the patients dropping out. The difference in the drop-out rate between the treatment groups in these patients with severe disease was statistically significant (p = 0.05). The treatment was discontinued by 1 patient in the PPS group and 2 in the placebo group due to adverse reactions.</p><p>Of the patients who completed the three-month double-blind period, 44% were continuing therapy with PPS one and a half years after the start of the study. These patients had been on therapy for periods ranging from six months to one and a half years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4)</head><p>In Parsons et al 1993, a total of 148 patients was enrolled in the study, 74 in each treatment group.</p><p>A total of 18 patients, 9 in each treatment group failed to complete the 3 month study. Of these patients, 3 in the pentosan polysulfate group and 5 in the placebo group dropped out because of adverse experiences and the remainder were lost to follow-up. It is likely that lack of efficacy was responsible for these latter dropouts. Only 3 patients in the pentosan polysulfate group and 5 in the placebo group discontinued treatment due to adverse reactions. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) In</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recruitment</head><p>All but one Nickel et al. <ref type="formula">(2015)</ref> of the 6 pivotal studies were conducted more than 10 years ago. 15/121 patients (12%) were randomized before this amendment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conduct of the studies</head><p>The study by Nickel et al. <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref> was terminated earlier despite numerous efforts to promote recruitment. A higher than expected response rate noted in a blinded analysis of study data in 2009 (44% vs the 25% response rate used in the sample size calculation) combined with the slow enrolment led to the interim analysis of study data by individuals uninvolved in study performance. These results prompted early termination of the study. Futility assessment revealed that continuing the study until its planned sample size may have taken up to additional 5 years, and would not have increased significantly the chance of a successful trial.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Baseline data</head><p>A total of 413 patients were exposed in the reported pivotal studies to PPS in the recommended dose of 300 mg per day (or a very comparable dose of 400 mg per day), the majority of these patients were Caucasian, female and the average age was above 40 years:</p><p>1) The study reported by Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 was conducted in 7 centers in Denmark and in the UK. Nineteen patients were exposed to PPS and 20 patients received placebo in protocol A while in protocol B, 33 patients were enrolled in each group. In protocol A, all patients were female and the median age was 63 years (range 34 to 80 years). The median duration of the disease was 7 years with a range of 1 to 50 years. In protocol B, 61 women and 5 men were included; the median age was 51 years (range 29 to 78 years). The median duration of the disease was 6 years with a range of 1 to 51 years.</p><p>In both protocols, patients were randomized after fulfilling the inclusion criteria and pre-trial investigations. All patients studied had had clinical/or cystoscopic evidence of painful bladder disease for at least 1 year and repeated negative urine cultures. The interval from cystoscopy to randomization varied but it was not allowed to exceed 4 months. The pre-trial symptom score values was evaluated from the day the patient began medication by the symptom scale.</p><p>Besides, the mast cells in the detrusor muscle were counted in 2 separate biopsies from each patient by the same observer.</p><p>In protocol A, the fulfilment of a pathological anatomical criterion for IC was necessary (&gt; 28 mast cells per mm² in the detrusor muscle in a bladder biopsy).</p><p>In protocol B, no definite pathological anatomical criteria were obtained but all patients had mast cell counts &lt; 28/mm².</p><p>The majority of patients have petechial bleeding at baseline (15/19 in protocol A and 24/33 in protocol B), but a relevant (39%) proportion had no petechial bleeding at baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) No clear information is provided on the patient demographics of the study reported by Parsons and</head><p>Mulholland, 1987, which was conducted in the US in 2 medical centers. Based on the results, 62 patients were exposed to PPS in this study with 10% male and 90% female patients.</p><p>Patients were eligible have at least one year of symptoms, consisting of urgency, frequency, nocturia and/or pain, negative urine cultures, a cystoscopic examination that showed an ulcer or petechial hemorrhage (after bladder distension) and negative cytology studies. Ulcers were present in 28% of the patients at baseline and pain in 75%. There were no abnormal serum tests, including prothrombine time, partial thromboplastin time, lactic dehydrogenase, serum glutamic oxaloacetic and pyruvic transaminases, haematocrit or white blood count. Micturitional profiles were obtained in some patients but not in all. These profiles were done before the study and at each visit and consisted of a 3-day recording of each voided volume from which the average voided volume of daily voids could be determined.  It should be noted that the study design was a double-blind placebo-controlled. The patients were randomized to drug or placebo groups by the pharmacy to begin therapy (treatment A). Therapy was begun with 100 mg pentosane polysulfate (or a look-alike placebo) 3 times daily or 200 mg twice daily, depending on which institution they attended. At the end of 3 months, if the patient failed to respond to therapy, cross-over to treatment B was begun (from drug to placebo or vice versa). If the patient responded to treatment A, he or she returned in 3 more months and if there still was a positive response cross-over to treatment B was instituted. To complete the study, the patient had to fail arms A and B, or to have 2 successive visits (6 months) with a positive response.</p><p>Patients were categorized in terms of the severity of their disease. Patients with a moderate degree of disease were defined as having anesthetic bladder capacity over 400 ml, 18 or fewer voids per day, and an average voided volume of 75 ml or more. Patients were considered to have a severe degree of disease if they had bladder capacity under anesthesia of less 400 ml, or more than 18 voids per day, or an average voided volume of less than 75 ml. A patient with any one of these three criteria was included in the severe group. Anesthesic bladder capacity was measured under 80 cm of water pressure held for one minute in all patients under general or spinal anesthesia (see    The majority of patients were Caucasian, female and the average age was above 40 years. Although, 5/6 pivotal studies were conducted in the US, the majority of the patients enrolled were Caucasians and are representative for the EU population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcomes and estimation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1) Primary efficacy analysis</head><p>Holm-Bentzen et al. <ref type="bibr">(1987)</ref>: no clinically significant difference between PPS and placebo was found for the median pre-trial and post-trial values for the total symptom score in protocols A and B.</p><p>For protocol A the decrease was 0.625 in score values in both groups, while for protocol B the decrease was 0.50. The decreases in total symptom score compared to baseline were statistically significant in both protocols. A clinically significant improvement was pre-defined as a decrease of at least 1.00 in the mean total symptom score per patient. A responder analysis evaluating the number of patients experiencing clinically significant improvement revealed a trend for higher responder rates under treatment with PPS compared to placebo (6 vs. 4 responders in protocol A and 9 vs. 7 responders in protocol B). Authors concluded that PPS was not superior over placebo in the treatment of painful bladder disease. <ref type="formula">(1987)</ref>: Responder analysis (number of patients experiencing at least 50% improvement per symptom) on the four symptoms evaluated (pain, urgency, frequency and nocturia).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parsons and Mulholland</head><p>Evaluation of all available patient data after cross-over showed that PPS was statistically significantly (p&lt;0.05) more effective than placebo in reaching improvement of all subjective symptoms (pain, urgency, frequency and nocturia). Voided volume showed a tendency towards significant increase (p = 0.06).</p><p>In this study there was no overall evaluation of the symptoms. Patients who responded to therapy showed improvement at 5 to 10 weeks and continued to improve during several months. Remission of disease tended to be long-term. Of 25 individuals treated for more than 18 months (in an open-label once they completed the study) only one broke through therapy. When the drug was terminated the disease reappeared within 3 to 12 weeks in 80 percent of these patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mulholland et al. (1990):</head><p>In this three month study 28% of patients treated evaluated themselves at the end of the treatment period as more than slightly improved relative to baseline; compared to 13% of the patients treated with placebo (p=0.04). and <ref type="formula">(2)</ref> on the commercial availability of PPS, which lead to slow recruitment into the study and to early termination; it might have resulted into a different population of patients who agreed to participate, including those who were not PPS naïve and who were non-responders to previous PPS therapy or potential non-responders based on disease phenotype. Regarding the other efficacy endpoints (frequency, nocturia, pain, dysuria, maximal bladder capacity during anaesthesia, petechial bleeding, first sensation and bladder capacity, mast cell/mm ² in the biopsies in protocol B, again no significant difference was found between the PPS and placebo groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parsons</head><p>However, for protocol A, there was a statically significant increase in bladder capacity (from 260 to 475 ml) in the patients treated with PPS compared to placebo (p&lt; 0.05). The bladder capacity in the placebo remained constant. For protocol A, there was a statistically significant decrease in the mast cell count during the trial (p&lt; 0.01).</p><p>2) In Parsons and Mulholland 1987, the micturitional profiles' results are reported in table 21.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 18 Average number of daily voids and bladder volumes determined by micturitional profiles</head><p>The average voided volumes were significantly improved on drug therapy (p = 0.009) but not on placebo. The average number of voids per day was unchanged after drug or placebo therapy. The micturitional profiles showed significant improvement in average voided volumes but not in average daily voiding episodes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) In Mulholland et al 1990, in terms of reduced pain, 27% pf the PPS patients evaluated</head><p>themselves as improved compared with 14% of the placebo patients (p =0.08). This was confirmed by the pain scale data where 46% of the PPS patients and 29% of the placebo patients recorded a decrease in pain of 1 or more (p= 0.07). The mean reduction in pain from baseline as measured by the pain scale was 0.5 for the PPS-treated patients compared with 0.2 for the placebo patients at three months. This difference between the treatment groups was not significantly but the difference from baseline was significantly different from zero (p = 0.05) for the PPS-treated group but not for the placebo-treated group. The later held true with p = 0.01 to 0.05 for the end of the months 1 and 2 as well.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 19 Efficacy data (% of patients improved in terms of pain, urgency) and overall improvement</head><p>At the three-month self-evaluation, 22% of the PPS patients and 11% of the placebo patients expressed an improvement in pressure to urinate (p = 0.08). This was not confirmed by the urgency scale data which revealed a slight margin of 39% to 46% in favour of placebo.</p><p>There was a mean increase in volume per void of 9.8 ml for the PPS-treated patients, and 7.6 ml per void for placebo patients. Among the PPS patients, 30% had an increase of 20ml or more compared with 20% of the placebo patients. The PPS group had a mean increase in total daytime volume of urine at the endpoint of 60 ml compared with a mean decrease of 20 ml for the placebo group. These differences were not statistically significant.</p><p>The changes from baseline at the endpoint in the remaining parameters studied were not different between treatments. There were voids per day (-1 for both treatments), percent of patients having 3 less voids per day (32% PPS, 24% placebo), and nocturia (-0.8 PPS, -0.5 placebo). There was a mean increase in volume per void of 20.4 ml for the PPS treated patients and a decrease of 2.1 ml per void for placebo treated patients (not significant). Among the PPS group, 40% had an increase of 20 ml or more compared with 24% of the placebo group (p = 0.02). None of the remaining voiding profile data pertaining to frequency or nocturia revealed any significant differences between the treatment groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) In</head><p>With respect to improved quality of life, the difference between the treatment groups was not statistically significant for improvement in sleep but approached significance for sexual intercourse (p = 0.06). At baseline there was a statistically significant difference (p=0.0037) among groups in voiding frequency with lower frequencies in the combination therapy. No further differences between the groups with regard to baseline characteristics were reported.</p><p>Overall, there were no statistically significant differences between the main treatments in symptom changes over time for any of the secondary endpoints.</p><p>An overview of the efficacy results generated is presented in the following table. Defined secondary efficacy endpoints of the study were:</p><p>-A responder analysis based on a 4-point reduction in the ICSI total score -A responder analysis based on a 50% or greater decrease on the PORIS pain, urgency and overall change in condition scores.</p><p>-A responder analysis counting those patients who indicated an at least 6 (moderately improved) or 7 (markedly improved) status on the GRA score.</p><p>Moreover, ICSI total score, pain intensity, patient reported response to GRA question 1 and urinary frequency change from baseline were evaluated as secondary endpoints.</p><p>There was no statistically significant difference between groups for any secondary endpoints.</p><p>An overview of all efficacy results is presented in the following table 25. The applicant substantiated the efficacy of PPS in applied indication presenting the main results on 6 pivotal studies (see <ref type="table">Table below</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of main studies</head><p>The following tables summarise the efficacy results from the main studies supporting the present application. These summaries should be read in conjunction with the discussion on clinical efficacy as well as the benefit risk assessment (see later sections). It should be noted that the mean reduction in pain from baseline as measured by the pain scale was significantly different from zero (p = 0.05) for the PPS-treated group but not for the placebo-treated group. The latter held true with p = 0.01 to 0.05 for the end of months 1 and 2 as well. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Efficacy for pivotal trials</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parsons</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis performed across trials (pooled analyses and meta-analysis)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary meta-analysis conducted by the applicant</head><p>The objective of this meta-analysis was to evaluate the efficacy of PPS for the treatment of interstitial cystitis (IC) versus placebo by combining the results of available placebo controlled studies.</p><p>Overall, based on the Applicant, all six studies were sufficient comparable to be included into the meta- Sensitivity analyses consisted in primary (GRA) and secondary endpoints (pain and urgency) analysis carried out in populations with different size: "ITT population" and "As-reported population" (subjects taken into account in publications), including all studies or only part of them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 24 Primary meta-analysis, ITT, global response assessment</head><p>There is no indication of heterogeneity in standard measures:</p><p>Q-value = 4.019 &lt; 5 (=expected value under homogeneity), p=0.547, I²=0. Despite I²=0, the results of the Nickel and Holm-Bentzen studies may deviate in reality to some degree from the other studies, but this is not discovered because of the high homogeneity of the results of the other 4 studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 25 Primary meta-analysis, as reported, global response assessment</head><p>There is no indication of heterogeneity in standard measures: Q-value = 3.518, p=0.621, I²=0. Benefit difference is defined as the estimated difference in responder rates of treatment groups PPS minus placebo within each study and overall.</p><p>Different results between the two approaches, ITT and as reported in the publication exist in the two studies from 1987 only, because the other 4 studies were already reported according to the ITT principle in their study publications.</p><p>Despite the heterogeneous results of the six studies, the estimated benefit differences in overall improvement are 12.4% both for the ITT approach and the as reported approach; the related pvalues are p&lt;0.001. The lower limits of the 95%-confidence intervals are 6.4% and 6.3% and thus both are &gt; 5.0% indicating a relevant superiority over placebo.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Co-primary meta-analysis conducted by the applicant</head><p>In order to reflect the prioritisation of efficacy endpoints as intended by the sponsors of the pivotal studies, the applicant also conducted a co-primary meta-analysis, evaluating the responder rates based on the pre-defined primary endpoints per study.</p><p>The co-primary meta-analysis based on the ITT population estimated a difference in the responder rates of 11.9% (p&lt;0.001) (95% IC: 5.8%-18%) between PPS and placebo-treatment. A very small, non-significant heterogeneity was detected between the studies (Q=5.098, p=0.404, I²=1.92%).</p><p>When evaluating the "as reported" results instead of the results in the ITT population in the co-primary meta-analysis, the difference in responder rates was practically equal (11.9%) (p&lt;0.001) without any indication of heterogeneity (Q=4.600, p=0.467, I²=0).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sensitivity-analysis conducted by the applicant</head><p>Beyond the main meta-analyses (primary and co-primary), two additional groups of comparative meta-analyses were designed and conducted based on the following endpoints:</p><p>-Response in individual symptoms, -Mean change in individual and overall symptom scores.</p><p>The patients in the studies reported by <ref type="bibr">Parsons and Mulholland, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Sant et al., 2003</ref> all fulfilled the NIDDK criteria for Interstitial Cystitis and met the ESSIC categories 2X or 3C. Accordingly, the patient population in those studies represent a more homogeneous group than the patients enrolled by <ref type="bibr">Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Nickel et al, 2015</ref>.</p><p>Therefore, a sensitivity analysis was conducted including only the 4 studies enrolling this more homogeneous patient population expecting a more precise estimation of the treatment effect.</p><p>The higher degree of homogeneity of this sensitivity meta-analysis is reflected by a very small Q value of Q=0.470 far away from its expected value of 4-1 = 3. The effect size for this homogeneous patient population was greater than the effect size seen in the primary and co-primary meta-analysis and showed a statistically significant difference of PPS over placebo (p&lt;0.001) with an estimated difference in responder rates of 17.0% with a 95% IC of [9.3%-24.7%]. As in the ITT analysis above and as expected, there is no indication of heterogeneity between the study results: Q = 0.471, p = 0.925, I² = 0.</p><p>The estimated combined benefit difference is 16.8% with a 95%-confidence interval of [8.9%, 24.8%].</p><p>As the primary efficacy endpoints in the four studies included in the sensitivity analysis are patientreported global response assessments, the sensitivity analysis applies for the primary as well as for the co-primary meta-analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The Applicant provided an additional meta-analysis to support the efficacy of PPS in IC.</head><p>To support the clinical relevance of the benefit differences calculated in the pivotal studies, the Applicant provided a further meta-analysis combining the responder rates of the different endpoints separately. In this meta-analysis, only GRA, pain and urgency evaluation were performed. The results of this meta-analysis are provided below separately for all six pivotal studies and for the four pivotal studies which used a traditional diagnostic approach.</p><p>For all six pivotal studies, the results for PPS are around 33% and 20% for placebo with an overlap in IC 95% for pain.</p><p>In the meta-analysis including only the 4 pivotal studies with traditional diagnostic approach, the results for PPS are around 31% and 15 % for placebo with no overlap in IC 95%. Based on the Applicant, the high placebo response rates of 15-20% were expected in a disease like IC as condition like depression, functional disorders and pain are known to be associated with high placebo-rates in randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies. where this smaller difference is still statistically significant (p=0.007). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supportive meta-analysis conducted by the applicant evaluating the main symptoms of IC</head><p>In order to provide more objective information on the efficacy of PPS, the pivotal clinical studies were also evaluated with regard to the information provided on the main symptoms pain and urgency.</p><p>Effects on symptom scores for pain and urgency are reported in the publications from Parsons and <ref type="bibr">Mulholland, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Nickel et al., 2015</ref> Imputation of results for the studies <ref type="bibr">Sant et al., 2003 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987</ref> lead to a benefit difference of 12.3% for the ITT (IC 95% [0.049-0.198], p = 0.001]) and "as reported" (IC 95%</p><p>[0.044-0.203], p = 0.002]) approach for pain and 10.3% (ITT approach)(IC 95%[0.044-0.162], p = 0.001) or 10.3% (as reported approach) (IC 95% [0.04-0.0165], p = 0.001) for urgency.</p><p>The sensitivity analyses including only the four studies (without Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 and Nickel et al 2015) with a better defined patient population revealed a benefit difference of 17.6% for pain (IC 95% [0.1-0.251], p = 0) and 13.0% for urgency (IC 95% [0.057-0.202], p = 0).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supportive studies</head><p>Nine supportive studies were provided by the applicant, most Among these 9 studies, 2 long-term studies "Hanno et al 1997"study in 2809 patients from 1986 to 1996 and "Jepsen et al 1998" study in 97 patients from 1987 to 1995, showed that improvement increased with duration of treatment in patients treated with PPS (100 mgX3/ day). However, it should be noted that PPS could be curative for some patients and that patients receiving treatment for a duration &gt; 90 months showed no further improvement or worsening in symptom values ("tachyphylaxis").</p><p>One randomized, double-blind dose-ranging study was performed by Nickel et al 2005 to evaluate three different doses of PPS (100 mg x3/ day, 200 mg x3/ day, 300 mg x3/day) for 32 weeks in 380 patients. No statistical difference was found among the 3 doses regarding ICSI scores and PORIS scores. Therefore, response to treatment was not dose-dependent. However, when patients were categorized by the severity of their symptoms at baseline according to the ICSI, the response in those with mild and moderate symptoms were not dose dependent but in patients with severe symptoms at baseline, a better response to the 600 mg dose was observed (p = 0.028).</p><p>Another An open-label study was performed to evaluate the safety and efficacy of subcutaneous low dose heparin application on top of oral PPS application in 41 patients <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">(Van Ophoven et al 2005)</ref>. The results show that the subgroup of patients with initially less favourable PPS treatment outcome (minor group) predominantly benefited from additional administration of subcutaneous heparin due mainly to the significant reduction of pain intensity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.3.">Discussion on clinical efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Design and conduct of clinical studies</head><p>All the six pivotal studies were placebo controlled double-blind, multicentre studies, of which the objectives were to assess the superiority of PPS versus placebo (except Sant et al 2003 which evaluated the superiority of PPS versus placebo and hydroxyzine). All but one of 6 pivotal studies conducted more than 10 years ago <ref type="bibr">(except and Nickel et al. (2015)</ref> study) were small studies and used old methodological standard. The Nickel study was a true confirmatory trial with a large sample size (targeted 645 subjects, actual 368 and 240 retained in the meta-analysis).</p><p>The conduct of the pivotal studies met recruitment difficulties especially in the more recent studies <ref type="bibr">(Sant et al 2003 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Nickel et al 2015)</ref>. Indeed, these latter studies were performed in USA and Canada when PPS was already commercially available which lead to recruitment of non-naïve PPS patients or patients with a less severe disease (milder symptoms) than in the 4 earlier studies. In the Nickel et al study, there were no cut-off criteria for pain or urgency, no determination of flare status, no entry criterion based on cystoscopy findings and no exclusion for commonly associated conditions such as irritable bowel disease, depression or pelvic floor dysfunction disease. Moreover, this study was stopped for futility as continuing the study until its planned sample size would not have significantly increased the chance of a successful trial.</p><p>On the other hand it seems that the 3 earlier studies <ref type="formula">(</ref> (2X to 3C) disease as BPS is a very broad symptom complex including also patient with milder severity than IC. "Pain" was considered as the key main symptom of the interstitial cystitis.</p><p>Considering the fact that no outcome measure is currently standardized the patient's global assessment or any impact of the IC disease are considered as the most relevant outcome measures.</p><p>According to the guidelines on chronic pelvic pain (Engeler 2015), symptom scores, evaluated with the O'Leary-Sant Symptom Index also known as the Interstitial Cystitis Symptom Index (ICSI), may help to assess the patient and act as outcome measures. However, this is a subjective assessment, other more objective criteria could have been taken into consideration such as increase of working or waking hours, return to work or school or increase of physical or sexual activities.</p><p>Given the heterogeneous population of the six pivotal studies, the applicant proposed to restrict the indication to patients diagnosed with IC using the traditional approach including cystoscopy with or Indeed, several associations such as International Society for the Study of bladder painful symptom (ESSIC), American urology association (AUA), and European association of Urology (EAU) recommend to use preferentially "bladder pain syndrome" or "painful bladder syndrome" (PBS) instead of interstitial cystitis (IC). Therefore the CHMP considered that the indication should refer to BPS with glomerulations / Hunner's lesions to outline the population in which efficacy was significantly demonstrated in the pivotal trials (formerly described as IC).</p><p>Regarding the study outcomes/endpoints, the key study endpoints/outcomes in all 6 pivotal studies were patient-reported outcomes via patient responder analysis. This might be considered as a reasonable approach for this type of disease. The responder definitions based on 6-point or 7-point GRA assessment used for primary efficacy evaluation in three pivotal studies are quite identical <ref type="bibr">(Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">, Sant et al., 2003</ref> and the responder definition based on ICSI scores used for primary efficacy evaluation in the latest study <ref type="bibr">(Nickel et al., 2015)</ref>  If only the four pivotal studies are considered which enrolled a homogeneous and clear defined patient population representative for the targeted patient population <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland, 1987, Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">, Sant et al., 2003</ref>, the responder analysis are deemed comparable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy data and additional analyses</head><p></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results on primary endpoints</head><p>The six pivotal randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies were identified as pivotal database to evaluate the efficacy and safety of PPS. Only 3 of them met the primary endpoints "overall global improvement" (assessed by a self-evaluation confirmed by an investigator's evaluation) in comparison to placebo <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993)</ref>.</p><p>Indeed, the first study <ref type="bibr">(Holm-Bentzen 1987)</ref> failed to detect a statistically significant difference in the mean total symptom score change, but showed a trend of higher responder rates (patients experiencing a clinically relevant improvement of at least 1.00 in the mean total symptom score) after four months of treatment with PPS compared to placebo. Likewise, the study reported by Sant et al 2003 did not show a significant benefit versus non-PPS treatment (placebo and hydroxyzine), only a trend. The last study Nickel et al 2015, which was performed by the current clinical standards and an up-to-date methodology failed to show any benefit in comparison to placebo and no statistically difference was reached between the 300 mg of PPS per day in comparison to 100 mg of PPS per day.</p><p>These latter two studies were performed in countries where PPS was already available which lead to recruitment issues and to inclusion of non PPS naïve patients or non-responders to previous PPS therapy or patients with milder symptoms as patients with severe symptoms could have a direct access to the treatment.</p><p>The beneficial effect of PPS in interstitial cystitis (IC) was only shown in the 3 pivotal studies which used traditional diagnostic approach <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland, 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993)</ref>  Given the severe limitations of the Nickel et al study, it is agreed that its results could not be taken into account for meta-analysis. In addition, the results of Holm-Bentzen study are difficult to interpret as the GRA was not used as primary endpoint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results of the meta-analysis</head><p>Several meta-analysis were performed by the applicant -primary endpoints meta-analysis (based on GRA improvement, both for ITT and non-ITT principles), sensitivity analysis (based on more homogenous patient population of four studies) and co-primary meta-analysis (evaluating the responder rates based on the pre-defined primary endpoints per study). Statistical methods for metaanalysis were used properly. However, the presentation was not fully consistent. Consideration of missing results as failures is adequate. In general, statistical methods used for meta-analysis were appropriate. The applicant provided the number of patients and the responder rates in the forest plot.</p><p>These data confirm that responder rates were adequately estimated in ITT populations as defined in the meta-analysis without any loss of patients. Responses for pooled PPS and pooled placebo groups are missing but it seems that this information is available in the material provided for the additional meta-analysis conducted by the Applicant. The applicant provided the response levels for pooled PPS and pooled placebo in the meta-analysis.</p><p>In the primary meta-analysis conducted by the applicant, the estimated benefit differences in overall improvement are 12.4% both for the ITT approach and the as reported approach. This primary metaanalysis included all 6 studies performed between 1987 and 2015. The clinical benefit estimate increased to 17% in the sensitivity analysis when excluding the 2 pivotal studies (Holm-Bentzen and  <ref type="figure">(p=0.007)</ref>.</p><p>The CHMP took into consideration the unmet medical need for pharmacotherapy in this disease which can be invalidating in its severe forms and the ad hoc expert group confirmed that also small improvement could be considered as a clinical relevant benefit. Furthermore given the severe limitations of the Nickel et al study (patients with milder IC entering during a symptom flare, regression to the mean, introduction (inadvertent or not) of conservative therapy, which accentuated the benefits of placebo, and failure of clinical sites to keep patients in the trial), CHMP considered that its results should not be taken into account in the meta-analysis.</p><p>Overall, the meta-analysis which combined the response rates of the four pivotal studies with patients meeting the ESSIC classification 2X to 3C which showed a benefit difference of 17% (PPS versus placebo), was taken into consideration to demonstrate the efficacy of PPS in the approved indication.</p><p></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key secondary endpoints</head><p>The secondary endpoints were only considered supportive but pain and urgency were considered as the key main symptoms.</p><p>Overall, based on the results of 3 pivotal studies <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mulholland et al 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">and Parsons et al 1993</ref> an effect on pain (~44 vs 15 to 18%), urgency (~50 vs ~20%) and frequency (~60 vs 40%) but not on alleviating nocturia was shown. This was not the case in <ref type="bibr">Sant et al., 2003</ref> study and the studies using less specific IC definitions (IC/BPS) <ref type="bibr">(Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Nickel et al., 2015 studies)</ref>.</p><p>The supportive meta-analysis conducted by the applicant mainly used the reported effect size on the symptoms pain and urgency and calculated the effects sizes on the ITT population as main outcome.</p><p>Regarding these symptoms, this supportive meta-analysis reached statistically significant benefit differences in line with the primary meta-analysis evaluating the global response assessment (GRA) whatever the approach (ITT or as reported or sensitivity analysis).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose finding</head><p>The majority of patients in the pivotal studies as well as in the supportive studies were treated with the established dose of 3x100 mg PPS per day and few patients received a very comparable dose of 2x200 mg PPS per day. The treatment duration was ranging from 3 months to 6 months.</p><p>Two dose-ranging studies evaluated a potential dose-response relationship <ref type="bibr">(Nickel et al., 2005</ref><ref type="bibr">, Nickel et al., 2015</ref> and came to the conclusion that neither a reduction of the dose to one third (1x100 mg PPS per day) nor a duplication or triplication of the dose (3x200 mg or 3x300 mg PPS per day) leads to statistically significant differences in the efficacy. It is agreed by the CHMP that the dose regimen should be 100 mgx3/ day as applied in the pivotal trials. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional expert consultation</head><p>At day 180 of the procedure the efficacy of elmiron was considered not being sufficiently demonstrated despite its well established use and international and European guidelines recommending pentosane polysulfate sodium for the treatment of IC for more than 10 years.</p><p>Therefore the CHMP decided to consult clinical experts in the disease adopting the following questions (Responses given by the ad hoc expert group are also outlined below): There was no consensus about the use of PPS in the patient population to be treated in clinical practice. Some experts would, depending on the patients risk profile, consider PPS due to its benign safety profile as a treatment option before invasive diagnostics. Other experts would use the drug due to the low level of evidence on efficacy and BPS being a diagnosis of exclusion only after full diagnostic workup to exclude confusable diseases and preferably in combination therapy.</p><p>The experts broadly agreed that study results from a population of BPS 2-3, a population difficult to treat, would be generalizable to patients suffering from other BPS categories.</p><p>There was broad agreement that more contemporary data on efficacy would be welcome to better define the use of the drug in today's clinical medicine.</p><p>3) Given the response rates in the subgroup "classical IC" in the Nickel et al study, do you consider the benefit difference 17% response rate (PPS versus placebo) based on a metaanalysis which combined the responses rates from the four pivotal studies with patients with "classical IC") as clinically relevant?</p><p>The experts considered that any response rate superior to placebo could be clinically relevant considering that there is no drug treatment authorized in this condition. The methodological weakness of the older trials was perceived as caveat for reliable interpretation of the efficacy of the product and the meta-analyses were considered of limited value due to different trial designs throughout publications. With regards to the Nickel study it was noted that many patients discontinued the trial. A reason for this could be the need for more effective pain treatment. The patient representatives emphasized that more robust data generation and definition of the patient population which benefits most from the drug would be welcome to spare the patient to try unsuccessful treatments but also the burden of invasive diagnostics was acknowledged. Also the high fluctuation and subjectivity of symptoms was acknowledged by the experts as a caveat for designing a trial in this condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) If you find the available data supportive, which type of IC patients, taking into</head><p>consideration the ICSI score or other criteria, would benefit from treatment with PPS?</p><p>In Europe PPS is often used off label and on a named patient basis. Whereas the French and the Belgian experts tended to prescribe PPS without full invasive diagnostic workup depending on the patients profile, experts from UK and Germany would use it after full exclusion of confusable diseases and mostly in combination therapy. A re-evaluation of the patient's response after 6 months of treatment would allow minimizing the risk of exposing patients who do not respond in the long term.</p><p>In summary the data of the pivotal studies suggest to use PPS in patients suffering from BPS with verified cystoscopic findings including hydrodistention and some experts emphasized that cystoscopy including hydrodistension is needed to display all glomerulations / Hunner's lesions and, at symptom persistence sooner or later cystoscopy would need to be done to finalize the diagnostic workup for this indication. Also hydrodistension (usually under general anesthesia) could induce symptom amelioration in some patients.</p><p>However experts also stressed the high burden of this workup for both the patient and the healthcare system cystoscopy being extremely painful and sometimes not useful in symptomatic patients. Cystoscopic findings for a decision to initiate PPS were considered of limited value in particular in symptomatic patients with low risk of important confusable diseases, such as bladder stones and cancer (e.g. in young women).</p><p>In particular the experts emphasized that there is no reason to believe that PPS is not effective in patients without glomerulations / Hunner's lesions as these morphological changes do not correlate with symptom severity. A restriction of the indication would also hardly be respected by clinicians considering the much broader well-established use of the product. Experts therefore were not in agreement to refer to these changes within a BPS indication. An indication statement adapted to clinical practice would rather refer to the severity of the condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Please discuss the most appropriate name of the condition and exactly which patients would be included in this condition. In particular the use of the terms bladder pain syndrome and interstitial cystitis should be explained as this will assist the COMP in understanding how the condition is currently defined by the medical profession.</head><p>In line with the answer to CHMP question 1, the expert group considered the term interstitial cystitis (IC) to be outdated and according to today's classification and medical practice the condition should be referred to as BPS. The experts concluded that IC correlates to a patient population with BPS type 2 -3 and in particular 3C (characterised by Hunner's lesions); these BPS subtypes are, according to ESSIC classification to be verified by cystoscopy including hydrodistension. IC represents therefore a subcategory of the condition BPS.</p><p>6) The prevalence in the literature is reported to have a range between 0.6% and 3% of the population when the term bladder pain syndrome is used. This is a very broad range, and is at variance with the prevalence proposed by the applicant, who is using the strict definition of interstitial cystitis and concludes on a number of 1.8 in 10,000 in Europe. The COMP would like to ask the expert group to consider which prevalence value is closer to the real situation in Europe for the condition as defined in question 1.</p><p>The experts agreed that if BPS is used the prevalence would be higher than what has been suggested by the sponsor. There were some concerns about the publications overestimating the incidence of BPS as they were based on questionnaires which only recorded the symptoms over one month. The experts were of the opinion that patients with BPS type 2 and 3 are not common. This was supported by a recent publication from 2015 <ref type="bibr">(T.Bschleipfer et al. Interstitielle Zystitis/Blasenschmerzsyndrom, Urologische Infektiologie, 2015, 265-276)</ref> which considered that based on current literature the prevalence of BPS is 52-500 / 100.000 in women and 8-41 / 100.000 in men. Considering that about 10% of BPS patients have cystoscopic findings IC as defined as BPS type 2 and could still be under the threshold of 5 in 10,000.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.4.">Conclusions on the clinical efficacy</head><p>The applicant provided six pivotal studies to support this application. Only 3 pivotal randomized double-blind multicentre placebo controlled studies <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mulholland et al 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">and Parsons et al 1993</ref> among the 6 pivotal studies met their primary endpoint "GRA" and some secondary endpoints such as pain.</p><p>Based on the primary meta-analysis conducted by the applicant including the six pivotal studies, the estimated benefit differences reached about 13% (ITT and as reported). This benefit difference (PPS Furthermore according to the meta-analysis of the four pivotal studies performed in patients meeting the ESSIC classification 2X to 3C the pooled response rate under PPS treatment was 2-fold higher than the pooled response rate under placebo ("GRA" primary endpoint and also pain and urgency)and efficacy of PPS was considered sufficiently demonstrated in this population.</p><p>The term BPS rather than interstitial cystitis (IC) was put forward by the International Society for the Study of BPS (ESSIC) and is currently used in the guidelines and by the experts. Therefore the applicant agreed to amend the applied therapeutic indication to:</p><p>"Elmiron is indicated for the treatment of bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions in adults with moderate to severe pain, urgency and frequency of micturition (see section 4.4)"</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.">Clinical safety</head><p>The safety of elmiron capsules was evaluated from scientific publications on six pivotal, placebocontrolled clinical studies as well as in supportive active-controlled or uncontrolled studies. No clinical safety studies with elmiron were performed by the applicant, in accordance with Article 10a of Directive 2001/83/EC (well-established medical use).</p><p>Patient exposure 561 patients were exposed to PPS in the six pivotal, placebo-controlled trials <ref type="bibr">(Holm-Bentzen 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons and Mulholland 1987;</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">, Sant 2003</ref><ref type="bibr">and Nickel 2015</ref>. 3407 patients were exposed to PPS in supportive active-controlled or uncontrolled studies <ref type="bibr">(Nickel 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Ophoven 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Davis 2008;</ref><ref type="bibr">Sairanen 2005;</ref><ref type="bibr">Fritjofsson 1987 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Hanno 1997)</ref>. 124 patients were exposed to PPS in two cohort studies <ref type="bibr">(Waters 2000 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Jepsen 1998)</ref>.</p><p>192 patients were exposed to PPS at least 6 months (corresponds to 1152 patient-months) in the (pivotal) clinical trials. Most patients were exposed to 300 mg PPS per day (234 patients), some were exposed to 400 mg PPS per day (52 patients).</p><p>429 female patients and 29 male patients were exposed to PPS in the (pivotal) clinical trials.</p><p>Overall, more than 3,500 patients were exposed to PPS in published clinical studies evaluating the safety and efficacy of PPS for the treatment of IC. In these studies, subjects mainly administered the established oral dose of 3x100 mg PPD per day, but also the threefold dose (3x300 mg PPS per day) was evaluated. The exposure in the studies covered periods of more than 3 years treatment with PPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adverse events</head><p>Holm-Bentzen et al. <ref type="bibr">(1987)</ref> reported that 5 patients receiving active drug complained of peripheral oedema. One patient had a skin rash that probably was related to PPS treatment. The applicant assumed that the same case of skin rash is mentioned twice in this publication. Among the 62 patients, who completed the study reported by Parsons and Mulholland <ref type="formula">(1987)</ref>  only digestive system events, diarrhoea or nausea were reported from more than one patient and occurred more often in the placebo group than in the PPS group.</p><p>Diarrhoea is reported with a frequency of 4.9% in the Nickel study <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref>, 15% in the Waters study <ref type="bibr">(2000)</ref> and in the Nickel study (2005) and 2.7% in the Parsons study. Nausea is reported with a frequency of 9.8% in the Nickel study <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref>, 8% in the Nickel study <ref type="bibr">(2005)</ref>, 2% in the Mulholland study and 3.7% in the Hanno study. Abdominal pain is reported with a frequency of 7% in the Nickel study <ref type="bibr">(2005)</ref>. Dyspepsia is reported with a frequency of 2 to 4% depending on the study.</p><p>Alopecia, cited as reversible, is reported with a frequency of 3.9% in the Hanno study and 5% in the Nickel study <ref type="bibr">(2015)</ref>. Hair-thinning/hair loss is reported with a frequency of 11% in the Waters study. as not related to study medication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Laboratory findings</head><p>No changes in blood and urinary samples were noted during the trial reported by Holm-Bentzen et al. <ref type="bibr">(1987)</ref>. The investigations performed before and after the trial included urine culture, urine cytology, urinary. There were no abnormal serum tests, including prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, lactic dehydrogenase, serum glutamic oxaloacetic and pyruvic transaminases, haematocrit or white blood count reported by <ref type="bibr">Parsons and Mulholland (1987)</ref>. A transient increase in a γ-glutamyltransferase was observed in 4 out of 87 patients without clinical manifestation <ref type="bibr">(Fritjofsson et al., 1987)</ref>. As reported by <ref type="bibr">Mulholland et al. (1990)</ref> there were no differences between the treatment groups in terms of clinically significant changes in any of the laboratory data. One patient in the PPStreated group had SGOT and SGPT values of 118 and 133 at three months compared with 56 and 115 at baseline respectively. There were no clinically relevant differences between the treatment groups for any of the laboratory data and there were no laboratory findings outside the normal range for any of the parameters measured in the study reported by Parsons et al., 1993. 25 months because of increasing SGOT and SGPT, which was verified by re-challenging with PPS. Another patient had increased AST after 5.5 months but stopped taking PPS because of no effect. One patient had increased creatinine levels of 2.2 mg/dl after 10.5 months but discontinued PPS because IC symptoms continued. There were no cases with laboratory measures critically outside the normal limits and related to the trial intervention in the study reported by <ref type="bibr">Davis et al. (2008)</ref>. No clinically meaningful change was noted in clinical laboratory tests, vital signs or physical examination in the study reported by <ref type="bibr">Nickel et al. (2015)</ref>.</p><p>According to the applicant, the laboratory data were not reported quantitatively at all or only qualitatively or as individual cases. controversial as the most informative study <ref type="bibr">(Faaij et al., 1999)</ref>, which used relevant monitoring tests (aPTT, Anti-Xa activity, t-PA activity and fibrin plate lysis) did not detect such effects after oral PPS at very high dosage (1500 mg PPS) in comparison with IV administration. Thus, it is reasonable to conclude that rectal bleeding is a clinically significant AR but does not preclude the need to inform prescribers about clinical importance of the other coagulopathies adverse reactions reported in post marketing even with a low frequency. Therefore, this "class effect" has been mentioned in the SmPC.</p><p>The AE "Coagulation disorders" has been added in section 4.8 of the SmPC to reflect the reporting of laboratory parameters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety in special populations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Children</head><p>No information on paediatric patients is reported in the scientific literature. The disease is nearly not existent in the paediatric population. The medicinal product will be indicated for the treatment of adult patients with Interstitial Cystitis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Elderly</head><p>The Applicant did not perform a safety analysis based on age. The average age of the patients was above 40 years in the literature (from 42.7 to 63 years depending on the study). Patients up to 80 years were included in the clinical trials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pregnant or breast feeding women</head><p>Pregnant or breast-feeding women were excluded from enrolment into the pivotal clinical trials.</p><p>Systemic bioavailability of PPS after oral administration is very limited, accordingly, exposure of a foetus or excretion into milk is very unlikely.</p><p>A study in eight pregnant women who had a planned abortion was conducted to generate data on the </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patients with renal or hepatic impairment</head><p>No specific information on patients with renal impairment is reported in the literature.</p><p>Because there is evidence of hepatic and renal contribution to the elimination of pentosan polysulfate sodium, hepatic or renal impairment may have an impact on the pharmacokinetics of pentosan polysulfate sodium. As stated in the product information patients with relevant hepatic or renal insufficiency should be carefully monitored when treated with pentosan polysulfate sodium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunological events</head><p>In a single case of cerebral sagittal sinus thrombosis after oral administration of PPS (see above), no indication of antibody formation was observed except a modest positive response received in an ELISA-assay for anti-heparin platelet factor 4 antibodies. The relevance and sensitivity of this ELISA test for PPS-induced antibodies is questionable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety related to drug-drug interactions and other interactions</head><p>Evaluable information on interactions is limited to the information provided in the literature. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post marketing experience</head><p>The oral PPS is approved in Canada since 1993, Australia since 1994 and US since 1996. The SmPC has been modified to reflect the AEs listed in Canadian, Australian and US SmPCs, including postmarketing data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.1.">Discussion on clinical safety</head><p>The safety of PPS capsules was evaluated from scientific publications on the six pivotal, placebocontrolled clinical studies as well as in supportive active-controlled or uncontrolled studies.</p><p>Overall, more than 3,500 patients were exposed to PPS in published clinical studies evaluating the safety and efficacy of PPS for the treatment of IC. In these studies, subjects mainly administered the established oral dose of 3x100 mg PPD per day, but also the threefold dose (3x300 mg PPS per day) was evaluated. The exposure in the studies covered periods of more than 3 years treatment with PPS.</p><p>The applicant provided a thorough compilation of the patient exposure for safety analyzing separately placebo-, active-controlled, open studies and compassionate use for patients exposed to PPS in general, to PPS with the proposed dose range and with long-term safety data. The applicant summarized that at least more than 4000 patients were exposed to PPS in studies and ~3800 to the proposed dose range (300 to 400 mg/day). The information submitted on long-term safety is limited (&gt;6 month of therapy, exclusively from uncontrolled studies only).</p><p>No dedicated studies were performed in special populations. Elderly people were included in the pivotal studies. Pregnant or breast-feeding women were excluded from enrolment into the pivotal clinical trials. No specific studies were performed in patients with renal or hepatic impairment as the systemic bioavailability of PPS is very low (&lt; 1%).</p><p>The ratio women/men was 10:1 in the pivotal studies, which is representative of the gender-based prevalence of the IC in the general population. Meanwhile, due to the very low number of male patients enrolled in the clinical trials, the RMP has been updated to add "use in male patient" as missing information in the summary of safety concerns table in order to collect safety data in men in post-marketing.</p><p>However, given the mode of action of PPS in the treatment of IC, the safety profile observed of PPS in the pivotal studies, it is agreed that there is no reason to expect a specific safety profile in men, as an impact on the male reproductive system is not expected. The only gender specific adverse event reported from clinical studies is "strong menstrual bleeding".</p><p>Overall, hair-thinning/hair loss/alopecia and gastro-intestinal disorders (e.g. diarrhoea, abdominal cramping, nausea, and headache) were the most frequently reported adverse reactions with PPS in the Overall, although this relationship between risk of serious coagulopathies and oral PPS is not obvious, the coagulopathy is not excluded and could be plausible considering other bleeding effects observed after the oral PPS administration and in case of co-administration with other medicinal products influencing coagulation. The applicant accepted to include PPS-thrombocytopenia and haemorrhage as important potential risks into the updated RMP and to add a contra-indication in patients who actively bleed in section 4.3 of the SmPC, a warning in 4.4 on patients undergoing invasive procedures and other increased risk of bleeding and an advise in section 4.5 of the SmPC to evaluate for haemorrhagic events in case of concomitant treatment with anticoagulants. Furthermore the AE "Coagulation disorders" has been added in section 4.8 of the SmPC to reflect the reporting of laboratory parameters.</p><p>Several cases of elevated hepatic enzymes (SGOT and SGPT) have been reported. One case of increased creatinine levels has been reported, possibly linked to PPS (creatinine decreased after stopping treatment).</p><p>The AE "Liver function abnormalities" has been added in section 4.8 of the SmPC to reflect the reporting of laboratory parameters which is considered acceptable.</p><p>The applicant did not report immunological events except a case of cerebral sagittal sinus thrombosis, although no dedicated studies are presented. Allergic reactions which are considered as a "class effect"</p><p>were added in the SmPC to inform about this class effect which may not have been observed directly in relation to the product.</p><p>Overall, adverse events led to discontinuation of the PPS treatment in a significant percentage of patients (about 8 to 18 % in the published studies). Lack of efficacy also led to discontinuation in a significant percentage of patients (7 to 56 % depending on the study). AEs leading to discontinuation were reported in up to 13.2% with a maximal incidence of 22.4%. Therefore it was added to 4.2 of the SmPC that response to treatment with pentosan polysulfate sodium should be reassessed every 6 months and that in case no improvement is reached 6 months after treatment initiation, treatment with pentosan polysulfate sodium should be stopped.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6.2.">Conclusions on the clinical safety</head><p>Overall, the safety profile of PPS is not considered of concern. Due to the heparin-like structure of PPS, a weak anticoagulant effect was observed with PPS and patients with risk factors for increased bleeding (undergoing invasive procedures, having underlying coagulopathy or taking anticoagulants) should be carefully evaluated for haemorrhage during the treatment. This risk is adequately addressed in various sections of the SmPC and as important identified risk in the RMP.</p><p>other pathology. The clinical picture is dominated by pain and pollakiuria. Although the pain is usually described as pelvic, it may also involve the perineum, vagina, suprapubically radiating to the groins, rectum, sacrum, scrotum and urethra. It becomes more severe upon bladder filling with relief after urination. The pollakiuria is the consequence of a nearly constant urge to urinate, which increases with bladder filling and is relieved by urination. 90% of the patients are afflicted women in their fifth and sixth decades of life. Symptoms often resemble those of patients with overactive bladder. Up to 50% of patients with symptoms of interstitial cystitis will have spontaneous resolution in time.</p><p>The diagnosis of IC is primarily one of exclusion, using symptoms, examination, urine analysis and urine culture (to rule out a urinary tract infection), cystoscopy with hydrodistension (to rule out bladder cancer, vesical stones, urethral diverticula and intravesical foreign bodies), and biopsy (to exclude other pathologies).</p><p>In the pivotal studies, the population was included with different IC definitions, mixing both broad </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.2.">Available therapies and unmet medical need</head><p>All available treatment options thus far are purely symptomatic. There are no medicinal products approved for the treatment of IC in Europe. Current treatment options include:</p><p>•off-label enteral and parenteral use of medicinal products (analgesics, corticosteroids, anti-allergics, PPS, Hydroxyzine, Amitriptyline, antibiotics, immunosuppressants, Gabapentin, pregabalin, and quercetin)</p><p>•bladder hydro-distension •intravesical application of medicinal products and medical devices (DMSO, PPS…)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•surgery</head><p>Therefor a medical need for approved treatment options in interstitial cystitis / bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions exists given the fact that there are no medicinal products authorised for this condition in Europe.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.3.">Main clinical studies</head><p>The The study objectives were "prospective evaluation of PPS for the treatment of IC". Key study endpoints/outcomes in all 6 pivotal studies were patient-reported outcomes via patient responder analysis which is considered as a reasonable approach for a functional disease.</p><p>The patient population enrolled in the 6 pivotal studies varied between the studies and altogether was enrolling a broader BPS population. The majority of patients were Caucasian, female and the average age was above 40 years. The majority of the patients enrolled are Caucasians and considered representative for the EU population.</p><p>Within the 6 pivotal studies data on two dosage regimens was provided: either 100 mg 3 times a day or 200 mg 2 times a day. The treatment duration was ranging from 3 months to 6 months. The recommended dose is 300 mg/day taken as one 100 mg capsule orally three times daily with assessment of response to treatment every 6 months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Favourable effects</head><p>Among the 6 pivotal studies, 3 studies <ref type="formula">(</ref> In the primary meta-analysis conducted by the applicant including all 6 pivotal studies published between 1987 and 2015, the estimated benefit differences in overall improvement were about 13% with the two approaches (ITT or as reported).</p><p>This benefit difference was mainly driven by the pivotal studies Parsons et al 1993 and Mulholland et al 1990 for the drug approval of Elmiron in the US and by an earlier study <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland 1987)</ref> including patients falling within ESSIC classification 2X to 3C (patients with cystoscopic changes i.e. either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions). A 4 th study enrolling patients falling within ESSIC classification 2X to <ref type="bibr">3C (Sant et al. (2003)</ref>) did not show a statistically significant benefit difference against placebo but a positive trend and was conducted in the US at the time when PPS (as Elmiron) was commercially available for the treatment of IC which lead to enrolment of patients previously treated with PPS. No beneficial effect was demonstrated in studies using less specific IC definition <ref type="bibr">(Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 and</ref><ref type="bibr">Nickel et al., 2015)</ref>. Also the severe limitations of the Nickel et al study (patients with milder disease entering during a symptom flare, regression to the mean, introduction (inadvertent or not) of conservative therapy, which accentuated the benefits of placebo, and failure of clinical sites to keep patients in the trial) are acknowledged by the CHMP. In addition, the results of Holm-Bentzen study are difficult to interpret as the GRA was not used as primary endpoint.</p><p>The estimated benefit differences reached 17% in the sensitivity analysis when excluding the 2 studies which is representative of the targeted patient population <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and</ref><ref type="bibr">Mulholland, 1987, Mulholland et al., 1990;</ref><ref type="bibr">Parsons et al., 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">, Sant et al., 2003</ref> are deemed comparable.</p><p>When considering the supportive meta-analysis on the key secondary symptoms "pain and urgency", the benefit differences reached statistically significance (whatever the approaches ITT or as reported)</p><p>in line with the primary meta-analysis evaluating the GRA.</p><p>It was therefore agreed with the applicant to base the indication on the more homogeneous population of the four pivotal studies including patients with BPS type 2 -3 outlining in 4.1 of the SmPC bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions reflecting the patient population in which clinical efficacy was demonstrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Uncertainties and limitations about favourable effects</head><p>The beneficial effect of PPS was mainly driven by the pivotal studies including patients falling within ESSIC classification 2X to 3C whereas no beneficial effect was demonstrated in studies using less specific IC / BPS inclusion criteria for patients. Also, the mechanism of action of PPS is currently not totally understood and only 1% of the orally administered PPS is absorbed.</p><p>The term "BPS" should be used rather than interstitial cystitis (IC). Indeed, the term BPS was put forward by the International Society for the Study of BPS (ESSIC) and is currently used in the guidelines and by the experts. Whereas a beneficial effect, as outlined by the ad hoc experts, might be generalizable to other BPS types, robust data on this effect are missing. In accordance with the experts view, it was also taken into account by the CHMP that the definition of a target population which benefits most from the drug would avoid to try unsuccessful treatments.</p><p>Given uncertainties about the favourable effects of elmiron in a broader BPS population the approved indication refers therefore to patients diagnosed with bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions using traditional diagnostic approach including cystoscopic examination with or without hydrodistension which corresponds to the population included in the four pivotal studies <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mulholland et al 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">, Parsons et al 1993</ref><ref type="bibr">and Sant et al 2003</ref> in which the efficacy was robustly demonstrated (in three of these studies the primary endpoint reached statistical significance).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.4.">Unfavourable effects</head><p>Hair-thinning/hair loss/alopecia and gastro-intestinal disorders (e.g. diarrhoea, abdominal cramping, and nausea, headache) were the most frequently reported adverse reactions with PPS in the literature. thrombocytopenia and haemorrhage was included as important potential risks into the RMP and a contra-indication in patients who actively bleed.</p><p>Regarding the potential immunological ADRs, the applicant explained that there might be different reasons for immunological ADRs and agrees that in some cases, allergic reactions related to PPS could be the cause (in case of skin rash). Therefore, the applicant included the AEs "rash" and "allergic reactions" into section 4.8 of the SmPC. Overall the safety profile of elmiron is considered not of concern.</p><p>3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Uncertainties and limitations about unfavourable effects</head><p>PK has not been studied in some of the special populations (elderly patients, hepatically or renally impaired patients, paediatric patients, pregnant and breast feeding women) and the lack of this data as well as precautionary statement are reflected in the SmPC.</p><p>The ratio women/men was 10:1 in the pivotal studies, which is representative of the gender-based prevalence of the IC in the general population. Meanwhile, due to the very low number of male patients enrolled in the clinical trials, the RMP had been updated to add "use in male patient" as missing information in the summary of safety concerns table in order to collect safety data in men in post-marketing. As limited information is available on use in patients concomitantly using anticoagulants, undergoing invasive procedures or in patients with increased risk of bleeding, a warning statement was included into the SmPC to evaluate these patients carefully for haemorrhage when taking elmiron. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.6.">Effects</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7.">Benefit-risk assessment and discussion</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7.1.">Importance of favourable and unfavourable effects</head><p>Considering the meta-analysis of the four pivotal studies performed with patients falling within ESSIC BPS classification 2X to 3C showed a benefit difference of 17% (PPS versus placebo) and the pooled response rate under PPS treatment even 2-fold higher than the pooled response rate under placebo ("GRA" primary endpoint and also pain and urgency) and following the ad hoc expert group and in the context of unmet medical need (no drug treatment authorized in this indication) the CHMP considers this response rate as clinically relevant in the target population in which efficacy was significantly demonstrated in the pivotal trials and defined with a bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations of Hunner's lesions and with moderate to severe pain, urgency and frequency of micturition. Also it was essential to define a target population which benefits most from the drug.</p><p>The safety of elmiron is not of particular concern. Due to the heparin-like structure of PPS, a weak anticoagulant effect might be observed with elmiron which could become apparent in patients with risk factors for increased bleeding and in patients who actively bleed. This potential risk is considered appropriatly addressed by routine risk minimisation measures.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.7.2.">Balance of benefits and risks</head><p>Patients diagnosed with bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions using traditional diagnostic approach including cystoscopic examination with or without hydrodistension correspond to the population included in four of the six pivotal studies.</p><p>Indeed in these four pivotal studies patients reported a better subjective improvement under treatment with pentosan polysulfate sodium compared to placebo. In three of these studies <ref type="bibr">(Parsons and Mulholland 1987</ref><ref type="bibr">, Mulholland et al 1990</ref><ref type="bibr">, Parsons et al 1993</ref>, and in contrast to efficacy results in the pivotal studies including a broader BPS population, the observed difference reached statistical significance.</p><p>The pooled analysis showed that the percentage of patients responding to treatment with PPS with a clinically relevant improvement in their overall assessment, pain and urgency was approximately 2-fold higher than the respective responder rates under placebo: Overall, the balance of benefit risks of PPS is positive in bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions in adults with moderate to severe pain, urgency and frequency of micturition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.8.">Conclusions</head><p>The overall B/R of elmiron is positive.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Recommendations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Outcome</head><p>Based on the CHMP review of data on quality, safety and efficacy, the CHMP considers by consensus that the risk-benefit balance of elmiron is favourable in the following indication:</p><p>elmiron is indicated for the treatment of bladder pain syndrome characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions in adults with moderate to severe pain, urgency and frequency of micturition (see section 4.4).</p><p>The CHMP therefore recommends the granting of the marketing authorisation subject to the following conditions:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions regarding supply and use</head><p>Medicinal product subject to medical prescription.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other conditions and requirements of the marketing authorisation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Periodic Safety Update Reports</head><p>The requirements for submission of periodic safety update reports for this medicinal product are set out in the list of Union reference dates (EURD list) provided for under Article 107c <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> of Directive 2001/83/EC and any subsequent updates published on the European medicines webportal.</p><p>The marketing authorisation holder shall submit the first periodic safety update report for this product within 6 months following authorisation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk Management Plan (RMP)</head><p>The MAH shall perform the required pharmacovigilance activities and interventions detailed in the agreed RMP presented in Module 1.8.2 of the marketing authorisation and any agreed subsequent updates of the RMP.</p><p>An updated RMP should be submitted:</p><p>• At the request of the European Medicines Agency;</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>During the meeting on 23 June 2016, the CHMP agreed on the consolidated List of Questions to be sent to the applicant. The final consolidated List of Questions was sent to the applicant on 24 June 2016. • The applicant submitted the responses to the CHMP consolidated List of Questions on 6 September 2016. • The Rapporteurs circulated the Joint Assessment Report on the applicant's responses to the List of Questions to all CHMP members on 17 October 2016. • During the PRAC meeting on 27 October 2016, the PRAC agreed on the PRAC Assessment Overview and Advice to CHMP. The PRAC Assessment Overview and Advice was sent to the applicant on 28 October 2016.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Off-label enteral and parenteral use of medicinal products (analgesics, corticosteroids, antiallergics, PPS, Hydroxyzine, Amitriptyline, antibiotics, immunosuppressants, Gabapentin, Pregabalin, efficacy and safety of PPS, when used for relief of bladder pain and other signs and symptoms of IC, lead to the recommendation to use PPS in European Treatment Guidelines for the treatment of bladder pain syndrome or IC. In the Guidelines on Chronic Pelvic Pain, which are released by the European Association of Urology since 2004 (Fall et al. 2004) oral usage of PPS is recommended as standard treatment for the therapy of bladder pain syndrome "BPS" already in the first version of these guidelines from 2004 until 2015 (strong recommendation (A) was given with a grade 1a level of evidence). In addition, a review article on treatment guidelines for classic and non-ulcer IC from the year 2000 lists oral treatment with PPS as an established treatment option for IC (Peeker et al. 2000). However, the guideline of the American Association of Urology published in 2014, gives a more conservative recommendation (evidence level given as "B") due to conflicting results of clinical studies and the guideline of the 5th International consultation on incontinence (Paul Abrams et al, 5th edition 2013) gives a grade recommendation of D with a level of evidence 1.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>elmiron is submitted under Article 10a (well-established use) of Directive 2001/83/EC (as amended) via the centralised procedure. In accordance with Article 10a of Directive 2001/83/EC the application shall rely on appropriate scientific literature substituting non-clinical tests and clinical studies if it can be demonstrated that the active substance of a medicinal product has been in well-established medicinal use within the European Union for at least 10 years, with a recognised efficacy and an acceptable level of safety. In this regard, the provisions of Annex I (Part II.1) to Directive 2001/83/EC shall apply. The requirements, described in Article 10a read in combination with the abovementioned Annex I, are discussed below: (1) The time over which PPS has been used in Europe for the treatment of IC: The first information on the usage of PPS in European Union is provided in publications of clinical studies conducted in the EU for the treatment of IC in 1986 -1997 : an early case report about the use of PPS in 11 patients with IC was published in Germany (Beer et al 1986) , a multicentre openlabel study in 87 patients conducted in 12 centres in Sweden and 5 centres in Finland (Fritjfsson et al 1987), including one of the pivotal studies (randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled) conducted in Europe which enrolled 115 patients in 7 centres in Denmark and the UK (Holm-Bentzen et al 1987). Another randomized active-controlled study comparing PPS versus Cyclosporine A was conducted in Europe and published in 2005. This study enrolled 64 patients in 7 Finnish urological units (Sairanen et al 2005). A clinical study conducted in Germany included 58 patients in order to evaluate the safety and efficacy of subcutaneous low-dose heparin application on top of oral PPS application (Van Ophoven et al 2005).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Structural formula of pentosan polysulfate sodium. R = SO 3 Na</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Kalota et al. (Kalota et al. 1992) demonstrated that PPS can reduce the damage done by the cytotoxic substance acrolein in transitional cells in the bladder of female rats, which suggests an enhancement of GAG layer properties by PPS. The ability of PPS to reduce toxic effects of acrolein, the active metabolite of cyclophosphamide, and the ability of PPS to improve the bladder's GAG functional layer properties; were highlighted. Nickel et al. (Nickel et al. 1998) investigated the relative efficacy of heparin, PPS and hyaluronic acid in preventing the absorption of 14 C labeled urea in protamine-pre-treated bladders compared with salinepre-treated control bladders. The results demonstrate that exogenous GAG's are effective in providing an epithelial permeability barrier in protamine-pre-treated bladders.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The anticoagulant effectiveness of PPS was demonstrated both in vitro and in vivo. The anticoagulant action of PPS is much lower than that of unfractionated heparin which clearly prolonged aPTT, TT and PT as well as inhibited thrombin and FXa activities to nearly the same degree. The antithrombotic effectiveness of PPS was demonstrated in various experimental thrombosis models in animals. PPS especially prevented the formation of venous thrombi when these were induced by activation of the plasmatic coagulation system due to endothelial damage or injection of activated clotting factors in combination with partial or complete interruption of blood flow. PPS was also effective in arterial thrombosis when thrombus formation was induced by administration of activated clotting factors and stasis, but it was almost ineffective in models of arterial thrombosis when these were mainly based on vessel lesions and activation of platelets. PPS was found to stimulate fibrinolysis in vivo in various species due to the release of t-PA from endothelial cells. Ofosu et al. 1986 concluded from in in-vitro experiments that PPS appear to directly inhibit prothrombin activation via several mechanisms (catalysing the inhibition of the initial trace amounts of thrombin formed by heparin cofactor II, direct inhibition of prothrombin activation by the inhibition of the formation of the prothrombinase complex, or inhibition of the expression of the catalytic activity of the prothrombinase complex). Scully et al. 1986 evaluated the relative potency of PPS for the activation of HC II/thrombin or AT/thrombin interaction in comparison to heparin and dermatan sulfate and to differentiate between high, average and low molecular weight fractions of PPS. Results indicate a coagulation control by PPS principally through inhibition of thrombin mainly (&gt; 80 %) due to HC II. The effect of PPS on platelet functions is not yet clear. PPS did not affect ADP-induced aggregation and showed only a minor inhibitory activity on collagen-as well as ristocetin induced aggregation but it inhibited the adhesion of platelets to collagen in a concentration dependent manner. The results of the action of PPS on thrombin-induced aggregation are controversial. PPS aggregated platelets in normal platelet-rich plasma when the aggregation was induced with the serum from patients with documented heparin-induced thrombocytopenia indicating that PPS may provoke immune thrombocytopenia in man.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Figure: 1. Type of test/study ID/GLP</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure</head><label></label><figDesc>PPS. In this NTP Report, genetic toxicity studies were evaluated which derived from an earlier effort by the NTP to develop a comprehensive database permitting a critical anticipation of a chemical's carcinogenicity in experimental animals. The genetic toxicity studies with PPS comprise the following tests (NTP Report): 1. Salmonella Typhimurium Mutagenicity Test (Ames .</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure: 24 FigureFigureFigureFigure</head><label>24</label><figDesc>. -survival of all dosed groups similar to control Figure: 25. -no effect on mean b.w : 29. ↑ histiocytic cellular infiltration both sex wherein effect seen ≥ 42 mg/kg/d (M) and ≥ 84 mg/kg/d (F) . Hemangiosarcoma (&gt; control) in both sex wherein M more sensitive than F Figure: 41. Hepatocellular adenoma and carcinoma highest dose (M= historical control / F&gt; historical control) these 2-year carcinogenicity studies were the following: "Under the conditions of these 2-year gavage studies, there was no evidence of carcinogenic activity* of Elmiron in male F344/N rats administered 14, 42, or 126 mg/kg or in female F344/N rats administered 28, 84, or 252 mg/kg. There was some evidence of carcinogenic activity of Elmiron in male B6C3F1 mice based on increased incidences of liver hemangiosarcoma. The increased incidences of hepatocellular neoplasms in male mice may have been related to Elmiron administration. There was some evidence of carcinogenic activity of Elmiron in female B6C3F1 mice based on the increased incidences of liver hemangiosarcoma and hepatocellular neoplasms. The increased incidences of malignant lymphomas in female mice may have been related to Elmiron administration. Elmiron administration caused increased incidences of non-neoplastic lesions (presence of vacuolated histiocytes) of the rectum, lung, mesenteric lymph node, and spleen (males) in rats and of the liver, rectum, mesenteric lymph node, and spleen in mice. Reproduction Toxicity PPS does not cross the placental barrier in humans. This is demonstrated in investigations of Forestier et al., 1986 (PPS); Rainaut et al., 1987 (PPS, low molecular heparins (LMWHs); Forestier et al., 1987 (LMWH); Omri et al., 1989 (LMWH); Deruelle and Coulon, 2007 (LMWHs). In a retrospective study 111 pregnancies under treatment with LMWHs were evaluated by Deruelle et al., 2006; all patients began treatment before the 15th week of pregnancy. The authors conclude that the use of LMWHs for patients requiring anticoagulant treatment from the first trimester appears safe for mother and foetus. Corresponding results were obtained in experimental animal studies. Andrew et al., 1985 conclude that standard heparin and a LMWH do not cross the placenta in the pregnant sheep. Doutremepuich et al., 1985 compare the passage of commercial heparin and a low molecular weight fragment of heparin across the placenta of rabbits. The authors show that the low molecular weight heparin fraction does not cross the placenta at the dose of 1 000 anti-Xa units/kg. For higher doses (8 000 and 16 000 anti-Xa units/kg) this heparin fraction gives a fetal heparin blood level above that after administration of commercial heparin.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>to Article 10a of Directive 2001/83/EC, if the Applicant can demonstrate that the active substance of the medicinal product has been in well-established medicinal use within the EU for at least 10 years, with recognised efficacy and an acceptable level of safety in terms of the conditions set out in Annex I of the abovementioned Directive, it is possible to replace results of pre-clinical and clinical trials by detailed references to appropriate scientific literature. Scientific publications of product-specific studies are evaluated which have outlined the efficacy of PPS in comparison to placebo, to other medicinal products or in an uncontrolled fashion. In the case of PPS capsules the information evaluated in this dossier is mainly taken from publications on studies conducted with Elmiron capsules which is the identical medicinal product as the product approved in the US and Canada.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 2 Distribution</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Pharmacokinetic parameters in healthy females following a single dose of oral PPS (Simon et al., 2005) Cumulative excretion of radioactivity in urine and feces (mean ± SD), n = 8 Plasma radioactivity concentrations (mean ± SD) Systemic bioavailability of PPS after oral administration of PPS is very low, accordingly, distribution of PPS was mainly evaluated after parenteral application.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>collected over 18 hr after intravenous injection of radiolabelled 125I-PPS contained 35% of the administered activity while stools passed at 18 and 42 hr post-injection contained 0.13% and 0.07% respectively (MacGregor et al., 1984). Radioactivity was detectable in urine within an hour of i.v. injection of 125I-PPS. The recovery of radioactivity in the urine within 24 hr following i.v. injection averaged 31% of the injected dose (range 22-43%) and was not related to the dose of unlabelled PPS (MacGregor et al., 1984). • Metabolism Metabolism of 125I-PPS radiolabelled PPS was evaluated via binding affinity to Polybrene in order to detect the desulfation of PPS and gel filtration in order to detect depolymerisation. PPS without affinity to Polybrene was concluded to be macromolecular desulfated PPS. The probable sites of desulfation are the liver and spleen which are rich sources of sulfatases. This assumption is supported by another experiment evaluating the organ distribution of PPS after i.v. administration. Only macromolecular PPS was present in plasma indicating that the kidney is the site of depolymerisation (MacGregor et al., 1984).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Based on one open-label study(Modi et al 2005), the therapeutic doses of PPS have no effect on the pharmacokinetics of R-and S-warfarin or on pharmacodynamics effect as measured by PT, PTT and INR. Besides, the orally administered PPS did not influence aPTT, anti-Xa activity, hepatic triglyceride lipase and lipoprotein lipase in comparison with intravenously PPS or placebo(Faaij et al 1999). There is no expected metabolic drug-drug interaction with desulfation and depolymerisation reactions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>systemically available PPS after oral administration. The evaluated parameters included activated partial thromboplastin time (APTT) and increase of anti-Xa activity as well as measures of endogenous fibrinolysis (tissue plasminogen activator (t-PA) activity and fibrin plate lysis).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>reported volume of distribution at steady state reported in Fellström et al was 0.67 ± 0.28 L/kg (for an average 70 kg adult, Vss 46.9 ± 19.6 L). The clearance reported in Fellström et al. was 49.9 ± 6.6 mL/min. Macgregor et al. showed progressive uptake of PPS by the spleen and the liver after i.v. administration. Forestier et al based the absence of trans placental passage of PPS on the absence of clinical signs (change in coagulation parameters). Elimination and Metabolism Reported renal clearance was 4.2 ± 1.2 mL/min in Fellström et al. Terminal elimination half-life was 24.1 ± 10.8 hours in Fellström et al; and in Simon et al. it was reported as 26.5 h (CV 23%) and 19.5 h (CV 16%) for 300 and 450 mg PPS respectively. The apparent plasma half-life of pentosan polysulfate sodium depends on the route of administration. While pentosan polysulfate sodium is rapidly cleared from circulation of i.v. administration, the apparent plasma half-life after oral administration is in the range of 24-34 hours. Simon et al. documented that after oral administration, the majority of PPS was excreted unchanged in faeces, and 6% of the dose was excreted in urine. In Simon et al, radioactivity in urine consisted mostly of components of lower molecular weight and lower degrees of sulfation (indicating PPS was metabolised by depolymerisation and desulfation). Pentosan polysulfate does not exhibit any crystalline structure or polymorphism, so no inter-conversion was expected.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the pharmacokinetic study published by Simon et al., 2005, inter-individual variability of exposure was relatively low. Coefficients of variation (CVs) of Cmax and AUC ranged from 9.3-25% in this population of 16 healthy women.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>No drug-drug interaction study was performed with PPS by the Applicant. A causal relationship between PPS und GIT-AEs is not obvious. In case of a causal relationship, most likely local irritant properties as suggested might be responsible regarding an interaction of PPS and mucus. In the context of the side effect rectal bleeding the applicant was asked to summarize the safety of oral PPS and provide additional information from several studies about the risk of rectal bleeding. Based on one open-label study (Modi et al 2005), the therapeutic doses of PPS have no effect on the pharmacokinetics of R-and S-warfarin or on pharmacodynamics effect as measured by PT, PTT and INR. Besides, the orally administered PPS did not influence aPTT, anti-Xa activity, hepatic triglyceride lipase and lipoprotein lipase in comparison with intravenously PPS or placebo (Faaij et al 1999).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Indeed, there were several agreed definition for IC available in urology among different regions one of the first agreed by US National Institute of Health -National Institutes of Diabetes, Digestive, and Kidney Disease (NIDDK) in US in 1987, by International Continence Society in 2002 (O'Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Symptoms Index ICSI), more recently by European Society for the Study of IC/BPS (ESSIC) in 2008, later by American Urological Association (AUA) in 2014 and European Association of Urology (EAU) Guidelines on Chronic Pelvic Pain of the European Association of Urology in 2015.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on 6-point GRA score (patients reporting 50% (moderate), 75% (great) 100% (complete cure) improvement overall) Secondary endpoints: -Investigator evaluation "worse", "no change", "fair", "good", "very good", "excellent" -Volume voiding profile over 3 consecutive days (success: decrease 3 or more per day in frequency and an increase of urine volume of at least 20 ml) -Pain &amp; urgency scale (success: at least 1-point improvement) Parsons et al., 1993 Primary endpoint: Responder analysis based on 6-point GRA score (patients reporting 50% (moderate), 75% (great) 100% (complete cure) improvement overall) Secondary endpoints: -Investigator evaluation "worse", "no change", "fair", "good", "very good", "excellent" -Volume voiding profile over 3 consecutive days (success: decrease 3 or more per day in frequency and an increase of urine volume of intensity (11-point numerical rating scale), -Responder analysis based on a 50% reduction in PORIS scale (for pain, urgency and overall assessment), -Responder analysis based on 7-point GRA score (patients reporting at least 6 moderately or 7 markedly improved)Sample sizeIn Holm-Bentzen et al, 1987, the minimum number of patients in each protocol estimated before the trial was calculated to 40 on the basis of the following parameters: 2 α = 5% (risk of type 1 error), β = 10% (risk of type 2 error), π1 = 20% (the estimated placebo effect) and π2 = 70% (the estimated drug effect).In Sant 2003, the projected sample size of 136 participants was selected to detect large differences in response rates of 30% versus 65% (80% power at a 2-sided significance level of 5%). The factorial design provides a savings in overall sample size and is especially useful in studying drugs with nonoverlapping mechanisms of effect. However, there is limited statistical power to compare results among individual treatment arms. This trial was intended primarily as a pilot study to evaluate the feasibility of conducting a larger clinical trial. A second objective was to evaluate whether or not there was sufficient evidence of efficacy to warrant expansion to a larger trial. The factorial design combined arms for analysis to increase the statistical power for the main comparisons over that available from comparing individual arms.In Nickel et al 2015, the target sample size was 645 patients to yield 600 (200 per treatment group) who were evaluable defined as those with 1 follow-up evaluation after baseline. A sample of 215</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Studies bySant et al. (2003)  andNickel et al. (2015)  were conducted in the US at a time, when PPS (Elmiron) was commercially available for the treatment of IC. Both studies faced severe recruitment problems, which lead to enrolment of patients, who were previously treated with PPS. The Study by Sant et al.(2003)  amended exclusion criteria in order to improve recruitment. Initially the study excluded patients who had been previously treated with ≥100 mg TID oral PPS for ≥12 consecutive weeks. This criterion was amended to an exclusion of PPS treatment during 4 weeks prior to the study;</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>et al. (1993): At the end of the three months treatment period 24 of 74 PPS treated patients (31%) evaluated themselves as at least 50% overall improved relative to the condition at the beginning of the study compared to 12 of 74 patients in the placebo group (16%) (p=0.01). Sant et al. (2003): In this study, the main treatment effect of PPS was evaluated by combining data from the placebo and hydroxyzine alone arms and comparing those to data from the PPS alone and PPS plus hydroxyzine combination arms. A responder analysis based on a patient-reported Global Response Assessment (GRA) at 24 weeks was defined as primary endpoint. The study did not enrol the planned patient number and the rather high number of drop outs during the study. A trend (p= 0.064) for better efficacy was observed in those patients treated with PPS (20 of 59, 34%) compared to the non-PPS group (11 of 62, 18%). Nickel et al. (2015): The primary efficacy results of this study were a responder analysis based on a 30% improvement in the O'Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Symptom Index (ICSI) at week 24. The primary analysis in the reported study was conducted on a last-observation-carried forward (LOCF)basis, for those patients who withdrew before completing the 24 weeks. There was no statistically significant difference between the different treatment groups for the primary endpoint pre-specified analysis of the ITT data set. The responder rates were 40.7%, 39.8% and 42.6% for the placebo, PPS 100 mg and PPS 300 mg group, respectively. The percent of responders was similar for PPS naïve and non-naive patients across all 3 treatment groups. A post-hoc subgroup analysis of the 94 patients meeting the NIDDK criteria revealed a 50%, 30.3% and 34.5% responder rate for the respective treatment groups.The authors explained that the differences in this study compared to the earlier studies of Mulholland et al(1990)  andParsons et al. (1993)  are based on (1) differences in the enrolled patient population (current study enrolled with milder symptoms, no cut-off criteria for pain or urgency, no determination of flare status, no entry criterion based on cystoscopy findings and no exclusion for commonly associated conditions such as irritable bowel disease, depression or pelvic floor dysfunction disease)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Holm-Bentzen et al 1987, the effect of treatment in the individual patient was expressed as a decrease of 1 or more numerical values in symptom score for pain, dysuria, frequency and nocturia.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Parsons et al 1993, based on a previous experience with controlled clinical trials with IC, the voided volume data (which tend to be widely variable between and within patients) were considered to be of secondary importance as a measure of efficacy. A voiding volume profile that measured the time and quantity of all voids during waking hours as well as the number of voids during sleeping hours during 3 consecutive days was completed by the patient before and after 3 months of treatment. This profile provided information concerning changes in average voided volume, frequency and nocturia during the treatment period.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>analysis. This decision corresponded to the proceeding by Hwang et al., 1997 who included the four studies which were available at that time and to the proceeding by Dimitrakov et al., 2007 who included all five of the six studies available at that time. As the latest clinical study was just recently published by Nickel et al., 2015, none of the two published meta-analyses included this large clinical study. The meta-analysis included all 6 pivotal studies performed between 1987 and 2015, of which 5 of them were carried out between 1987 and 2003. They were relatively small trials, mainly exploratory, except the Nickel study which was a true confirmatory trial with a large sample size (targeted 645 subjects, actual 368 and 240 retained in the meta-analysis). The primary endpoint of the meta-analysis was the responder rate based upon a patient's global response assessment (GRA), as defined in the individual studies when available or calculated afterwards if not directly available in studies. The main analysis was performed on the ITT population (all randomized subjects in trials) along with several sensitivity analysis, in order to test the robustness of the main results.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>. The publication from Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 reported effects on pain, but not on urgency. The publication from Sant et al., 2003 reported no responder rates on different symptoms, but just overall scores and their mean changes from baseline. The supportive meta-analyses mainly used the reported effect size on the symptoms pain and urgency and calculated the effects sizes on the ITT population as main outcome. The Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 study could not be included in the meta-analysis because there are no response data available for Urgency but there are good data for Frequency. Therefore, this study was excluded in meta-analysis of symptom urgency. Likewise, the study of Sant at 2003 was excluded, as rates of improvement in urgency were not available for this study. However, meta-analysis were performed in including available data of frequency instead of urgency for the Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 study and urgency success rates for the Sant et al 2003 from the overall improvement result of the study with a method of data extraction. Statistically significant benefit differences of 12.1% (ITT approach, Sant et al 2003 excluded) (IC 95% [0.03-0.211], p =0.009) and 9.9% (ITT approach, Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 and Sant et al excluded 2003) (IC 95% [0.029-0.168], p = 0.005) were reached for an improvement of pain and urgency evaluated respectively in the supportive meta-analyses.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of them were open-label and uncontrolled or retrospective studies with a small number of patients and published between 1983 and 2000. Only 4 were more recent and published from 2005 and 2008.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>randomized double-blind clinical trial was performed by Davis et al 2008 to evaluate the safety and efficacy of intravesical PPS administration on top of oral PPS treatment in 41 women. The use of the association of intravesical PPS and oral PPS appears to enhance the proliferation of the GAG layer of the bladder, to produce greater relief and return to normal protective coating when maintained with oral PPS.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al 1990 and Parsons et al 1993) were recruiting (a) without clear hypothesis tested and (b) without clear management of selection biases as these studies were performed with old methodological requirements. Sample sizes to test certain hypothesis were calculated only for three of the six pivotal studies: in Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 study (40 patients per group), Sant et al 2003 study (136 patients per group), and Nickel et al 2015 study (target 645 patients would yield 600 (200 per treatment arm). No sample sizes were defined prospectively for Parsons and Mulholland 1987 study, Mulholland et al 1990 study, and Parsons et al 1993 study. This is a weakness of this literature based application. The population included in the pivotal studies differs between the studies. The population was included with different IC definitions, mixing both broad IC/BPS (i.e. In European Holm-Bentzen et al. 1987 Study and in Canadian/US Nickel et al 2015 Study) definitions meeting the ESSIC classification 2X and 3C (i.e. in US Parsons and Mulholland 1987 Study, Mulholland et al 1990 Study, Parsons et al 1993 Study, and in Sant et al 2003 Study) but it is agreed that the broader population (IC/BPS) includes IC</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_28"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>without hydrodistension corresponding to the IC criteria established by the National Institute of diabetes and digestive and kidney diseases (NIDDK) (Cases meeting the ESSIC classification 2X and 3C would meet the NIDDK criteria for IC). These IC patients were included in four pivotal studies(Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al 1990, Parsons et al 1993 and Sant et al 2003, of whom 3 met the primary endpoints(Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al 1990, Parsons et al   1993.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_29"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>was shown to correlate with the GRA-responders. Although no global response assessment was conducted in the study reported by Parsons and Mulholland, 1987, the data imputation used for the meta-analysis conducted by the applicant is deemed sufficiently comparable. For the responder analysis used in the study reported by Holm-Bentzen et al, 1987 comparability with the other responder definitions could not be demonstrated.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_30"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Nickel studies) which presented the lowest response rates and included a less homogeneous population than in the four other pivotal studies (mixing both broad IC/BPS).These benefit differences mainly driven by the two pivotal studies Parsons et al 1993 and Mulholland et al 1990 for the drug approval of Elmiron in the US and by an earlier study (Parsons and Mulholland Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 93/115 1987) which met their primary endpoints seem relatively low and the studies were performed with old methodological standard requirements and with a low number of patients. Furthermore the most recent study (Nickel et al 2015) with up-to-date methodology provided un-conclusive results (and negative results in the subgroup of patients meeting the NIDDK criteria). Thus, the applicant provided a new meta-analysis which took into account the results of the post Hoc analysis of the Nickel et al study in the subgroup of patients with IC (2X to 3C). Compared to the sensitivity analysis including only the four pivotal studies, which included the pre-defined homogeneous patient population of IC patients characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions, the estimated benefit difference in success rates decreased from 17.0% to 13.3% where this smaller difference is still statistically significant</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_31"><head>1)</head><label></label><figDesc>Please discuss the definition (s) of IC / pain bladder syndrome and what is known about the etiology and pathogenesis of this condition. Which are the available treatment alternatives? Is there an unmet medical need for new treatments? Chronic pelvic pain can have multiple reasons which may be deriving from within the bladder (e.g. chronic inflammation of the bladder region, characterized by Hunner's lesions / Glomerulations) or from outside the bladder (e.g. pudendus neuralgia); BPS is a diagnosis of exclusion. For the definition of BPS (and former IC) the experts referred to the ESSIC classification (Engeler et al 2015). It was considered that the IC definition at the time when most of the pivotal studies were performed would, as per todays classification, fall under BPS type 2 -3. Considering today's classification and medical practice an indication today would therefore need to refer to BPS. The experts further emphasized that a categorization reflecting current clinical practice would refer to symptomatic severity and modern clinical trials would be designed to measure patient related outcomes. It was noted that particular intravesical changes such as Glomerulations and Hunner's lesions are not correlating with clinical severity of this condition. The medical need for effective treatments in this condition was clearly seen by the experts. Current oral pharmacological treatment options are second line (after behavioral modifications and stress management) and comprise amitryptilin, cimetidine, hydroxyzine and PPS, PPS having a particularly benign safety profile. All treatment to date is symptomatic and none of above treatments is authorized in the EU in this condition. 2) Considering the results of the four pivotal studies, the results of Holm-Bentzen et al. (1987) and Nickel et al. (2015) studies and the European and international treatment guidelines of this condition, do you think that the available data support that PPS (Pentosan Polysulfate Sodium) has a place in the treatment of interstitial cystitis (IC)?There was consensus about the weak evidence on efficacy of PPS deriving from the older studies showing a limited treatment effect. With regards to the more recent Nickel at al. (2015) study some experts were concerned about the efficacy results and would not use PPS as monotherapy, others were rather content to view results of this study as an outlier in terms of efficacy.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_32"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>versus placebo) reached 17% when excluding 2 pivotal studies (Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 and Nickel et al 2015) with the lowest response rates and with a population less homogeneous than in the four other clinical studies (mixing both broad IC/BPS). Indeed, this benefit difference was mainly driven by the statistically significant results of the three pivotal studies Parsons et al 1993, Mulholland et al 1990 and Parsons and Mulholland 1987 including patients falling within ESSIC classification 2X to 3C. Given the heterogeneity of the population included in Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 and Nickel et al and the clear efficacy results when pooling the remaining four pivotal studies including patients diagnosed IC falling within the ESSIC (BPS) classification 2X to 3C, it was agreed to refer in the indication to patients diagnosed IC / BPS using the traditional approach including cystoscopy with or without hydrodistension showing either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_33"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>only one single side effect (skin rash) was reported. In the study published by Fritjofsson et al. (1987), diarrhoea was reported in 6 patients and one patient complained of dyspepsia during treatment. Swelling of legs occurred in 2 patients. Mulholland et al. (1990) and Parsons et al. (1993) described the occurrence of adverse reactions in the safety sections. The Applicant explained that the incidence of adverse reactions observed in both studies were low in both treatment groups and the observed effects are not different from effects expected to occur in any random population over a three-month period. In Parsons et al. (1993) study,</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_34"><head>Coagulation findings .Figure</head><label>findings</label><figDesc>Number of previous studies showed a risk for coagulopathy after oral administration (Gaffney et al., 1986) both after single and multiple dosages, and both in clinical and in non-clincial settings (Marsch et al 1985). See Figure 5 below. In particular, one observation in Davis et al., 2008 study cannot be neglected: ~40% of blood clotting tests (prothrombin time, partial thromboplastin time, and platelet count) were outside normal ranges for both oral PPS and oral plus intravesicular PPS. These findings are in line with several other findings of possible impact on coagulation of oral PPS, such as reported rectal bleeding. According to the applicant, the literature case reports and cases from the studies, are arguing that the issue is very</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_35"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>IC/BPS (i.e. In European Holm-Bentzen et al. 1987 Study and in Canadian/US Nickel et al 2015 Study) or definitions falling within ESSIC BPS classification 2X to 3C (i.e. in Parsons and Mulholland 1987 Study, Mulholland et al 1990 Study, Parsons et al 1993 Study, and in Sant et al 2003 Study). In accordance with the advice of the ad hoc expert group and the ESSIC classification (Engeler et al 2015) the CHMP considered that the definition of former IC at the time when most of the pivotal studies were performed would, as per todays classification, fall under BPS characterized by glomerulations or Hunner's lesions (BPS type 2X -3C) and the applicant agreed to amend the indication accordingly. Furthermore pain is considered as the main key symptom of the disease and should be taken into consideration in the definition of the disease.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_36"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>applicant provided literature on six randomised, double-blind, placebo-controlled studies as pivotal database to evaluate the efficacy and safety of PPS of which Mulholland et al 1990 and Parsons et al 1993 studies were the pivotal studies for MAA in USA and Canada.All but one of 6 pivotal studies were conducted more than 10 years ago (except the more recent study of Nickel et al 2015). IC patients characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions (BPS type were included in four of the pivotal studies(Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al   1990, Parsons et al 1993 and Sant et al 2003.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_37"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al 1990 an Parsons et al 1993) met their primary endpoint "overall global improvement" (assessed by a patients self-evaluation confirmed by an investigator's evaluation based on patients reporting at least 6 moderately improved or 7 markedly improved on 7 point numerical rating scale) and their key secondary endpoints such as pain in comparison to placebo. The 3 other studies (Holm-Bentzen et al 1987, Sant et al 2003 and Nickel et al 2015) did not meet their primary and their key secondary endpoints.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_38"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>Holm-Bentzen et al 1987 and Nickel et al 2015)  which presented the lowest response rates and enrolled a broader and less homogeneous patient population.The applicant provided a comparison of the definitions of the primary endpoints "GRA" and responder rates among all 6 studies and especially in the four pivotal studies. It is agreed that the responder rates used in the four pivotal studies enrolling a homogeneous and clear defined patient population</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_39"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Existing post-marketing experience andNickel et al. (2005)  data indicate that most common reported AEs were diarrhoea, rectal bleeding and abdominal pain. However a causal relationship between PPS and GIT-AEs is not obvious as GITs are equally reported as associated with the underlying disease and independent of any treatment. In case of a causal relationship, most likely local irritant properties might be responsible regarding an interaction of PPS and mucus the addition to the SmPC to stop the treatment in case of AE and in case of non-efficiency after 6 month of therapy takes this into account.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table of contents 1. Background information on the procedure</head><label></label><figDesc>.............................................. 7 1.1. Submission of the dossier ...................................................................................... 7 1.2. Steps taken for the assessment of the product ......................................................... 8</figDesc><table><row><cell>PPS Pentosan Polysulfate Sodium</cell></row><row><cell>PT Prothrombin time</cell></row><row><cell>PTT Partial Thromboplastin Time</cell></row><row><cell>PVC Polivinyl chloride</cell></row><row><cell>QD Once daily</cell></row><row><cell>QOL Quality of Life</cell></row><row><cell>Q&amp;A Questions and Answers</cell></row><row><cell>RA Responder analysis (Assessment)</cell></row><row><cell>RH Relative Humidity</cell></row><row><cell>RIA Radioimmunoassay</cell></row><row><cell>RP HPLC reverse phase high performance liquid chromatography</cell></row><row><cell>Rx treatment arm</cell></row><row><cell>SAE Serious adverse event</cell></row><row><cell>SEC Size-exclusion chromatography</cell></row><row><cell>SmPC Summary of Product Characteristics</cell></row><row><cell>TCA trichloroacetic acid</cell></row><row><cell>TID, t.i.d. Three times daily</cell></row><row><cell>TLC Thin layer chromatography</cell></row><row><cell>Tmax Time of Maximum concentration observed</cell></row><row><cell>TSE Transmissible Spongiform Encephalopathy</cell></row><row><cell>TUR Transurethral resection</cell></row><row><cell>UV Ultraviolet</cell></row><row><cell>XRD X-Ray Diffraction</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>ESSIC classification of types of BPS according to the results of cystoscopy with hydrodistension and biopsies</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>) is commercially available since 1949 and used off-label for the treatment of IC (Sievert et al 2000, recent survey conducted in Germany in 2014-2015 (see also quantitative aspects below). Furthermore, several publications in German medical literature (textbooks and publications) refer to the usage of Pentosanpolysulfat SP54 for the treatment of IC: 1. Roth, S., Ubrig, B., Semjonov, A., Rathert, P.T. (ed.), Klinische Urologie -Vom Befund zur Therapie, Springer Verlag Berlin, Heidelberg, New York, 2001, Auflage 2 2. Ulrich Kuhlmann, Joachim Böhler, Friedrich C. Luft, Mark Dominik Alscher, Ulrich Kunzendorf (ed.), Nephrologie. Pathophysiologie -Klinik -Nierenersatzverfahren, 6. Auflage 2015 Thieme Verlag 3. Paul Karp, Die Interstitielle Cystitis -ein Leiden zwischen Hoffnung und Frustration,</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Saarländische Ärzteblatt, Ausgabe 4/2008, pp 14-16</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Frank Oberpenning, Arndt van Ophoven, Lothar Hertle, Chronische interstitielle Zystitis. Dtsch</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Arztebl 2002; 99: A 204-208 [Heft 4]</cell></row><row><cell>5.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Loch, A. &amp; Stein, U.[Interstitial cystitis. Current aspects of diagnosis and therapy]. Urologe A,</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>List of off-label use prescriptions of Pentosanpolysulfat SP54 for the treatment of IC</figDesc><table><row><cell>Time period</cell><cell>06/2015-05/2016</cell><cell>06/2014-05/2015</cell><cell>06/2013-05/2014</cell><cell>06/2012-05/2013</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 3List ofTable 4 Table 4</head><label>3List44</label><figDesc>PPS prescriptions in the prescription cost analysis of the HSCIC Importation of Elmiron based on single patient prescriptions are handled in France via an "Autorisation Temporaire d'Utilisation nominative" (ATUn). ATUn registrations for the importation of Elmiron authorised outside the EU on single patient prescriptions exist since 2004. According to the ANSM approximately 660 prescriptions for Elmiron were handled via the nominative ATU procedure in France in 2015. The number of ATU nominatives authorized in France since 2006 are presented in the following. Number of ATU nominative authorized in France in the indication of IC Approx 10.000 units and more of Elmiron or 330.000 DDD were imported by companies based on individual prescriptions in 2014. The ATU criteria to exclude other diseases were the followings:</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">ELMIRON 100 mg gelule</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>Number</cell><cell>of</cell><cell>Number of new</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">treated patients</cell><cell>patients</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2006</cell><cell>179</cell><cell></cell><cell>109</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2007</cell><cell>214</cell><cell></cell><cell>111</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Year Product 2008 2009 2010</cell><cell>240 Delivered 286 capsules 335</cell><cell></cell><cell>119 Reflect 3-months treatment courses 132 (180 capsules) 166</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2014</cell><cell>Elmiron 2011</cell><cell>25.400 373</cell><cell></cell><cell>141 173</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PPS 100mg 2012</cell><cell>26.700 446</cell><cell></cell><cell>148 197</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2013</cell><cell>PPS 100mg 2013</cell><cell>28.200 448</cell><cell></cell><cell>157 215</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Elmiron 2014</cell><cell>23.300 427</cell><cell></cell><cell>129 248</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2012</cell><cell>Elmiron_Cap 100mg 2015</cell><cell>25.100 429</cell><cell></cell><cell>139 227</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PPS_Cap 100mg</cell><cell>24.900</cell><cell></cell><cell>138</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Elmiron_Cap 100mg</cell><cell>30.500</cell><cell></cell><cell>169</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2011</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>PPS_Cap 100mg</cell><cell>21.100</cell><cell></cell><cell>117</cell></row><row><cell>-</cell><cell>ECBU</cell><cell>Elmiron_Cap 100mg</cell><cell>33.800</cell><cell></cell><cell>188</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2010</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">PPS_Cap 100mg Bladder ultrasound</cell><cell>17.500</cell><cell></cell><cell>97</cell></row><row><cell>-</cell><cell cols="3">2009 Elmiron Cap Cystoscopy with bladder hydrodistension 29.900</cell><cell></cell><cell>166</cell></row><row><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">2008 Elmiron Cap Bladder Biopsy</cell><cell>34.500</cell><cell></cell><cell>192</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2007 Elmiron Cap</cell><cell>27.200</cell><cell></cell><cell>151</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell cols="2">2006 Elmiron Cap Norway:</cell><cell>31.500</cell><cell></cell><cell>175</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2005 Elmiron Cap</cell><cell>37.600</cell><cell></cell><cell>209</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">2004 Elmiron Cap</cell><cell>32.600</cell><cell></cell><cell>181</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell cols="2">France:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Assessment report</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Page 15/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>List of Elmiron prescriptions in Norway from IMS Health</figDesc><table><row><cell>Year</cell><cell>Units</cell><cell>Reflect 3-months</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>treatment courses</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(180 capsules)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The Applicant has undertaken a comprehensive review of the literature published on the use of the product in IC/PBS and found between 158 and 209 publications especially from 1997 to 2014 in the different databases in Europe. The majority of publications were published in North America (86 publications over 158) and 32 publications were published in Europe. The latter are relevant for the demonstration of the degree of scientific interest in the EU. Based on these figures, the degree of scientific interest for PPS was at its maximum in2006-2008 (14-16  publications/ year) and it still</figDesc><table><row><cell>•</cell><cell>Pubmed database review identified 158 publications from 1978 (32 from Europe), toping to</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>~15/year in 2008 and ~3/year during last 3 years</cell></row><row><cell>•</cell><cell>German Institute of Medical Documentation and Information (DIMDI) database review</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>identified 209 publications and German National Library of Medicine (LIVIVO) database -197</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>publications.</cell></row></table><note>maintains a mean level of about 4-5 publications per year.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The batches of the medicinal product are identical to those proposed for marketing and were packed in the primary packaging proposed for marketing.Samples were tested for appearance, identification, dissolution, loss on drying, microbiological quality, impurities and assay. The analytical procedures used are stability indicating.At 25 °C / 60% RH and 30 °C / 75% RH, all results remained within the proposed specification limits.At 40 °C / 75% RH after 6 months storage, results were observed for batches packaged in blisters, which indicate that the blisters should not be stored above 30°C.An in-use stability study was performed. The results showed no significant changes and a 30 day in-use shelf-life after first opening of bottles is considered acceptable.Based on available stability data, the proposed shelf-life of 30 months for the bottle and 21 months for blister under storage conditions as stated in the SmPC (section 6.3) is acceptable. The bottles should be kept tightly closed in order to protect from moisture. After first opening the product should be used within 30 days. Blisters should not be stored above 30 ºC.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 23/115</cell></row></table><note>Stability data from 3 commercial scale batches of finished product stored under long term conditions at 25 ºC / 60% RH, under intermediate conditions at 30 ºC / 75% RH, and under accelerated conditions at 40 ºC / 75% RH according to the ICH guidelines were provided.In addition, bulk capsules, capsules packed in bottles and capsules packed in blisters were exposed to light as defined in the ICH Guideline on Photostability Testing of New Drug Substances and Products. No out of specification results were observed for any of the tested parameters, demonstrating that the finished product is photostable.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>s.c. or i.v. administration of doses between 50 and 100 mg. To evaluate the anticoagulant activity of PPS in vivo after different routes of administration the aPTT assay should be used; because of their low sensitivity to PPS TT and PT assays are not suitable and will indicate only a moderate anticoagulant activity of the drug. Comparative studies with PPS and UFH revealed that the overall anticoagulant efficacy of PPS both in vitro and in vivo after parenteral administration is lower than that of UFH.</figDesc><table><row><cell>The comparative measurement of in vitro anticoagulant activities of PPS and UFH demonstrated the</cell></row><row><cell>strong anticoagulant action of heparin and the relatively low effect of PPS what the Applicant</cell></row><row><cell>summarises in Table 1. Heparin clearly prolonged aPTT, TT and PT as well as inhibited thrombin and F</cell></row><row><cell>Xa activities to nearly the same degree. A direct comparison of the anticoagulant effectiveness</cell></row><row><cell>between PPS and UFH in vitro in rats and humans demonstrated an about 10 times stronger action of</cell></row><row><cell>UFH on the aPTT. Equieffective concentrations of PPS for the prolongation of TT were about 20-40</cell></row><row><cell>times higher than that for UFH. PT was least sensitive to both PPS and UFH; equieffective</cell></row><row><cell>concentrations were about 12 times higher for PPS than for UFH.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 6 Comparative anticoagulant actions of PPS and UFH in vitro in human plasma using common clotting assays. Concentrations required for nearly equieffective anticoagulant actions Assay PPS UFH Reference</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>aPTT</cell><cell>5.6 µg/ml</cell><cell>0.8 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Campbell et al. (1987)</cell></row><row><cell>TT</cell><cell>77.5 µg/ml</cell><cell>1.8 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Doctor et al. (1991)</cell></row><row><cell>PT</cell><cell>124 µg/ml</cell><cell>16 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>aPTT</cell><cell>10 µg/ml</cell><cell>1 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TT</cell><cell>100 µg/ml</cell><cell>5 µg/ml</cell><cell>Doctor and Sauls (1983)</cell></row><row><cell>PT</cell><cell>200 µg/ml</cell><cell>50 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PTT</cell><cell>12 µg/ml</cell><cell>2 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TT</cell><cell>75 µg/ml</cell><cell>2 µg/ml</cell><cell>Soria et al. (1980)</cell></row><row><cell>PT</cell><cell>24 µg/ml</cell><cell>2 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TT</cell><cell>20 µg/ml</cell><cell>1 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vinazzer et al. (1980)</cell></row><row><cell>aPTT</cell><cell>20 µg/ml</cell><cell>~ 15 µg/ml</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">After oral administration of 400 mg PPS (Fellström et al. 1987) or about 700 mg PPS (Marshall et al.</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">1997), maximum plasma concentrations in the range of 20-70 ng/ml were observed for unchanged</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">PPS. When total PPS-related radioactivity was assessed after oral administration of 300 mg PPS, Cmax</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">was 250 ng equivalents/ml. Therefore, even at these doses, which are much higher than the intended</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">clinical dose, the concentrations of unchanged PPS obtained in plasma were about 1000x lower than</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">those associated with anticoagulant effects. Even if all metabolites of PPS are taken into account, there</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">is still a safety factor of approximately 100.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Messmore et al. 1989 evaluated the effect of heparin on platelet functions in normal human plasma</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">and correlated this interaction to both the chemical properties such as molecular weight, degree of</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">sulfation, and the inhibitory activity against FXa, thrombin or both.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 8 : 2-year carcinogenicity studies</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Species/Sex/</cell><cell>Dose (mg/kg/d)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number/Group</cell><cell>/ Duration /Route</cell><cell>Major findings</cell></row><row><cell>Study ID/ GLP</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>aspects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>oral gavage once</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Rat F344/ 50/sex/grp</cell><cell>daily / 5 days /week for 104-105 weeks</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NTP 512 2004 / GLP</cell><cell>0, 14, 42 and 126 mg/kg/d (M)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>0, 28, 84 and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>252 mg/kg/d (F)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>PPS did not affect reproductive performance. Breeding parameters, fertility, or necropsy endpoints related to reproduction were not altered by the test substance. No differences were noted in epididymal sperm morphology, epididymal sperm density, sperm motility, testicular spermatid counts, or estrous cyclicity.In the Appendix H of the NTP Technical Report 512(2004), findings concerning the reproductive tissue and the estrous cycle characterization of rats and mice used in the 3-month gavage studies are summarized. Neither tissue weights (cauda epididymis, epididymis, testis), nor spermatid measurements/spermatid counts and spermatozoal motility nor evaluation of estrous cycle length (days) and estrus stages (diestrus, proestrus, estrus, metestrus) revealed statistically dose dependent differences related to the administration of the test substance.</figDesc><table><row><cell>study,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 33/115</cell></row></table><note>).F0 female and male body weights were unchanged. Body weights of the F 1 high dose group males and females were significantly decreased. Feed consumption values were unchanged. In this reproductive toxicity</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the ecotoxicity/environmental risk has been conducted by the Applicant. The PECsw was calculated considering the recommended daily dose of 300 mg/day, a Fpen value of 0.0002 which corresponds to the prevalence of interstitial cystitis supporting the Orphan designation of elmiron, and default WASTEWinhab and DILUTION values. The phase I Fpen exceeds the 0.01 µg/L threshold by a 3-fold factor. However, additional studies (phase II) are not considered as necessary since pentosan polysulfate sodium is a carbohydrate derivative which is viewed as unlikely to result in a significant risk to the environment. Although calculated Log Kow values are generally not acceptable</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>in silico a</cell><cell>-0.55</cell><cell>Potential PBT: N</cell></row><row><cell>K ow</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Phase I</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Calculation</cell><cell></cell><cell>Value</cell><cell>Unit</cell><cell>Conclusion</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">PEC surfacewater , default or</cell><cell>0.03</cell><cell>µg/L</cell><cell>&gt; 0.01 threshold</cell></row><row><cell>refined</cell><cell>(e.g.</cell><cell>prevalence,</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>literature)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Other concerns (e.g. chemical</cell><cell></cell><cell>No</cell></row><row><cell>class)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">An assessment of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>(EMA/CHMP/SWP/44609/2010), requesting an experimental determination of Log Kow is not viewed as necessary for the same reason in general. In addition, available data suggest that the Log Kow value of pentosan polysulfate would unlikely reach a value of concern.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Main studies with pharmacokinetic data for PPS and summary of the PK data B., L.Dencker and A. Tengblad (1987). "Preferential localization of 3Hpentosanpolysulphate to the urinary tract in rats." Pharmacology &amp; toxicology 61(3): 162-166. Absorption Fellström et al 1987 and Simon et al. 2005 both showed a very low bioavailability, around or less than 1%. In three-way crossover study of Faaij et al. (1999), 18 healthy male subjects received an i.v. bolus injection of 50 mg PPS, an oral dose of 1500 mg PPS, or placebo; oral bioavailability varied between -0.1 and 0.1% and did not differ from placebo. This conclusion was based in detection of PPS based on effect parameters (APTT and increase of anti-Xa activity as primary parameters. Simon et al., 2005 concluded that PPS was poorly absorbed (bioavailability &lt;1%) in healthy females. This conclusion was based in detection of intact PPS content in urine. In this clinical study healthy female subjects administered a single oral dose of [3H]PPS (200 µCi, &lt;15 mg) + 300 mg unlabelled PPS or [3H]PPS (300 µCi, &lt;15 mg) + 450 mg unlabelled PPS to generate samples containing higher concentration of radioactivity in plasma, urine and faeces for metabolic profiling analysis.Excretion and mass balance in urine and faeces for the low dose group: the total recovery of radioactivity in 200 µCi dose group after 120 h was 90.43% ± 8.10% (range 73.22-97.89%):</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell></row></table><note>polysulphate (Elmiron): pharmacokinetics and effects on the urinary inhibition of crystal growth." • Forestier, F., A. M. Fischer, F. Daffos, S. Beguin and H. Diner (1986). "Absence of transplacental passage of pentosan polysulfate during mid-trimester of pregnancy.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>The author states that it is unclear why patients with IC have these gastrointestinal diseases or disorders more frequently than the general population, apart from similar abnormalities in the movement of the smooth muscle tissue, the type of inflammation process and the occurrence of ulcers.The Applicant found an exception in the Marshall et al., 1997 clinical study involving 21 patients with metastatic advanced cancer. Patients were treated with PPS three times per day in cohorts at planned doses of 180, 270, 400, 600 and 800 mg/m 2 body surface in the continuous highest oral dose administered up to almost 2000 mg PPS daily over up to two months. PPS did not cause significant systemic adverse events, but 20 out of total of 21 patients developed moderate to severe gastrointestinal adverse events within 1-2 months at doses of 400mg/m 2 TID.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Prevalence (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Diagnosis</cell><cell>IC</cell><cell>General</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>population</cell></row><row><cell>Allergy</cell><cell>41-47</cell><cell>22.5</cell></row><row><cell>Irritable bowel syndrome</cell><cell>25.4</cell><cell>2.9</cell></row><row><cell>Sensitive skin</cell><cell>22.6</cell><cell>10.6</cell></row><row><cell>Vulvodynia</cell><cell>10.9</cell><cell>15.0</cell></row><row><cell>Fibromyalgia</cell><cell>12.8</cell><cell>3.2</cell></row><row><cell>Chronic fatigue syndrome</cell><cell>7.7</cell><cell>8.5</cell></row><row><cell>Migraine</cell><cell>18.8</cell><cell>18.0</cell></row><row><cell>Asthma</cell><cell>9.2</cell><cell>6.1</cell></row><row><cell>Crohn's disease/ulcerative colitis</cell><cell>7.3</cell><cell>0.07</cell></row><row><cell>Thyroid disease</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>?</cell></row><row><cell>Rheumatoid arthritis</cell><cell>4-13</cell><cell>1-2</cell></row><row><cell>Systemic lupus erythematosus</cell><cell>1.7</cell><cell>0.05</cell></row><row><cell>Sjögren's syndrome</cell><cell>8.0</cell><cell>0.5</cell></row></table><note>Overview of associated disorders in IC patients (van de Merwe, 2006)Gastrointestinal disorders as part of IC were stressed likewise by Jocham et al., 2013. Investigating the care situation of patients with IC in Germany he found that 4.81% of the patients reported gastrointestinal problems as symptoms associated with IC.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head>Table 10 ESSIC classification of types of BPS according to the results of cystoscopy with hydrodistension and biopsies</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>a Cystoscopy: glomerulations grade 2-3; b Lesion per Fall's definition with/without glomerulations; c</cell></row><row><cell>Histology showing inflammatory infiltrates and/or detrusor mastocytosis and/or granulation tissue</cell></row><row><cell>and/or intrafascicular fibrosis.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Inclusion criteria as defined in the six pivotal, placebo-controlled studies Assessment report EMA/287422/2017 Page 58/115 Patients meeting the ESSIC classification 2X to 3C (characterized by either glomerulations or Hunner's lesions were included in four pivotal studies (Parsons and Mulholland 1987, Mulholland et al 1990, Parsons et al 1993 and Sant et al 2003).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Table 12 : Dose regimens used in pivotal studies</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987</cell><cell>2x200 mg</cell></row><row><cell>Parsons and Mulholland, 1987</cell><cell>2x200 mg, 3x100 mg</cell></row><row><cell>Mulholland et al., 1990</cell><cell>3x100 mg</cell></row><row><cell>Parsons et al., 1993</cell><cell>3x100 mg</cell></row><row><cell>Sant et al., 2003</cell><cell>3x100 mg</cell></row><row><cell>Nickel et al., 2015</cell><cell>3x100 mg</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 13 : Efficacy endpoints of the 6 pivotal, placebo-controlled studies</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Study</cell><cell cols="2">Efficacy endpoints</cell></row><row><cell>Holm-Bentzen et al.,</cell><cell cols="2">Efficacy endpoints:</cell></row><row><cell>1987</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Symptom evaluation (pain, frequency, nocturia and dysuria)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>including total symptom score (pre-defined threshold for clinical</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Relevance: improvement of at least 1,0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Cystometric first sensation and bladder capacity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Cystoscopic appearance</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Cystoscopic maximal bladder capacity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>-</cell><cell>Mast Cell Count</cell></row><row><cell>Parsons and</cell><cell cols="2">Symptom evaluation (urgency, frequency, nocturia and pain) 50 %</cell></row><row><cell>Mulholland, 1987</cell><cell cols="2">improvement per symptom; no overall evaluation</cell></row><row><cell>Mulholland et al.,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 14 Patient characteristics at baseline</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc>The US-study reported by Parsons et al., 1993 enrolled 74 patients in each group, all of whom had documented IC of at least 1 year in duration. The mean age was 42.7 years in the PPS group and 45.5 years in the placebo group. All patients in the PPS group were female and 93% of the placebo-treated patients were female. The vast majority of patients were Caucasians (97% in the PPS group and 96%</figDesc><table><row><cell>"patients'</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_36"><head>Table 15 Patient characteristics at baseline</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>and enrolled 4</cell></row></table><note>There were no significant differences between the treatment groups at baseline in terms of age, sex, distribution, race, duration of disease, cystoscopic findings or bladder capacity.5) The factorial design study reported by Sant et al., 2003 was conducted in the US</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_37"><head>Table 16 Baseline patient characteristics by treatment group</head><label>16</label><figDesc>The latest study reported by Nickel et al., 2015 enrolled 122 patients in the US (mean age 42.7 ± 15.71; 92.6% females, 84.4% Caucasians) in the PPS 300 mg group, 128 patients (mean age 45.6 ± 15.73; 92.2% females, 84.4% Caucasians) in the PPS 100 mg group, and 118 patients (mean age 44.6 ± 14.58; 85.6% females, 87.3% Caucasians) in the placebo group.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_38"><head>Table 17 ITT data set demographic and baseline characteristics, efficacy at study end points and treatment emergent adverse events in 5% or more of patients</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_39"><head>Table 20 Efficacy results on secondary endpoints</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_40"><head>Table 21 Efficacy results on all endpoints (all patients treated with PPS versus patients not treated with PPS.</head><label>21</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>, slightly improved</cell></row></table><note>6) In Nickel et al 2015, for secondary efficacy evaluations, the patients enrolled in this study rated average pain intensity during the previous 3 days using an 11-point numerical rating scale.Furthermore, two other Patient-reported outcome questionnaires were used in this study: -The Patient's Overall Rating of Symptoms Score (PORIS) questionnaire including a total of three questions, one for pain, urgency and overall change. The three questions address the overall change in IC, pain, and urgency after treatment as worse, no better (0% improvement)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head>Table 22 Efficacy results on all endpoints for the placebo and PPS 300 mg groups.</head><label>22</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head>Table 23 Primary Efficacy results from pivotal studies Study / IC definition Primary effect vs pbo Supportive effects vs pbo Comment</head><label>23</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1. Holm-Bentzen et</cell><cell>Not different from pbo</cell><cell>Increased median MBC</cell><cell>Predominantly</cell></row><row><cell>al., 1987</cell><cell>(based on EP: symptom</cell><cell>(260 -&gt; 475 ml vs ~300</cell><cell>negative study,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>evaluations (pain, frequency,</cell><cell>-&gt; 290 ml, p&lt;0.05)</cell><cell>results might be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>nocturia and dysuria)</cell><cell></cell><cell>contaminated by</cell></row><row><cell>(European Study)</cell><cell>including total symptom</cell><cell></cell><cell>broad IC definition</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>score (pre-defined threshold</cell><cell>No difference in other</cell><cell>(interpretation)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>for clinical Relevance:</cell><cell>EP (Cystometric first</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IC: part of IC/BPS</cell><cell>improvement of at least 1,0)</cell><cell>sensation and bladder</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>capacity and Mast Cell</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Count)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Parsons and</cell><cell>Pain:</cell><cell>Statistically significant</cell><cell>Predominantly</cell></row><row><cell>Mulholland, 1987</cell><cell>RxA: 44 vs 15%, p=0.02</cell><cell>mean % improvement for all 4 symptoms</cell><cell>positive study Response: 50 %</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RxA+B: 45 vs 18%, p=0.02</cell><cell></cell><cell>improvement per</cell></row><row><cell>(US Study)</cell><cell>Urgency:</cell><cell></cell><cell>symptom;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RxA: 38 vs 18, p=0.08</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IC</cell><cell>RxA+B: 50 vs 19% p=0.03</cell><cell></cell><cell>No overall evaluation; patient</cell></row><row><cell>Falling within ESSIC</cell><cell>Frequency:</cell><cell></cell><cell>flow chart (A vs B vs</cell></row><row><cell>classification 2X to 3C</cell><cell>RxA: 65 vs 42%, p=0.06</cell><cell></cell><cell>A+B) is not clear; statistical</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>RxA+B 63 vs 39%, p=0.005</cell><cell></cell><cell>inconsistency in</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Rx(A) vs Rx(A+B)</cell></row></table><note>MBC: maximal bladder capacity; GRA: global response assesment; ICSI: O'Leary-Sant Interstitial Cystitis Symptoms Index; IRA: investigator RA; N/A: not available; n.s.: not significant; PORIS: Patient's Overall Rating of Improvement of Symptoms; Pbo: Placebo; PRA: patient RA; PRO:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_45"><head>Table 26 Sensitivity analysis, ITT, Global response assessment Table 27 Sensitivity analysis, as reported, Global response assessment</head><label>26</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_46"><head>Table 28 0% to 13.3%</head><label>28</label><figDesc>The applicant provided a further meta-analysis which took into consideration the results of the post Hoc analysis of Nickel et al study in the subgroup of patients with IC (2X to 3C according to the ESSIC classification). Compared to the sensitivity analysis including only the four pivotal studies, which included the pre-defined homogeneous patient population of patients falling within ESSIC classification 2X to 3C, the estimated benefit difference in success rates has decreased from 17.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Responder rates per treatment arm (six pivotal studies)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PPS</cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>(95% CI)</cell></row><row><cell>GRA</cell><cell>33,0%</cell><cell>19.3%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(28.6% -37.7%)</cell><cell>(13.9% -26.3%)</cell></row><row><cell>Pain</cell><cell>36.7%</cell><cell>21.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(31.4% -42.3%)</cell><cell>(11.6% -36.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Urgency</cell><cell>31.3%</cell><cell>18.4%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(23.0% -41.0%)</cell><cell>(8.6% -35.3%)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Table 29 Responder rates per treatment arm (four pivotal studies)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PPS</cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>(95% CI)</cell></row><row><cell>GRA</cell><cell>33.0%</cell><cell>15.8%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(27.1% -39.4%)</cell><cell>(11.6% -21.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Pain</cell><cell>32.7%</cell><cell>14.2%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(26.0% -40.3%)</cell><cell>(9.6% -20.6%)</cell></row><row><cell>Urgency</cell><cell>27.4%</cell><cell>14.2%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(21.1% -34.8%)</cell><cell>(9.6% -20.6%)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_47"><head>Table 30 Meta-analysis: incl Nickel et al subgroup ITT. Global response assessment (ICSI for Nickel et al 2015)</head><label>30</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_48"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>but not in Sant et al., 2003 study and the studies using less specific IC definition (IC/BPS) as it was in the Holm-Bentzen et al., 1987 study and in the most recent Nickel et al., 2015 study. TheHowever, interpretation of the data from the Nickel study is difficult given the severe limitations with regards to difficulties in patient enrolment, early termination, study design, enrolment of patients previously treated with PPS, severe recruitment problems and high dropout rates used for the analysis of efficacy.Regarding the most pronounced and unexpected outcome of the post-hoc subgroup analysis reported by Nickel et al., 2015 the response rate of 50% in the placebo subgroup based on a 30% ICSI score improvement, such high placebo response rate was not observed in any other pivotal study and has to be taken as a clear indication for the multifactorial biases impacting the study results (patients with</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">milder IC entering during a symptom flare, regression to the mean, introduction (inadvertent or not) of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">conservative therapy, which accentuated the benefits of placebo, and failure of clinical sites to keep</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">patients in the trial). It should be noted that a high placebo response rate was also observed in the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">whole study: 40.7% (versus 39.8% for patients treated with 100 mgX1/day and 42.6% in those</cell></row><row><cell>treated with 100mgX3/day) at 24 weeks.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">To justify the abnormal high placebo response rate, the applicant provided the results of 2 other</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">placebo-controlled studies performed in patients with IC (2X to 3C) diagnosed with cystoscopy and the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">response rates of the patients treated with placebo are about 12% (Warren et al., 2000) and 16% (van</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Ophoven et al., 2004) which correspond to the placebo response rates of the other pivotal studies</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(12.5-17.7%). Therefore, it can be concluded that the severe limitations of the study published by</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Nickel and colleagues in 2015, could have impacted the validity and usability of the study results</cell></row><row><cell>overall.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">response rate of a subgroup of patients with IC (2X to 3C) included in a post-HOC analysis in Nickel et</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">al study were better for placebo (50%) than PPS 100 mg/day (30.3%), 100 mg x3/ day (34.5%).</cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 92/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_50"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Hair-thinning/alopecia are known adverse reactions associated with heparin treatment and it is thus not surprising to have these AEs described with PPS. Headache is reported with a frequency of 11.5% in the Nickel study(2015), 2.9% in the Hanno study and 2% in the Mulholland study. Rectal bleeding is reported with a frequency of 4 % in the Nickel study(2005). Bleeding events as rectal bleeding are related to the heparin-like structure of PPS.Overall, hair-thinning/hair loss/alopecia and gastro-intestinal disorders (e.g. diarrhea, abdominal cramping, nausea and dyspepsia) were the most frequently reported adverse reactions with PPS in the literature.No treatment-related SAEs were reported in the clinical studies with PPS capsules. PPS is a highly sulfated glycosaminoglycan comparable to heparin and systemically available PPS has relevant anticoagulant activity. Some cases of thrombocytopenia occurring during parenteral PPS treatment and mimicking the heparin-induced thrombocytopenia syndrome have been reported, especially in the French literature (Tardy-Poncet et al., 1994), thus any potential effects of oral PPS treatment on the coagulation system would be considered as an AE of special interest. The case of a 28-year old patient with Interstitial Cystitis was reported by Strohmaier et al. (1987) in the context of the evaluation of glycosaminoglycan excretion. This patient received 750 mg/day PPS in order to increase the glycosaminoglycan excretion, which was reduced based on his underlying disease. The patient developed haematomas spontaneously and macrohaematuria. No further information is provided. Given the weak anticoagulant effect of PPS, PPS could have favored the apparition of haematoma in two published cases of serious AEs: -An epidural hematoma reported in a woman receiving lumbar epidural steroid injection (Siddiqui et al.2001). In addition to PPS, the woman was treated with 300 mg gabapentin three times a day and 25 mg amitriptyline orally at night. The authors concluded, that this patient's epidural haematoma was related to either PPS or it might have been a direct consequence of multiple needle punctures. However, the Applicant explained that an extensive epidural haematoma that leads to neurologic symptoms is unlikely to arise from needle trauma alone. An interaction in section 4.5 was also added : "Due to the weak anticoagulant effect of pentosan polpysulfate sodium, patients, who are concomitantly treated with coumarin anticoagulants, heparin, t-PA, streptokinase, high dose aspirin, or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs should be evaluated for hemorrhage." A single case report of cerebral sagittal thrombosis after oral administration of PPS for the treatment of Interstitial Cystitis was reported in scientific literature (Rice et al., 1998): the patient received a low dose oestrogen as oral contraceptive and it is known that thrombotic risk is higher during the first year of contraceptive use, however the treatment was introduced for a long time at the time of the event (8 years). On the contrary, PPS was only introduced for 3 weeks at the time of the event. No information on decreased platelet counts is available as an indication for thrombocytopenia (blood counts only have been evaluated 2-weeks after stopping PPS administration and were normal). A modest titer anti-heparin platelet factor 4 antibody was found but the relevance and sensitivity of this ELISA test for PPS-induced antibodies is questionable. PPS-induced thrombocytopenia comparable to heparin-induced thrombocytopenia cannot be excluded. It should be noted that some cases of thrombocytopenia occurring during parenteral PPS treatment and mimicking the heparin-induced thrombocytopenia have been reported. Deaths 7 deaths were reported in a long-term, open-label study (Hanno et al. 1997), considered as not related to study medication. 3 deaths were reported in the study published by Jepsen et al. (1998), considered</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">streptokinase, high dose acetylsalicylic acid, or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medicinal products)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">should be evaluated for hemorrhage".</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Serious adverse event/deaths/other significant events</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Serious adverse events</cell></row><row><cell>-</cell><cell cols="2">A neck hematoma reported in a woman after an attempted internal jugular catheter insertion</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(Gill et al. 2002) and oral administration of PPS in doses of 3x300 mg PPS per day for at least 4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>months.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">No alteration of coagulation parameters have been reported in a small PD study on 18 healthy</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">volunteers after administration of oral doses of 1500 mg PPS.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">As limited information is available on use in patients concomitantly using anticoagulants, undergoing</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">invasive procedures or in patients with increased risk of bleeding, these patients should be evaluated</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">carefully for hemorrhage when taking PPS. Therefore, the applicant added:</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">-a contra-indication in section 4.3 of the SmPC: "due to the weak anticoagulant effect of pentosan</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">polysulfate sodium, Elmiron must not be used in patients who actively bleed. Menstruation is no</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">contraindication" and</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">-a warning in section 4.4 of the SmPC: "Pentosan polysulfate sodium is a weak anticoagulant. Patients</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">undergoing invasive procedures or having signs/symptoms of underlying coagulopathy or other</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">increased risk of bleeding (due to other therapies such as coumarin anticoagulants, heparin, t-PA,</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Assessment report</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 98/115</cell></row></table><note>-</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_51"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Forestier et al., 1986). The data generated in this study provide no indication of trans-placental passage of PPS.Since no further data from clinical studies with PPS in pregnant or nursing women are available, the Summary of Product Characteristics (SmPC) states that PPS capsules should not be used during pregnancy or lactation unless clearly necessary.</figDesc><table><row><cell>trans placental passage of PPS (</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 101/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_52"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Drug-drug interactions between PPS and warfarin were evaluated in an open-label study(Modi et al.   2005). PK parameters of warfarin and INR were similar in the absence and presence of PPS. Pentosan polysulfate sodium is a weak anticoagulant. Patients undergoing invasive procedures or having signs/symptoms of underlying coagulopathy or other increased risk of bleeding (due to treatment with other medicinal products influencing coagulation such as anticoagulants, heparin derivatives, thrombolytic or antiplatelet agents including acetylsalicylic acid, or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory medicinal products should be evaluated for haemorrhagic events. Patients who have a history of heparin or pentosan polysulfate sodium induced thrombocytopenia should be carefully monitored when treated with pentosan polysulfate sodium. This is reflected in a warning in section 4.5 of the SmPC, with a cross-reference to section 4.4.Discontinuation due to adverse events.Holm-Bentzen et al.(1987)  reported that 2 patients in protocol A stopped the medication because of headache, nausea and dizziness and in protocol B one patient stopped medication because of a skin rash after 2 weeks and another one stopped because of aggravation of bladder symptoms. No information is provided, whether these patients stopping medication during the study were treated with PPS or placebo. Out of the 87 patients enrolled in study published byFritjofsson et al. (1987), 7 patients terminated treatment early due to AEs (2 patients due to swollen legs and gastrointestinal distress, respectively; urinary infection in one, dysphagia in one, anaemia in one).In the report ofParsons et al. (1993), 3 patients in the PPS group and 5 patients in the placebo group discontinued treatment due to AEs. In the compassionate use study reported by Jepsen et al.,(1998)    16/97 patients stopped taking PPS due to AEs. The majority of those (81.6%) stopped therapy during the first 6 months.Waters et al. (2000)  reported about the retrospective analysis in 27 patients treated with PPS for at least 8 weeks; 4 patients (15%) stopped taking PPS because of side effects including diarrhoea, abdominal cramping, nausea, hair thinning. Symptoms worsened in 2 patients (9%) of the patients, forcing discontinuance. In the study reported bySant et al. (2003), a total of 10 patients (8%) withdrew from study due to adverse events.Nickel et al. (2005)  reported that in the study evaluating daily oral administration of 300, 600 and 900 mg PPS for up to 32 weeks, 150 patients (39.5%) discontinued treatment before the end of this study. Of them, 22.4% did so because of AEs (primarily diarrhoea and abdominal pain). AEs were the reason for discontinuation of treatment in 18%, 16.8%, and 30.7% of patients taking 300, 600, and 900 mg PPS, respectively, and this was dose dependent (p&lt;0.05). In the study reported byNickel et al. (2015), AEs, which were mostly gastrointestinal, led to the withdrawal of 12 patients (10.2%) in the placebo group, 17 (13.3%) in the PPS 100 mg group and 14 (11.5%) in the PPS 300mg group. The applicant provided safety findings for discontinuations due to AEs for separate studies but without critical cumulative review. In particular, they are related to rather limited local GI tolerance. In one of the studies(Nickel et al   2005), these AEs were dose dependent.</figDesc><table><row><cell>dose-ranging</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 102/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_53"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Bleeding events as rectal bleeding are considered to be related to the heparin-like structure of PPS.Several cases of serious bleeding AEs with PPS have been published in the literature: one case of epidural hematoma, one case of neck hematoma, one case of hematomas (location not specified). For two cases, a needle trauma was reported (steroid epidural injection and venous jugular catheter insertion) and PPS might have favoured the occurrence of bleeding as PPS has a weak anticoagulant effect (heparin-like substance).</figDesc><table><row><cell>literature.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 103/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_54"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The most common adverse events reported from the clinical studies are headache, dizziness and gastro-intestinal events like diarrhoea, nausea, abdominal pain and rectal bleeding.Cases of serious bleeding AEs with PPS have been published in the literature: one case of epidural hematoma, one case of neck hematoma, one case of hematomas (location not specified). For two cases, a needle trauma was reported (steroid epidural injection and venous jugular catheter insertion) and PPS might have favoured the occurrence of bleeding as PPS has a weak anticoagulant effect (heparin-like substance).It was therefore concluded that due to the heparin-like structure of PPS, a weak anticoagulant effect might be observed with PPS and patients with risk factors for increased bleeding (undergoing invasive procedures, having underlying coagulopathy or taking anticoagulants) should be carefully evaluated for haemorrhage during the treatment as it is mentioned in section 4.4 of the SmPC. Furthermore PPS-</figDesc><table><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell>Page 110/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_55"><head>Table Eff ect Short Description Unit Treatm ent Cont rol Uncertainties/ Strength of evidence</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_56"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Furthermore, there are no pharmaceutical treatment alternatives. Indeed, no drug treatment is currently authorized in this indication in Europe. The relatively benign safety profile is considered appropriately addressed by routine risk minimization measures.The term BPS rather than interstitial cystitis (IC) was put forward by the International Society for the Study of BPS (ESSIC) and is currently used in the guidelines and by the experts.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>PPS</cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell>GRA</cell><cell>33,0%</cell><cell>15.8%</cell></row><row><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>(27.1% -39.4%)</cell><cell>(11.6% -21.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Pain</cell><cell>32.7%</cell><cell>14.2%</cell></row><row><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>(26.0% -40.3%)</cell><cell>(9.6% -20.6%)</cell></row><row><cell>Urgency</cell><cell>27.4%</cell><cell>14.2%</cell></row><row><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>(21.1% -34.8%)</cell><cell>(9.6% -20.6%)</cell></row><row><cell>Assessment report</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>EMA/287422/2017</cell><cell></cell><cell>Page 114/115</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Assessment report EMA/287422/2017Page 70/115</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Not applicable.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.7.">Risk Management Plan</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacovigilance plan</head><p>Not applicable, as no additional pharmacovigilance activities are proposed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk minimisation measures</head><p>Safety concern Routine risk minimisation measures Additional risk minimisation </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety concern</head><p>Routine risk minimisation measures Additional risk minimisation measures dose aspirin, or nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drugs) should be evaluated for hemorrhage. Caution should be exercised when using pentosan polysulfate sodium in patients who have a history of heparin or pentosan polysulfate induced thrombocytopenia. Missing information: Use in male patients None proposed, as there is no reason to expect a specific safety profile in men, as an impact on the male reproductive system is not expected. The only gender specific adverse event reported from clinical studies is "strong menstrual bleeding" None proposed</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conclusion</head><p>The CHMP and PRAC considered that the risk management plan version 05 is acceptable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.8.">Pharmacovigilance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacovigilance system</head><p>The CHMP considered that the pharmacovigilance system summary submitted by the applicant fulfils the requirements of Article 8(3) of Directive 2001/83/EC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.">Product information</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.9.1.">User consultation</head><p>The results of the user consultation with target patient groups on the package leaflet submitted by the applicant show that the package leaflet meets the criteria for readability as set out in the Guideline on the readability of the label and package leaflet of medicinal products for human use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Benefit-Risk Balance</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Therapeutic Context</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.1.">Disease or condition</head><p>Interstitital Cystitis (IC) is a chronic, debilitating disorder, distressing bladder condition, which is characterised by pelvic pain associated with bladder filling, pollakiuria with a voiding frequency of more than eight urinations per day and more than two urinations per night, cystoscopic lesions (petechiae, Hunner's ulcers) revealed by a bladder hydrodistention test, and/or histological anomalies such as inflammatory mononuclear cell infiltrates and tissue granulation, in the absence of infection or any • Whenever the risk management system is modified, especially as the result of new information being received that may lead to a significant change to the benefit/risk profile or as the result of an important (pharmacovigilance or risk minimisation) milestone being reached.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>References</head><p>Conditions or restrictions with regard to the safe and effective use of the medicinal product to be implemented by the Member States.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessment report EMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="104" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessment report EMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="106" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessment report EMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Assessment report EMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="113" to="115" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
