<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>1 Recommendations/Risk Benefit Assessment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Recommendation on Regulatory Action</head><p>The subcutaneous formulation of canakinumab (ILARIS) was originally approved in 2009 for the treatment of adults and children older than 4 years of age with cyropyrin-associated periodic syndromes (CAPS), and approval of canakinumab for the treatment of children with systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis (SJIA) occurred in 2013. The current application is seeking approval of canakinumab doses, depending on the weight and response of a given patient, of 2 mg/kg to 300 mg administered by subcutaneous injection every four weeks to treat adults and children with Familial Mediterranean Fever in whom colchicine is contraindicated, is not tolerated, or does not provide an adequate response (crFMF), Hyperimmunoglobulin D Syndrome (HIDS)/Mevalonate Kinase Deficiency (MKD), and Tumor Necrosis Factor Receptor Associated Periodic Syndrome (TRAPS).</p><p>The primary efficacy data derives from the phase 3 study CACZ885N2301 (N2301). Study N2301 was a four-part study, consisting of a screening period (Epoch 1), a 16-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment phase (Epoch 2) comparing a single dose of canakinumab 150 mg (2 mg/kg if ≤ 40 kg) versus placebo in children with active crFMF (63 subjects), HIDS/MKD (72 subjects), or TRAPS (46 subjects), a 24-week randomized withdrawal phase (Epoch 3) with subjects re-randomized to placebo or canakinumab 150 mg q 8 weeks, and a 72-week open-label treatment phase (Epoch 4). The study was adequately designed and conducted to allow for an interpretation of the effect of canakinumab in patients with crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS.</p><p>Review of the data from Study N2301 demonstrated that the study met the pre-specified primary endpoint, with a greater proportion of canakinumab-treated subjects achieving resolution of their index flare (Physician Global Assessment (PGA) &lt; 2, and C-reactive protein (CRP) ≤ 10 mg/L or reduction ≥ 70% from baseline) at Day 15 and who did not experience a new flare (PGA ≥ 2 and CRP ≥ 30 mg/L) from the time of resolution of the index flare until the end of Epoch 2 compared to placebo-treated subjects (respectively, 61% versus 6% for crFMF, 35% versus 6% for HIDS/MKD, and 45% versus 8% for TRAPS). In addition, more subjects in the canakinumab group resolved their index flare at Day 15 compared with placebo (81% versus 31% for crFMF, 65% versus 37% for HIDS/MKD, and 64% versus 21% for TRAPS).</p><p>The data were further supported by subgroup and sensitivity analyses, as testing of major secondary endpoints, which all showed that for PGA &lt; 2 and CRP ≤ 10, canakinumab was superior to placebo for all three conditions; for serum amyloid A (SAA) ≤ 10, improvement was observed in all three conditions, but statistical significance only reached in TRAPS subjects.</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS <ref type="bibr">(canakinumab)</ref> 8</p><p>While the data demonstrated the efficacy of canakinumab in subjects with active crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS, as measured by responder rate, PGA, and inflammatory markers, given that most placebo subjects switched to canakinumab and some patients required up-titration as early as Day 8, the comparison between canakinumab and placebo is difficult to interpret. Nonetheless, the indications studied are orphan in nature, without treatments that are consistently beneficial to the patients affected, and canakinumab does offer, based on the efficacy data under review thus far (Epoch 2), an option that these individuals do not currently have.</p><p>Supportive data were contributed by four proof-of-concept (PoC) phase 2 studies in subjects with crFMF (Study CACZ885N2301and Study CACZ885D2204), HIDS/MKD (Study CACZ885D2402), and TRAPS (Study CACZ885D2203). Available safety data from the ongoing Epoch 3 and Epoch 4 of Study N2301 are pooled with safety data from Epoch 2 to provide safety information for longer term treatment (Study N2301 Epochs 2 -4 dataset). In addition, pooled safety data from five completed phase 2 and 3 studies in subjects with CAPS were included to further support the safety profile for canakinumab in the group of periodic fever syndromes.</p><p>The data were sufficient to provide an adequate amount of drug exposure for evaluation of the safety of canakinumab in the crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS populations. Review of the data did not identify any new safety signals and the overall safety profile of canakinumab in children and adults with these three conditions appears to provide an acceptable degree of risk given the severity of the disease and the demonstrated efficacy of canakinumab.</p><p>Based on my review of the clinical data as a whole, I recommend approval of subcutaneously administered canakinumab at the doses proposed for the treatment of FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS in children and adults.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk Benefit Assessment</head><p>The risk-benefit assessment of canakinumab at dosages of 2 mg/kg to 300 mg subcutaneously administered every four weeks weeks for the treatment of crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS is in favor of approval for the current application given the magnitude of the clinically meaningful responses observed in the randomized controlled trial and the overall safety profile of canakinumab in the crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS populations. Approval of canakinumab will provide an additional efficacious therapy for patients who have active crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies</head><p>There are no current clinical recommendations for postmarketing risk evaluation and mitigation strategies for canakinumab in patients with crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS.</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 10 reactive protein (CRP), serum amyloid A (SAA), fibrinogen), an elevated erythrocyte sedimentation rate (ESR), and leukocytosis. Febrile episodes and associated symptoms in patients with these diseases can have a notable effect on quality of life (QoL), affecting school, work and interpersonal relationships. Although the inflammatory attacks cause much morbidity and significantly decreases the QoL of patients, the major source of mortality and most serious complication in patients with FMF, HIDS/MKD or TRAPS is represented by progressive secondary amyloidosis that may develop over several years and can progress to chronic kidney disease with subsequent renal failure. Renal amyloidosis is observed in up to 60% of untreated FMF patients, up to 25% of TRAPS patients, and in &lt;10% of HIDS/MKD patients.</p><p>FMF is an autosomal recessive disease that affects mainly people of Mediterranean ancestry. Approximately 90% of patients with FMF experience the onset of disease before the age of 20 years. FMF is characterized by short febrile attacks caused by neutrophil-induced serosal inflammation and a gradual accumulation of amyloid in the kidneys. These febrile attacks are associated with pain in the abdomen, chest, joints, muscles, scrotum, and/or skin. Colchicine is effective in preventing attacks, as well as preventing the development of amyloidosis; however, some patients do not experience sufficient relief with colchicine or have problematic side effects.</p><p>HIDS/MKD is an autosomal recessive disorder which is characterized by febrile attacks that last 3 to 7 days, and occur every 4 to 6 weeks. These attacks are often associated with abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, headache, polyarthralgia, non-destructive arthritis, and/or skin lesions. HIDS, originally named based on the high serum levels of immunoglobulin D (IgD) in the first cases described, is caused by mutations in the gene encoding mevalonate kinase, a critical enzyme acting early in the isoprenoid pathway. Therefore, HIDS is also referred to as MKD and the two terms are often used interchangeably. This clinical overview consistently uses the terminology 'HIDS/MKD' to follow the current consensus among specialists to use HIDS for the phenotype of fever episodes and MKD as the overall disease name. No specific treatment exists. Corticosteroids have been used to treat some individuals; but such therapy has been noted to increase the frequency of febrile attacks in some individuals.</p><p>TRAPS is an autosomal dominant disorder that affects mostly people of northern European descent. The median age of onset is 3 years. TRAPS is characterized by febrile attacks that tend to last longer than those of FMF or HIDS. These attacks are associated with abdominal pain, severe myalgia, and painful erythema on the trunk or extremities. An estimated 14% to 25% of TRAPS patients develop reactive amyloidosis. Treatment with non-steroidal antiinflammatory drug (NSAIDs) or glucocorticoids can reduce the severity of symptoms but does not affect the frequency of febrile attacks.</p><p>The scientific rationale for the use of canakinumab to treat FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS rests on the knowledge that: 1. IL-1β is the key mediator of inflammation in all the classical periodic fever syndromes. 2. The identified genes which are mutated in FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS lead to altered protein which activates IL-1β secretion and causes inflammation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>11</head><p>Canakinumab was designed to specifically inhibit IL-1β without interfering with other pathways of IL-1 signaling, such as interleukin-1α (IL-1α). Thus, canakinumab represents a targeted therapy against the inflammatory process in FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS, and may represent a potential new therapy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Product Information</head><p>Canakinumab (ACZ885; ILARIS®) is a high-affinity fully human monoclonal anti-human interleukin-1β (IL-1β) antibody of the IgG1/κ isotype. IL-1β is a key mediator of the inflammatory response. Increased production of IL-1β has been shown to cause a number of autoinflammatory conditions. Canakinumab binds to human IL-1β, blocking the interaction of this cytokine to its receptors and functionally neutralizing the bioactivity of this cytokine.</p><p>Canakinumab is currently approved in more than 70 countries, including the United States (US) and European Union (EU), for the treatment of cryopyrin-associated periodic syndromes (CAPS) and systemic juvenile idiopathic arthritis (SJIA) in adults and children. The doses and regimens approved for these auto-inflammatory conditions vary by region, with weight-based dosing employed for patients with low body weight from 7.5 to 40 kg. The highest dose approved is 600 mg or 8 mg/kg administered as a subcutaneous (sc) injection every 8 weeks (q8w). Canakinumab is also approved to treat acute gouty arthritis attacks in the EU and other countries at a dose of 150 mg administered as a subcutaneous injection soon after the onset of an attack.</p><p>The current application is seeking approval of canakinumab doses of 2 mg/kg to 300 mg administered by subcutaneous injection every four weeks to treat children and adults 2 years of age and older with colchicine-resistant/intolerant crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Currently Available Treatments for Proposed Indications</head><p>To date, there are no approved therapies for crFMF, HIDS/MKD or TRAPS. As discussed above, certain medications have been used to treat the symptoms of these periodic fever syndromes, but these provide limited control over the relapsing febrile attacks and none treat the underlying inflammation.</p><p>For patients with FMF, colchicine has shown to be effective in controlling febrile attacks and preventing secondary amyloidosis. However, 5% of FMF patients are intolerant to colchicine because of side effects. Additionally, 5-10% of FMF patients do not respond to colchicine treatment at all. This group of crFMF patients who do not respond to or are intolerant to colchicine has very few, if any, treatment options.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>12</head><p>And while there are agents approved for the treatment of the periodic fever syndromes known as CAPS (the specific labeled indications being Familial Cold Auto-Inflammatory Syndrome (FCAS) and Muckle-Wells Syndrome (MWS) for rilonacept and canakinumab, and Neonatal-Onset Multisystem Inflammatory Disease (NOMID) for anakinra), there is no therapy supported by data from randomized, well-controlled clinical trials for patients with HIDS/MKD or TRAPS., Thus, there is a significant unmet medical need.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Availability of Proposed Active Ingredient in the United States</head><p>ILARIS is commercially available in the United States. It is supplied in a sterile, single-use 6ml, glass vial containing 180 mg of drug product as a lyophilized powder for reconstitution. Subcutaneous injection of canakinumab is approved for the treatment of adults and children 4 years of age or older with CAPS at doses of 150 mg for patients weighing &gt;40 kg or 2 mg/kg for patients weighing 15 kg to ≤40 kg, and adults and children 2 years of age or older with SJIA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Important Safety Issues With Consideration to Related Drugs</head><p>Drugs that block IL-1 interfere with the normal immune response and are likely to induce a certain degree of immunosuppression. Currently, IL-1 inhibitors approved in the United States include canankinumab (Ilaris), anakinra (Kineret), and rilonacept (Arcalyst). Data from clinical studies and reports from the literature have shown that the use of IL-1 blockers have been associated with increased risk of infections. The ILARIS package insert states that canakinumab has been associated with an increased incidence of serious infections and cautions against the administration of live vaccines while on canakinumab therapy. The most common adverse reactions reported by patients with CAPS treated with canakinumab were nasopharyngitis, diarrhea, influenza, headache, and nausea. The most common adverse drug reactions reported by patients with SJIA treated with canakinumab were nasopharyngitis and upper respiratory tract infections, abdominal pain and injection site reactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Summary of Presubmission Regulatory Activity Related to Submission</head><p>The Phase 3 clinical study (N2301) submitted in the current application was conducted under IND 100040, which was opened with the Division of Anesthesia, Analgesia, and Rheumatology Products in 2006. The following Agency-sponsor interactions occurred subsequent to the submission of N2301: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Ethics and Good Clinical Practices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Submission Quality and Integrity</head><p>In general, the data quality and integrity of the studies were adequate. The amount of missing data did not interfere with reaching conclusions on the safety and efficacy of the product. A number of statistical issues were identified during the review but did not interfere with the final interpretation of the data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Compliance with Good Clinical Practices</head><p>All studies were conducted in accordance with the ethical principles in the Declaration of Helsinki and Good Clinical Practice. The studies were conducted in compliance with the prespecified protocols. Informed consent, protocol amendments, and administrative letters for each study received Institutional Review Board/Independent Ethics Committee approval prior to implementation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Financial Disclosures</head><p>The sponsor has adequately disclosed financial arrangements with clinical investigators as recommended in the FDA guidance for industry. Three investigators were identified with a potential conflict of interest. See the Appendix for the financial disclosure template.</p><p>for Protocol , received in excess of $25,000 from Novartis for a research grant used to study patients with inflammatory syndromes.</p><p>for Protocol , received in excess of $25,000 from Novartis for research grants.</p><p>for Protocol , has not received funds from Novartis, but does have a patent on the , one of the patient evaluation tools used in Protocol . It is unlikely that the participation of the aforementioned investigators in the clinical development program adversely impacted the outcome of the study given their limited involvement. Potential for bias was further minimized by using multiple investigators in this randomized, double-blind, placebocontrolled study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Significant Efficacy/Safety Issues Related to Other Review Disciplines</head><p>There were no significant efficacy or safety issues related to other review disciplines for the current submission.</p><p>Reference ID: 3978992</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(b) (6), (b) (4) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6), (b) (4) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (4), (b) (6)</formula><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 16 increase in total IL-1β indicating successful binding is observed in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients in Study N2301.</p><p>With the small sample size, variability in time to up-titration and up-titration being driven by clinical responsiveness, direct assessment of the doses against each other is not appropriate in this trial. Canakinumab treatment was associated with a decrease of IL-1β-induced downstream mediators, including the acute phase proteins CRP and SAA. This adds to the evidence that canakinumab neutralizes the activity and down -regulates the production of IL-1β in vivo.</p><p>The incidence of treatment related anti-canakinumab antibodies was &lt; 1% in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients across all Phase 2 and 3 studies. No patient had neutralizing antibodies. No ADA were detected in any patient in Study N2301. Two patients (one crFMF and one TRAPS) in the Phase 2 studies had treatment-emergent ADA, with no link to adverse events (AEs), loss of efficacy or change in PK. As discussed above, the periodic fevers are severe conditions for which few treatments are available, with only FMF having an FDA-approved therapy, colchicine, available. Otherwise, at the time that this pivotal study was initiated, the standard of care for patients consisted largely of non-approved therapies including NSAIDs and high-dose corticosteroids. However, as described below, the sponsor was able to conduct a single-dose, placebo-controlled study that was adequately designed to demonstrate a clinically meaningful difference between canakinumab and placebo. In general, the data contained in the sponsor's submission, including the design, conduct, and analyses of the study are acceptable. Nonetheless, as most placebo subjects, as well as many canakinumab subjects, underwent "blinded escape" as early as Day 8, the extent of treatment comparison is limited, especially at later time points. Thus, in addition to the prespecified primary and secondary analyses, the FDA review team examined endpoints at time points earlier than 16 weeks. Given the limitations in the data at 16 weeks, when the vast majority of patients were on canakinumab, an argument can be made that any efficacy summarized in the proposed label should be limited to the Resolution of Index Flare.</p><p>One pivotal Phase 3 trial was conducted to support the current submission. As discussed in greater detail below, Study N2301 was a randomized, placebo-controlled study (Epoch 2), comparing subjects treated with canakinumab 150 mg (2 mg/kg if ≤ 40 kg) and subjects treated with placebo in children and adults with active crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS a 24-week randomized withdrawal phase (Epoch 3), with subjects re-randomized to placebo or canakinumab 150 mg q 8 weeks, and a 72-week open-label treatment phase (Epoch 4). In the current submission, the sponsor provided efficacy data from Epoch 2 (16 weeks).</p><p>A dosing schedule of 150 mg sc q4w (or 2 mg/kg sc q4w for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) has been demonstrated to be highly effective in three PoC open-label studies: one study in patients with TRAPS (Study D2203) and two studies in patients with crFMF (Study DTR01, adult and pediatric patients; Study D2204, pediatric patients) ( <ref type="table">Table 2</ref>). In addition, a higher dose (300 mg or 4 mg/kg) with a longer dosing interval (every 6 weeks) was shown to be effective in HIDS/MKD patients (Study D2402). In Study N2301, the initial dosing regimen of 150 mg sc (or 2 mg/kg sc for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) q4w was utilized to harmonize exposure between the three conditions while allowing for up-titration to a maximal dose of canakinumab 300 mg (or 4 mg/kg for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) q4w to optimize the regimen and achieve efficacy in difficult cases. The sponsor hypothesizes that dose regimens used for open-label treatment (across Epochs 2 to 4) were considered to constitute the lowest clinically efficacious doses to maintain clinical efficacy in individual patients. In order to evaluate if clinical efficacy could be maintained at a lower dosing frequency, canakinumab 150 mg sc (or 2 mg/kg sc for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) at a reduced frequency of every 8 weeks (q8w) was evaluated during the randomized withdrawal epoch (Epoch 3); Epoch 3 will be reported separately when the data become available.</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>21</head><p>While these endpoints are acceptable, statistical issues were identified during the review that potentially limited interpretation of endpoints, such that, as most placebo subjects, as well as many canakinumab subjects, underwent "blinded escape" as early as Day 8, the extent of treatment comparison is limited, and an argument can be made that any efficacy summarized in the proposed label should be limited to the Resolution of Index Flare. For a detailed review of the statistical limitations, the reader is referred to the Division of Biometrics review for this application. External, independent, and respective Malignancy Adjudication and Infection Adjudication committees were formed on the program level to review pertinent data from this trial. A Data Monitoring Committee was not required. An overview of the study is shown ( <ref type="figure">Figure 1</ref>):</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">Discussion of Individual Studies/Clinical Trials</head><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 22</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Design of Study N2301</head><p>Source: Sponsor's submission Subjects who experienced persistent "mild," "moderate," or "severe" disease activity (i.e., PGA ≥ 2 [clinical flare]) or CRP persistently &gt; 10 mg/L with less than 40% reduction from baseline from Day 8 to Day 14 were able to receive a single add-on sc injection of canakinumab (150 mg sc [or 2 mg/kg for patients ≤ 40 kg]) as a blinded escape option. Patients whose index flare did not resolve, or who had persistent disease activity from Day 15 up to Day 28 (PGA ≥ 2 or CRP &gt;10 mg/L and no reduction by at least 70% from baseline), could also receive an additional dose of 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg for patients ≤ 40 kg), provided the add-on injection was not given earlier. If the patient's condition did not improve after administration of the single add-on canakinumab injection, rescue medication was used until Day 29. Of note, any patient who received blinded add-on canakinumab was considered a non-responder for the primary analysis.</p><p>For patients who received the single add-on canakinumab injection, up-titration to canakinumab 300 mg (or 4 mg/kg for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) q4w was initiated from Day 29 onward (these patients were also considered non-responders for the purpose of the primary analysis). These patients were not eligible for further up-titration. However, at the discretion of the investigator, they were permitted to remain in the study and receive canakinumab 300 mg (or 4 mg/ kg for patients weighing ≤ 40 kg) q4w.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p><p>23</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study population:</head><p>The study population consisted of male and female patients ≥ 2 years of age at the time of the screening visit for the randomized cohorts, and patients &gt; 28 days but &lt; 2 years old for the nonrandomized treatment arm.</p><p>For randomized crFMF patients: diagnosis of type 1 FMF disease according to Tel Hashomer criteria but no active flare at the time of screening, at least one of the known MEFV gene exon 10 mutations, and one of the following two criteria: documented active disease despite colchicine therapy or documented intolerance to effective doses of colchicine. At randomization, patients must have had acute crFMF flare characterized by inflammation and serositis, and active clinical crFMF flare as evidenced by PGA ≥ 2, and CRP &gt; 10 mg/L. Major exclusion criteria for the study included:  Use of the following therapies (within varying protocol defined timeframes): Corticosteroids (oral prednisone) &gt;0.2 mg/kg/day (or greater than the maximum of 15 mg/day for children over 60 kg), anakinra, canakinumab, rilonacept, tocilizumab, TNF inhibitors, abatacept, tofacitinib, rituximab, leflunomide, thalidomide, cyclosporine, intravenous immunoglobulin, 6-Merceptopurine, azathioprine, cyclophosphamide, or chlorambucil, intraarticular, peri-articular or intramuscular corticosteroid injections, any other investigational biologics  History of malignancy of any organ system (other than localized basal cell carcinoma of the skin or in-situ cervical cancer), treated or untreated  Significant medical diseases, including but not limited to the following: a. Clinical evidence or history of multiple sclerosis or other demyelinating diseases, or Felty's syndrome  Live vaccinations within 3 months prior to the start of the trial, during the trial, and up to 3 months following the last dose</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Endpoints:</head><p>The primary endpoint of the trial was predefined as the proportion of responders within each cohort, responders defined as subjects who had resolution of their index flare at Day 15 and did not experience a new flare from the time of the resolution of the index flare until the end of Epoch 2. Resolution of index flare was defined as PGA &lt; 2, and CRP ≤ 10 mg/L, or reduction ≥ 70% from baseline. (New flare was defined as PGA ≥ 2 and CRP ≥ 30 mg/L.)</p><p>Major secondary efficacy endpoints were prespecified and analyzed in the following order: -% subjects who achieved a PGA &lt; 2 at Week 16 -% subjects with serologic remission at Week 16 (CRP ≤ 10 mg/L) -% subjects with a normalized SAA level at Week 16 (SAA ≤ 10 mg/L)</p><p>The following exploratory variables were also measured:  Physician's severity assessment of key disease-specific signs and symptoms  Auto-inflammatory disease activity index (AIDAI)  Patient/parent's global assessment of disease activity (PPGA)  Health-related quality of life o SF-12 health survey-acyte version 2 (SF-12v2) for patients aged 18 years and older at baseline o Child health questionnaire-parent form 50 (CHQ-PF50) for patients between 5 and 18 years of age at baseline o Sheehan disability scale version 3 (SDS v3)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brief Description of Efficacy Endpoints</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Physician Global Assessment of disease activity (PGA)</head><p>The PGA was evaluated by the investigator based on a 5-point scale:</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">Reference ID: 3978992</formula><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 25  0 = None (no) disease associated clinical signs and symptoms  1 = Minimal disease associated signs and symptoms  2 = Mild disease associated signs and symptoms  3 = Moderate disease associated signs and symptoms  4 = Severe disease associated signs and symptoms</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Physician's severity assessment of key disease-specific signs and symptoms</head><p>Key signs and symptoms differed for each individual condition. The following signs and symptoms were assessed: 1. TRAPS: skin rash, musculoskeletal pain, abdominal pain, eye manifestations 2. HIDS/MKD: lymphadenopathy, aphthous ulcers, abdominal pain 3. crFMF: chest pain, abdominal pain, arthralgia/arthritis, skin rash Physician's severity assessment of key disease-specific signs and symptoms were evaluated by the investigator based on a 5-point scale:</p><formula xml:id="formula_2"> 0 = Absent  1 = Minimal  2 = Mild  3 = Moderate  4 = Severe</formula><p>Fever (body temperature ≥ 38°C [100.4°F]), was assessed via vital sign measurements</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Resolution of the index flare</head><p>Resolution of the index flare was defined as PGA &lt; 2, and CRP within normal range (≤ 10 mg/L) or reduction by at least 70% from baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New disease flare</head><p>From Day 29 onwards, a new disease flare was defined as simultaneous occurrence of a clinical flare and a serological flare defined as follows:</p><formula xml:id="formula_3"> PGA ≥ 2 (clinical flare)  CRP ≥ 30 mg/L (serological flare)</formula><p>For patients who achieved resolution of index flare at Day 15, this definition was applied from Day 16 until the end of Epoch 2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Auto-inflammatory Disease Activity Index (AIDAI)</head><p>The AIDAI was collected daily on an electronic diary by the patient (for children, a parent could assist when needed) in the evening. Scores were calculated per week.</p><p>The AIDAI diary contains 13 items as follows:  All items have to be scored as either yes or no. It has been validated 1 for use in hereditary recurrent fever syndromes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient/Parent's global assessment of disease activity (PPGA)</head><p>Patient's assessment of disease activity (PPGA) was collected on an electronic diary daily in the evening.</p><p>The PPGA is based on a 5-point scale:  0 = None/absent (no) disease associated clinical signs and symptoms  1 = Minimal disease associated signs and symptoms  2 = Mild disease associated signs and symptoms  3 = Moderate disease associated signs and symptoms  4 = Severe disease associated signs and symptoms</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Medical Outcome Short Form (12) Health Survey -Acute version 2 (SF-12v2)</head><p>The SF-12 ® measures the impact of disease on overall quality of life and consists of eight subscales (physical function, pain, general and mental health, vitality, social function, physical and emotional health) which can be aggregated to derive a physical-component summary score (PCS) and a mental-component summary score (MCS). Scores are determined with the use of norm-based methods which standardize scores based on an assessment of the general U.S. population free of chronic conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Child Health Questionnaire -Parent Form (CHQ-PF50)</head><p>The CHQ-PF50 is an instrument used to measure HRQoL in children 5 to 17 years of age from a parent's perspective. This questionnaire was to be completed by the parent with no input from the patient.</p><p>The CHQ-PF50 provides summary (physical and psychosocial health) scores for a 14concept health status and for well-being concepts: physical functioning, role/social emotional, role/social behavior, role/social physical, bodily pain, general behavior, mental health, self-esteem, general health perception, change in health, parental impactemotional, parental impact -time, family activities, and family cohesion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS)</head><p>The Sheehan Disability Scale (SDS) was developed to assess functional impairment in three inter-related domains: work/ school, social, and family life. The patient rates the extent to which work/school, social life or family responsibilities are impaired by his or her symptoms on a 10-point visual analog scale (VAS).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 27 These endpoints were assessed at time points as presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_9">Table 3</ref> below. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sample Size Considerations:</head><p>A Fisher's exact test with a 2.5% one-sided significance level would have 90% power to detect a between-treatment difference of 45%, assuming that the proportion of responders for the canakinumab treatment group is 0.65 and the proportion of placebo responders is 0.2 when the sample size per treatment arm is 28, rounded to 30 per treatment arm and per disease cohort (i.e., a total of total 180 patients). Since a 20% screening failure rate was expected, it was estimated that approximately 225 patients would have to be screened. A full review of the statistical methods is contained in the Division of Biometrics review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protocol Amendments:</head><p>Protocol Amendments were made for the study as outlined below:</p><p> Protocol Amendment #1 notified the Agency of a new investigator at Center 1206.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>29</head><p> Protocol Amendment #2 was written to address the request From the Pediatric Committee (PDCO) at the European Medicines in the framework of respective Pediatric Investigational Plans to include patients &gt; 28 days in the clinical trial compared to the previously ≥2 years of age. Patients &gt; 28 days but &lt; 2 years old were allowed to enter the study directly into the open-label arm of Epoch 2, but would not be considered toward the total number of patients enrolled for the primary efficacy and safety analyses. The amendment also provided clarity on the management of randomized and non-randomized cohorts in accordance with clinical practice. (Further, the cover letter for this amendment noted that "Amendment 1" was a "non-substantial" amendment first implemented in the United Kingdom and was not submitted to the Agency, issued to address the request from the Medicines and Healthcare Products Regulatory Agency in the United Kingdom to refer to local label requirements for birth control in females of child-bearing potential when treated with canakinumab.)  Protocol Amendment #3 notified the Agency of a new investigator at Center 1204.  Protocol Amendment #4 notified the Agency of Form 1572 changes.</p><p>Overall, these amendments are not expected to bias or affect the interpretation of the results of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Review of Efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Summary</head><p>The primary efficacy data derives from the phase 3 study N2301. Study N2301 was a four-part study, consisting of a screening period (Epoch 1), a 16-week, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment phase (Epoch 2) comparing a single dose of canakinumab 150 mg (2 mg/kg if ≤ 40 kg) versus placebo in children and adults with active crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS, a 24-week randomized withdrawal phase (Epoch 3) with subjects re-randomized to placebo or canakinumab 150 mg q 8 weeks, and a 72-week open-label treatment phase (Epoch 4). In this submission, the sponsor provided data from the 16-week randomized, doubleblind placebo-controlled treatment phase (Epoch 2). The study was adequately designed and conducted to allow for interpretation of the effect of canakinumab in patients with crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS.</p><p>Review of the data demonstrated that the study met the pre-specified primary endpoint with a greater proportion of canakinumab-treated subjects responders compared to placebo in each cohort. The results were consistent regardless of age, gender, prior use of biologics and concomitant use of colchicine (for the crFMF cohort). Specifically, more subjects achieved a complete response with canakinumab than with placebo: TRAPS, 45% versus 8%; HIDS/MKD, 35% versus 6%; crFMF, 61% versus 6%. Also, more subjects in the canakinumab group These data demonstrated a significant and clinically meaningful therapeutic effect of canakinumab in subjects with active TRAPS, HIDS/MKD, and crFMF. The data were further supported by subgroup and sensitivity analyses and testing of the major secondary endpoints, which showed that canakinumab's therapeutic effect was consistent across subgroups and measures of disease activity.</p><p>However, as switching and up-titration was allowed, there is a concern surrounding treatment comparison. Blinded escape was allowed before Day 29, and most placebo subjects switched to canakinumab 150 mg every 4 weeks: TRAPS, 75%; HIDS/MKD, 32%; crFMF, 16%.</p><p>There was in fact a high proportion of patients initially randomized to placebo who crossed over to canakinumab, an indication that this limits efficacy (and safety) comparisons given the lack of comparator group. Patients who crossed over from placebo to canakinumab, or who up-titrated the dose of canakinumab, or who discontinued the study, were considered non-responders in the primary analysis.</p><p>In terms of the efficacy of increasing the dose from 150 mg to 300 mg, this study was not designed to reliably evaluate the potential benefit of up-titration, as there was no control group of patients who had persistent disease activity/flare but remained on the 150 mg dose. Therefore, it is difficult to determine if differences over time in patients who up-titrated were due to differences between the doses. Nonetheless, there was supportive evidence of efficacy for canakinumab, as compared to placebo, for the components of the primary endpoint, CRP and PGA score, as well as for the secondary endpoint, SAA level.</p><p>For evaluations of binary endpoints in which patients who cross over or up-titrate are considered to be non-responders, it is difficult to determine whether observed differences between canakinumab and placebo are due to difference in treatment effects on the outcome of interest or due to differences in the proportions of patients remaining on the initially assigned treatment. Furthermore, evaluations of continuous endpoints are essentially uncontrolled due to the small subset of placebo patients remaining on assigned therapy at later time points. Because of the design of the study and the considerable cross-over from the control arm to canakinumab, reliable results are largely limited to short-term endpoints (such as resolution of index flare).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Indication</head><p>The current submission for canakinumab is to support the following orphan indications:</p><p> Familial Mediterranean Fever (FMF) in adults and children aged 2 years and older in whom colchicine is contraindicated, is not tolerated, or does not provide an adequate </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Methods</head><p>Refer to Section 5.3 for discussion of Study N2301 trial design. Study N2301 served as the critical trial for the evaluation of the efficacy of canakinumab in the treatment of FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS. This study was well-controlled and utilized endpoints that assessed clinically important manifestations of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Demographics</head><p>The patients included in this trial are representative of the typical respective periodic fever patient populations. Baseline disease characteristics were also consistent with active disease.</p><p>The baseline demographics and background characteristics for the pivotal study are summarized below ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_13">Table 4)</ref>.  Concomitant medications were used by 93% of subjects exposed to canakinumab, and 88% of subjects only exposed to placebo. Most (87%) of crFMF subjects were taking concomitant colchicine during Epoch 2.</p><p>A small proportion of subjects had prior exposure to biologics (24% of crFMF subjects, 18% of HIDS/MKD subjects, and 35% of TRAPS subjects).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 34</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.3">Subject Disposition</head><p>A total of 180 patients (60 per cohort, 30 per treatment arm) were planned to be randomized. A total of 181 patients were randomized and four patients entered the non-randomized open-label treatment arm. In the crFMF cohort, 100 patients were screened and 63 patients were randomized (31 to 150 mg q4w canakinumab and 32 to placebo). In the HIDS/MKD cohort, 98 patients were screened and 72 patients were randomized (37 to 150 mg q4w canakinumab and 35 to placebo).</p><p>In the TRAPS cohort, 82 patients were screened and 46 patients were randomized (22 to 150 mg q4w canakinumab and 24 to placebo). All randomized patients were included in the Full Analysis Set (for efficacy analysis) and the Safety set (for safety analysis). Four non-randomized patients (two crFMF patients with non-exon 10 mutations and two HIDS/MKD patients &gt; 28 days but &lt; 2 years old) received open-label treatment.</p><p>As previously noted, the vast majority of patients randomized to placebo crossed over to canakinumab and patients frequently up-titrated from canakinumab 150 mg to 300 mg <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">(Table 5</ref>).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.4">Analysis of Primary Endpoint(s)</head><p>In Study N2301, the primary efficacy variable of the randomized treatment epoch (Epoch 2) and for the overall study was the proportion of responders within each cohort, whereby a responder was defined as a patient who had resolution of his/her index disease flare (i.e., PGA &lt; 2 and CRP either ≤ 10 mg/L or ≥ 70% reduction from baseline) at Day 15 and did not experience a new flare (i.e., PGA ≥ 2 and CRP ≥ 30 mg/L) before the end of Epoch 2 (end of Week 16). In the primary analysis, patients who needed dose escalation in the canakinumab arms, who crossed over from placebo to canakinumab, or who discontinued from the study due to any reason prior to evaluating the primary endpoint were considered as non-responders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>36</head><p>The primary objective was met in all three disease cohorts. Canakinumab demonstrated superior efficacy over placebo. All treatment differences in the proportion of responders were statistically significant in favor of canakinumab vs. placebo ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">Table 6</ref>). In crFMF patients, there were 55% more responders on canakinumab vs. placebo (OR=23.75, p&lt;0.0001). In HIDS/MKD patients, there were 29% more responders on canakinumab vs. placebo (OR=8.94, p=0.0020). In TRAPS patients, there were 37% more responders on canakinumab vs. placebo (OR=9.17, p=0.0050). However, as most placebo subjects, as well as many canakinumab subjects, underwent "blinded escape" as early as Day 8, the extent of treatment comparison is limited. Thus, additional efficacy analyses were performed at earlier time points. While at least half of the patients randomized to canakinumab 150mg q4w (49% to 68%) stayed on the initial dose through the entire treatment period, the vast majority of patients randomized to placebo (84% to 88%) switched over to canakinumab 150mg q4w and/or were further up-titrated to 300mg q4w. There were only 4 FMF patients, 3 HIDS/MKD patients, and 2 TARPS patients who remained on placebo by Week 16. The proportion of patients who were initially randomized to canakinumab 150 mg q4w and required dose escalation to 300 mg q4w before Day 29 were 16.1% in FMF, 32.4% in HIDS/MKD and 36.4% in TRAPS, respectively. In contrast, the proportion of patients who were initially randomized to placebo and needed blinded escape before Day 29 was 62.5% in FMF, 62.9% in HIDS/MKD, and 75.0% in TRAPS, respectively. Before Day 15, more patients randomized to placebo received an add-on injection of canakinumab than patients randomized to canakinumab 150 mg q4w. At Day 15, a higher proportion of canakinumab-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients experienced resolution of their index flare as measured by PGA &lt; 2, and CRP within normal range (≤ 10 mg/L) or reduction by at least 70% from baseline. The efficacy of canakinumab at Day 15 was observed in all 3 disease cohorts; however, the results should be interpreted with caution as some patients had already received add-on injection of canakinumab before Day 15. Nevertheless, compared to evaluation of treatment effect at Week 16, the short-term results at Day 15 are more reliable since less cross-over and/or up-titration had occurred at Day 15 than at later time points ( <ref type="table" target="#tab_17">Table 7)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.5">Analysis of Secondary Endpoints(s)</head><p>Study N2301 also had three secondary efficacy endpoints in Epoch 2: the percentage of patients who achieved a PGA &lt; 2 ("minimal" or "absent" disease activity); the percentage of patients with serologic remission (defined as CRP ≤ 10 mg/L); and the percentage of patients with normalized SAA (defined as SAA ≤ 10 mg/L), all assessed at the end of Week 16. The primary endpoint and the three secondary endpoints were assessed in a hierarchical testing strategy designed to protect the family-wise type 1 error rate at α=2.5% (one-sided tests). If the primary objective of the study was met, the superiority of canakinumab 150 mg q4w over placebo in each secondary endpoint was then assessed in the closed testing procedure.</p><p>Overall, canakinumab provided greater improvements in clinical and serological responses, as assessed by PGA &lt; 2 (absent or minimal disease), serological remission per CRP ≤ 10 mg/L and normalization of SAA to ≤ 10 mg/L at the end of Week 16, compared with placebo across all cohorts of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients.</p><p>Results of the closed testing procedure, which was performed after the primary objective was met, demonstrated the superiority of canakinumab to placebo for PGA &lt; 2 and CRP ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks of treatment in all cohorts of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients. For SAA ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks, canakinumab was superior to placebo in TRAPS patients and showed similar trend of greater improvements relative to placebo in crFMF and HIDS/MKD patients. Taken together, canakinumab demonstrated greater benefit in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients compared with placebo in all primary and secondary efficacy endpoints, reflecting rapid and sustained flare control, absent to minimal disease activity, normalization of CRP and normalization of SAA <ref type="table" target="#tab_19">(Table 8)</ref>.  The median time to first resolution of fever (&lt; 38.0°C) was 1 to 1.5 days shorter for patients randomized to canakinumab 150 mg q4w compared with placebo in all 3 disease cohorts. This analysis was performed in a small subset of patients (15/63 (24%) crFMF patients, 42/72 (58%) HIDS/MKD patients and 19/46 (41%) TRAPS patients) who had fever (as assessed by daily diary) at baseline. While these results suggest the efficacy of canakinumab, the clinical significance of 1 to 1.5 days less fever is unclear. For each cohort the results for resolution of fever were:  In crFMF patients, the median time to first resolution of fever (&lt; 38.0°C) was 2.0 days for canakinumab 150 mg q4w group vs. 3.0 days for the placebo group (Hazard ratio=2.48; 95% CI: 0.79-7.73; p=0.0589).  In HIDS/MKD patients, the median time to first resolution of fever (&lt; 38.0°C) was 2.0 days for canakinumab 150 mg q4w group vs. 3.5 days for the placebo group (Hazard ratio=3.32; 95% CI: 1.60-6.88; p=0.0006).  In TRAPS patients, the median time to first resolution of fever (&lt; 38.0°C) was 2.0 days for canakinumab 150 mg q4w group vs. 3.5 days for the placebo group (Hazard ratio=2.55; 95% CI: 0.90-7.25; p=0.0393).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.7">Subpopulations</head><p>Canakinumab showed greater efficacy compared to placebo with the respect to the proportion of responders after 16 weeks in both age subgroups across all 3 disease cohorts. Similar results were also observed for the secondary efficacy endpoints of PGA &lt; 2 and CRP ≤ 10 mg/L in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients. For SAA ≤ 10 mg/L, canakinumab was more efficacious than placebo in both age subgroups in crFMF patients, while in HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients this effect was apparent in patients &lt; 18 years old but not in the very small number of HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients ≥ 18 years old <ref type="table" target="#tab_21">(Table 9)</ref>.  For patients with an inadequate response after the first dose, an up-titration to 300 mg (or 4 mg/kg) further improved flare control, reduced disease activity and normalized CRP and SAA levels. In the exploratory analysis, patients randomized to canakinumab 150 mg q4w who were up-titrated to 300 mg q4w before Day 29 were considered responders if they had resolution of flare at Day 29 and no flare after Day 29 for the primary endpoint of the proportion of responders and in addition if they had PGA &lt; 2, CRP ≤ 10 mg/L or SAA ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks for each of the secondary endpoints.</p><p>Overall, results of this analysis suggest that the individualized up-titration is beneficial for crFMF patients and especially HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients to achieve sufficient control of clinical and serological parameters. The improvements in flare control, disease activity and levels of CRP and SAA observed with up -titration from 150 mg to 300 mg q4w were most pronounced in the disease cohorts (i.e., HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients) who most needed uptitration. However, given that most placebo subjects switched to canakinumab and some patients required up-titration as early as Day 8, the comparison between canakinumab and placebo is difficult to interpret.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.7.1">crFMF subjects</head><p>Dose escalation further improved flare control, reduction of PGA scores to no or minimal disease and return of CRP to normal levels in crFMF patients treated with canakinumab. The proportion of canakinumab-treated crFMF patients who resolved their index flare by Day 29 and had no new flare up to the end of Epoch 2 increased to 70.97% when patients received an add-on dose if needed before Day 29, representing a 9.7% higher responder rate with up-titration to 300 mg q4w. The response rates for PGA &lt; 2 (74.19%) and CRP ≤ 10 mg/L (74.19%) after 16 weeks also improved with up-titration to 300 mg q4w before Day 29, reflecting an increase of 9.7% and 6.5%, respectively. There was no change in the rate of SAA ≤ 10 mg/L (remained at 25.81%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>41</head><p>For the crFMF subjects who were taking concomitant colchicine during Epoch 2, canakinumab showed greater efficacy than placebo with respect to the proportion of responders after 16 weeks (62% versus 0%); the risk difference in favor of canakiumab versus placebo (62%) in subjects taking concomitant colchicine was of similar magnitude as that in the overall population (55%), indicating the added benefit of canakinumab beyond that provided by colchicine therapy. Both the canakinumab and placebo group received comparable daily colchicine doses, and treatment responders did not receive higher doses of colchicine versus non-responders.</p><p>Among those with prior exposure to biologics (24% of crFMF subjects), there were more responders in Epoch 2 in the canakinumab group than in the placebo group for the crFMF cohort (57% for canakinumab versus 0% for placebo). The responder profile among subjects without prior exposure to biologics was similar to the overall population, with a higher proportion of subjects on canakinumab compared to placebo achieving a complete response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.7.2">HIDS/MKD subjects</head><p>Dose escalation further improved flare control, reduction of PGA scores to no or minimal disease and return of CRP and SAA to normal levels in HIDS/MKD patients treated with canakinumab. The proportion of canakinumab-treated HIDS/MKD patients who resolved their index flare by Day 29 and had no new flare up to the end of Epoch 2 increased to 56.76% when patients received an add-on dose if needed before Day 29, representing a 21.6% higher responder rate with up-titration to 300 mg q4w. The response rates for PGA &lt; 2 (67.57%), CRP ≤ 10 mg/L (48.65%) and SAA ≤ 10 mg/L (18.92%) after 16 weeks also improved with uptitration to 300 mg q4w before Day 29, reflecting an increase of 21.6%, 8.1% and 5.4%, respectively, for these secondary endpoints.</p><p>Among those with prior exposure to biologics (18% of HIDS/MKD subjects), there was one subject in the canakinumab group who was a responder compared with 0 subjects in the placebo group. The responder profile among subjects without prior exposure to biologics was similar to the overall population, with a higher proportion of subjects on canakinumab compared to placebo achieving a complete response. Among those with prior exposure to biologics (35% of TRAPS subjects), there were more responders in Epoch 2 in the canakinumab group than in the placebo group for the TRAPS cohort (50% versus 13%). The responder profile among subjects without prior exposure to biologics was similar to the overall population, with a higher proportion of subjects on canakinumab compared to placebo achieving a complete response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analyses at Day 15</head><p>Canakinumab provided flare control, as indicated by the majority of patients in all three disease cohorts resolving their index flare by Day 15. Overall, 80.65%, 64.86% and 63.64% of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients, respectively, achieved flare control with 150 mg or 2 mg/kg canakinumab. Approximately two to three times more patients resolved their index flare at Day 15 with canakinumab treatment compared to placebo: 80.65% for canakinumab vs. 31.25% for placebo in the crFMF cohort, 64.86% vs. 37.14% in the HIDS/MKD cohort, and 63.64% vs. 20.83% in the TRAPS cohort. This corresponds to 49.4%, 27.7% and 42.8% more crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients, respectively, who resolved their index flare by Day 15 with canakinumab treatment compared to placebo.</p><p>The results at Day 15 should be interpreted with caution, as some patients had received add-on injection of canakinumab before Day 15. However, compared to the evaluation of treatment effect at Week 16, the short-term results at Day 15, as discussed by the Biometrics reviewer, appear more reliable because less cross-over and up-titration had occurred at Day 15 compared to later time points.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.8">Analysis of Clinical Information Relevant to Dosing Recommendations</head><p>For those patients who did not achieve resolution of their index flare by Day 15 with the first dose of 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg), administration of a second dose of 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg) was effective for resolution of the index flare at Day 29 in 60.0% of crFMF patients and 62.5% of TRAPS patients, but in only 26.7% of HIDS/MKD patients.</p><p>For patients on placebo who did not resolve their index flare by Day 15, an add -on dose with canakinumab 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg) led to resolution by Day 29 for 77.8%, 55.6% and 62.5% of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients, respectively. These responder rates are similar to those in patients randomized to and receiving canakinumab 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg) q4w from Day 1 (i.e., 80.65%, 64.86% and 63.64%, respectively), providing additional evidence of efficacy for canakinumab in patients initially exposed to placebo.</p><p>For all three randomized cohorts of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients, the proportion of patients who needed blinded escape with an add-on injection of canakinumab 150 mg </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>43</head><p>(or 2 mg/kg) between Days 8 and 28 was lower in the randomized canakinumab group than in the placebo group. However, 16% of crFMF patients, and even more HIDS/MKD patients (32%) and TRAPS patients (36%), were up-titrated from 150 mg to 300 mg q4w <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 10</ref>). * Adapted from Sponsor's submission</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.9">Discussion of Persistence of Efficacy and/or Tolerance Effects</head><p>The majority of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients did not re -flare over 16 weeks of treatment in Epoch 2. Among canakinumab-treated patients (150 mg or 300 mg q4w), 90.3%, 64.9% and 77.3% of crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients, respectively, had no new flare (i.e., PGA ≥ 2 and CRP ≥ 30 mg/L) after resolution of the index flare up to the end of Week 16. While data are only available from 16 weeks of treatment, it is reasonable to assume that these results would be maintained, especially given the lack of anti-drug antibody development.</p><p>There was no evidence of drug tolerance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.10">Additional Efficacy Issues/Analyses</head><p>The primary objective of the study was achieved for all three cohorts: canakinumab was superior to placebo in the proportion of patients who resolved their index disease flare at Day 15 and had no new flare before the end of Epoch 2. Canakinumab also demonstrated superior efficacy compared to placebo on the secondary endpoints of PGA &lt; 2 and CRP ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks in all 3 cohorts. Higher proportions of patients had normalized SAA (≤ 10 mg/L) after 16 weeks with canakinumab treatment compared to placebo in all 3 cohorts, with a statistically significant difference observed in TRAPS patients. These improvements in the clinical and serological parameters of disease were accompanied by increased health-related mQoL for patients as assessed by CHQ-PF50 (Child Health Questionnaire -Parent Form 50) and SF-12 (Medical Outcome Short Form 12 Health Survey) physical component summary scores. ILARIS® is additionally approved outside the US for use in acute gouty arthritis attacks at a dose of 150 mg given as a single subcutaneous injection as soon as possible following onset of an attack. With approval in many markets for use across the above-mentioned indications, there is a large body of evidence supporting the safety of canakinumab in pediatric and adult patients.</p><p>My review of the data did not identify new safety signals and the overall safety profile of canakinumab in crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS appears to provide an acceptable degree of risk given the severity of the disease and the demonstrated efficacy of canakinumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Methods</head><p>Study N2301 was a randomized, multicenter, double-blind, placebo controlled study of canakinumab in patients with crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS. The primary objective was to demonstrate that canakinumab treatment at a dose of 150 mg (or 2 mg/kg in subjects weighing ≤ 40 kg) administered subcutaneously every 4 weeks is superior to placebo in achieving a clinically meaningful reduction of disease activity defined as resolution of the index flare at Day 15 and no new disease flares over 16 weeks of treatment. The study is ongoing; the original cut-off date was August 25, 2015 (last patient last visit for the Week 16 primary endpoint analysis).</p><p>The cut-off date for safety data from ongoing studies included in the sBLA submissions was November 06, 2015. The cut-off date for safety data for the 120-Day Safety Update was March 31, 2016. Therefore, the 120-Day Safety Update provided new safety data for canakinumab studies in TRAPS, HIDS/MKD, FMF and other more related indications: CAPS and SJIA. Overall, 21 SAEs were reported for 17 patients. Four patients reported five SAEs in the crFMF cohort of which two were suspected to be related to study treatment (infectious colitis and acute sinusitis). Nine patients reported 12 SAEs in the HIDS/MKD cohort of which 3 were suspected to be related to study treatment (hyper Immunogobulin D [IgD] syndrome, anal abscess and herpes virus infection). Four patients reported four SAEs in the TRAPS cohort of which none were suspected to be related to treatment. A review of these cases did not alter the safety profile of canakinumab. There were no new cases of neutropenia, thrombocytopenia, vertigo/dizziness, immunogenicity, autoimmunity or malignancy in any of the cohorts. Canakinumab demonstrated a similar safety profile in TRAPS, HIDS/MKD and crFMF to that observed in the already approved CAPS indication.</p><p>Given the short duration of the trial and the limited number of subjects who continued on placebo during the study, comparisons between the canakinumab and placebo groups based on proportions are very limited. Interpretation of the safety data for canakinumab, as it relates specifically to subjects exposed to canakinumab, is severely limited in the current application due to the lack of subjects exposed to placebo during the same time period as patients exposed to canakinumab, as well as the small number of subjects in each treatment group.</p><p>The sponsor's presentation of safety data was found to be reasonable and the sponsor's safety tables are presented.</p><p>This submission is supported by efficacy and safety data from the recently completed randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled treatment phase (Epoch 2) of the ongoing pivotal confirmatory Phase 3 study (Study N2301), with additional safety data from the ongoing randomized withdrawal phase (Epoch 3) and the open-label treatment phase (Epoch 4) of this study. Additionally, four completed Phase 2 studies in the three indications support this application, in conjunction with supportive safety data from five completed Phase 2 and 3 studies in the approved indication of CAPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.2">Categorization of Adverse Events</head><p>All safety evaluations were conducted and reported according to Good Clinical Practice guidelines with data collected for AEs, clinical laboratory test results, and vital signs. Standardized Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) queries and predefined lists of preferred terms (PTs) were developed by the sponsor and used to analyze the data for safety events.</p><p>Adverse events were included in the safety analysis if the onset date was on or after the first dose start date of a specified period. Subject listings included all AEs, even those that occurred more than 60 days after the last dose of study medication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.3">Pooling of Data Across Studies/Clinical Trials to Estimate and Compare Incidence</head><p>All AEs were coded and grouped into PTs by system organ class (SOC). As studies completed at various times, it is likely that AEs have been coded with different Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities (MedDRA) versions. For the pooled analyses, low level term codes are mapped to the latest MedDRA version available at the time of analysis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Adequacy of Safety Assessments</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1">Overall Exposure at Appropriate Doses/Durations and Demographics of Target Populations</head><p>The key safety population supporting canakinumab in crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS is the N2301 Epoch 2 Safety set presented in the pivotal CSR ("N2301 Epoch 2"), which included a total of 181 randomized patients (63 crFMF patients, 72 HIDS/MKD patients, and 46 TRAPS patients) with a median duration of exposure of 113 days in this Any ACZ group (which includes all patients who took at least one dose of canakinumab during Epoch 2) and a cumulative exposure of 47.6 patient-years. This safety population reflects the safety results for each patient </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.4">Routine Clinical Testing</head><p>The types and frequencies of safety tests used to assess AEs, vital signs, labs, and other tests were adequate to assess the safety of canakinumab in FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS. These safety tests were adequate to evaluate the known IL-1 associated AEs.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.5">Metabolic, Clearance, and Interaction Workup</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.6">Evaluation for Potential Adverse Events for Similar Drugs in Drug Class</head><p>Study N2301 incorporated monitoring for toxicities associated with IL-inhibitors, such as infections, hypersensitivity, and injection site reactions. Details of these analyses are found in Section 7.3.4 (Submission Specific Primary Safety Concerns).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Major Safety Results</head><p>Overall, the incidence and profile of AEs in the crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS cohorts was comparable across the treatment groups within each cohort and across the cohorts. The profile of AEs in canakinumab-treated patients was also comparable between Study N2301 Epoch 2 and Epochs 2-4. The most frequently affected SOC in crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS patients was infections and infestations, with the most common infections being those of the upper respiratory tract. All infections were mild or moderate in severity; the majority were not considered related to study drug and resolved, and few were SAEs. Other frequently observed AEs in crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS subjects were pyrexia, headache, diarrhea, abdominal pain, and injection site reaction.</p><p>The profile of AEs in the Study N2301 groups was comparable to that of the CAPS group. The SOC with the highest frequency of AEs in the CAPS pool was infections and infestations. Similar to what was reported in the N2301 study population, the most frequently reported AEs in the CAPS group were nasopharyngitis, headache, upper respiratory tract infection, rhinitis, diarrhea, and arthralgia.</p><p>In Epoch 2, the most commonly reported AEs by preferred term (PT) in the crFMF Any ACZ Group (all patients who took at least one dose of canakinumab during Epoch 2) were FMF (22.4%), injection site reaction (13.8%), and diarrhea (12.1%). The most commonly reported AEs in the HIDS/MKD Any ACZ group were pyrexia (23.5%), headache (17.6%), and diarrhea and oropharyngeal pain (each 11.8%). The most commonly reported AEs in the TRAPS Any ACZ group were pyrexia (14.0%), and abdominal pain, injection site reaction, and nasopharyngitis (each 11.6%). All injection site reactions were mild and none were SAEs or AEs that led to discontinuation. In Study N2301 Epochs 2-4, comparable to what was observed in Epoch 2, the most frequently affected primary SOC in the Total ACZ group was infections and infestations (59.2%), with nasopharyngitis (10.7%) and upper respiratory tract 0infection (10.1%) being the most common infection events. Other SOCs with AEs reported for more than 25% of patients in the Total ACZ group were: general disorders &amp; administration site conditions (40.8%), gastrointestinal disorders (37.3%), and musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (26.6%).</p><p>When adjusted for exposure per 100 patient-years, the most commonly occurring SOC of infections and infestations showed a comparable rate between the Total ACZ group (which includes all data collected from randomization to canakinumab or the day of each patient's first dose of canakinumab) and the lower-exposed Total placebo group <ref type="bibr">(204.6 vs. 202.3)</ref>. Similarly, all other SOCs showed comparable or lower exposure-adjusted event rates for the Total ACZ group compared with the Total placebo group from Study N2301.</p><p>Similar to what was observed in canakinumab-treated patients in Epoch 2, in the N2301 Epochs 2-4 Safety set, the most commonly reported AEs in the Total ACZ group were pyrexia (21.3%), headache (17.8%), diarrhea (13.0%), abdominal pain, and injection site reaction.</p><p>Overall, the frequency and type of SAEs observed during the clinical trials of canakinumab in TRAPS, HIDS/MKD and crFMF subjects was similar and consistent with data from prior trials for current indications, with no new safety signals identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1">Deaths</head><p>There were no deaths in any studies of periodic fever syndrome patients, no deaths in the CAPS safety populations, and no deaths in study N2301 as of the cut-off date.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.2">Nonfatal Serious Adverse Events</head><p>In the N2301 Epoch 2 crFMF cohort, the incidence of SAEs was low in the Any ACZ group (five subjects, 8.6%). No SAE was reported in more than one subject. The SAEs considered by the investigator to be possibly related to study drug were granulomatous liver disease, pharyngotonsillitis, and atypical pneumonia. In the N2301 Epoch 2 HIDS/MKD cohort, the Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 50 incidence of SAEs was 11.8% (eight subjects) in the Any ACZ group. With the exception of pneumonia, reported in two subjects in the placebo to 150 mg group, no SAE was reported in more than one subject. One SAE, neutropenia, which occurred in a subject in the placebo group, was considered by the investigator to be related to study drug. In the N230 1 Epoch 2 TRAPS cohort, the incidence of SAEs was low, affecting 4.7% (two subjects) in the Any ACZ group. No SAE was reported in more than one subject. No SAE was considered by the investigator to be related to study drug.</p><p>In Epochs 2-4, the incidence of SAEs in the Total ACZ group was 10.7% (18 subjects). No SAE was reported in more than one patient in any particular cohort except umbilical hernia (two subjects (3.4%) in crFMF ACZ group) and pneumonia (three subjects (4.4%) in HIDS/MKD ACZ group). The SOC with the highest frequency of SAEs was infections and infestations (4.1% in the Total ACZ group).</p><p>The exposure-adjusted SAE rate per 100 patient-years was 30.5 in the Total ACZ group and 85.2 in the Total placebo group.</p><p>In the CAPS pooled population, the frequency of SAEs was comparable (28 patients, 14.4%)</p><p>to that of the <ref type="figure">Total ACZ group (18 patients, 10.7%)</ref>. SAEs occurred most commonly in the infections and infestations SOC (7.2%). SAEs reported in &gt; 1 patient in the CAPS pooled group were: vertigo, appendicitis, pneumonia, tonsillitis, headache, pregnancy, and abortion induced. The exposure-adjusted SAE rate per 100 patient-years in the CAPS pool was 15.9, compared with 30.5 in the Total ACZ group and 85.2 in the Total placebo group. Although the exposure-adjusted SAE rate was higher in the Total ACZ group vs. the CAPS pool, this was partly driven by the disease-specific SAEs of FMF, HIDS, and MKD and by a small number of individual patients who experienced a unique set of multiple SAEs. In addition, a slightly higher percentage of patients in the N2301 Total ACZ group reported &gt; 1 SAE (approximately 50%) vs. the CAPS group (approximately 40%). Overall, the profile of SAEs in Study N2301 was similar to that reported in the CAPS pooled population, and are summarized below (   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACZ885=canakinumab</head><p>Source: Sponsor's submission</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.4">Significant Adverse Events</head><p>There were two non-randomized HIDS/MKD subjects, both &gt; 28 days but &lt; 2 years of age. One subject reported multiple non-serious AEs, with the most frequently reported being diarrhea, aphthous ulcer, nasopharyngitis, and pyrexia, in addition to increased liver function tests. The other subject had a history of immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP), and had an active medical condition of abnormal hepatic function reported during a first screening, which was ongoing at the beginning of open-label treatment.</p><p>This latter subject reported AEs of upper respiratory tract infection, hepatic failure, hypocalcemia, hypophosphatemia, and pancytopenia. In addition, this subject experienced the SAEs of pancytopenia and hepatic failure. Both SAEs were considered to be related to study 55 treatment due to their occurrence after the start of study treatment. The hepatic failure SAE was considered severe and led to study discontinuation; but was reported as resolved after the last assessment in the study.</p><p>The Novartis response to our July 14, 2016, Information Request states that the investigator suspected abnormal hepatic function due to an unspecified viral infection. The subject had elevated liver function tests at the time of screening in early January of 2015, and experienced an upper respiratory infection a couple of weeks later. In the second week of February, 2015,, the patient was diagnosed with ITP, and about a week after that, the alkaline phosphatase was above 600, the investigator suspecting abnormal hepatic function since early January being due to a viral infection.</p><p>At the end of March, 2015, the patient had another episode of increased liver function tests, and the investigator deemed the patient a screening failure. But a week later, the patient underwent re-screening (at which time the transaminases were elevated-with an ALT of 172, and alkaline phosphatase of 345, and the investigator enrolled the patient into the study), and shortly after that the patient was thought to have completely recovered from ITP.</p><p>On May 12, 2015, the alkaline phosphatase was 346; prednisolone was tapered and the nowsubject received open-label canakinumab on May 13-at which time AST and ALT were 15 and 24, respectively, and platelets were 387,000. Two weeks later, AST was 258, ALT was 370, alkaline phosphatase was 576, and platelets were 195,000. On June 08, ALT was 922, AST was 504, and platelets 90,000; on June 11, alkaline phosphatase was 1622 and total bilirubin 2.8, rising to 4.9 on June 15; platelet count was 67,000.</p><p>Bilirubin increased to 12.5 on June 21, 2015, AST and ALT had gone down to 278 and 175, respectively, with a platelet count of 38,000. Ammonia level was 89 on June 24, and a few days after that liver transplant was considered, as prothrombin time had been worsening. Bone marrow biopsy revealed a relatively hypoplastic bone marrow-which responded well to G-CSF. While the subject had also received famotidine, due to the temporal relation to canakinumab administration, the investigator suspected this as the cause of the pancytopenia. Liver biopsy on September 18 showed 50% loss of hepatocytes/necrosis.</p><p>The pancytopenia recovered on August 31, 2015. On September 15, the ALT was 162, AST was 56 and bilirubin was 2.3; the investigator considered HIDS/MKD as a contributory factor for the reported events.</p><p>It is my opinion that this subject had pre-existing conditions, and no conclusions can be drawn that canakinumab contributed to the aforementioned events.</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 56</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infections</head><p>In Epochs 2-4, the exposure-adjusted event rate of infections and infestations was similar between the Total ACZ (204.6/100 PYR) and the Total placebo (202.3/100 PYR) groups. In Epochs 2-4 the majority of infections were non-serious, mild to moderate infections of the upper respiratory tract that did not lead to discontinuation. No patient was confirmed by the Infection Adjudication Committee to have an opportunistic infection in Epoch 2 or in Epochs 2-4 up to the data cut-off date. Overall, the infection profile observed in the N2301 pooled dataset was consistent with that of the CAPS pooled dataset. The exposure adjusted event rate (per 100 patient-years) was similar between the Total ACZ group <ref type="bibr">(204.6)</ref> in Epochs 2-4 and the CAPS group <ref type="bibr">(193.9)</ref>. The most common SAEs were similar in the CAPS and FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>crFMF</head><p>In Epoch 2, the exposure adjusted event rate per 100 patient-days of AEs in the infections and infestations SOC was lower in the ACZ group compared to placebo (0.48 per 100 patient-days in the Any ACZ group and 1.07 per 100 patient days in the placebo group). The most common infections in the Any ACZ group were nasopharyngitis (10.3%) and upper respiratory tract infection (8.6%). There were two SAEs related to infection: pharyngotonsillitis (any ACZ) and atypical pneumonia (placebo).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HIDS/MKD</head><p>In Epoch 2, the exposure adjusted event rate of AEs in the infections and infestations SOC was slightly higher in the ACZ group compared to the placebo group (1.00 per 100 patient-days in the Any ACZ group and 0.56 per 100 patient-days in the placebo group). The data did not suggest a higher frequency of infections in patients treated with 300 mg q4w canakinumab vs patients treated with 150 mg q4w canakinumab. The most common infections in the Any ACZ group were nasopharyngitis (10.3%) and upper respiratory tract infection (8.8%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRAPS</head><p>In Epoch 2, the exposure adjusted event rate of AEs in the infections and infestations SOC was similar between ACZ and placebo (0.56 per 100 patient-days in the Any ACZ group and 0.69 per 100 patient-days in the placebo group). The most common infections in the Any ACZ group were nasopharyngitis (11.6%), and rhinitis and upper respiratory tract infection (9.3% each). There were no SAEs related to infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Malignancies</head><p>No malignancy events were reported in any cohort (crFMF, HIDS/MKD, or TRAPS) during Epoch 2 or Epochs 2-4. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Injection Site Reactions</head><p>The exposure adjusted event rate of injection site reactions was higher in the ACZ group compared to the placebo group. Injection site reactions are known adverse drug reactions with canakinumab and are described in the currently approved labeling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hypersensitivity</head><p>In Epochs 2-4, across the crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS cohorts, few patients reported an AE related to potential hypersensitivity. Cases included gingival swelling, urticarial, and face edema. All of the cases were mild and resolved without study drug discontinuation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug-induced liver injury</head><p>The sponsor performed a review of all possible cases of drug-induced liver injury based on elevated liver enzyme AEs and clinical chemistry lab-identified events. There were no confirmed drug-induced liver injuries in N2301 Epoch 2 or Epochs 2-4. The exposure-adjusted event rate of potential DILI-related AEs in Epoch 2 was higher in the Total ACZ group (16.8, 95% CI: 7.3, 33.1) than the Total placebo group (24.9, 95% CI: 3.0, 89.9). Overall, the proportion of patients with possible DILI-related AEs was slightly lower in the Total ACZ group of N2301 (1.8%) compared with the CAPS pooled population (4.1%).</p><p>In the non-randomized group, a patient with HIDS/MKD experienced a notable SAE of hepatic failure. The patient was 19 months old at the time when he entered the screening Epoch 1. During screening, he had elevated liver function tests and was diagnosed with immune thrombocytopenic purpura treated with pulse steroid therapy. At that time, the liver function test elevations were thought to be related to a viral infection. He was considered a screen failure and did not receive canakinumab. He underwent re-screening approximately three months later. His liver function tests were elevated at screening (ALT 172 IU/L, AST 32 IU/L, and alkaline phosphatase 345 IU/L 58 canakinumab 2mg/kg sc. He subsequently developed worsening hepatic failure and pancytopenia. A liver biopsy showed hepatocyte necrosis. He was treated with G-CSF and methylprednisolone. Given that the patient had liver function elevations and pre-existing immune thrombocytopenic purpura prior to receiving canakinumab, the relationship between the events and exposure to canakinumab is unclear. Further, the clinical picture is complicated by the fact that liver involvement has been reported in HIDS/MKD. 2</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4">Supportive Safety Results</head><p>The profile of AEs and SAEs in the Phase 2 TRAPS, HIDS/MKD and crFMF studies was similar to that observed in Study N2301.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.1">Common Adverse Events</head><p>The table below <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">(Table 13</ref>) displays adverse events by primary SOC. Overall, the rates and types of the AEs reported in the clinical trials of canakinumab for the treatment of SJIA are similar to those observed in the clinical development program of canakinumab for CAPS and no new safety signals were identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>crFMF</head><p>The exposure adjusted event rates per 100 patient-days of AEs were comparable across the treatment groups (2.07 in the 150 mg q4w group, 4.51 in the placebo group, and 2.48 in the Any ACZ group). The most commonly reported AEs by preferred term in the Any ACZ group were FMF (22.4%), injection site reaction (13.8%), and diarrhea (12.1%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>HIDS/MKD</head><p>The exposure adjusted event rates per 100 patient-days of AEs were comparable across the treatment groups (2.42 in the 150 mg q4w group, 2.82 in the placebo group, and 3.86 in the Any ACZ group). The most commonly reported AEs in the Any ACZ group were pyrexia (23.5%), headache (17.6%), and diarrhea and oropharyngeal pain (each 11.8%).</p><p>Both of the non-randomized HIDS/MKD patients who were &gt;28 but &lt;2 years of age experienced AEs during Epoch 2. One patient reported AEs of upper respiratory tract infection, hepatic failure, hypocalcemia, hypophosphatemia, and pancytopenia. The patient had a history of immune thrombocytopenic purpura and abnormal hepatic function prior to enrollment in the study. The other patient had multiple non-serious AEs, the most frequently reported being diarrhea, aphthous ulcer, nasopharyngitis, and pyrexia. This patient also experienced events of alanine aminotransferase increased and aspartate aminotransferase increased.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRAPS</head><p>Reference ID: 3978992</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>59</head><p>The exposure adjusted event rates per 100 patient-days of AEs were comparable across the treatment groups (1.42 in the 150mg q4w group, 2.08 in the placebo group, and 2.76 in the any ACZ group). The most commonly reported AEs in the Any ACZ group were pyrexia (14%), and abdominal pain, injection site reaction, and nasopharyngitis (each 11.6%). between canakinumab and placebo are due to difference in treatment effects on the outcome of interest or due to differences in the proportions of patients remaining on the initially assigned treatment. Furthermore, evaluations of continuous endpoints are essentially uncontrolled due to the small subset of placebo patients remaining on assigned therapy at later time points. Because of the design of the study and the considerable cross-over from the control arm to canakinumab, reliable results are largely limited to short-term endpoints (such as resolution of index flare).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3">Advisory Committee Meeting</head><p>No issues were identified that would warrant another advisory committee meeting. Thus, an advisory committee meeting was not held for this supplemental application.  <ref type="figure">-------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>--This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> The "coding dictionary" consists of a list of all investigator verbatim terms and the preferred terms to which they were mapped. It is most helpful if this comes in as a SAS transport file so that it can be sorted as needed; however, if it is submitted as a PDF document, it should be submitted in both directions (verbatim -&gt; preferred and preferred -&gt; verbatim). </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">---- /s/ ---------------------------------------------------</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CLINICAL FILING CHECKLIST FOR BLA 125319</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IS THE CLINICAL SECTION OF THE APPLICATION FILEABLE? __Yes______</head><p>If the Application is not fileable from the clinical perspective, state the reasons and provide comments to be sent to the Applicant.</p><p>Please identify and list any potential review issues to be forwarded to the Applicant for the 74day letter.</p><p>1. We note the inclusion of multiple endpoints and analyses in the CLINICAL STUDIES sections of each of the proposed labels for the three indications. A focus of the review will be assessing the extent to which the proposed information adds to an understanding of the clinical effects of the drug and how the drug should be used. It is unclear whether the proposed amount of detail is necessary to inform this understanding.</p><p>3. We note your proposal to limit the intended FM indication to those patients in whom colchicine is contraindicated, is not tolerated or does not provide an adequate response. As noted in the Advice letter dated February 7, 2014, and the meeting minutes dated July 1, 2015, it is unclear if it is reasonable to limit the proposed FMF indication since the efficacy of canakinumab might be similar regardless of colchicine response or intolerance.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRAPS Treatment</head><p>• Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) are often used during acute episodes for some symptomatic relief of the myalgias and fever, but offer no protection against future attacks and have no impact on reducing the SAA levels.</p><p>• High dose corticosteroids are often used to treat acute episodes • The use of standard immunosuppressants has not been successful in reducing the frequency and the intensity of the inflammatory episodes. • In a Phase 2 study, a higher dose with a longer interval (300 mg or 4 mg/kg q6w) was demonstrated to be effective in HIDS/MKD patients (Study D2402).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pivotal Clinical Trial Enrollment</head><p>• The protocol for Study N2301 allowed patients aged 2 years or older to be enrolled in the randomized population and very young patients aged &gt; 28 days but &lt; 2 years to be enrolled in the non-randomized population.</p><p>• Patients in Study N2301 received the same initial dosing schedule as recommended for CAPS pediatric patients, but with a shorter interval of administration (150 mg or 2 mg/kg q4w), with the possibility to up-titrate based on the early assessment of clinical response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Immunogenicity profile</head><p>• Incidence of anti-canakinumab antibody development during • No neutralizing antibodies detected in any study.</p><p>-Low rate of loss of efficacy, not found related to patients with ADA. Similarly, there was no evidence of decreased canakinumab levels or target binding related to development of ADA.</p><p>• Potential immunogenicity-related AEs were also not associated with development of ADA.</p><p>• No anaphylaxis or anaphylactoid reactions were reported in any studies.</p><p>• 16% of FMF patients, 32% of HIDS/MKD patients and 36% of TRAPS patients required up-titration to 300 mg q4w (or 4 mg/kg) between Days 8 and 28 to achieve sufficient flare control • Exploratory analyses on the primary and secondary endpoints showed that up-titration to 300 mg q4w further improved the efficacy of canakinumab in patients who did not achieve an adequate response after the first dose of 150 mg • Based on these results, the recommended starting dose for canakinumab in FMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients is 150 mg <ref type="figure">(or  -----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>For randomized HIDS patients: clinical diagnosis of HIDS but no active flare at the time of screening, genetic/enzymatic diagnosis of HIDS, and prior documented history of ≥ 3 febrile acute HIDS flares in a six-month period when not receiving prophylactic treatment. At randomization, patients must have had active clinical HIDS flare as evidenced by PGA ≥ 2 and CRP &gt; 10 mg/L. For randomized TRAPS patients: clinical diagnosis of TRAPS but no active flare at the time of screening, mutation of the TNFRSF1A gene, and chronic or recurrent disease activity periodicity. At randomization, patients must have had active clinical TRAPS flare as evidenced by PGA ≥ 2 and CRP &gt; 10 mg/L.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(a) fever, ≥ 38°C (100.4°F); (b) overall symptoms; (c) abdominal pain; (d) nausea/vomiting; (e) diarrhea; (f ) headaches; (g) chest pain; (h) painful nodes; (i) arthralgia or myalgia; (j) swelling of the joints; (k) eye manifestations; (l) skin rash; (m) pain relief drugs taken.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>••</head><label></label><figDesc>Name: Canakinumab (ILARIS®) • Class: IL-1 inhibitor -Human monoclonal antibody against IL-1 Approved indications: -Cryopyrin-Associated Periodic Syndromes (CAPS), including FCAS and MWS -Active Systemic JIA in patients aged 2 years and older • Proposed indications: -FMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS • Route: lyophilized powder 180 mg (150 mg/mL) • Summary: Fileable from a clinical perspective Proposed Indications • Familial Mediterranean Fever (FMF) in adults and children aged 2 years and older in whom colchicine is contraindicated, is not tolerated, or does not provide an adequate response. • Hyperimmunoglobulin D Syndrome (HIDS)/Mevalonate Kinase Deficiency (MKD) in patients aged 2 years and older. • Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) receptor Associated Periodic Syndrome (TRAPS) in patients aged 2 years and older. fever syndromes include: TRAPS, HIDS/MKD, CAPS, and Periodic Fever • Common to all these is that each has a genetic mutation identified • Manifested by episodic fever, myalgias, arthralgias, and serositis -Febrile episodes impact quality of life -Major source of morbidity is progressive secondary amyloidosis 5 Clinical Overview-FMF • Mutations in the MEFV gene identified in FMF lead to functional change in the pyrin protein which interacts with caspase I and PSTPIP, a protein causally involved in the syndrome of pyogenic arthritis, pyoderma gangrenosum, and acne (PAPA syndrome), another autoinflammatory disease. These genetic alterations in the pyrin gene lead to enhanced IL-mouse model • Approximately 30% to 40% of cases of FMF are only partially responsive to colchicine and 5% are considered resistant -Only approved medication for treatment of FMF in US is colchicine 6 Clinical Overview-HIDS/MKD • Febrile attacks that last 3 to 7 days, every 4 to 6 weeks -</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>indication, Tumor Necrosis Factor Receptor Associated Periodic Syndrome (TRAPS) • SN0212: New indication, Hyperimmunoglobulin D Syndrome/Mevalonate Kinase Deficiency (HIDS/MKD) • SN0213: New Indication, Familial Mediterranean Fever (FMF) • SN0214: New formulation, 150 mg/mL solution for injection in vial 38 Supportive Phase 2 Studies (cont) • A dosing schedule of 150 mg or 2 mg/kg sc q4w was demonstrated to be effective in 3 open-label Phase 2 studies in FMF and TRAPS patients (Studies DTR01, D2204 and D2203).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table of Tables</head><label>of</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 1 :</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Pivotal phase 3 study .......................................................................................16Table 2: Summary of uncontrolled phase 2 studies in crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS18Table 3: Table of assessments......................................................................................26 Table 4: Baseline demographics and background characteristics for Study N2301........31 Table 5: Patient disposition in study N2301 by disease cohort ..........................................34 Table 6: Comparison between treatment groups of patients who responded at Week 16 by cohort, Study N2301, full analysis set ........................................................35 Table 7: Analysis of add-on injection and resolution of index flare at Day 15 ................35 Table 8: Results of the secondary endpoints at Week 16 by cohort, Study N2301, full analysis set .....................................................................................................37 Table 9: Proportion of responders after 16 weeks by age group (full analysis set) ........39 Table 10: Patients with blinded escape at Days 8 to 28 (Full analysis set) ....................42 Table 11: Serious Adverse Events by Primary SOC and PT regardless of relation to treatment in N2301 and CAPS Safety Set ......................................................49 Table 12: Discontinuations in study N2301 ........................................................................53 Table 13: Adverse events by primary SOC regardless of study treatment relationship by dose level .................................................................................................................58</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table of Figures</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Design of Study N2301 ...................................................................................21</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>7</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3978992</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>17 5 Sources of Clinical Data 5.1 Tables of Studies/Clinical TrialsTable 1: Pivotal phase 3 study Source: Sponsor's submission 5.2 Review Strategy</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87 sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab) ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell> Supplement 87: New Indication, colchicine-resistant Familial Mediterranean Fever</cell></row><row><cell>(crFMF)</cell></row><row><cell>There are three sBLA supplements being provided by Novartis to the ILARIS® BLA 125319 in</cell></row><row><cell>close sequence to support registration of three periodic fever syndromes:</cell></row><row><cell> Supplement 85: New indication, Tumor Necrosis Factor Receptor Associated Periodic</cell></row><row><cell>Syndrome (TRAPS)</cell></row><row><cell> Supplement 86: New indication, Hyperimmunoglobulin D Syndrome/Mevalonate Kinase</cell></row><row><cell>Deficiency (HIDS/MKD)</cell></row><row><cell>18</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3978992</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Diagnosis of active peptic ulcer disease i. Coagulopathy j. Significant CNS effects including vertigo and dizziness  Any conditions or significant medical problems which immunocompromise the patient and/ or places the patient at unacceptable risk for immunomodulatory therapy, e.g.</figDesc><table><row><cell>, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>h.</cell></row><row><cell>24</cell></row></table><note>History of organ transplantation b. Elevated alanine aminotransferase (ALT) ≥2x 3x ULN c. Elevated aspartate aminotransferase (AST) ≥2x 3x ULN d. Increase in total bilirubin defined as per Common Terminology Criteria (CTC) Grade ≥2 e. Serious hepatic disorder (Child-Pugh scores B or C) f. Chronic Kidney Disease as per NKF stages ≥4 g. Thyroid disease Mark Boriginia. Absolute neutrophil count decreased as per CTC Grade ≥1 b. Thrombocytopenia CTC Grade ≥1 c. Any active or recurrent bacterial, fungal (with exception of onychomycosis) or viral infection d. HIV infection, Hepatitis B or Hepatitis C infections e. Presence of tuberculosis f. Requirement for administration of antibiotics against latent TB g.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 3 : Table of assessments.</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 3978992</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>flare at Day 15 compared with placebo: TRAPS, 64% versus 23%; HIDS/MKD, 65% versus 37%; crFMF, 81% versus 31%.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>resolved their index</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3978992</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Hyperimmunoglobulin D Syndrome (HIDS)/Mevalonate Kinase Deficiency (MKD) in patients aged 2 years and older.  Tumor Necrosis Factor (TNF) receptor Associated Periodic Syndrome (TRAPS) in patients aged 2 years and older.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>response.</cell></row><row><cell></cell></row><row><cell>31</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 4 : Baseline demographics and background characteristics for Study N2301</head><label>4</label><figDesc>The median duration of disease and median number of flares per year at randomization reflected chronic severe disease (crFMF: 14.7 years, 18 flares per year; HIDS/MKD: 9.8 years, 12 flares per year; TRAPS: 8.2 years, 9 flares per year).</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 3978992</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 5 : Patient disposition in study N2301 by disease cohort</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>crFMF</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Initial</cell><cell cols="2">150mg (N=31)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Placebo (N=32)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>randomized</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Total (N=63)</cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Actual</cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>150mg to</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sequence</cell><cell>21 (68%)</cell><cell>10 (32%)</cell><cell>5 (16%)</cell><cell>22 (69%)</cell><cell>5 (15%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Completed</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>10</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>22</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>62</cell></row><row><cell>Discontinued</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell></row><row><cell>Responders</cell><cell>19 (61.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>2 (6.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>after 16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>weeks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full analysis</cell><cell>31</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>32</cell><cell></cell><cell>63</cell></row><row><cell>Set</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">HIDS/MKD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Initial</cell><cell cols="2">150mg (N=37)</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo (N=35)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>randomized</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Total (N=72)</cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Actual</cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>150mg to</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sequence</cell><cell>18 (49%)</cell><cell>19 (51%)</cell><cell>4 (12%)</cell><cell>19 (54%)</cell><cell>12 (34%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Completed</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>69</cell></row><row><cell>Discontinued</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Responders</cell><cell>13 (35.1%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>2 (5.7%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>15</cell></row><row><cell>after 16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>weeks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full analysis</cell><cell>37</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>35</cell><cell></cell><cell>72</cell></row><row><cell>Set</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>TRAPS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Initial</cell><cell cols="2">150mg (N=22)</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo (N=24)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>randomized</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Total (N=46)</cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Actual</cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>150mg to</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell>Placebo to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell><cell>150mg</cell><cell>300mg</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sequence</cell><cell>11 (50%)</cell><cell>11 (50%)</cell><cell>3 (13%)</cell><cell>19 (79%)</cell><cell>2 (8%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Completed</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>19</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>44</cell></row><row><cell>Discontinued</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell></row><row><cell>Responders</cell><cell>10 (45.5%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>2 (8.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>12</cell></row><row><cell>after 16</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>weeks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Full analysis</cell><cell>22</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>24</cell><cell>46</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Set</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Source: Data from Dr. Lan Zeng, Biometrics Reviewer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Canakinumab</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo</cell><cell cols="3">Treatment Comparison</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">150mg Q4W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>Odds</cell><cell>(95% CI)</cell><cell>One-sided</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell>p-value</cell></row><row><cell>TRAPS</cell><cell>10/22 (46)</cell><cell>(24, 68)</cell><cell>2/24 (8)</cell><cell>(1,27)</cell><cell>9.17</cell><cell>(1.5, 94.6)</cell><cell>0.0050*</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">HIDS/MKD 13/37 (35)</cell><cell>(20, 53)</cell><cell>2/35 (6)</cell><cell>(1, 19)</cell><cell>8.9</cell><cell>(1.7, 86.4)</cell><cell>0.0020*</cell></row><row><cell>crFMF</cell><cell>19/31 (61)</cell><cell>(42, 78)</cell><cell>2/32 (6)</cell><cell>(1, 21)</cell><cell>23.8</cell><cell>(4.4, 228)</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001*</cell></row></table><note>Comparison between treatment groups of patients who responded at Week 16 by cohort, Study N2301, full analysis set* Indicates statistical significance (one-sided) at p-value of 0.025 level based on Fisher exact testSource: Adapted from sponsor's submission</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 7 : Analysis of add-on injection and resolution of index flare at Day 15 Add-on injection before Day 15 Resolution of index flare at Day</head><label>7</label><figDesc>M=number of evaluable patients; CI=confidence Interval. * indicates statistical significance (one-sided) at the 0.025 level based on Fisher exact test.</figDesc><table><row><cell>15</cell></row></table><note>Source: Biometrics Review</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 8 : Results of the secondary endpoints at Week 16 by cohort, Study N2301, full analysis set</head><label>8</label><figDesc>distribution of baseline PGA scores was similar between the randomized canakinumab and placebo groups. Most patients improved to no or minimal disease activity after 16 weeks of canakinumab treatment. In canakinumab-treated patients (150 mg or 300 mg q4w), the proportion of patients with moderate or severe disease decreased from 90.3% at baseline to 3.2% after 16 weeks of treatment in crFMF patients, from 73.0% to 2.7% in HIDS/MKDpatients, and from 59.1% to 4.5% in TRAPS patients. The proportion of canakinumab-treated patients with no or minimal disease activity increased from 0% at baseline to 93.6% after 16 weeks in crFMF patients, from 0% to 91.9% in HIDS/MKD patients, and from 0% to 81.8% in TRAPS patients. Shifts in PGA scores after 16 weeks are not shown for the randomized placebo group, as the majority of placebo patients switched to active treatment starting at Day 8. TRAPS patients treated with canakinumab. Large reductions from baseline were observed by Day 15 and continued through end of Epoch 2 (Week 17/Day 113).The proportion of canakinumab-treated patients (150 mg or 300 mg q4w) with CRP ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks increased from 0% at baseline to 93.5% at Week 17 for crFMF patients, from 0% to 62.2% for HIDS/MKD patients, and from 0% to 77.3% for TRAPS patients.Rapid and sustained decreases in SAA levels were observed in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS patients treated with canakinumab. Large reductions from baseline were observed by Day 15 and continued through end of Epoch 2 (Week 17/Day 113).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Canakinumab</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo</cell><cell cols="3">Treatment Comparison</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">150mg Q4W</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>Odds</cell><cell cols="2">(95% CI) One-sided</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Ratio</cell><cell></cell><cell>p-value</cell></row><row><cell>TRAPS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PGA &lt;2</cell><cell>10/22 (45)</cell><cell>(24, 68)</cell><cell>1/24 (4)</cell><cell>(0.1, 21)</cell><cell>24</cell><cell>(3, 225)</cell><cell>0.0028*</cell></row><row><cell>CRP ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>8/22 (36)</cell><cell>(17, 59)</cell><cell>2/24 (8)</cell><cell>(1, 27)</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>(1, 37)</cell><cell>0.0149*</cell></row><row><cell>SAA ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>6/22 (27)</cell><cell>(11, 50)</cell><cell>0/24 (0)</cell><cell>(0, 14)</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>(1, 269)</cell><cell>0.0235*</cell></row><row><cell>HIDS/MKD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PGA &lt;2</cell><cell>17/37 (50)</cell><cell>(29, 63)</cell><cell>2/35 (6)</cell><cell>(0.7, 19)</cell><cell>14</cell><cell>(3, 66)</cell><cell>0.0006*</cell></row><row><cell>CRP ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>15/37 (41)</cell><cell>(25, 58)</cell><cell>2/35 (6)</cell><cell>(0.7, 19)</cell><cell>13</cell><cell>(3, 64)</cell><cell>0.0010*</cell></row><row><cell>SAA ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>5/37 (14)</cell><cell>(5, 29)</cell><cell>1/35 (3)</cell><cell>(0.07, 15)</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>(1, 52)</cell><cell>0.0778</cell></row><row><cell>crFMF</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PGA &lt;2</cell><cell>20/31 (65)</cell><cell>(45, 81)</cell><cell>3/32 (9)</cell><cell>(2, 25)</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>(4, 69)</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001*</cell></row><row><cell>CRP ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>21/31 (68)</cell><cell>(49, 83)</cell><cell>2/32 (6)</cell><cell>(0.8, 21)</cell><cell>30</cell><cell>(6, 151)</cell><cell>&lt;0.0001*</cell></row><row><cell>SAA ≤10mg/L</cell><cell>8/31 (26)</cell><cell>(12, 45)</cell><cell>0/32 (0)</cell><cell>(0, 11)</cell><cell>17</cell><cell>(0.9, 333)</cell><cell>0.0286</cell></row></table><note>n=number of patients in each cohort who had PGA&lt;2, CRP≤10 mg/L or SAA ≤ 10mg/L; M=total number of patients in the cohort* Indicates statistical significance (one-sided) at p-value of 0.025 level based on Fisher exact test Source: Adapted from Sponsor's submission 6.1.6 Other Endpoints Rapid and sustained improvements in PGA scores were observed in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS subjects treated with canakinumab. In the total group of canakinumab-treated subjects across all three cohorts, a high proportion of patients shifted from moderate or severe (PGA &gt; 2) to no or minimal (PGA &lt; 2) disease activity as early as Day 15, and this improvement was maintained through the end of Epoch 2 (Week 17/Day 113).Rapid and sustained decreases in CRP levels were observed in crFMF, HIDS/MKD andThe proportion of canakinumab-treated patients (150 mg or 300 mg q4w) with SAA ≤ 10 mg/L after 16 weeks increased from 0% at baseline to 25.8% at Week 17 for crFMF patients, from 0% to 21.6% for HIDS/MKD patients, and from 4.5% to 36.4% for TRAPS patients.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 9 : Proportion of responders after 16 weeks by age group (full analysis set)</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">&lt; 18 years</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">≥ 18 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Treatment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Treatment</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>150 mg q4w</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>comparison</cell><cell>150 mg q4w</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>comparison</cell></row><row><cell>Cohort</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>OR (95% CI)</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>OR (95% CI)</cell></row><row><cell>FMF</cell><cell cols="3">10/14 (71.4) 1/15 (6.7) 35.0 (2.9, 1622.67)</cell><cell>9/17 (52.9)</cell><cell>1/17 (5.9)</cell><cell>18.0 (1.8, 836.7)</cell></row><row><cell>HIDS</cell><cell>9/28 (32.1)</cell><cell>2/26 (7.7)</cell><cell>5.7 (1.0, 58.4)</cell><cell>4/9 (44.4)</cell><cell>0/9 (0.0)</cell><cell>Inf (1.1, Inf)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">TRAPS 5/14 (35.7)</cell><cell>1/13 (7.7)</cell><cell>6.7 (0.6, 341.0)</cell><cell>5/8 (62.5)</cell><cell>1/11 (9.1)</cell><cell>16.7 (1.0, 864.2)</cell></row><row><cell cols="7">n=number of responders; M=number of evaluable patients; CI=confidence Interval; Inf=infinity; OR=odds ratio</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Source: Biometrics Reviewer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Dose escalation further improved flare control, reduction of PGA scores to no or minimal disease and return of CRP and SAA to normal levels in TRAPS patients treated with canakinumab. The proportion of canakinumab-treated TRAPS patients who resolved their index flare by Day 29 and had no new flare up to the end of Epoch 2 increased to 72.73% mg q4w before Day 29, reflecting an increase of 22.7%, 27.3% and 4.6%, respectively, for these secondary endpoints.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>titration to 300</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.7.3 TRAPS subjects</cell></row><row><cell>42</cell></row></table><note>when patients received an add-on dose if needed before Day 29, representing a 27.3% higher responder rate with up-titration to 300 mg q4w. The response rates for PGA &lt; 2 (68.18%), CRP ≤ 10 mg/L (63.64%) and SAA ≤ 10 mg/L (31.82%) after 16 weeks also improved with up-</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 10 : Patients with blinded escape at Days 8 to 28 (Full analysis set)</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Canakinumab 150 mg q4w</cell><cell></cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell>Cohort</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>n/M (%)</cell><cell>95% CI</cell></row><row><cell>crFMF</cell><cell>5/31 (16.13)</cell><cell>(5.45, 33.73)</cell><cell>20/32 (62.50)</cell><cell>(43.69, 78.90)</cell></row><row><cell>HIDS</cell><cell>12/37 (32.43)</cell><cell>(18.01, 49.79)</cell><cell>22/35 (62.86)</cell><cell>(44.92, 78.53)</cell></row><row><cell>TRAPS</cell><cell>8/22 (36.36)</cell><cell>(17.20, 59.34)</cell><cell>18/24 (75.00)</cell><cell>(53.29, 90.23)</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">n=number of patients with blinded escape; M=total number of patients evaluated</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: [Study N2301 Week 16-Table 14.2-3.11]</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Reductions in AIDAI score were observed by Weeks 1 -2 and continued through Week 16, with subjects who were up-titrated from 150 mg to 300 mg q4w having higher baseline median AIDAI scores and exhibiting comparable or larger median reductions compared to subjects who continued on 150 mg q4w. Improvements in the physical and psychological component summary scores of the CHQ-PF50 were observed after 16 weeks of treatment with canakinumab; median changes in the CHQ-PF50 physical component summary scores after 16 weeks in the randomized 150 mg q4w group reflected moderate to large benefits of canakinumab treatment to health-related quality of life in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS pediatric subjects &gt; 5 to &lt; 18 years, but no change in the group of HIDS/MKD pediatric subjects who were up-titrated to 300 mg q4.Overall, improvements in SF-12 physical and mental component summary scores (PCS and MCS) were observed as early as Day 29, and for PCS further improved after 16 weeks of treatment with canakinumab in subjects at least 18 years of age. Median changes in SF-12 PCS scores in the randomized 150 mg q4w group after 16 weeks reflected benefits of canakinumab treatment of quality of life in crFMF, HIDS/MKD and TRAPS subjects at least 18 years of age, with no relevant change in the group of crFMF subjects who were up-titrated to 300 mg q4w . In addition, improvements in the SDS global function impairment score were observed after 16 weeks of canakinumab treatment, based on three interrelated domains of work/school, social life and family life.Again, comparisons to placebo from Day 15 onward are limited by the high proportion of subjects switching from placebo to canakinumab starting at Day 8.There was no pooling of efficacy data from the randomized, placebo-controlled pivotal Phase 3 studies and the four open-label, uncontrolled Phase 2 studies, as the study design, efficacy variables and dosing regimens differ across the studies. ) is approved in more than 70 countries, including the European Union and United States, to treat CAPS and SJIA in adults, adolescents and children. The doses and regimens approved for these two autoinflammatory conditions vary by region, with weightbased dosing employed for the low-body weight patients where dosing down to age 2 is approved. The highest doses are approved in SJIA, where patients receive 4 mg/kg (maximum of 300 mg) administered every 4 week.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row><row><cell>7 Review of Safety</cell></row><row><cell>Safety Summary</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS® (canakinumab</cell></row><row><cell>44</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 11</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>):</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Table 11 : Serious Adverse Events by Primary SOC and PT regardless of relation to treatment in N2301 and CAPS Safety Set</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 12 : Discontinuations in study N2301</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_33"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>). He was enrolled in the study and received one dose of open-label</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Mark Borigini, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sBLA125319 85/86/87</cell></row><row><cell>ILARIS (canakinumab)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 13 : Adverse events by primary SOC regardless of study treatment relationship by dose level</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Compensation to the investigator for conducting the study where the value could be</figDesc><table><row><cell>Appendix:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Clinical Investigator Financial Disclosure</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Review Template</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Application Number: BLA 125319 supplements 85/86/87</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Submission Date(s): March 23, 2016</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Applicant: Novartis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Product: Canakinumab</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reviewer: Mark Borigini, MD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Date of Review: August 29, 2016</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Covered Clinical Study (Name and/or Number):</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Was a list of clinical investigators provided:</cell><cell>Yes</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>(Request list from</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">applicant)</cell></row><row><cell>Total number of investigators identified:</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Number of investigators who are sponsor employees (including both full-time and part-time</cell></row><row><cell>employees): 0</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Number of investigators with disclosable financial interests/arrangements (Form FDA 3455):</cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">If there are investigators with disclosable financial interests/arrangements, identify the</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">number of investigators with interests/arrangements in each category (as defined in 21 CFR</cell></row><row><cell>54.2(a), (b), (c) and (f)): N/A</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_36"><head>CLINICAL FILING CHECKLIST FOR BLA 125319</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">CLINICAL FILING CHECKLIST FOR BLA 125319 CLINICAL FILING CHECKLIST FOR BLA 125319</cell></row><row><cell>BLA Number: 125319 Content Parameter Applicant: Novartis Content Parameter</cell><cell cols="3">Stamp Date: March 23 (s85), Yes No NA Comment Yes No NA Comment</cell></row><row><cell>24. For drugs not chronically administered (intermittent or</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">March 28 (s86), and March 29, studies (DTR01,</cell></row><row><cell>short course), have the requisite number of patients been</cell><cell></cell><cell>2016 (s87) X</cell><cell>D2204, D2402,</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">-exposed as requested by the Division? MARK BORIGINI 08/30/2016 JANET W MAYNARD 08/30/2016 Drug Name: Canakinumab (Ilaris®) BLA Type: Supplemental On initial overview of the NDA/BLA application for filing: Content Parameter Yes No NA 25. Has the applicant submitted the coding dictionary 2 used for X mapping investigator verbatim terms to preferred terms? 26. Has the applicant adequately evaluated the safety issues that are known to occur with the drugs in the class to which the X new drug belongs? 27. Have narrative summaries been submitted for all deaths and FORMAT/ORGANIZATION/LEGIBILITY adverse dropouts (and serious adverse events if requested X 1. Identify the general format that has been used for this application, e.g. electronic common technical document (eCTD). by the Division)? X OTHER STUDIES 28. Has the applicant submitted all special studies/data 2. Is the clinical section legible and organized in a manner to allow substantive review to begin? X EFFICACY 16. Do there appear to be the requisite number of adequate and requested by the Division during pre-submission X discussions? 3. Is the clinical section indexed (using a table of contents) and paginated in a manner to allow substantive review to X well-controlled studies in the application? 29. For Rx-to-OTC switch and direct-to-OTC applications, are</cell><cell>D2203) and informed by previous dose considerations in other inflammatory conditions for which canakinumab is approved (sJIA and Comment CAPS). The applicant's strategy for dose selection was reasonable for these rare conditions. Pivotal Study: CACZ885N2301</cell></row><row><cell>begin? 4. For an electronic submission, is it possible to navigate the application in order to allow a substantive review to begin the necessary consumer behavioral studies included (e.g., label comprehension, self selection and/or actual use)? PEDIATRIC USE</cell><cell>X X</cell><cell>X</cell><cell>Indication: FMF, HIDS/MKD, TRAPS</cell></row><row><cell>(e.g., are the bookmarks adequate)? 30. Has the applicant submitted the pediatric assessment, or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>The applicant has</cell></row><row><cell>5. Are all documents submitted in English or are English translations provided when necessary? provided documentation for a waiver and/or deferral?</cell><cell>X X</cell><cell></cell><cell>orphan designation for the three proposed</cell></row><row><cell>LABELING 6. Has the applicant submitted a draft prescribing information that appears to be consistent with the Physician Labeling Rule (PLR) regulations and guidances (see http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/GuidanceComplianceRegulatory Information/LawsActsandRules/ucm084159 htm SUMMARIES 7. Has the applicant submitted all the required discipline summaries (i.e., Module 2 summaries)? 8. Has the applicant submitted the integrated summary of safety (ISS)? 9. Has the applicant submitted the integrated summary of efficacy (ISE)? 10. Has the applicant submitted a benefit-risk analysis for the product? 11. Indicate if the Application is a 505(b)(1) or a 505(b)(2). 505(b)(2) Applications 12. If appropriate, what is the relied upon listed drug(s)? 13. Did the applicant provide a scientific bridge demonstrating the relationship between the proposed product and the listed drug(s)/published literature? 17. Do all pivotal efficacy studies appear to be adequate and PREGNANCY, LACTATION, AND FEMALES AND well-controlled within current divisional policies (or to the extent agreed to previously with the applicant by the MALES OF REPRODUCTIVE POTENTIAL USE 31. For applications with labeling required to be in Pregnancy Division) for approvability of this product based on and Lactation Labeling Rule (PLLR) format, has the proposed draft labeling? applicant submitted a review of the available information 18. Do the endpoints in the pivotal studies conform to previous regarding use in pregnant, lactating women, and females Agency commitments/agreements? Indicate if there were and males of reproductive potential (e.g., published not previous Agency agreements regarding literature, pharmacovigilance database, pregnancy registry) primary/secondary endpoints. in Module 1 (see 19. Has the application submitted a rationale for assuming the applicability of foreign data to U.S. population/practice of http://www.fda.gov/Drugs/DevelopmentApprovalProcess/D evelopmentResources/Labeling/ucm093307.htm)? medicine in the submission? ABUSE LIABILITY SAFETY 20. Has the applicant presented the safety data in a manner consistent with Center guidelines and/or in a manner 32. If relevant, has the applicant submitted information to assess the abuse liability of the product? FOREIGN STUDIES previously requested by the Division? 33. Has the applicant submitted a rationale for assuming the 21. Has the applicant submitted adequate information to assess the arythmogenic potential of the product (e.g., QT interval applicability of foreign data in the submission to the U.S. population? studies, if needed)? 14. Describe the scientific bridge (e.g., BA/BE studies) 22. Has the applicant presented a safety assessment based on all current worldwide knowledge regarding this product? DATASETS 23. For chronically administered drugs, have an adequate 34. Has the applicant submitted datasets in a format to allow reasonable review of the patient data? DOSAGE 15. If needed, has the applicant made an appropriate attempt to determine the correct dosage regimen for this product (e.g., appropriately designed dose-ranging studies)? efficacious? number of patients (based on ICH guidelines for exposure 1 ) been exposed at the dosage (or dosage range) believed to be 35. Has the applicant submitted datasets in the format agreed to previously by the Division?</cell><cell>X X X X X X X X X X X X X X X X</cell><cell>X X X X X</cell><cell>505(b)1 indications. PLLR labeling was submitted in supplement 84, which is under review All studies were globally conducted and, thus, included US sites. While the applicant formal dose-ranging has not performed</cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell><cell>studies, dose</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>considerations were</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>explored in several</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>open label phase 2</cell></row><row><cell>File name: Clinical Filing Checklist for BLA 125319 File name: Clinical Filing Checklist for BLA 125319 File name: Clinical Filing Checklist for BLA 125319</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1 2 3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_37"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Are all datasets for pivotal efficacy studies available and complete for all indications requested? X 37. Are all datasets to support the critical safety analyses available and complete? X 38. For the major derived or composite endpoints, are all of the raw data needed to derive these endpoints included? X</figDesc><table><row><cell>Content Parameter</cell><cell>Yes No NA</cell><cell>Comment</cell></row><row><cell>36. CASE REPORT FORMS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>39. Has the applicant submitted all required Case Report Forms</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>in a legible format (deaths, serious adverse events, and</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>adverse dropouts)?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>40. Has the applicant submitted all additional Case Report</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Forms (beyond deaths, serious adverse events, and adverse</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>drop-outs) as previously requested by the Division?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>41. Has the applicant submitted the required Financial Disclosure information?</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GOOD CLINICAL PRACTICE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>42. Is there a statement of Good Clinical Practice; that all</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>clinical studies were conducted under the supervision of an</cell><cell>X</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IRB and with adequate informed consent procedures?</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>File name: Clinical Filing Checklist for BLA 125319</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_38"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Abdominal pain, vomiting, diarrhea, headache, arthralgia/arthritis -Rash -Continuous spectrum of disease phenotypes (including severe disorder, mevalonic aciduria, with cerebellar ataxia, mental retardation, failure to thrive, and early death) -Mutations in gene encoding mevalonate kinase • originally named HIDS based on high serum levels of IgD -MKD is overall disease name • specifying the type of disease with term, HIDS, for phenotype of fever episodes prospectively included in Study CACZ885N2301.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>27 28 30 36</cell></row><row><cell>FMF Safety TRAPS Safety Summary and Conclusions Midcycle Deliverables Therapies for HIDS/MKD</cell><cell>• Safety set of the 16-week treatment period of Study N2301, • Safety set of the 16-week treatment period of Study N2301, • Filable from a clinical perspective • Efficacy Results • High-dose corticosteroids the most frequently affected primary SOC in the canakinumab the most frequently affected SOC was infections and • Priority review designation -Confirmation of all results proposed for labeling • NSAIDs used during acute episodes for myalgias and group was infections and infestations (39.7%), infestations (34.9%), with nasopharyngitis (11.6%), rhinitis • While efficacy appears robust, will have to consider optimal nasopharyngitis (10.3%), upper respiratory tract infection (9.3%), and upper respiratory tract infection (9.3%) being the labeling and dose (8.6%) most common infectious events • Safety Results -Deaths, SAE, Discontinuations due to AE, Common AE -AEs of interest-As per labeled Warnings, as well as any new -Most commonly reported AEs by PT were FMF (22.4%), -Most commonly reported AEs were pyrexia (14.0%), abdominal safety signals injection site reaction (13.8%), and diarrhea (12.1%) pain (11.6%), injection site reaction (11.6%), and fevers -No protection against future attacks -No impact on reducing SAA levels</cell><cell>• SAEs low (8.6%)-no discontinuations nasopharyngitis (11.6%) Consults • SAEs low (4.7%) -Possibly related: gran liver disease, tonsillitis and atypical</cell><cell>pneumonia -Thought not related to study drug • Recommend foregoing routine OSI inspection</cell><cell>-Approved product, two approved indications, long history</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3928679</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3978992</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Piram M, et al (2014) Ann Rheum Dis; 73:2168-73.Reference ID: 3978992</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="52">Reference ID: 3978992</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2"> Hinson DD, et al (1998)  American Journal of Medical Genetics; 78:408-12.Reference ID: 3978992</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">For chronically administered drugs, the ICH guidelines recommend 1500 patients overall, 300-600 patients for six months, and 100 patients for one year. These exposures MUST occur at the dose or dose range believed to be efficacious.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7">Reference ID: 3928679</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8">Reference ID: 3928679</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="25">Reference ID: 3928679</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="39">Reference ID: 3928679</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="46">Reference ID: 3928679Dose Recommendations</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">mg/kg) every 4 weeks, with the possibility to up-titrate to 300 mg (or 4 mg/kg) every 4 weeks for those patients who do not achieve sufficient control after the first dose of 150 mg.47Reference ID: 3928679</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3928679</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Source: Sponsor's submission</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.3">Dropouts and/or Discontinuations</head><p>There was a &gt;90% completion rate overall and across crFMF, HIDS, and TRAPS cohorts. There were very few discontinuations; the most common reasons for discontinuation were lack of efficacy and subject/guardian decision <ref type="table">(Table 12)</ref>.</p><p>Clinical Review Mark Borigini, MD sBLA125319 85/86/87 ILARIS (canakinumab) 60</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ACZ885=canakinumab</head><p>Source: Sponsor's submission</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.2">Laboratory Findings</head><p>The potential drug-induced liver injury events consisted mainly of mild hepatic transaminase elevations and none was confirmed to reflect severe liver injury attributable to canakinumab and without other identified causes. Less than five percent of those subjects exposed to canakinumab experienced a neutropenia-related AE.</p><p>The rate of all biochemistry abnormalities was lower or comparable to patients in the pooled CAPS population. The increases in creatinine in the Total ACZ group (28.4%) were comparable to CAPS patients (26.6%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.3">Vital Signs</head><p>Overall, the majority of subjects exposed to canakinumabmaintained normal vital sign measurements for crFMF, for HIDS/MKD, and for TRAPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4">Electrocardiograms (ECGs)</head><p>There were no abnormalities attributable to canakinumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.5">Special Safety Studies/Clinical Trials</head><p>Not applicable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.6">Immunogenicity</head><p>The immunogenicity assay used was validated to detect anti-canakinumab antibodies in human serum. No samples were confirmed as being immunogenicity-positive, and thus titration and neutralizing antibody determinations were not performed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5">Other Safety Explorations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.1">Dose Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>Subjects having a cumulative dose &gt;600 mg over 16 weeks were uptitrated to canakinumab 300 mg and would not necessarily have the same characteristics as subjects in the ≤600 mg group (those who responded to canakinumab 150 mg); subjects in the two dose level groups may be at Nonetheless, the incidence of AEs was generally higher (93% versus 79%) in subjects with a dose level &gt;600 mg versus &lt;600 mg in subjects exposed to canakinumab across all cohorts.</p><p>The most frequently affected primary SOC in those subjects exposed to canakinumab was infections and infestations, with a substantially higher incidence of AEs in subjects with cumulative doses &gt;600 mg (50% versus 78% for those with cumulative doses ≤600 mg and &gt;600 mg, respectively). Other SOCs with substantially higher incidence of AEs in subjects with higher doses were: blood and lymphatic system disorders (3% versus 22%), eye disorders (2% versus 14%^), general disorders and administration site conditions (34% versus 54%), gastrointestinal disorders (31% versus 51%), musculoskeletal and connective tissue disorders (18% versus 44%), nervous system disorders (17% versus 34%), respiratory, thoracic and mediastinal disorders (18% versus 36%), and skin and subcutaneous tissue disorders (15% versus 25%) for those with cumulative doses ≤600 mg and &gt;600 mg, respectively.</p><p>The AEs with the higher incidence in subjects with cumulative doses &gt;600 mg compared with subjects on doses ≤600 mg included abdominal pain, arthralgia, cough, diarrhea, headache, injection site reaction, nasopharyngitis, oropharyngeal pain, pyrexia, rhinitis, and vomiting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.2">Time Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>Exposure adjusted (per 100 patient-years) event rates of AEs were analyzed for Study N2301 by dose level, with the pattern of AEs following similar patterns by SOC and PT as AEs by dose level.</p><p>The most frequently affected primary SOC was infections and infestations in subjects exposed to canakinumab, with a similar incidence of AEs in subjects with cumulative doses ≤600 mg and &gt;600 mg; there was no indication of a dose response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.3">Drug-Demographic Interactions</head><p>Subgroup evaluation of AEs was limited due to small sample sizes in each subgroup and the small number of AEs; however, no consistent correlations between the types and frequency of AEs based on race, gender, or age (including children ages 2 to 4 Clinically notable hematological abnormalities by weight were presented for subjects with weight ≤40 kg and &gt;40 kg at baseline. A higher percentage of subjects in the ≤40 kg group (who received 2 mg/kg in place of 150 mg canakinumab) showed a decrease in platelet count and neutrophil count compared with the &gt;40 kg group.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.4">Drug-Disease Interactions</head><p>None noted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.5">Drug-Drug Interactions</head><p>None noted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6">Additional Safety Evaluations</head><p>n/a</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.1">Human Carcinogenicity</head><p>No specific trials were conducted to assess for carcinogenicity in humans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.2">Human Reproduction and Pregnancy Data</head><p>No studies of canakinumab were conducted in pregnant or lactating women.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.3">Pediatrics and Assessment of Effects on Growth</head><p>Canakinumab received orphan drug designation for the treatment of TRAPS (September 4, 2012), hyperimmunoglobulin D and periodic fever syndrome (HIDS) (December 5, 2013), and FMF (December 5, 2013). Thus, these applications are exempt from the requirements of the Pediatric Research Act (PREA). However, these supplements include data in children and the sponsor is seeking approval for patients 2 years of age and older with crFMF, HIDS/MKD, and TRAPS.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.4">Overdose, Drug Abuse Potential, Withdrawal and Rebound</head><p>Not applicable. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Postmarket Experience</head><p>The Sponsor submitted a periodic safety update report for canakinuamb for the reporting period of January 1, 2015 to June 30, 2015, to summarize the post-marketing experience. Canakinumab is currently approved in 74 countries for varying indications. In the United States, canakinumab is approved for the treatment of CAPS and SJIA.</p><p>For the reporting period from January 1, 2015 to June 30, 2015, the Sponsor estimated that the world-wide exposure to canakinumab was patient treatment years. The estimated cumulative patient exposure since June 30, 2015 is patient treatment years. No safety information was included in this submission that changed the known risks of canakinumab. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Labeling Recommendations</head><p>Labeling negotiations are ongoing at the time of this review. A summary of the major labeling considerations is included below: Proprietary interest in the product tested held by investigator: 1 Significant equity interest held by investigator in sponsor of covered study: 0</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indications and usage</head><p>Is an attachment provided with details of the disclosable financial interests/arrangements:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request details from applicant) Is a description of the steps taken to minimize potential bias provided:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request information from applicant)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of investigators with certification of due diligence (Form FDA 3454, box 3) 0</head><p>Is an attachment provided with the reason:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request explanation from applicant) Reviewer's Comments: Any bias resulting from these arrangements is minimized by independent data monitoring by Novartis; multiple investigators used in the studies and double-blind placebo controlled trials. • In all 4 studies, using various dosing regimens, results of the the 3 conditions with clinically meaningful improvements observed across a spectrum of measures (physician and patient based), and in inflammatory biomarkers. In addition, no new safety signals emerged in the study populations. 40</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CLINICAL FILING CHECKLIST FOR BLA 125319</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
				<title level="m">Canakinumab (ACZ885) for FMF, HIDS/MKD, TRAPS Filing Meeting</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2015-05-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">4%), with nasopharyngitis (10.3%) and upper respiratory tract infection (8.8%) being the most common infectious events -Most common AEs-pyrexia (23.5%), headache (17.6%), diarrhea (11.8%)</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">HIDS/MKD Safety • Most frequently affected SOC was infections and infestations</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">57</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>oropharyngeal pain (11.8%) -SAEs (11.8%)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">• Pneumonia in 2 patients in placebo to 150 mg canakinumab group • Incidence of AEs leading to discontinuation in the canakinumab group in the HIDS/MKD 16-week treatment period cohort was 2</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Back-up Slides Reference ID</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">3928679</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
