<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 205353Orig1s000 MEDICAL REVIEW(S) CLINICAL REVIEW ADDENDUM</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 205353Orig1s000 MEDICAL REVIEW(S) CLINICAL REVIEW ADDENDUM</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Template Version: March 6, 2009 Application Type NDA Application 205353 Received March 24, 2014 Review Extension Major Amendment Amendment Received October 7, 2014 PDUFA Goal Date February 24, 2015</note>
					<note>Division / Office Hematology Products / OHOP Reviewers Barry W. Miller, MSN, CRNP Nicole Gormley, MD Division / Office Biometrics 5 / Biostatistics Reviewer Chia-Wen Ko, PhD Review Completion January 14, 2015 Established Name Panobinostat Proposed Trade Name Farydak Therapeutic Class Histone Deacetylase inhibitor Applicant Novartis Pharmaceuticals, Corp. Clinical Review Addendum Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat) 4 Clinical Review Addendum Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat) BARRY W MILLER 01/22/2015 CHIA-WEN KO 01/22/2015 NICOLE J GORMLEY 01/22/2015 CLINICAL REVIEW Application Type NDA Application Number(s) 205353 Priority or Standard Priority Submit Date(s) March 22, 2014 Received Date(s) March 24, 2014 PDUFA Goal Date November 24, 2014 Division / Office DHP/OHOP Reviewer Name(s) Adam George, PharmD. Review Completion Date 08/27/14</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Formulations 10 mg, 15 mg, 20 mg capsules Dosing Regimen 20 mg orally, once daily, 3 times a week for 2 weeks of eight repeated 3-week cycles, followed by eight additional cycles for patients with clinical benefit. Indication In combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least 2 prior therapies including bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent. Intended Population Adults <ref type="bibr">Clinical Review Addendum Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat)</ref>   <ref type="figure">BENEFIT ASSESSMENT .....................................</ref>  <ref type="figure">................................................................................................... 6   3 REVIEW OF EFFICACY ......................................................................................</ref> Clinical Review Addendum Miller, <ref type="bibr">Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat)</ref>   1 Recommendations/Risk Benefit Assessment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Figures</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Recommendation on Regulatory Action</head><p>This review team recommends approval of panobinostat under Subpart H (21 CFR 314.510), in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least two prior therapies including bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent . Accelerated approval is based on the finding of prolonged progression-free survival in a subgroup population of patients from Trial 2308. Confirmation of clinical benefit is required.</p><p>Approval for this indication is supported by the results of Trial 2308, a randomized, controlled trial of panobinostat, intravenous bortezomib, and dexamethasone compared to placebo, bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma who had received 1 to 3 prior therapies. The applicant proposed that panobinostat should be used in all patients with relapsed multiple myeloma, but the benefit-risk assessment does not support approval for that indication. Despite a statistically significant primary endpoint of PFS in the single randomized controlled trial, poor trial conduct resulting in a large amount of missing data limited confidence in the trial results, and significant risks contributed to an overall negative benefit-risk determination for the proposed indication.</p><p>In a pre-specified subgroup analysis of patients who had received prior treatment with both bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent and a median number of two prior treatments, a favorable benefit-risk assessment sufficient for accelerated approval was attained. It remains to be confirmed in post-marketing studies that panobinostat is efficacious, safe, and tolerable in patients with multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Benefit-Risk Assessment</head><p>For the approximately 24,000 patients diagnosed with multiple myeloma in the United States this year, several treatment options are available. Cure is rare and even though many patients can live years with multiple myeloma, relapses are common, serious, and life-threatening. Novel agents are needed to manage this disease. Although there are several active combinations of cytotoxic and immunochemotherapeutics that can be used for treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma, efficacy is variable and the durations of response are limited. Moreover, repeat administration of treatments can be myelosuppressive and cumulative toxicities pose additional challenges.</p><p>Results of the analysis of the subgroup of patients who had received prior treatment with both bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent on Trial 2308, demonstrated that panobinostat, an oral histone deacetylase inhibitor, has activity in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with multiple myeloma who received a median of 2 prior regimens. The safety review, however, revealed substantial hematologic and non-hematological risks, including fatal events. The risks were moderated in part by close monitoring and dose interruption and/or reduction for toxicities, a strategy that would be needed for safe use of the drug in practice. It is not clear that this can be accomplished without explicit instructions to the patients and education of the healthcare providers. With such controls of risk in place, the current measure of clinical benefit outweighs the expected risks for patients with relapsed multiple myeloma who have no other effective therapy available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Recommendations for Labeling</head><p>The following are recommendations for panobinostat labeling based on this review:</p><p>• Limit use to patients who have received at least two prior therapies.</p><p>• Limit use to patients who have received both bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent.</p><p>• Include a boxed Warning addressing cardiac events and arrhythmias, and diarrhea. The Warning and Precautions section should also address myelosuppression, hemorrhage, and hepatotoxicity.</p><p>• Include instructions for dose interruption and modification for patients who develop myelosuppression, diarrhea, nausea or vomiting, QTc prolongation, and hepatic impairment.</p><p>• Include instructions for monitoring for neutropenia and thrombocytopenia, QTc prolongation, and electrolyte abnormalities.</p><p>• Display the incidence of laboratory abnormalities rather than reported adverse events for cytopenias and blood chemistries.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Recommendations for Post-market Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies</head><p>The applicant will develop a communication plan to inform healthcare professionals about the risk of cardiac events (EKG changes and arrhythmias) and diarrhea in patients taking panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.5">Recommendations for Post-market Requirements and Commitments</head><p>1. Conduct a randomized dose-finding clinical trial sufficient to characterize the safety and efficacy of at least two different doses of panobinostat in combination with subcutaneous bortezomib and dexamethasone. Eligible patients will include <ref type="bibr">Clinical Review Addendum Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat)</ref> 6 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma who have been previously exposed to immunomodulatory agents. The primary objective is to assess the overall response rate (ORR) in both treatment arms according to IMWG criteria by investigator assessment. Trial results will inform the dose selection for a randomized Phase 3 confirmatory trial. Submit a complete study report with data.</p><p>2. Conduct a multicenter, randomized, three-arm, double-blind, placebo controlled phase 3 trial of two different doses of panobinostat in combination with subcutaneous bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma who have been previously exposed to immunomodulatory agents. The primary objective will be progression-free survival. Submit a complete study report with full data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Introduction</head><p>This Application was discussed at an Oncologic Drugs Advisory Committee meeting held on November 6, 2014. FDA review of analysis was presented to the Committee and summarized as follows:</p><p>Trial 2308 is a randomized, placebo-controlled, double-blinded trial, with an add-on treatment design using bortezomib and dexamethasone as backbone therapy. Adequate disease response measurements were missing for 25% of patients on trial. The panobinostat treatment arm results included:</p><p>• Improvement in median progression-free survival of 3.9 months as assessed by investigators.</p><p>• Improvement in median progression-free survival of 1.9 months as assessed by a sensitivity analysis, which included the following as events: death, progression as assessed by investigators, initiation of another antineoplastic therapy, discontinuation of therapy due to disease progression, and disease progression that was documented after 2 or more missing assessments.</p><p>• 6% improvement in overall response rate.</p><p>• Increased incidence of deaths not due to progressive disease (7% vs. 3.5%) and adverse events of myelosuppression, hemorrhage, infection, and cardiac toxicity.</p><p>• No statistically significant difference in overall survival.</p><p>• No difference between arms in a time-to-treatment failure sensitivity analysis, which included the following as events: death, disease progression as assessed by investigators, and discontinuations due to adverse events. <ref type="bibr">Clinical Review Addendum Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat)</ref> Following FDA, Applicant, and Open Public Hearing presentations, the Committee was asked to discuss and vote on the following: Given this benefit to risk profile of the addition of panobinostat to bortezomib and dexamethasone, does the benefit outweigh the risks for patients with relapsed multiple myeloma?</p><p>In response, five of the seven committee members voted "No" and two voted "Yes". Those committee members who voted in the negative described unease regarding the lack of additional data, such as improvement in overall survival or quality of life endpoints, to support the observed improvement in progression-free survival (PFS). While these committee members generally agreed that Trial 2308 demonstrated that panobinostat shows activity in patients with myeloma, concerns with the toxicity and uncertain magnitude of PFS improvement were cited as contributing to a negative benefit to risk profile overall.</p><p>Some members hypothesized that toxicities exhibited on Trial 2308 may be better managed in the United States as compared to the international sites from the trial, but that the data under consideration does not provide evidence of this. One committee member specifically questioned whether the dose and combination of agents from the trial was ideal for maximizing benefit while minimizing toxicity. With regard to magnitude of improvement in PFS, some committee members referred to the censoring and missing data as raising questions about this magnitude, particularly in light of the lack of supportive data from other assessed endpoints.</p><p>Several committee members who voted "No" encouraged the applicant to continue to pursue clinical development of this agent in hopes of better elucidating a population of patients with multiple myeloma who would safely benefit from treatment with panobinostat in combination with other treatment. Committee members who voted "Yes" described a judgment that the demonstrated magnitude of improvement in PFS was sufficient to support a positive benefit to risk profile for the use of panobinostat in this complex and challenging population of patients.</p><p>After the Advisory Committee meeting and in consideration of the advice received, the Applicant proposed a modified indication for the use of panobinostat based on a prespecified subgroup of patients. The Applicant submitted additional subgroup analyses for FDA review; which constituted a major amendment to the Application. Review of the additional analyses relevant to the proposed indication based on the subpopulation is included herein. The key efficacy findings based on the complete trial population of 768 patients, as detailed in the primary Clinical Review of Efficacy, follows:</p><p>• Investigator-assessed median PFS difference was 3.9 months: 12.0 months in the panobinostat + bortezomib and dexamethasone (BD) arm vs. 8.1 months in the placebo + BD arm. The hazard ratio was 0.63 (95% CI: 0.52, 0.76), p-value &lt;0.0001.</p><p>• An interim analysis for OS was not mature.</p><p>• Overall response rate (ORR) was 61% [11% complete response (CR)] on the panobinostat + BD arm with a median duration of response (DOR) of 13.1 months vs. 55% (6% CR) in the placebo + BD arm with median DOR of 10.9 months.</p><p>• A sensitivity analysis of Independent Review Committee-assessed median PFS resulted in a difference of 2.2 months: 9.9 months in the panobinostat + BD arm vs. 7.7 months in the placebo + BD arm. The hazard ratio was 0.69 (95% CI: 0.58, 0.83), p-value &lt;0.0001.</p><p>Limitations to confident interpretation of the randomized controlled trial include: Missing data contributed to the high proportion of censored events in the analysis of PFS; 47% of events were censored in the panobinostat + BD arm compared to 32% in the placebo + BD arm.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">•</formula><p>In the trial subpopulation of 193 patients who had received prior treatment with both bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent, the median number of prior treatments was two. A summary of the key efficacy findings follows:</p><p>• Investigator-assessed median PFS difference was 4.8 months: 10.6 months in the panobinostat + BD arm vs. 5.8 months in the placebo + BD arm. The hazard ratio was 0.52 (95% CI: 0.36, 0.76). <ref type="bibr">Miller, Gormley, Ko NDA 205353 Farydak (panobinostat)</ref> • ORR was 55% on the panobinostat + BD arm with a median DOR of 12.0 months vs. 41% in the placebo + BD arm with median DOR of 8.3 months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review Addendum</head><p>This subpopulation better represents how patients with multiple myeloma are treated in the U.S., though the median age of patients is even younger than in the entire trial population (60 years). This subgroup will better inform patients and prescribers of the risk and benefit of treatment with panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Methods</head><p>A protocol specified subgroup analysis of patients enrolled on Trial 2308 who had received prior treatment with both bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent was identified by the Applicant as supporting a more favorable benefit-risk determination. This patient subgroup more closely aligns with the current multiple myeloma treatment paradigm for patients treated in the U.S. compared to the overall trial population. Bortezomib, thalidomide, and lenalidomide form the foundation of current standard treatments for primary, maintenance, and relapsed multiple myeloma. Two-and threeagent combinations are preferred regimens. Other agents commonly used include corticosteroids and alkylating agents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Subpopulation: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent</head><p>Efficacy analyses were performed on the subpopulation of 193 patients on Trial 2308 who had received prior treatment with bortezomib and with lenalidomide or thalidomide. This subgroup of 193 patients was defined using the patient treatment history dataset.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.1">Demographics</head><p>Compared to the overall trial population, this subgroup was comprised of a larger percentage of patients from the United States (15%). The median age of 60 years is even younger than the overall trial population (63 years) and 9 years younger than the median age (69 years) at myeloma diagnosis in the U.S. ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature.    </p><formula xml:id="formula_1">--------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------- /s/ ---------------------------------------------------- Established</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Tables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Recommendations/Risk Benefit Assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Recommendation on Regulatory Action</head><p>The clinical safety reviewer does not recommend granting the Applicant approval of NDA 205353 for the use of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least 1 prior therapy. In the opinion of this reviewer, the increased rate of grade &gt;3 toxicities and serious adverse events along with the imbalance of deaths due to treatment emergent events associated with the combination of panobinostat in combination with dexamethasone is not outweighed by a 3.9 month improvement in investigator assessed median progression free survival. This reviewer recommends that this application be presented to an Oncology Drugs Advisory Committee in order to seek the opinion of hematology oncology experts on the benefit:risk profile of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone for the treatment of patients with relapsed multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Risk Benefit Assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risks</head><p>Based upon review of the safety data from 758 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma evaluable for safety in the randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial (D2308), the regimen of panobinostat 20 mg administered orally once daily 3 times a week <ref type="bibr">(days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10, 12)</ref>, on a 2 weeks on 1 week off schedule for up to 16 cycles in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone is associated with added toxicity and is not well tolerated compared to treatment with bortezomib and dexamethasone. In trial D2308 there were 386 patients who were exposed to investigational therapy with panobinostat 20 mg in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. A total of 372 patients were exposed to the control arm of bortezomib in combination with dexamethasone (a standard U.S. regimen for the treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma).</p><p>Grade 1-4 adverse events occurred in 99.7% of patients in both treatment arms. The most common adverse events that occurred in &gt;20% of patients in the panobinostat arm and at a &gt;10% greater frequency than the control arm were diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, fatigue, nausea, neutropenia, peripheral edema, decreased appetite, hypokalemia, pyrexia and vomiting. The frequency of patients that experienced grade &gt;3 adverse events was higher in the panobinostat arm 95% (n=367) compared to the incidence in the control arm 83% (n=307). The most common (&gt;10%) grade &gt;3 toxicities that occurred more frequently in the panobinostat arm compared to the control arm were Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) thrombocytopenia (31% vs. 11%), diarrhea (26% vs. 9%), pneumonia (10% vs. 8%) and neutropenia (10% vs. 2%). Serious adverse events were also more common in the panobinostat arm with 230 patients (60%) experiencing at least 1 SAE compared to 155 patients (42%) in the control arm. The most common SAEs that occurred in &gt;5% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to the control arm were pneumonia (15% vs. 11%), diarrhea (11% vs. 2%) and thrombocytopenia (7% vs. 2%). Fifty-five percent of patients treated with panobinostat 55% (n=211) experienced an adverse event that led to hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization compared to 37% (n=138) of patients treated with the control arm.</p><p>The addition of panobinostat to bortezomib and dexamethasone led to reduced tolerability. Overall, 36% of patients receiving panobinostat discontinued therapy due to an adverse event compared to 20% of patients (n=76) in the control arm. The most common reason for treatment discontinuation in the panobinostat arm was diarrhea which accounted for 4% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 2% of patients in the control arm. Adverse events of any toxicity grade leading to treatment interruption or dose modification occurred 89% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 76% patients in the control arm. The two most common reasons for dose modification or treatment interruption in the panobinostat arm compared to the control arm were thrombocytopenia (31% vs. to 11%) and diarrhea (26% vs. 9%).</p><p>During the trial, 26 patients (7%) in the panobinostat arm died due to treatmentemergent toxicities compared to 12 patients (3%) in the control arm. The categories of hemorrhage and infection were the main contributors to the observed imbalance of deaths between the treatment arms. Five patients in the panobinostat arm died due to hemorrhage compared to 1 patient in the control arm. Ten patients died due to infection in the panobinostat arm compared to 6 in the control arm.</p><p>The toxicities of primary concern with this Applicant were asthenic conditions, severe gastrointestinal toxicity (nausea, vomiting and diarrhea) leading to serious events of dehydration, severe thrombocytopenia leading to serious hemorrhagic events, neutropenia resulting in severe infections such as pneumonia and sepsis. Of particular concern is the increased number of deaths due to hemorrhage. All 5 of the patients who died due to hemorrhage had grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia at the time of the event. Patients in the control arm of trial D2308 also experienced grade &gt;3 events of thrombocytopenia but in contrast only 1 patient died. This finding implies that the dose modification and supportive care strategies used to mitigate the risk of hemorrhage due to thrombocytopenia with panobinostat were not adequate. This is particularly concerning given the fact that in clinical practice patients may not be monitored as frequently and may therefore be subjected to an increased risk of bleeding due to severe thrombocytopenia. Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk conclusion</head><p>Trial D2308 demonstrated the proposed regimen of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone is associated with severe toxicities such as asthenic conditions, severe gastrointestinal toxicity (nausea, vomiting and diarrhea) leading to serious events of dehydration, severe thrombocytopenia leading to serious hemorrhagic events, neutropenia resulting in severe infections such as pneumonia and sepsis. All of these toxicities occurred at a rate that is higher than the control arm of bortezomib and dexamethasone which is a standard regimen with known clinical benefit for the treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma. In addition, these toxicities contributed to an increased number of patients on panobinostat discontinuing therapy or requiring a dose reduction or treatment interruption. These toxicities also led to a two fold increase in treatment emergent deaths. In patients with multiple myeloma disease progression is not immediately life threating and does not typically require immediate initiation of therapy. For this reason it is difficult to justify that a 3.9 month improvement in median PFS outweighs the risk of the severe toxicity and increased number of deaths associated with panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies</head><p>None proposed at the time of finalization of this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Recommendations for Postmarket Requirements and Commitments</head><p>This reviewer is recommending the Applicant receive PMRs for the following:</p><p> Based upon the dose-related toxicity findings from trial B2207, the increased rate of adverse events requiring dose modification or interruption in trial D2308 and the Applicants dose intensity analysis, the Applicant should conduct a doseranging trial to evaluate the safety and efficacy of lower doses or an alternate dosing regimen of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone.</p><p> To submit the data from the final analysis of overall survival for trial D2308. Applicant's proposed indication: in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, is indicated for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma, who have received at least 1 prior therapy.</p><p>Applicant's proposed dosage and administration: 20 mg once daily orally, 3 times a week (days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10, 12), on a 2 weeks on 1 week off dosing regimen for eight cycles (each cycle consist of 3 weeks (21 days). Patients with clinical benefit should continue treatment for eight additional cycles [each cycle is 3 weeks long (21 days)].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Tables of Currently Available Treatments for Proposed Indications</head><p>There are 3 products that are indicated for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least 1 prior therapy. In addition, cyclophosphamide, melphalan and carmustine have broad indications for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma. In 2008 bortezomib was granted a broad indication for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma. This approval was based upon new data submitted in an efficacy supplement from a randomized trial that compared bortezomib, melphalan and prednisone to melphalan and prednisone in patients with previously untreated multiple myeloma. The justification for the broad indication was also supported by the 2005 approval. Carfilzomib is approved for the treatment of patients with relapsed multiple myeloma, but after two prior therapies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Availability of Proposed Active Ingredient in the United States</head><p>Panobinostat is not currently marketed in the United States.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Important Safety Issues With Consideration to Related Drugs</head><p>Panobinostat is a histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitor. The pharmacologic class of HDAC inhibitors is associated with the following risks:  Severe myelosuppression manifested as thrombocytopenia, leukopenia and anemia  Serious and fatal infections including pneumonia and sepsis  Electrocardiographic changes such as QT prolongation and T-wave and STsegment changes.  Severe nausea vomiting and diarrhea  Severe dehydration  Myocardial ischemia Currently there are two histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors which are approved for use in the United States, Zolinza ® (vorinostat) and Istodax ® (romidepsin). Both romidepsin and vorinostat are approved for use in patients with hematologic malignancies. The toxicities described above are known safety issues with the currently marketed HDAC inhibitors and are included in the labeling for either or both of these agents.</p><p>The Applicant is proposing an indication for "in combination with bortezomib" which is based upon the results of a randomized trial that evaluated panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. For this reason it is also relevant to discuss the toxicities of bortezomib. Bortezomib is associated with the following toxicities:</p><p> Severe neuropathy; sensory and motor  Hypotension  Acute development or exacerbation of congestive heart failure and new onset decreased left ventricular ejection fraction Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>13</head><p>On 01/25/12, FDA notified the Sponsor that their proposed tradename "Farydak" was acceptable.</p><p>The Agency and the Applicant had a type C meeting on February 29, 2012 to discuss the statistical and clinical issues related to the Phase 3 study CLBH589D2308. A summary of the discussions related to the safety of panobinostat are summarized below:  The Agency recommended against the Sponsor's proposed interim analysis for efficacy. During the meeting the Sponsor proposed using the first interim analysis for futility and moving the second interim analysis to the time of approximately 368 events (80% information). This was acceptable to the Agency.  The Agency agreed to the Applicant's proposal that the summary of clinical safety would include analyses of pooled safety data from 2 patient populations. The populations were; 1) patients with relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma that received panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone and 2) patients that received single agent panobinostat at a dose of 20 mg three time per week being treated for various disease states, including multiple myeloma  The Agency agreed to the format of the datasets to be submitted for the NDA.</p><p>The format was the Novartis standard data structure and not CDISC. We stated that CDISC datasets were preferred.</p><p>The Agency and the Applicant had a Type B meeting on February 5, 2014 to discuss the content and format of the NDA for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least 1 prior therapy. A summary of the discussions related to the safety of panobinostat are summarized below:  We agreed to the proposed content and format of the Summary of Clinical Efficacy (SCE) and Summary of Clinical Safety (SCS) and to waive the requirement for providing an Integrated Summary of Effectiveness (ISE) and Integrated Summary of Safety (ISS)  We recommended that diarrhea be included in the Applicant's proposed analyses of notable adverse events in the SCS  We agreed with the proposed categories for patient narratives  We agreed to the proposed content of the safety update</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Other Relevant Background Information</head><p>Reference ID: 3617392</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(b) (4)</formula><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Summary of findings from trial E2214 For the 129 patients treated in study E2214, only 1 complete response (CR) was identified by independent review committee (IRC) assessment vs. 5 CR (&lt; 4%) by investigator. The 22% (by IRC) to 27% (by investigator) ORR put forward by the applicant was primarily driven by patients who achieved a partial response (PR) (21% by IRC and 23% by investigator) which is not a meaningful clinical outcome in the proposed patient population and disease setting. The duration of the only one IRC assessed CR was less than two weeks.</p><p>Of the 129 patients exposed to panobinostat in trial E2214 the most frequent AEs of any grade were thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, nausea, fatigue, vomiting, anemia and pyrexia. The most frequent Grade 3/4 AEs were thrombocytopenia (79.1%), neutropenia (22.5%) and anemia (20.9%). Twelve (9%) patients experienced bleeding events on treatment (8 patients with grade 3/4), 11 patients recovered and 1 patient died due to sepsis/dengue fever. Among these 12 patients, all had thrombocytopenia of any grade. The most common bleeding events included epistaxis (11.6%) and petechiae (9.3%). Hypothyroidism regardless of causality was reported in 20 patients (15.5%), all of which were in grade 1 or 2 in severity with 17 of the 20 patients (85%) had prior radiation therapy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Ethics and Good Clinical Practices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Submission Quality and Integrity</head><p>The submission contained all required components of the electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD). The overall quality and integrity of the application was reasonable to begin review of the application. During review of the datasets the review team was unable to find a dataset for trial D2308 that included patient ID number and treatment arm assignment and were unable to confirm patient assignment to the investigational arm or control arm. The Applicant was sent an information request to provide this dataset. The Applicant provided this dataset in SD#3 of the NDA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Compliance with Good Clinical Practices</head><p>For trials D2308, B2207 and DUS71 the protocols, protocol amendments and informed consents, were reviewed by independent ethic committee (IEC) or institutional review board (IRB) for each investigational site. All trials were conducted according to the ethical principles of the Declaration of Helsinki. Written informed consent was obtained </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Significant Efficacy/Safety Issues Related to Other Review Disciplines</head><p>At the time of finalization of the clinical safety review the reviews of other disciplines were pending. Please refer to the CDTL review for discussion of the chemistry manufacturing and controls, preclinical pharmacology/toxicology and clinical pharmacology reviews. discussion of the efficacy review strategy. The safety clinical review was primarily based on the safety data from trial D2308. The safety data for trial B2207 and DUS71 were also reviewed and provide supportive information to the safety evaluation of panobinostat for the proposed indication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Sources of Clinical Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Tables of Studies/Clinical Trials</head><p>The electronic submission, with the clinical study reports, and other relevant documents from the submission were reviewed and analyzed. Trial D2308 was a multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial that evaluated panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone compared to placebo in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma. Patients were required to have received at least 1 prior therapy (but no more than 3 prior therapies) for their multiple myeloma and have a need for treatment per the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG) definition. A total of 762 patients were planned to be randomized 1:1 to receive panobinostat+ bortezomib +dexamethasone or placebo + bortezomib+ dexamethasone. Patients were stratified based upon the following factors:</p><p> Number of prior lines of therapy: 1 vs. 2 or 3 Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p><p> Prior use of bortezomib: yes or no</p><p>The primary objective of the study was to compare progression-free survival (PFS) in patients treated with panobinostat in combination with bortezomib/dexamethasone vs. patients treated with placebo in combination with bortezomib/dexamethasone. The key secondary objective was to compare overall survival (OS) between the treatment arms.</p><p>Patients, investigator staff, persons performing the assessments, and data analysts were blind to treatment assignment from the time of randomization until final database lock. Unblinding was permitted in case of patient emergencies.</p><p>Trial population (Source: protocol D2308 amendment version 5) Inclusion criteria 1. Patient has a previous diagnosis of MM, based on IMWG 2003 definitions; all three of the following criteria had been met: a. Monoclonal immunoglobulin (M-component) on electrophoresis, and on immunofixation on serum or on total 24 hour urine (or demonstration of M protein in cytoplasm of plasma cell for non secretory myeloma) b. Bone marrow (clonal) plasma cells &gt;10% or biopsy proven plasmacytoma c. Related organ or tissue impairment (CRAB symptoms: anemia, hypercalcemia, lytic bone lesions, renal insufficiency, hyperviscosity, amyloidosis or recurrent infections) 2. Patient with 1 to 3 prior lines of therapy who requires retreatment of myeloma for one of the 2 conditions below: a. Relapsed, defined by disease that recurred in a patient that responded under a prior therapy, by reaching a MR or better, and had not progressed under this therapy or up to 60 days of last dose of this therapy. Patients who received prior treatment with bortezomib may be eligible b. Relapsed and refractory to a therapy provided that meets both conditions:</p><p>i. Patient has relapsed to at least one prior line ii. And patient was refractory to another line (except bortezomib), by either not reaching a MR, or progressed while under this therapy, or within 60 days of its last dose 3. Patient has measureable disease at study screening defined by at least one of the following measurements as per IMWG 2003 criteria: a. Serum M-protein &gt;1 g/dL b. Urine M-protein &gt;200 mg/24 hour 4. Patient treated with local radiotherapy with or without concomitant exposure to steroids for pain control or management of cord/nerve root compression, is eligible. Two weeks must have lapsed since last date of radiotherapy, which is recommended to be a limited field. Patients who require concurrent radiotherapy should have entry to the protocol deferred until the radiotherapy is completed and 2 weeks have passed since the last date of therapy Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 20 5. Patient's age is &gt;18 years at time of signing the informed consent 6. Patient has an Eastern Cooperative Oncology Group (ECOG) performance status &lt;2 7. Patient has the following laboratory values within 3 weeks before starting study drug: a. Absolute neutrophil count (ANC) &gt;1.5 x 10 9 /L b. Platelet count &gt;100 x 10 9 /L c. Serum potassium, magnesium, phosphorus, within normal limits (WNL) for institution d. Total calcium (corrected for serum albumin) or ionized calcium greater or equal to lower normal limits (&gt; LLN) for institution, and not higher than CTCAE grade 1 in case of elevated value e. AST/SGOT and ALT/SGPT &lt;2.5 x ULN f. Serum total bilirubin &lt;1.5 x ULN (or &lt;3 x ULN if patient has Gilbert syndrome) g. Serum creatinine &lt;1.5 x ULN or calculated creatinine clearance &gt;60 ml/min 8. Patient has provided written informed consent prior to any screening procedures 9. Patient is able to swallow capsules 10. Patient must be able to adhere to the study visit schedule and other protocol requirements 11. Women of childbearing potential must have a negative serum pregnancy test at baseline Exclusion criteria 1. Patients who have progressed under all prior lines of anti-MM therapy (primary refractory) 2. Patients who have been refractory to prior bortezomib (i.e., did not achieve at least a MR, or have progressed under it or within 60 days of last dose) 3. Allogeneic stem cell transplant recipient presenting with graft versus host disease either active or requiring immunosuppression 4. Patient has shown intolerance to bortezomib or to dexamethasone or components of these drugs or has any contraindication to one or the other drug, following locally applicable prescribing information 5. Patient has grade &gt;2 peripheral neuropathy or grade 1 peripheral neuropathy with pain on clinical examination within 14 days before randomization 6. Patient received prior treatment with deacetylase inhibitors including panobinostat 7. Patient needing valproic acid for any medical condition during the study or within 5 days prior to first administration of panobinostat/study treatment 8. Patient taking any anti-cancer therapy concomitantly (bisphosphonates are permitted only if commenced prior to the start of screening period) Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 9. Patient has secondary primary malignancy &lt;3 years of first dose of study treatment (except for treated basal or squamous cell carcinoma, or in situ cancer of the cervix) 10. Patient who received: a. A prior anti-myeloma chemotherapy or medication including IMiDs and dexamethasone &lt;3 weeks prior to start of study b. Experimental therapy or biologic immunotherapy including monoclonal antibodies &lt;4 weeks prior to start of study c. Prior radiation therapy &lt;4 weeks or limited field radiotherapy &lt;2 weeks prior to start of study 11. Patient has not recovered from all therapy related toxicities associated with above listed treatments to less than grade 2 CTCAE 12. Patient has undergone major surgery &lt;2 weeks prior to starting study drug or who have not recovered from side effects of such therapy to less than grade 2 CTCAE 13. Patients with evidence of mucosal or internal bleeding cause, uncontrolled thyroid dysfunction) that could cause unacceptable safety risks or compromise compliance with the protocol 19. Patient has a known history of HIV seropositivity or history of active/treated hepatitis B or C (a test for screening is not required) 20. Women who are pregnant or breast feeding or women of childbearing potential not willing to use a double method of contraception during the study and 3 months after the study evaluation completion treatment, of which one must be a barrier method. 21. Patient is a male not willing to use a barrier method of contraception (a condom) during the study and for 3 months after the study evaluation completion treatment</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatments</head><p>The trial was conducted in 2 treatment phases. In treatment phase 1 (cycles 1-8) patients received panobinostat at a dose of 20mg orally (or matching placebo) on days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10 and 12 of a 21 day cycle. Bortezomib was administered intravenously (IV) at a dose of 1.3 mg/m 2 on days 1, 4, 8 and 11. Dexamethasone was administered at a dose of 20 mg orally on days 1, 2, 4, 5, 8, 9, 11 and 12.</p><p>Patients who met the modified EBMT criteria for no change (NC) [i.e., did not meet the criteria for complete response (CR), near-complete response (nCR), partial response (PR), minimal response (MR), or progressive disease (PD)/relapse] or achieved a response of MR or better and did not have any toxicity greater than CTCAE grade &gt;2 could enter treatment phase 2. Treatment phase 2 started with cycle 9. In treatment phase 2 (cycles 9-12) patients received panobinostat at a dose of 20 mg orally (or matching placebo) on days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10, 12, 22, 24, 26, 29, 31 and 33 of a 42 day cycle. Bortezomib as administered intravenously (IV) at a dose of 1.3 mg/m 2 on days 1, 8, 22 and 29 and dexamethasone was given at a dose of 20 mg orally on days 1, 2, 8, <ref type="bibr">9, 22, 23, 29 and 30.</ref> Reviewer comment: The dose of bortezomib utilized for trial D2308 is slightly different than the dose schedule recommended in the prescribing information for Velcade. The recommended dose schedule of bortezomib for extended therapy of more than 8 cycles is 1.3 mg/m 2 administered once weekly for 4 weeks (Days 1, 8, 15 and 22) followed by a 13 day rest period (Days 23 to 35). The dosing regimen of bortezomib used for trial D2308 differs from the dosing regimen of bortezomib recommend in the prescribing information in that for trial D2308 the recommended day 15 dose was omitted and a day 29 dose was added. From a safety standpoint it is unlikely that the tolerability profile of the schedule used in trial D2308 will have any clinically meaningful difference from the schedule recommended in the prescribing information for Velcade.</p><p>Panobinostat/placebo (Source: section 6.6.2 of D2308 protocol amendment 5) Patients were instructed to take oral panobinostat/matching placebo three times a week at the same time on each dosing day. Doses were to be separated by a minimum of Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 23 30 hours. Each dose of panobinostat/placebo was to be taken with a large glass (approximately 240 mL) of non-carbonated water. Patients were instructed to swallow the capsules whole and not chew them. If vomiting occurred during the course of treatment, then no re-dosing of the patient was allowed before the next scheduled dose.</p><p>Patients were instructed to avoid grapefruits, grapefruit juice, Seville (sour) oranges and Seville orange juice throughout the study period.</p><p>Bortezomib (Source: section 6.6.2 of D2308 protocol amendment 5) Before each dose of bortezomib the following criteria were to be met:  platelet count was ≥ 25 x 10 9 /L (platelet transfusion support was permitted)  ANC was ≥ 750/μL (growth factor support was permitted as defined in the protocol)</p><p>The amount of drug to be administered was determined based on body surface area. Body surface area was calculated based on body weight using a standard nomogram.</p><p>The dose was calculated on Day 1 of each cycle; the dose administered was to remain the same throughout each cycle but was recalculated at the start of the next cycle. If a patient experienced a notable change in weight (e.g. loss or gain of ≥ 8 lbs. or 3.6 kg) within a cycle, as determined by an unscheduled weight assessment, then the patient's dose was recalculated at that time.</p><p>Dexamethasone (Source: Source: section 6.6.3 of D2308 protocol amendment 5) Patients were administered commercially available dexamethasone at a dose of 20 mg per day according to the schedule described above.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1 D2308 trial design</head><p>(Source: <ref type="figure">Figure 4</ref>-1 of D2308 protocol amendment 5) Dose modifications and interruptions (Source: 9.4.6 of D2308 clinical study report) Patients whose study treatment was interrupted due to an adverse event or abnormal laboratory value were to be followed at least once a week for 4 weeks, and subsequently at a minimum of every 4 weeks, until resolution or stabilization of the event, whichever came first.</p><p>If a patient required a dose delay of &gt;21 days from the intended day of the next scheduled dose, the patient was to be discontinued from study treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Panobinostat/placebo</head><p>The dose of panobinostat/placebo could be reduced to the levels described in <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">Table 3</ref>. Dose levels lower than 10 mg three times per week in combination with a minimum 0.7 mg/m 2 dose of bortezomib, with or without dexamethasone, were not permitted. Patients requiring dose modifications lower than these minimum doses were to be discontinued from therapy.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Patients receiving a reduced dose level of panobinostat/placebo due to toxicity could be considered for dose re-escalation to their previously prescribed dose (i.e., 10 mg escalate to 15 mg) if either the study treatment-related AE had reverted in severity to grade ≤ 1 or baseline level, and at least nine scheduled doses at the reduced level had been administered and tolerated.</p><p>The protocol for trial D2308 provided the following guidelines for dose modifications due to toxicity: The protocol also provided guidelines for dose modifications of panobinostat/placebo due to QTcF abnormalities. If a patient could not be dosed due to prolonged QTcF for more than 7 days since last dose, they were to be discontinued from investigational therapy. 30</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bortezomib</head><p>The dose of bortezomib could be reduced by 25% (1.3 mg/m 2 dose reduced to 1.0 mg/m 2 dose; 1.0 mg/m 2 dose reduced to 0.7 mg/m 2 dose). The minimum allowed dose was 0.7 mg/m 2 . Guidelines were provided for dose modifications of bortezomib due to toxicity <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">(Table 6</ref>). Specific dose modification guidelines for neuropathy related to bortezomib were also provided <ref type="table" target="#tab_19">(Table 7)</ref>.  Patients requiring discontinuation of bortezomib due to peripheral neuropathy could continue on panobinostat/placebo ± dexamethasone. Bortezomib could be restarted at any time during treatment phases 1 and 2 if clinically indicated and in accordance with the local prescribing instructions. Patients requiring permanent discontinuation of bortezomib due to any other reason or permanent discontinuation of panobinostat/placebo were to discontinue study treatment and be followed for progressive disease/relapse and survival.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dexamethasone</head><p>The dose of dexamethasone could be reduced to 10 mg. Patients unable to tolerate the minimum dose of dexamethasone 10 mg could continue on the rest of their randomly assigned regimen without receiving dexamethasone. Dose modification guidelines for toxicity related to dexamethasone are described in <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">Table 8</ref>.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Management of diarrhea (Source: section 6.6.5.1.4 of D2308 protocol amendment 5) Patients were instructed to contact their physician at the onset of diarrhea. Each patient was instructed to have loperamide readily available and begin treatment for diarrhea at the first episode of poorly formed or loose stools or the earliest onset of bowel movements that were more frequent than normally expected. Prophylaxis with loperamide was not recommended.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prohibited therapies</head><p>Prohibited treatments included chemo-, biologic or immunologic therapy and/or other investigational agents, as well as deacetylase inhibitors, including valproic acid. Prophylactic anti-emetics such as granisetron could be administered at the discretion of the Investigator. However, anti-emetics associated with QT prolongation (e.g. dolasetron, ondansetron, tropisetron) were prohibited.</p><p>Co-medications which are known to prolong the QT interval and/or induce Torsades de Pointes (strong CYP3A4/5 inhibitors or CYP2D6 substrates) were prohibited unless approved by the Sponsor. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Concomitant medications</head><p>Growth factor support Granulocyte colony stimulating factor (G-CSF) or granulocyte-macrophage colony stimulating factor (GM-CSF) was not to be used prophylactically in the first cycle. G-CSF was to be initiated for an individual patient in accordance with American Society of Clinical Oncology's guidelines <ref type="bibr">(Smith, et al 2006)</ref>, if the patient experienced febrile neutropenia and/or grade 4 neutropenia for &gt;7 days. Growth factors could then be administered prophylactically in all subsequent cycles for that patient.</p><p>Patients who were receiving available recombinant erythropoiesis stimulating agents (ESA) such as epoetin and darbepoetin prior to starting study treatment could continue therapy throughout the study. ESA therapy could also be introduced during the study. Amendment 2, 668 patients randomized: Global amendment to adjust the sample size to compensate for a higher than expected drop-out rate in the absence of any safety concerns. A review of blinded data concluded that the drop-out rate was higher than originally assumed. The main reason for the drop-out rate was that patients who discontinued treatment withdrew their consent to be followed for response assessment as per protocol. As a consequence, the expected drop-out rate as written in the statistical section of the original protocol needed to be updated. <ref type="bibr">March 7, 2012</ref> Amendment 3, 742 patients randomized: This amendment was a global amendment to enhance robustness of the second interim analysis (IA2), in order to provide a more precise estimate of the treatment effect and to increase the probability of detecting a treatment effect. This amendment increased the PFS event fraction for IA2 from 67% to 80% (306 to 368 events). If the study were to be stopped at IA2, the higher fraction of planned PFS events would reduce the risk of an overestimation of the treatment effect. The treatment effect assumptions (HR 0.74) were unchanged. The power to detect a treatment effect and to stop the study at IA2 for efficacy collected data was used in sensitivity analyses of PFS and other efficacy-related endpoints, including an analysis using an independent response assessment in patients for whom M-protein was not measured by PEP or PEP was used without measurement of M-protein spike. The independent response assessments were to be performed by an IRC. September 10, 2013</p><p>Data cut-off for clinical study report</p><p>Reviewer comment: These protocol amendments did not impact the safety evaluation of the treatment arms. I defer to the clinical efficacy reviewer for evaluation of the impact of these amendments on the efficacy findings from trial D2308.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.1.4">Safety evaluation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 2 Trial D2308 Schedule of Study Assessments</head><p>Reference ID: 3617392 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>38</head><p>(Source: section 9.5.4 of D2308 clinical study report) Safety assessments consisted of collecting all adverse events (AEs) and serious adverse events (SAEs), with their severity and relationship to study drug, and pregnancies. Assessments also included the regular monitoring of hematology, coagulation and blood chemistry panels and urinalyses performed at study centers, as well as regular assessments of vital signs, physical condition including performance status, and body weight. A central ECG laboratory ( was used for independent review of ECG evaluations.</p><p>(Source: section 7.5 of D2308 clinical study report Physical examinations including a systematic, abbreviated neurological assessment were conducted at screening, day 1 cycle 1, day 1 of each cycle prior to the administration of study treatment and at the end of treatment visit. Vital signs including oral temperature, respiratory rate, sitting blood pressure, and sitting pulse were conducted at screening, day 1 cycle 1, day 5 cycle 1, day 1 of each cycle prior to the administration of study treatment and at the end of treatment visit. Performance status was evaluated at screening, day 1 cycle 1, day 1 of each cycle prior to the administration of study treatment and at the end of treatment visit. Weight/BSA was measured at baseline, at the start of every cycle, and at the EOT visit. ECG assessments were conducted according the schedule outlined in <ref type="table" target="#tab_25">(Table 9)</ref> Reference ID: 3617392</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(b) (4)</formula><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) A baseline multiple gated acquisition (MUGA) scan or echocardiogram (ECHO) was to be performed at screening (or at day 1 cycle 1 if screening assessment was conducted &gt;7 days prior to first dose of investigational therapy). If the result from this MUGA/ECHO shows a clinically relevant change (e.g. a reduction of &gt;5% or as defined by the institution), a formal cardiac evaluation was to be sought and a repeat MUGA/echo be conducted at the beginning of every-other treatment cycle (or at the discretion of the cardiologist/investigator). More frequent assessments could be performed if medically indicated as determined by the Investigator, and these evaluations were to be recorded on the Unscheduled Visit CRF.</p><p>(Source: section 9.6.3 of D2308 clinical study report) Hematology, coagulation, biochemistry, urinalysis and thyroid function tests were performed by local laboratories. Analyses of serum and urine M-protein, and serum and urine immunofixation assays were also performed locally by the site labs or by locally selected laboratories that served as "central laboratory" for a few sites.</p><p>Hematology included the following parameters: complete blood count (CBC) consisting of red blood cell (RBC), a total white blood cell count (WBC) with differential (total neutrophil count including bands, lymphocyte, monocyte, eosinophil, and basophil counts); hemoglobin (Hgb); and platelet count. Hematology assessments were conducted at screening at day 1 cycle 1, prior to each administration of Bortezomib or ≤72 hours prior to dosing and at the end of treatment visit.</p><p>Coagulation profile included prothrombin time (PT) or International Normalized Ratio (INR), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and fibrinogen. A coagulation profile was required be performed at screening. More frequent assessments could be performed if medically indicated as determined by the investigator, and these Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) evaluations were to be recorded on the unscheduled visit CRF. Coagulation parameters were to be monitored more frequently for patient receiving warfarin or other anticoagulant therapy.</p><p>Urinalysis included dipstick and microscopic exams. Dipstick examination included protein, glucose, blood, and specific gravity. Microscopic examination is only required if dipstick analysis is abnormal (with exception of proteinuria) and includes: WBC/HPF, RBC/HPF, and any additional findings. A urinalysis was required to be performed at screening. Repeat assessments were performed if medically indicated.</p><p>Thyroid Stimulating Hormone (TSH) and free T4 (thyroxine) were measured at screening, prior to treatment on Day 1 of following treatment cycles: 2, 3 and 4 and at the end of treatment visit. More frequent assessments could be performed if medically indicated. Findings from these evaluations were to be recorded on the Unscheduled Visit CRF.</p><p>(Source: section 7.5.5 of D2308 clinical study report) At any time during the trial abnormal laboratory parameters that are clinically relevant (e.g., require dose modification and/or interruption of study drug, lead to clinical symptoms or signs or require therapeutic intervention), were to be recorded in the CRF. When abnormal laboratory values or test results constituted a clinically significant adverse event, they were to be recorded on the CRF Adverse Events page.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Review of Efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Summary</head><p>Please refer to Mr. Miller's review for discussion of the efficacy review of NDA 205353.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Review of Safety</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Summary</head><p>The safety review of the Applicant's proposed dosing regimen of panobinostat 20 mg administered orally once daily 3 times a week (days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10, 12), on a 2 weeks on 1 week off dosing regimen for up to 16 cycle in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma, who have received at least 1 prior therapy utilized the results of the randomized multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial D2308. The safety review of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone also included the results of a dose escalation trial (B2207) and a single arm trial (DUS71).</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Trial B2207 was a dose escalation trial that explored the tolerability of doses of panobinostat from 10 mg to 30 mg in combination with bortezomib at doses of 1 mg/m 2 or 1.3 mg/m 2 administered weekly for 3 weeks. In this trial a total of 17 patients were exposed to panobinostat 20 mg administered 3 times weekly every week of a 21 day cycle which was determined to be the maximum tolerated dose (MTD) in combination with bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2 . Fifteen patients were evaluable for dose limiting toxicities (DLT) and of these patients 3 experienced a DLT <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 13</ref>). In comparison none of the 11 patients treated at lower dose cohorts experienced a DLT. Out of 17 patients exposed to panobinostat in combination with bortezomib at the MTD, 77% of patients had at least 1 adverse event that required dose adjustment or interruption. In comparison, out of the 14 patients in cohort 1 and 2 that were evaluable for toxicity 8 patients (57%) experienced at least 1 adverse event that led to dose adjustment or interruption. Eight patients (47%) treated at the MTD experienced thrombocytopenia that led to dose adjustment or interruption. In comparison, out of the 14 patients in cohort 1 and 2 that were evaluable for toxicity 5 (36%) experienced thrombocytopenia that led to dose adjustment or interruption. All of the patients (100%) dosed at the MTD experienced a grade 3-4 adverse event. More important is the finding that 77% (n=13) of patients treated at the MTD experienced a serious adverse compared to 43% (n=6) patients in cohorts 1 and 2.</p><p>Reviewer Comment: This early dose escalation trial provides preliminary evidence that the dose and schedule selected for the MTD of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone is associated with severe toxicity is difficult for patients to tolerate.</p><p>During the dose expansion phase of trial B2207 a dose the schedule of panobinostat 20 mg administered 3 times per week for 2 weeks on and 1 week off of a 21 day cycle in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone was explored. The rationale for exploring this schedule was to allow for platelet recovery and minimize dose interruptions. In the dose expansion phase 15 patients were evaluable for toxicity. A total of 11 patients (73%) had at least 1 adverse event that led to dose adjustment or interruption. Thrombocytopenia led to dose adjustment or interruption in 4 (27%) of patients. Grade 3-4 adverse events occurred in 87% of patients and SAEs occurred in 40% with 33% experiencing adverse events that led to hospitalization. Despite the reduced dosing schedule from weekly for 3 weeks to weekly for 2 weeks of a 21 days cycle, 75% were not able to tolerate the intended dose schedule. In addition, severe toxicity occurred in 87% of the patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer Comment:</head><p>The results of the dose expansion phase are consistent with the findings from the dose escalation phase. The Applicant's proposed dosing schedule of panobinostat 20 mg in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone is associated with severe toxicity and is difficult for patients to tolerate.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Despite the early signals of severe toxicity and issues with tolerability the Applicant further investigated the 20 mg dose of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in an adequately designed randomized, double-blind, placebo controlled trial. The control arm of bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2 in combination with dexamethasone is a standard of care regimen commonly used for the treatment of patients with relapsed multiple myeloma.</p><p>In trial D2308 a total of 758 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma were exposed to investigational therapy and evaluable for safety. There were 368 patients who received at least one dose of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, and 372 patients that received at least one dose of placebo in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. Overall the demographics of the trial populations were well-balanced between the treatment arms. The mean age of 62 years for both treatment arms is consistent with the mean age of the trial populations for other products approved for second line multiple myeloma (e.g., bortezomib and lenalidomide). The median duration of exposure to panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone was more than a month shorter than the median exposure for patients who received placebo + bortezomib +dexamethasone (153 days panobinostat vs. 184 days placebo) suggesting that the investigational arm was less tolerable than the control arm.</p><p>The percentage of patients in each treatment arm that experienced an adverse event of any grade was 99.7% for the panobinostat arm and the control arm. The most common adverse events that occurred in &gt;20% of patients in the panobinostat arm and at a &gt;10% greater frequency than the control arm were diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, fatigue, nausea, neutropenia, peripheral edema, decreased appetite, hypokalemia, pyrexia and vomiting <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">(Table 30</ref>). The incidence of patients that experienced grade &gt;3 adverse events was higher in the panobinostat arm 95% (n=367) compared to the incidence in the control arm 83% (n=307). Grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia was the most common severe adverse event (experienced by 57% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 25% of patients in the control arm). The most common grade &gt;3 adverse events that occurred in &gt;10% of patients in the panobinostat arm were thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, neutropenia, hypokalemia, anemia, fatigue, pneumonia, lymphopenia, asthenia and hyponatremia. It is important to point out that grade 3-4 diarrhea, neutropenia and hypokalemia occurred and a 3 fold higher rate than in the control arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 22</ref>). Serious adverse events were also more common in the panobinostat arm with 230 patients (60%) experiencing at least 1 SAE compared to 155 patients (42%) in the control arm. The most common SAEs that occurred in &gt;5% of patients in the panobinostat arm were pneumonia, diarrhea and thrombocytopenia <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 19)</ref>. Fifty-five percent of patients treated with panobinostat (n=211) experienced an adverse event that led to hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization compared to 37% (n=138) of patients treated in the control arm.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>43</head><p>The percentage of patients that discontinued therapy due to an adverse event was higher in the panobinostat arm compared to the control arm. Overall 36% (n=139) of patients receiving panobinostat discontinued therapy due to an adverse event compared to 20% of patients (n=76) in the control arm. The most common reason for treatment discontinuation in the panobinostat arm was diarrhea which accounted for 4% of patients in the panobinostat arm which is 2 fold higher than the rate in the control arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 18</ref>). Adverse events of any toxicity grade leading to treatment interruption or dose modification occurred in 342 (89%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 281 (76%) patients in the control arm. The most common reason for dose modification or treatment interruption in the panobinostat was thrombocytopenia which occurred in 31% of patients <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 21</ref>) treated with panobinostat compared to 11% of patients in the control arm. These data corroborate the data from the early phase trials that the proposed dose regimen of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone is associated with severe toxicity the frequency of which is greater than a standard of care regimen for multiple myeloma (bortezomib + dexamethasone). This increase in severe toxicity is also accompanied by and increased frequency of patients requiring treatment interruption/dose modification or treatment discontinuation.</p><p>During the review of the safety data a number of primary safety concerns were identified:</p><p> Grade &gt;3 asthenic conditions including fatigue, malaise and weakness were reported in in 93 (24%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 47 (13%) of patients in the control arm. Due to asthenic conditions 90 patients (23%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 42 patients (11%) in the control arm had a treatment modification or interruption. Asthenic conditions also lead to treatment discontinuation in 23 patients (6%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 11 patients (3%) in the control arm. Exploratory reviewer analysis of submitted QOL data from trial D2308 suggests that panobinostat had a greater negative impact on the QOL of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to patients in the control arm. Formal statistical analyses with alpha allocation were not conducted on the QOL data. Therefore, these findings should be interpreted with caution.  Severe gastrointestinal toxicity manifested as nausea, vomiting and diarrhea that led to serious events of dehydration  Severe thrombocytopenia and neutropenia. Events of severe thrombocytopenia led to an increase in grade 3-4 hemorrhagic events in the panobinostat arm, 4% vs 2% for the control arm. In addition, 5 patients receiving panobinostat died due to hemorrhage compared to 1 patient receiving the control arm.  Grade 3-4 infections/infestations occurred in 119 patients (31%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 90 (24%) patients in the control arm. Pneumonia, sepsis and septic shock occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequent in the panobinostat arm. In addition, deaths due to infection occurred in 10 patients (3%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 6 patients (2%) in the control arm. These findings are consistent with the known toxicity profile of HDAC inhibitors.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>44</head><p>The severity of toxicity with this panobinostat regimen is also evidenced by an imbalance in treatment emergent deaths. There were 26 patients (7%) in the panobinostat arm who died due to treatment emergent toxicities compared to 12 patients (3%) in the control arm. This reviewer did not agree with the reported event preferred term for a number of the deaths. For this reason, deaths were also grouped into reviewer categories based upon the reviewer's interpreted cause of death. The reviewer categories of hemorrhage and infection were the main contributors to the observed imbalance of deaths between the treatment arms. Hemorrhage and infection are both toxicities associated with panobinostat therapy which lends support that this observed imbalance in deaths is likely due to panobinostat toxicity and not simply a chance finding.</p><p>Of additional concern is that there were 2 patient sub-populations identified that experienced a high frequency of adverse events compared to the broader D2308 trial population. Patient's age &gt;65 years experienced higher rates of diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, anemia and fatigue. Most notably patients age &gt;65 years experienced a 10% increase in grade &gt;3 diarrhea, 17% increase in grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia, 5% increase in grade &gt;3 anemia and 10% increase in grade &gt;3 fatigue <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">(Table 35</ref>). Adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation occurred in 44% (n=71) of patients age &gt;65 years compared to 30% (n=68) of patients age &lt;65 years who received panobinostat. Adverse reactions leading to treatment interruption and/or dose modification occurred in 91% of patients age &gt;65 years compared to 87% age &lt;65 years who received panobinostat. There were 14 patients (9%) age &gt;65 years compared to12 patients (5%) age &lt;65 years who died due to a reason other than disease progression in the panobinostat arm.</p><p>Patients of Asian race also experienced a higher frequency of adverse events compared to the non-Asian D2308 trial population. Overall Asian patients experienced a higher frequency of grade 1-4 and grade &gt;3 adverse reactions compared to Caucasian patients. Most notably, Asian patients experienced a 13% increase in grade &gt;3 diarrhea, 11% increase in grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia and 20% increase in grade &gt;3 hypokalemia <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">(Table 36)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Methods</head><p>The safety review of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone was performed by reviewing the following items submitted by the Applicant: Reviewer comment: Overall the Applicant's safety analyses were able to be replicated almost to the exact number and frequency and were therefore exceptionally reliable. For this reason the Applicant's results for some of the more complex analyses were utilized in order to meet the timelines of this priority review Application. The only discrepancy was with the treatment assignment for 5 patients in the Applicant's proposed safety analysis population. This is further discussed in section 7.2.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.1">Studies/Clinical Trials Used to Evaluate Safety</head><p>Study reports and raw and analysis data sets were provided for trial CLBH589B2207, LBH589DUS71 and the randomized controlled trial CLBH589D2308. The randomized controlled trial D2308 will serve as the main trial to evaluate the safety of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone due to the large number of patients evaluable for safety (n=758) and the inclusion of a control arm (placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone) which will allow for a direct comparison of safety between the two arms. The safety findings from trials B2207 and DUS71 will be discussed briefly as they provide supportive information for evaluating the toxicity profile of panobinostat in a single-arm setting.</p><p>7.1.2 Categorization of Adverse Events D2308 (Source: section 7.5 of D2308 amendment 5 protocol) Adverse events were assessed according to the common toxicity criteria for adverse events (CTCAE) version 3.0. If CTCAE grading did not exist for an event, the severity of mild, moderate, severe or life-threatening, or grades 1-4 could be used. CTCAE grade 5 was not used for this trial. Information regarding death was collected in the end of treatment or study evaluation completion CRF page. Adverse event monitoring was continued for at least 4 weeks following the patient receiving their last dose of study treatment. According the protocol abnormal laboratory values or test results were considered adverse events only if they induced clinical signs or symptoms, were considered clinically significant or required therapy (e.g., any hematological abnormality that requires transfusion or cytokine treatment). These events were captured on the Adverse Events CRF under the signs, symptoms or diagnosis associated with them.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.3">Pooling of Data Across Studies/Clinical Trials to Estimate and Compare Incidence</head><p>An analysis of all grade 1-4 adverse events was conducted and included all patients who received panobinostat at a dose of 20mg orally on days 1, 3, 5, 8, 10 and 12 of a 21 day cycle in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in clinical trials of Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 46 relapsed multiple myeloma submitted to the NDA <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 10</ref>). This analysis includes the 386 patients exposed to panobinostat in trial D2308, 15 patients in the expansion cohort of trial B2207 and 55 patients enrolled in trial DUS71. In trial B2207 only the 15 patients in the expansion cohort received panobinostat at the same dose and schedule as that used for trial D2308.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Reviewer comment: Overall the incidence of adverse events was similar between patients enrolled in trial D2308 and all patients with relapsed multiple myeloma that received panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone at the recommended dosing schedule used in trial D2308.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Adequacy of Safety Assessments</head><p>In general, the safety assessments conducted in trial D2308 were adequate to evaluate the toxicity profile of panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. The one exception is that routine clinical laboratory testing was not adequate to evaluate if panobinostat had an effect on platelet function. Refer to section 7.2.4 of this review for further discussion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1">Overall Exposure at Appropriate Doses/Durations and Demographics of Target Populations</head><p>The datasets for trial D2308 included 769 unique patient ID numbers. The Applicant was sent an information request (IR) to clarify why 769 patients were included in the dataset but the clinical study report states that only 768 patients were randomized. The Applicant responded as followed:</p><p>"There were a total of 768 patients randomized in the study but 769 patient IDs were assigned to randomized treatment code. One patient was randomized twice with patient ID (SID1A = 0261_00001) and patient ID (SID1A = 0261_00003), both times randomized to PBO+BTZ+Dex.</p><p>This patient was randomized under the SID1A of 0261_00001 on 20-Jun-2011 and never received any treatment. The same patient was again randomized on 20-Jul-2011 under the SID1A of 0261_00003 and received study treatment from 22-Jul-2011 till (sic) 25-Sep-2011. The patient was initially screened and did not meet all inclusionexclusion criteria but was not documented as screen failure since the screening period exceeded three weeks, which is the allowed screening period in the protocol. Therefore, the patient was subsequently randomized again with a different ID.</p><p>This patient was considered in both Full Analysis Set and Safety set with the second randomization ID (0261_00003), and assigned to PBO+BTZ+Dex for both analysis sets. The patient with ID 0261_00001 was considered to be a protocol violation with severity code=8 (i.e. exclusion from all analysis) and was not included in any efficacy or safety analysis.</p><p>This describes the difference in FAS consisting of 768 patients though 769 patients IDs were assigned randomization treatment code. <ref type="bibr">NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</ref> For transparency, all relevant raw and derived datasets (including ATTEEBMT and AAEV) include all 769 assigned patient IDs."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Clinical</head><note type="other">Review Adam George, PharmD.</note><p>In the clinical study report for trial D2308 the Applicant reports that a total of 758 patients received at least one dose of investigational therapy with 381 patients having received panobinostat and 377 patients receiving placebo. During review of the IVR raw dataset it was discovered that 2 patients received medication packs that contained drug which was different from the patient's randomization assignment. The Applicant was sent an IR and they confirmed that 2 patients (0292_00002 and 0087_00001)received medication packs that contained drug which was different from the patient's randomization assignment. The Applicant responded to the IR as followed:</p><p>Patient CLBH589D2308_0292_00002 received placebo matching panobinostat (LBH589) 20 mg on Cycle 1 day 1 (first dose) instead of assigned panobinostat. From Cycle 3 day 1 onwards this patient received panobinostat. This patient is assigned to panobinostat as randomized for full analysis set and placebo as treated in safety set (D2308 CSR table 11-1)</p><p>Reviewer comment: I disagree with the Applicants proposal to include this patient in the placebo group for safety analyses. The patient was randomized to the panobinostat arm and received treatment with panobinostat from Cycle 3 through cycle 9. For the majority of the duration of therapy the patient was exposed to panobinostat. For exposure and safety analyses this patient will be included in the panobinostat group.</p><p>Patient CLBH589D2308_0087_00001 received panobinostat (LBH589) 20 mg on Cycle 5 day 1 (not the first dose) instead of assigned placebo. Since "as treated" is analyzed according to the first non-zero dose of the study drug, this patient is assigned to placebo for both full analysis set and safety set.</p><p>Reviewer comment: I disagree with the Applicants proposal to include this patient in the placebo (control) group for the safety analyses. This patient received 2 cycles of therapy with panobinostat. For exposure and safety analyses this patient will be included in the panobinostat group.</p><p>Based upon this response to IR the applicant was sent an additional IR to re-conduct the major safety analyses assigning patients 0292_00002 and 0087_00001 to the panobinostat arm. In response to this IR (SD 19) the Applicant also identified 3 additional patients who were randomized to placebo and received at least one dose of panobinostat. These patients are 0170_00002, 0319_00005 and 0909_00001. In their response to IR the Applicant re-conducted the major safety analyses with all 5 of the patients randomized to placebo who received at least 1 dose of panobinostat and assigned them to the panobinostat arm. The Applicant titled this analysis "modified safety set 2". The Applicant's modified safety set 2 analyses will be utilized for the purposes of this safety review.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.1">Demographics of Safety/Exposure population</head><p>For analyses of safety and exposure the modified safety set 2 from the Applicants response to IR (SD 19) was used. In the modified safety set 2 analysis population there were a total of 386 patients that received treatment with at least 1 dose of panobinostat and 372 patients received treatment with placebo.</p><p>Overall the demographics were well balanced between the treatment arms <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 11</ref>). The mean age of 62 years for both treatment arms is consistent with the mean age of the trial populations other products approved for second line multiple myeloma (e.g., bortezomib and lenalidomide). Forty-two percent of patients in both treatment arms were age &gt;65 years. disorders was balanced between the treatment arms this will not be a confounding factor in analyzing the occurrence of cardiac events that occurred in trial D2308.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2">Exposure</head><p>The median duration of exposure to panobinostat + bortezomib +dexamethasone was more than a month shorter than the median exposure for patients who received placebo + bortezomib +dexamethasone (153 days panobinostat vs. 184 days placebo) <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table  12</ref>). This finding provides the first clue that the dosing regimen of panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone used in trial D2308 is less tolerable then the control arm (placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone) which is currently a standard of care for the treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma. It is relevant to point out that the median duration of exposure for the patients in the modified safety set 2 was nearly identical to the safety analysis set presented in the clinical study report for trial D2308.</p><p>In the clinical study report for trial D2308, the Applicant provided an analysis of exposure by categories. Categories were based upon a cycle length of 3 weeks <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table  12</ref>). Based upon this analysis it becomes evident that starting early on in treatment, less patients were able to tolerate the combination of panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone compared to the control arm of placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone. This is supported by the fact that by week 6 (cycle 2) 16% of patients in the panobinostat arm received less than 2 cycles compared to 10% of patients in the placebo arm. By week 12 (cycle 4) 32% of patients in the panobinostat arm received less than 12 weeks of therapy compared to 24% of patients in the placebo arm. By week 24 (end of treatment phase 1) 54% percent of patients in the panobinostat arm received less than 8 cycles of therapy compared to 46% of patients in the control arm.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)  <ref type="formula">(14)</ref> 5 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> 20 <ref type="formula">(5)</ref> 19 <ref type="formula">(5)</ref> 53 <ref type="formula">(14)</ref> 83 <ref type="formula">(22)</ref> 153 <ref type="formula">(41)</ref> 46 <ref type="formula">(12)</ref> 3 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> 29 <ref type="formula">(8)</ref> 29 <ref type="formula">(8)</ref> 60 <ref type="formula">(16)</ref> 86 <ref type="formula">(22)</ref> 122 <ref type="formula">(32)</ref> 55 <ref type="formula">(14)</ref> 5 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> 20 <ref type="formula">(5)</ref> 18 <ref type="formula">(5)</ref> 53 <ref type="formula">(14)</ref> 83 <ref type="formula">(22)</ref> 149 <ref type="formula">(40)</ref> 46 <ref type="formula">(12)</ref> 3 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> Reviewer comment: Given the fact that patients in the panobinostat are were exposed to less therapy in the first treatment phase, the case to be made is that this is a direct result of toxicity as opposed to discontinuation due to disease progression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2">Explorations for Dose Response</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2.1">Trial B2207</head><p>In trial B2207 the Applicant explored doses of panobinostat from 10 mg to 30 mg in combination with bortezomib at doses of 1 mg/m 2 or 1.3 mg/m 2 . Patients in the trial could also receive dexamethasone 20 mg after completing cycle 1. In the dose escalation phase of the trial, patients received panobinostat 3 times per week every week of a 21 day cycle. In the dose escalation phase the MTD was determined to be panobinostat 20 mg in combination with bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2 . <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 13</ref> shows the number of patients evaluable for dose limiting toxicity (DLT) in each cohort and the number of DLTs observed in each cohort. Despite the fact that 3 DLTs were observed in cohort 6, the MTD was determined to be panobinostat 20 mg in combination with bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2 . The Applicant provided reason for this is that since a total of 15 patients were treated at this dose (cohort 3 + cohort 6) and only 3 DLTs were observed the DLT rate was less than the prespecified rate of 33%.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Reviewer comment: The DLTs observed in cohort 6 are consistent with the severe toxicities that were observed with greater frequency in the panobinostat arm compared to the placebo arm in trial D2308. When evaluating the toxicity findings from the randomized trial in conjunction with trial B2207, it is evident that the DLTs observed during dose escalation were early signals of the severe toxicity of the regimen proposed for this NDA.</p><p>Out of 17 patients exposed to panobinostat in combination with bortezomib at the MTD 77% of patients had at least 1 adverse event that required dose adjustment or interruption. In comparison, out of the 14 patients in cohort 1 and 2 that were evaluable for toxicity 8 (57%) experienced at least 1 adverse event that led to dose adjustment or interruption. Eight patients (47%) treated at the MTD experienced thrombocytopenia that led to dose adjustment or interruption. In comparison, out of the 14 patients in cohort 1 and 2 that were evaluable for toxicity 5 (36%) experienced thrombocytopenia that led to dose adjustment or interruption. More important is the finding that 77% (n=13) of patients treated at the MTD experienced a serious adverse compared to 43% (n=6) patients in cohorts 1 and 2. In addition, 100% of patients dosed at the MTD experienced a grade 3-4 adverse event.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Reviewer comment: The toxicity findings from the dose escalation phase with the 20 mg panobinostat and 1.3 mg/m 2 regimen are quite concerning. The rate of grade 3-4 adverse events, SAEs and adverse events leading to hospitalization are exceedingly high; 100%, 77% and 59% respectively. In addition, there is a clear dose:toxicity relationship given the fact that lower dose cohorts experienced substantially less toxicity. As will be discussed in this review, the high rate of toxicity observed in this trial is consistent with the findings from the randomized trial D2308.</p><p>Following a review of the safety data from the dose escalation phase, the decision was made to explore a schedule of panobinostat administered 3 times per week for 2 weeks on and 1 week off of a 21 day cycle. The rationale for exploring this schedule was to allow for platelet recovery and minimize dose interruptions. In the dose expansion phase 15 patients were evaluable for toxicity. A total of 11 patients (73%) had at least 1 adverse event that led to dose adjustment or interruption. Thrombocytopenia led to dose adjustment or interruption in 4 (27%) of patients. Grade 3-4 adverse events occurred in 87% of patients and SAEs occurred in 40% with 33% experiencing adverse events that led to hospitalization.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 15 Summary of adverse events in dose expansion trial B2207</head><p>Reviewer comment: The 2 week on 1 week off dosing schedule evaluated in the dose-expansion phase lowered the incidence of events of thrombocytopenia that led to dose reduction or interruption. The overall incidence of adverse events leading to dose reduction or interruption was similar, 75% weekly for 3 weeks schedule vs. 73% for 2 week on 1 week off schedule. In addition, the rate of grade 3-4 adverse events was still extraordinarily high at 87%. In the opinion of this reviewer, the altered treatment schedule did not improve the overall tolerability of the regimen. This finding indicates that the issue with tolerability is dose dependent and not schedule dependent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.2.2">Trial DUS71</head><p>Trial DUS71 was a phase 2, two stage, single arm design, that investigated panobinostat 20 mg administered 3 times a week for 2 weeks on 1 week off of a 21 day cycle in combination in with bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma that received at least 2 prior therapies. In this study 55 patients were evaluable for safety.</p><p>This trial was conducted in patients with later stage disease (at least 2 prior therapies) than trials B2207 and the randomized trial D2308. Patients with later stage disease tend to be a sicker population than those who have received at least 1 prior therapy and therefore are more susceptible to toxicity. Despite this, trial DUS71 utilized the same dosing regimen of panobinostat + bortezomib and dexamethasone as trial D2038 as is Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) worth mentioning. Also, it is the opinion of this reviewer that the safety findings from this trial are consistent with those from trial D2308 and B2207 <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 16</ref>).</p><p>Similar to the findings from trial B2207, ninety percent of patients in trial DUS71 experienced a grade 3-4 adverse event and 71% of patients experience a SAE. The most common grade 3-4 toxicities were thrombocytopenia (64%), diarrhea (20%), fatigue (20%), anemia (15%), neutropenia (15%), and pneumonia (15%). Again, calling into question the tolerability and risk of this regimen 87% of patients experienced an adverse events leading to treatment interruption or dose modification. The most common of these events were thrombocytopenia (42%), fatigue (24%), diarrhea (20%), and vomiting (11%). Reviewer comment: In the opinion of this reviewer this early trials served as preliminary evidence that the regimen of 20 mg of panobinostat 3 times weekly for 2 weeks of a 21 week cycle is intolerable and exposed patients to significant toxicity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.3">Special Animal and/or In Vitro Testing</head><p>Refer to summary of the Preclinical Pharmacology/Toxicology review in Section 4.3. Routine clinical testing was not adequate to evaluate if panobinostat had an effect on platelet function. This is particularly important given the findings of serious events of hemorrhage that were observed in the randomized trial. PT/PTT were only evaluated at the discretion of the investigator. Activated clotting time was not evaluated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.5">Metabolic, Clearance, and Interaction Workup</head><p>Refer to summary of the Clinical Pharmacology review in Section 4.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.6">Evaluation for Potential Adverse Events for Similar Drugs in Drug Class</head><p>Refer to section 7.3.5</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Major Safety Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1">Deaths</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D2308</head><p>Deaths due to reasons other than disease progression are described in <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">Table 18</ref>. Brief synopses of the narratives for patients who died in the panobinostat arm are provided below. The narratives for the deaths in the panobinostat arm were reviewed. This reviewer did not agree with the reported event preferred term for a number of the deaths. For this reason deaths were also grouped into reviewer categories based upon the reviewer's interpreted cause of death.</p><p>The narratives for the deaths in the placebo arm were also reviewed. For the events in the placebo arm, I agree with the reported event preferred term for 11 of the 12 events. After review of the narrative for patient 0510_00001 it is likely that the cause of anoxic brain injury was due to cardiac arrest secondary to sepsis from hemophilus influenzae infection. For this reason the cause of death will be considered infectious.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>58</head><p>A total of 48 patients died during treatment or within 28 days after received their last dose of investigational therapy. Of these 48 patients 10 died due to disease progression, 4 patients in the panobinostat arm and 6 patients in the placebo arm. Therefore, 26 patients (7%) in the panobinostat arm died due to treatment emergent toxicities compared to 12 patients (3%) in the placebo arm. The categories of hemorrhage and infection were the main contributors to the observed imbalance of deaths between the treatment arms. This finding is particularly relevant given the fact these are toxicities associated with panobinostat therapy. This lends support that imbalance in deaths is likely due to panobinostat toxicity and not simply a chance finding in a randomized trial.  <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> 5 <ref type="formula">(1)</ref> 3 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 0 10 (3) 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 2 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 18 (5) 6 (2) 12 <ref type="formula">(3)</ref> 1 (&lt;1) 0 2 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 6 (2) 0 0 0 2 (1) 0 0 Reviewer comment: Deaths due to hemorrhage and infection were the main contributors to the imbalance in deaths observed in the panobinostat arm compared to the placebo arm.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) (C2D13) the patient experienced musculoskeletal pain, headache and back pain and was hospitalized. On the same day she was diagnosed with cardiac arrest, hypotension (grade 4), grade 1 hyperkalemia and grade 4 bradycardia. Cardiopulmonary resuscitation was administered and mechanical ventilation was initiated. She experienced a 2 nd event of cardiac arrest and she subsequently died due to myocardial infarction. Investigational therapy was permanently discontinued and she received her last dose of therapy on .</p><p>Reviewer comment: This case is confounded by the patient's medical history.</p><p>Patient# 0430-00001 Patient 00001 was a 72 year old male who received prior treatment with bortezomib and melphalan as first line therapy and bortezomib dexamethasone and thalidomide as second line therapy for MM. Relevant current medical conditions include coronary artery disease, essential hypertension and type 2 diabetes mellitus. At baseline he was being treated with valsartan.</p><p>He received his first dose of investigational therapy on . Baseline ECGs revealed abnormal findings of first degree AV block, flat T waves and biphasic T waves. Mean QTcF was 426 ms (range 412 to 444 ms). On C2D1 , three pre-dose ECGs revealed abnormal ectopic supraventricular rhythm. The mean QTcF was 422 ms (range 416 to 426 ms). On C6D1 ), the pre-dose ECGs were abnormal with findings of first degree AV block, flat T waves and biphasic T waves. The mean QTcF was 418.3 ms (range 338 to 443 ms). On the patient was diagnosed with acute cardiac failure and myocardial ischemia and died. He received his last dose of panobinostat on</p><p>The investigator did not suspect a relationship between the events (cardiac failure acute, myocardial ischemia) and panobinostat.</p><p>Reviewer comment: The case is confounded by the patient's age and past medical history. The patient's cardiac conduction abnormalities at baseline appeared to remain stable. However, based on the information provided in this report a causal relationship Reference ID: 3617392 </p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>On</head><p>(C4D12) the patient was diagnosed with bronchitis which resulted in hospitalization. During hospitalization he experienced grade 3 atrial fibrillation. Bortezomib was temporarily interrupted. Patient was treated for these events and they resolved on . On the patient was rehospitalized for asthenia, dizziness and general physical health deterioration. The next day patient lost consciousness. On he was diagnosed with grade 4 pulmonary edema and edema of the brain (grade 4). Panobinostat and dexamethasone were permanently discontinued. Bortezomib therapy continued to be discontinued from prior event. The patient was treated for these events but subsequently died due to pulmonary edema on . Their last dose of panobinostat was on The investigator did not suspect a relationship between the events (bronchitis, atrial fibrillation, asthenia, dizziness, general physical health deterioration, loss of consciousness, brain edema, pulmonary edema) and panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Neurologic</head><p>Patient# 0503-00003 Patient 00003 was a 78 year old female who received prior treatment with lenalidomide and dexamethasone as first line treatment for MM. Past medical history is significant for deep vein thrombosis. Relevant current medical conditions included hypertension, hyperlipidemia and anemia. She was receiving treatment with metoprolol, valsartan, atorvastatin, furosemide and diltiazem. At screening her BUN was modestly elevated at 7.4 mmol/L (normal 2.1 to 7.1 mmol/L) and creatinine was 88.4 µmol/L (normal 44.2 to 132.6 µmol/L).</p><p>The patient received her first dose of investigational therapy on . ECG was normal at QTcF was 410.6 ms. On (C1D4) patient experience grade 4 fatigue and panobinostat and dexamethasone were temporarily interrupted. On she experienced grade 3 hypotension and was hospitalized. The event resolved on and the dose bortezomib and dexamethasone were reduced and therapy was restarted. On (C2D1) fatigue resolved and panobinostat was restarted at a reduced dose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>On</head><p>(C2D13) she was hospitalized due to grade 3 diarrhea, grade 3 dehydration and grade 4 sepsis. Treatment with panobinostat, bortezomib and dexamethasone were interrupted at this time. During hospitalization on she was diagnosed with pneumonia and pseudomonal bacteremia. Her ANC at the time of diagnosis was 5.7 x 10 9 /L. On she developed atrial fibrillation and on the she developed acute renal failure. The next day ) she experienced a cerebral vascular accident confirmed by MRI (lacunar infarction). Ten days after receiving her last dose of panobinostat the patient died on due Reference ID: 3617392</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p><p>Patient 00011 was a 71 year old female who received prior therapy with ifosfamide, epirubicin, etoposide, melphalan, bortezomib, lenalidomide, dexamethasone and everolimus for MM. She received prior localized radiotherapy (site not specified). She had no relevant past medical conditions. Relevant current medical conditions included secondary immunodeficiency, increased blood creatine phosphokinase. The patient received her first dose of panobinostat 20 mg in combination with bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2 and dexamethasone 20 mg on On (Day 126) the patient was hospitalized due to dizziness, stupor and aphasia. She was diagnosed with a transient ischemic attack. Study medication was permanently discontinued and she received her last dose of study medication on . On the patient was discharged and all events were reported as resolved. No laboratory results or medical treatments for this event were provided in the narrative. On the patient experienced stupor and aphasia and was hospitalized for the second time. It is reported that she had a cerebral infarction on . CT scan on the day of the infarction revealed major CNS bleeding. She was diagnosed with a ischemic stroke and cerebral hemorrhage. The patient fell into a coma and subsequently died on . The investigator did not suspect a relationship between the events (dizziness, stupor, aphasia, transient ischemic attack, ischemic stroke, cerebral hemorrhage) and the study treatment.</p><p>Reviewer comment: No platelet counts for the time period surrounding the event were available.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DUS71</head><p>Four patients died on treatment or within 28 days of study treatment. Of the four ontreatment deaths, three were attributed to the underlying malignancy (plasma cell myeloma). The other death (patient DUS71-1009/00009) was due to multiple organ failure in a 72 year old female patient who died at day 96, 19 days after having discontinued therapy with study drug on day 77.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient 1009-00009</head><p>The patient was a 72 year old female with relapsed multiple myeloma. Prior therapy included localised radiotherapy, bortezomib, dexamethasone, doxorubicin, lenalidomide and perifosine. Her first dose of study treatment was on During the course of treatment she had multiple events of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia but no events of grade &gt;3 neutropenia. On C4D11 ( ) the patient developed shortness of breath and was hospitalized due to grade 4 pneumonia. Pneumonia was confirmed by x-ray. The patient received the last dose of the study treatment on (C4D12). She received treatment with azithromycin. The patient's respiratory state continued to deteriorate and over several days, the patient went into multiple system organ failure with renal failure and significant volume overload. On , 19 days after the last dose of the study treatment, the patient became hypotensive, consistent with her sepsis syndrome and progressive multiple Reference ID: 3617392 </p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D2308</head><p>In the panobinostat arm 230 patients (60%) experienced at least 1 SAE compared to 155 patients (42%) in the placebo arm. The most common SAEs that occurred in &gt;5% of patients in the panobinostat arm were pneumonia, diarrhea and thrombocytopenia <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 19</ref>). The raw AE dataset included a field for events that led to hospitalization and/or prolongation of hospitalization. In patients treated with panobinostat 55% (n=211) experienced an adverse event that led to hospitalization or prolongation of hospitalization compared to 37% (n=138) of patients treated with placebo.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 20)</ref>.  <ref type="formula">(3)  6 (2)</ref> 6 (2) 7 (2) 0 11 (3) 2 (1) *Events that occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequently in the panobinostat arm.</p><p>Adverse events of any toxicity grade leading to treatment interruption or dose modification occurred in 342 (89%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 281 (76%) patients in the placebo arm. The most common reason for dose modification or treatment interruption in the panobinostat was thrombocytopenia which occurred in 31% of patients <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 21)</ref>.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)  <ref type="formula">(8)  9</ref> (2) 16 (4) 11 (3) 33 <ref type="formula">(9)  11</ref> (3) 16 (4) 6 (2) 20 (5) 5 (1) 5 (1) *Events that occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequently in the panobinostat arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.4">Significant Adverse Events</head><p>The incidence of patients that experienced grade &gt;3 adverse events was higher in the panobinostat arm 95% (n=367) compared to the incidence in the placebo arm 83% (n=307). Grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia was the most common severe adverse event experienced by 57% of patients in the panobinostat arm. The most common grade &gt;3 adverse events that occurred in &gt;10% of patients in the panobinostat arm were thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, neutropenia, hypokalemia, anemia, fatigue, pneumonia, lymphopenia, asthenia and hyponatremia.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) Bortezomib is associated with a relatively high rate of asthenic conditions. The prescribing information for bortezomib informs prescribers that based upon an integrated analysis of data from patients with relapsed multiple myeloma and mantle cell lymphoma asthenic conditions were reported in 54% of patients with grade &gt;3 events occurring in 3-7% of patients.</p><p>Based upon the results of trial D2308, panobinostat added toxicity to this regimen with regard to asthenic conditions. In trial D2308 asthenic conditions including fatigue, malaise and weakness were reported in 224 patients (58%) who received panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone compared to 156 patients (42%) who received placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone. Grade &gt;3 adverse events occurred in 93 (24%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 47 (13%) of patients in the placebo arm. In addition, 90 patients (23%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 42 patients (11%) in the placebo arm had an asthenic condition that led to treatment modification or Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 79 interruption. Asthenic conditions also lead to treatment discontinuation in 23 patients (6%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 11 patients (3%) in the placebo arm.</p><p>This finding is important because asthenic conditions can have a negative impact on how a patient feels and functions in their daily life. In part, this is reflected by the fact that there was a two fold increase in the frequency of patients who discontinued treatment with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone over patients in the placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone arm.</p><p>In trial D2308, quality of life (QOL) and symptom data was collected using 3 different rating scales; EORTC-QLQ-C30, EORTC-QLQ-MY20 and FACT/GOG-NTX. These instruments are usually incorporated into trials because the EU requests this information. The US FDA has identified limitations of these instruments and rarely are they found adequate to support labeling claims. These endpoints were not alphacontrolled and no claims were proposed by the Applicant based upon them.</p><p>An exploratory analysis was conducted by this reviewer to evaluate the findings from these instruments. The evaluation found that there was excessive missing data, rendering the data unreliable.</p><p>For example, for each one of the three rating scales by week 12 (cycle 4) roughly 50% of patients in each treatment arm fully completed the assessments. By week 24 (cycle 8) only 60-70% of patients were missing completed assessments. Despite the limitations of these data it is reasonable, from an exploratory standpoint, to present the findings from the individual questions of these rating scales that relate to asthenic conditions in order to further understand the impact of these events on patients.</p><p>Due to the increasing amount of missing data for the QOL assessments at later timepoints, the week 12 results will be presented for the following reasons: 1) week 12 is cycle 4 which is a reasonable enough duration of time to evaluate toxicity and 2) because this time point had the least amount of missing data of timepoints &gt;12 weeks. The EORTC-QLQ-C30 change from baseline to week 12 scores for fatigue were higher for patients treated with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone compared to patients treated with placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 23)</ref> indicating worsening fatigue for patients who received panobinostat.</p><p>For the FACT/GOG-NTX the physical well-being subscale includes 7 questions and of these questions there is 1 question each about lack of energy, nausea and patient bother from side effects of treatment. These questions are relevant to the toxicities associated with panobinostat. One additional limitation to the findings from the FACT/GOG-NTX is that the Applicant did not present findings from the individual questions in the physical well-being subscale. The results presented were for the total physical well-being subscale. For this reason the <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">Table 23</ref> will present the results from the physical well-being subscale as a whole. The results of this subscale show that the Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. <ref type="bibr">NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</ref> change from baseline to week 12 scores were lower for patients treated with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone compared to patients treated with placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone indicating a worsening of physical well-being for patients treated with panobinostat. This finding suggests that lack of energy, nausea and patients being bothered by sides effects of treatment had a greater negative impact on patients treated with panobinostat.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 24</ref>) compared to patients who received placebo +bortezomib + dexamethasone. This finding is significant because bortezomib is associated with gastrointestinal toxicity for which the prescribing information contains a warning. Of the gastrointestinal toxicities diarrhea had the largest impact on the tolerability of the panobinostat. Diarrhea lead to treatment interruption or dose modification in 26% of patients treated with panobinostat compared to 9% of patients in the placebo arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 21)</ref>. Diarrhea was also the most common adverse event leading to discontinuation of treatment for 4% of patient receiving panobinostat compared to 2% of patients receiving placebo <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 20)</ref>. In trial D2308 management of diarrhea included instructing patients to initiate loperamide at the first episode of poorly formed or loss stools. Premedication with loperamide was not recommended. During the trial 173 (45%) patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 96 (26%) required antipropulsives (e.g., Lomotil or Immodium). Events of non-infection colitis were rare but did occur in 3 patients (&lt;1%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 0 patients in the placebo arm. None of the 3 events were grade &gt;3 in severity. Events of ileus (including sub-ileus and paralytic ileus) occurred in 2% (n=9) of patients in the panobinostat arm (2%) and in 2% of patients (n=7) of patients in the placebo arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment:</head><p>The fact that 26% of patients receiving panobinostat had treatment interruption or modification due to diarrhea despite specific guidelines for the treatment of diarrhea further suggests that the 20 mg dose of panobinostat may not be optimal. It does appear that treatment with antipropulsives and/or dose modification/interruption can adequately manage this toxicity based upon the fact that despite the high frequency of this toxicity only 4% of patients discontinued therapy due to this event. For this reason it may be important to communicate in labeling the need for these measures to mitigate this risk.</p><p>Nausea and vomiting had a lesser impact on the tolerability of panobinostat each leading to treatment discontinuation in only 2 patients (1%). Vomiting requiring dose adjustment or interruption occurred in 23 (6%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 6 (2%) of patients in the panobinostat arm. Nausea requiring dose adjustment or interruption occurred in 17 (5%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 8 (2%) of patients in the placebo arm. The protocol for trial D2308 did not include specific guidelines for prophylaxis or treatment of nausea/vomiting. However, there were 162 patients (42%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 99 (27%) that received medications for treatment or prophylaxis of nausea and/or vomiting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment:</head><p>Since the protocol for trial D2308 did not include specific guidelines for prophylaxis or treatment of nausea/vomiting it is reasonable to assume that standard of care measures were utilized along with the protocol guidelines for treatment interruption/dose modification. It is evident that the community standard of care for treatment and prophylaxis for management for the nausea and vomiting associated with panobinostat are adequate. It would be reasonable to communicate in the prescribing information for panobinostat the nausea/vomiting guidelines for dose medication/treatment interruption.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dehydration</head><p>Severe gastrointestinal toxicities of nausea, vomiting and diarrhea can often cause dehydration. In trial D2308 adverse events of dehydration were reported more frequently in patients receiving panobinostat compared to patients receiving placebo. However, the incidence of dehydration was significantly less than the incidence of nausea, vomiting or diarrheas. There were no grade 4 events of dehydration in either treatment arm. Serious adverse events of dehydration occurred in 11 (3%) of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 5 (1%) in the placebo arm. Dehydration led to hospitalization in 10 patients (3%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 3 patients (1%) in the placebo arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 25 Incidence of dehydration in trial D2308</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Preferred term</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone (n=386)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone (n=372)</head><p>Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4 Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4 Dehydration 28 (7) 10 (3) 10 (3) 5 (1)</p><p>Reviewer comment: In reviewing the SAEs of dehydration there were cases in which patients had events of vomiting and/or diarrhea and subsequently became dehydrated. For this reason it is important to communicate that the gastrointestinal toxicities associated with panobinostat can lead to serious events of dehydration.</p><p>In the proposed draft prescribing information for panobinostat the Applicant is proposing to include in the warning for gastrointestinal disorders a statement that "Fluid and electrolyte blood levels, especially potassium, magnesium and phosphate, should be monitored periodically during therapy and corrected as clinically indicated to prevent potential dehydration and electrolyte disturbances" This statement can be strengthened to reflect the fact that serious events of dehydration have occurred. However, I agree with the Applicant's proposal to communicate the risk of dehydration due gastrointestinal toxicity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3.5.3">Cytopenias</head><p>Thrombocytopenia Grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia occurred in 57% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 25% of patients in the placebo arm. Severe thrombocytopenia is concerning as it can increase a patient's risk of bleeding which may require platelet transfusion. Severe hemorrhagic events due to grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia were uncommon but did occur in 11 patients (3%) the panobinostat arm. The most likely reason for relatively small number of severe hemorrhagic events is that grade 3/4</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. <ref type="bibr">NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</ref> thrombocytopenia was managed with dose interruption/modification of panobinostat and administration of platelets. This assumption is corroborated by the fact that 30% of patients in the panobinostat arm required a platelet transfusion due to thrombocytopenia compared to 10% of patients in the placebo arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 26</ref>). Additionally, 31% of patients in the panobinostat arm required dose modification/interruption due to thrombocytopenia compared to 11% of patients in the placebo arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 21)</ref>. Neutropenia Events of severe neutropenia grade &gt;3 are clinically important because patients with an absolute neutrophil count (ANC) less than 1000 are at increased risk of infection. Adverse events of grade 3/4 neutropenia occurred in 24% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 8% of patients in the placebo arm. Additionally, neutropenia that required dose interruption or modification occurred in 10% of patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 2% of patients in the placebo arm. Consistent with the increased rate of severe neutropenia, colony stimulating factor (GCSF or GMCSF) use was higher in the panobinostat arm (13%) compared to 4% in the placebo arm. Pancytopenia was rare but did occur in 5 patients (1%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 2 patients (&lt;1%) in the placebo arm.</p><p>Reviewer comment: Bortezomib is associated with severe thrombocytopenia and neutropenia for which the prescribing information contains a warning. The increase in frequency of severe (grade 3-4) events of thrombocytopenia and neutropenia with panobinostat are concerning given the fact that this increase is additional toxicity over what is observed with bortezomib therapy. In addition, the increase in toxicity is profound with a two-fold increase in grade 3-4 thrombocytopenia and grade 3-4 neutropenia. Also, concerning is the numbers of patients in the panobinostat arm that required dose modification/interruption for these toxicities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.5.4">Hemorrhage</head><p>In trial D2308 five patients died due to events of hemorrhage. All 5 patients had grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia at the time of the hemorrhagic event. To further evaluate this Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 84 toxicity signal a MAED analysis was conducted for the narrow SMQ hemorrhage. The rate of hemorrhagic events of all toxicity grades 1-4 was 8% greater in the panobinostat arm compared to the placebo arm. There was also a two fold increase in severe (grade 3-4) and serious events of hemorrhage in the panobinostat arm compared to the placebo arm <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">(Table 27</ref>). In the panobinostat arm 10 patients (3%) received a platelet transfusion due to a hemorrhagic event compared to 5 patients (1%) in the placebo arm.  <ref type="formula">(4)</ref> 44 <ref type="formula">(12)  9</ref> (2) 8 <ref type="formula">(2)</ref> The grade 3-4 hemorrhagic events in the panobinostat arm were further reviewed. Out of the 16 patients that had a grade 3/4 hemorrhagic event there were 11 patients that had grade 4 thrombocytopenia at the time of the event with all 11 patients having a platelet count less than 20 x 10 9 /L. This is relevant because a platelet count &lt;20 x 10 9 /L significantly increases a patient's risk for bleeding. One patient (0039_00003) out of 11 was receiving concomitant warfarin which also increases the risk of bleeding. Of the remaining 5 patients, 4 had an adverse event of grade 3 thrombocytopenia at the time of the hemorrhagic event. Patient 0312_00005 had grade 3 thrombocytopenia but the event of cerebral hemorrhage was confounded by central nervous system involvement with disease which increases the risk of cerebral hemorrhage. The 1 patient (0335_00004) who did not have grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia at the time of the hemorrhagic event had factors that significantly confound the case. Prior to the grade 4 event of upper gastrointestinal hemorrhage the patient had adverse events grade 4 hepatic cirrhosis and grade 4 liver failure which began approximately 6 days prior to the onset of gastrointestinal hemorrhage. The patient died of progressive disease 5 days after the onset of gastrointestinal hemorrhage and autopsy confirmed that the patient had liver involvement with disease. The patient's last dose of panobinostat was on August 2 nd approximately 18 days prior to the bleeding event. It is likely that progressive disease was the cause of the gastrointestinal hemorrhage and not panobinostat.</p><p>Severe thrombocytopenia is one of the major toxicities of panobinostat occurring in 57% of the patients who received panobinostat in trial D2308. Based upon the findings form the dose escalation trial B2207 this toxicity appears to be dose related. For this reason it is relevant to discuss the impact of dose modification/interruption on the cases of grade 3/4 hemorrhage. In trial D2308 the dose of panobinostat was to be interrupted Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. <ref type="bibr">NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</ref> and reduced for any grade 3 event of thrombocytopenia with bleeding and any grade 4 event of thrombocytopenia. Thrombocytopenia (grade 1-4) that required dose interruption/modification occurred in 31% of patient in the panobinostat arm compared to 11% of patient in the placebo arm. Despite the fact that 57% of patients experienced grade 3-4 thrombocytopenia, only 4% of patients in the panobinostat arm had a severe (grade 3-4) hemorrhagic event. This finding is supportive of the fact that the dose modification guidelines for thrombocytopenia in trial D2308 were effective in mitigating severe bleeds. However, the risk of hemorrhage with panobinostat is still greater than that observed with bortezomib, a product associated with hemorrhage.</p><p>It is also important to point out cases of severe hemorrhagic events that occurred in scenarios where the dose modification guidelines for trial D2308 were not followed. Of the 16 patients in the panobinostat arm that experienced a grade 3/4 hemorrhagic event there were 5 patients that experienced adverse events of thrombocytopenia that met the requirements for dose-reduction but the dose of panobinostat was not reduced. It is important to note that none of these patients died due to a hemorrhagic event. Based upon this finding it is important to communicate to prescribers the importance of adhering the dose modification/interruption guidelines proposed in labeling.</p><p>Reviewer comment: It will also be important to describe these severe and fatal events of hemorrhage in the prescribing information for panobinostat in order to communicate the risk of severe hemorrhage to prescribers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.5.5">Infection</head><p>Serious and fatal infections including pneumonia and sepsis are associated with the pharmacologic class of HDAC inhibitors. As a SOC grade 1-4 infections/infestations occurred at a similar incidence between the 2 treatment arms. In the panobinostat arm 265 (69%) patients compared to 250 (67%) patients in the placebo arm experienced a grade 1-4 infection. In contrast severe (grade &gt;3) infections occurred more frequently in patients treated with panobinostat compared to placebo. Grade 3-4 infections/infestations occurred in 119 (31%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 90 (24%) patients in the placebo arm. Pneumonia, sepsis and septic shock occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequent in the panobinostat. In addition, deaths due to infection occurred in 10 patients (3%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 6 patients (2%) in the placebo arm. These findings are consistent with the known toxicity profile of HDAC inhibitors.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)  <ref type="formula">(3)  9</ref> (2) 9 (2) 6 (2) 6 (2) 5 (1) 4 (1) 90 (24) 39 (10) 6 (2) 3 (1) 6 (2) 6 (2) 2 (1) 3 (1) 5 (1) 7 (2)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hepatitis B virus infection</head><p>There were 3 patients in the panobinostat arm compared to 1 patient in the placebo arm that developed hepatitis B virus infection. Testing for prior hepatitis B or C infection was not required at screening. Eligibility criteria for trial D2308 only queried for known history of infection. None of the 4 patients had a known prior history of hepatitis B infection and therefore there is no information to conclude that these are cases of reactivation of hepatitis B infection. It is important to point out that all 3 cases in the panobinostat arm occurred in patients at site 355 located in Taiwan. The one case in the placebo arm occurred in a patient at site 311 located in Korea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment:</head><p>Hepatitis B infection is more prevalent in Asian counties. Based upon review of table 14.1-1.2 of the clinical study report there were a total of 131 patients (34%) from the regions of South East Asia and Western Pacific enrolled in the panobinostat arm. In contrast 107 patients (29%) from these regions were enrolled in the placebo arm. It is likely that the difference between the treatment arms in the number of cases of hepatitis B infection is due the increased number of patients from Asian counties enrolled in the panobinostat arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.5.6">Cardiac ischemic events</head><p>Cardiac ischemic events are an uncommon but serious adverse events associated with the pharmacologic class of HDAC inhibitors. Cardiac toxicity mainly described as congestive heart failure and decreased ventricular ejection fraction is associated with bortezomib and is a warning in the prescribing information. However, the prescribing information for bortezomib also describes an increased risk of ischemic adverse Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. <ref type="bibr">NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)</ref> reactions. In trial D2308 there was an increase in the number of cardiac ischemic deaths. Three patients in the panobinostat arm (1%) died due to cardiac ischemic events compared to 0 in the placebo arm. Two of the patients died due to myocardial infarction and 1 due to myocardial ischemia. To further evaluate this signal a MAED narrow SMQ analysis was conducted to evaluate the risk of ischemic heart disease with panobinostat. Consistent with the finding of an increased number of deaths there was also an increase in the number of grade 1-4 cardiac ischemic events. A total of 14 patients (4%) in the panobinostat arm compared to 5 (1%) in the placebo arm had a grade 1-4 event of ischemic heart disease. Of these events 8 (2%) in the placebo arm were grade 3/4 compared to 1 (&lt;1%) in the placebo arm. A breakdown of these events by preferred term is provided in <ref type="table" target="#tab_12">Table 29</ref>. </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1) 2 (1) 2 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 8 (2) 1 (&lt;1) 3 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 2 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 0 0 5 (1) 5 (1) 0 0 0 0 0 0 1 (&lt;1) 1 (&lt;1) 0 0 0 0 0 0</formula><p>Reviewer comment: The increase in the number of ischemic cardiac events in the panobinostat +bortezomib arm is not overwhelmingly high compared to the placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone arm. However, it should not be ignored that this is an increase in frequency over and above the control arm which is also associated with cardiac toxicity.</p><p>In addition, there was an increase in the frequency of these events in the panobinostat arm compared to the control arm. For this reason these findings could be communicated in labeling. An option would be to describe the rate these events compared to the control arm in the adverse events section of the prescribing information.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.5.7">Hypothyroidism</head><p>Pre-clinical studies in animals showed that the TSH fell in animals treated with panobinostat. Human hypothyroidism is heralded by a rise in TSH. Based upon review of the raw adverse event dataset, 5 patients (1%) experience grade &lt;2 adverse events of hypothyroidism in panobinostat arm compared to 3 patients (1%) in the control arm. A description of the cases for both treatment arms is below.</p><p>Panobinostat 0003_00007: patient had current condition of hypothyroidism at baseline but was not receiving treatment. Patient developed grade 2 hypothyroidism and was treated with levothyroxine.</p><p>0075_00003: no prior history of hypothyroidism, elevated FT4 at baseline. Patient developed grade 1 hypothyroidism but did not receive treatment for the event.</p><p>0121_00006: no prior history of hypothyroidism, elevated TSH at baseline. Patient developed grade 1 hypothyroidism but did not receive treatment for the event.</p><p>0318_00006: no prior history of hypothyroidism, elevated TSH at baseline, Patient developed grade 1 hypothyroidism and was treated with levothyroxine 0336_00005: no prior history of hypothyroidism, normal baseline thyroid function, Patient develop grade 2 hypothyroidism but did not receive treatment Placebo 0064 00002; patient had current condition of hypothyroidism for which they were receiving treatment with levothyroxine. The patient subsequently developed grade 2 worsening of hypothyroidism. 0075 00014; no prior history of hypothyroidism, the patients thyroid function was normal at baseline. The patient developed grade 1 hypothyroidism but did not receive treatment for this event.</p><p>0325 00008; no prior history of hypothyroidism, low FT4 levels and normal TSH at baseline, 2 days after last dose patient was diagnosed with grade 2 hypothyroidism and treated with levothyroxine.</p><p>Reviewer comment: Based upon these cases and the fact that the rate of hypothyroidism was similar between treatment arms, it does not appear that panobinostat is associated with hypothyroidism. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.1">Common Adverse Events</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D2308</head><p>Out of 758 patients that were exposed to at least 1 dose of investigational therapy 756 (99.7%) experienced at least 1 adverse event during the trial. The percentage of patients in each treatment arm that experienced an adverse event of any grade was 99.7% for the panobinostat arm and the placebo arm. The most common adverse events that occurred in &gt;20% of patients in the panobinostat arm and at a &gt;10% greater frequency than the placebo arm were diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, fatigue, nausea, neutropenia, peripheral edema, decreased appetite, hypokalemia, pyrexia, vomiting <ref type="table" target="#tab_15">(Table 30)</ref>.</p><p>Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.2">Laboratory Findings</head><p>In general laboratory abnormalities occurred more frequently than corresponding reports of adverse events of hematologic toxicity or electrolyte abnormalities. The frequency of grade 3-4 reported adverse events was consistent with corresponding Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 91 laboratory abnormalities. This highlights the fact that grade 1-2 adverse events of hematologic toxicity and electrolyte abnormalities were underreported in this trial.</p><p>Thrombocytopenia, neutropenia and leukopenia occurred more frequently in patients receiving panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone compared to patients who received placebo in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone. This finding is consistent with the adverse event reports of these toxicities <ref type="table" target="#tab_7">(Table 31)</ref>.  Reviewer comment: It is likely that the high rate of gastrointestinal toxicity observed with panobinostat lead the finding of an overall decrease in body weight from baseline in patients who received panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4">Electrocardiograms (ECGs)</head><p>As a class HDAC inhibitors are associated with QT prolongation and morphologic changes in ECG including T-wave and ST-segment changes. Isolated cases of QTinterval prolongation have also been observed with bortezomib. Therefore, it is important to evaluate the ECG findings from trial D2308 in order to determine if the addition of panobinostat to bortezomib and dexamethasone resulted in an increased incidence or severity of ECG adverse reactions. For trial D2308 ECGs were centrally reviewed by an independent reviewer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4.1">QT interval abnormalities</head><p>The QT interdisciplinary review team (QT-IRT) was consulted to review the ECG results with regarding to QT prolongation from trial D2308.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A summary of the review is below:</head><p>The labeling language related to the QT risk appears to be adequate in mitigating risk after drug is approved to be marketed (please see our minor edits in the following). The sponsor's exposure-QTc analysis is not reliable because the QT prolongation is dose but not concentration dependent. Although the case of TdP was only noted with consecutive IV dosing, which has been discontinued, and plasma concentrations are lower with oral dosing, we would like to bring to the Division's attention that TdP risk has not been included in the proposed label. We defer final labeling decisions to the Division.</p><p>In the clinical study report for trial D2308 the Applicant states that "none of the patients who received panobinostat in trial D2308 had a QT interval &gt;500 ms". In reviewing the ECG2 raw dataset this reviewer discovered that patient 0900_00002 had a QTc interval &gt;500 ms at cycle 1 day 5. The QT-IRT team was asked to review and comment of this Reviewer comment: The case of Torsades de pointes the QT-IRT reviewer is referring to occurred in a patient in trial A2101 receiving the intravenous formulation of panobinostat at 20 mg/m 2 administered continuously on a daily basis. Exposures with this dosing regimen are significantly higher than that with oral dosing of panobinostat at the regimen investigated in patients with multiple myeloma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4.2">Other ECG abnormalities</head><p>In the clinical study report for trial D2308 the Applicant presented the results of ECG abnormalities. Due to the complexity of recreating this analysis and the fact that the clinical study report safety population is similar to that used in the modified safety set 2, the Applicant's analysis from clinical study report table 12-17 was utilized and reviewed.</p><p>Below are the newly occurring ECG abnormalities that occurred at a rate &gt;2 % higher in the panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone arm. Event rates are presented due to the fact not all patients in each treatment arm were evaluable for developing a given event. For example, a patient with a baseline finding of sinus tachycardia would not be evaluable for a newly occurring post-baseline event. The N value presented is the number of patients at risk for developing the event.</p><p>The findings of increased rates of ST segment depression, flat T-waves and inverted Twaves in the panobinostat arm are suggestive and corroborate the adverse reaction findings of increased cardiac ischemic events. Flat T-waves can be a non-specific finding but can represent cardiac ischemia or hypokalemia. Therefore, the finding of a 20% increase in flat T-waves is consistent with the higher frequency of hypokalemia in patients treated with panobinostat.  After adjusting for baseline prognostic factors there appears to be a trend for higher risk in the high dose intensity case group for all grades and grade 3/4 thrombocytopenia, diarrhea, anemia and hypokalemia compared to the respective matched control group. In addition, there appears to be a trend for higher risk in the low DI PAN group for all grade and grade 3/4 for thrombocytopenia and diarrhea.  For the PFS only 58 out of 207 PFS events from primary analysis were included in this analysis with a very limited number of PFS events per quartile (only 4 events in the fourth quartile). Although considering this limitation, there appears to be no effect of PAN DI on the occurrence of PFS events.  No case control analysis was performed for fatigue (all grades and grade 3/4), neutropenia (all grades and grades 3/4), hemorrhage (all grades) and PFS as there was no significant difference in the prognostic factors across quartiles. For all other endpoints the case control analysis was performed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.2">Time Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>The Applicant conducted a Kaplan Meier analysis to describe the time to onset of the first event of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia in patients enrolled in trial D2308. This analysis included all 758 patients in the safety population. Patients who did not have an event of grade &gt;3 were included in this analysis and censored. Based upon the Applicants analysis the median time to onset of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia was 1.08 months for patients treated with panobinostat. The median was not able to be estimated for patients in the panobinostat arm (source table 14.3-3.4 of clinical study report). This reviewer did not agree with this analysis due to the fact that it includes patients that did no experience an event. The most clinically relevant time to event analysis should only include patients that experienced an event of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia. Therefore, a reviewer analysis was conducted which only included patients that experienced an event. Based upon this analysis the median time to onset of first event of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia was 31 days (95% CI: 29, 31) for the panobinostat arm compared to 28.5 days for the placebo arm (95% CI: 28, 31).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment:</head><p>Based upon the reviewer analysis there is not clinically meaningful difference between to the time to onset of grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia between the treatment arms.  Reviewer comment: These findings are concerning given that a significant number of patients with relapsed multiple myeloma are age &gt;65 years. There is a considerable increase in the rate of death for patients age &gt;65 years. In addition, the fact that 91% of Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) patients age &gt;65 years required dose interruption/modification again calls into question whether the Applicant has selected the correct dose of panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.3.2">Race</head><p>The clinical pharmacology review notes that in the small subgroup of 13 Japanese patients for whom pharmacokinetic sampling was collected panobinostat exposure was higher compared to Caucasian patients. This finding coincides with the fact that there was a general tendency for a higher frequency of adverse event <ref type="formula">(</ref> To further explore this finding, a separate analysis of adverse events was conducted to determine whether there was a difference between the toxicity profile of panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone in Asian patients compared to Caucasian patients that received panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone. Overall Asian patients experienced a higher frequency of grade 1-4 and grade &gt;3 adverse reactions compared to Caucasian patients. Most notably Asian patients experienced a 13% increase in grade &gt;3 diarrhea, 11% increase in grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia and 20% increase in grade &gt;3 hypokalemia. These findings are consistent with the clinical pharmacology findings in Japanese patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Clinical Review</head><p>Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)  <ref type="formula">(7)</ref> 13 <ref type="formula">(5)  16 (7)</ref> 55 <ref type="formula">(22)</ref> 3 (1) 2 (1)</p><p>Reviewer comment: These findings are quite profound and call into question the risk versus benefit of panobinostat in Asian patients. At minimum, the results of this AE analysis should be included in the prescribing information for panobinostat. A separate dose-finding trial for patients of Asian race may help to identify the correct dose for Asian patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.4">Drug-Disease Interactions</head><p>All patients enrolled in trial D2308 had a diagnosis of relapsed/refractory multiple myeloma so no differences in safety variables can be assessed for different diagnoses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.5">Drug-Drug Interactions</head><p>Refer to clinical pharmacology review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6">Additional Safety Evaluations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.1">Human Carcinogenicity</head><p>In the pooled safety analysis of 456 patients exposed to panobinostat at the recommended dose schedule of 20 mg of panobinostat 3 times a week on a 2 week on 1 week off schedule, a total of 8 patients (2%) reported events in the SOC neoplasms benign, malignant and unspecified compared to 11 patients (3%) who received placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone. Among the 8 patients who received treatment with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone, 5 (1.1%) patients one case each of basal Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat) 100 cell carcinoma, endometrial cancer, lipoma, neoplasm malignant, and thyroid neoplasm. Among the 11 patients in who received treatment with placebo + bortezomib + dexamethasone, 10 patients (2.1%) reported different types of neoplasms which included 1 case of lipoma, 1 case of lung adenocarcinoma, 1 case of melanocytic naevus, 1 case of prostate neoplasm, 1 case of skin neoplasm, 1 case of prostate cancer, 2 cases of rectal cancer and 2 cases of small cell lung cancer.</p><p>Review of the integrated summary of safety dataset revealed that patient 0081_00002 enrolled in trial B2201 investigating single agent panobinostat in patients with refractory cutaneous T-cell lymphoma developed a thyroid neoplasm. This finding is relevant given the preclinical findings in animals of thyroid tumors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.2">Human Reproduction and Pregnancy Data</head><p>There are no adequate and well-controlled studies of panobinostat in pregnant women. Studies conducted in animals with panobinostat have demonstrated reproductive and embryo-fetal toxicity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.3">Pediatrics and Assessment of Effects on Growth</head><p>The safety and effectiveness of panobinostat have not been established in the pediatric population. Panobinostat was granted orphan drug designation on August 20, 2012. Products with orphan drug status are exempt from the requirements of the Pediatric Research Equity Act (PREA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.4">Overdose, Drug Abuse Potential, Withdrawal and Rebound</head><p>There was one death due to drug overdose in trial D2308. A brief description of this event is provided in section 7.3.1 of this review. There were 2 patients in trial D2308 who had reports of an adverse reaction overdose. A summary of the narrative provided for these events is below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient 0214_00001</head><p>In the narrative for this patient it explains that the patient reported taking 2 doses of panobinostat on the same day the patient initiated therapy. The event of overdose was reported as resolved on . No treatment was reported for this event and the patient was not hospitalized due to this event. Adverse reactions of grade 3 lymphopenia and grade 3 hyponatremia were reported as starting on Given the timing of the event in relation to initiation of therapy it is difficult to determine if the events lymphopenia and hyponatremia were due to overdose or a toxicity observed during prescribed therapy of 20 mg. Hyponatremia and lymphopenia are common toxicities associated with panobinostat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient 0338_00002</head><p>In the narrative for this patient it explains that on C1D15 ( , C1D17 ( and C1D19 ( ), the patient had taken extra doses of panobinostat. No treatment was reported for this event and the patient was not hospitalized due to this event. The event of overdose was reported as resolved on . It is relevant to point out that 3 days later on the patient had a grade 4 event of thrombocytopenia and a grade 4 event of pancytopenia. This patient did not have any prior adverse reactions of cytopenias prior to those experienced on Reviewer comment: As described in section 7.3.1 the death due to overdose is highly confounded. The adverse reactions of overdose for patients 0214_00001 and 0338_00002 are cases of medication administration errors. In this reviews opinion these events do not represent cases of drug overdose due to drug abuse or overdose with suicidal intent.</p><p>Given the case of overdose for patient 0338_00002 it may be helpful to describe in labeling that severe myelosuppression such as thrombocytopenia and pancytopenia have been observed within days after overdose with panobinostat. For this reason it would be reasonable to advise physicians to monitor patients closely for myelosuppression after overdose of panobinostat. In addition, the case of overdose for patient 0214_00001 suggests that it would also be reasonable to advise physicians to also monitor for electrolyte abnormalities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.7">Additional Submissions / Safety Issues</head><p>The Applicant submitted a 90 safety update to supplement 60 on January 16, 2014 (SD# 16). This update was reviewed and the findings were consistent with the safety findings discussed in this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Postmarket Experience</head><p>No post-market experience is available because panobinostat has not been marketed in any country. The literature review consisted of evaluation of the current National Comprehensive Cancer Network (NCCN) guidelines on the treatment of multiple myeloma as well as review of the current prescribing information for Velcade ® . The current prescribing information for Istodax ® was also reviewed due to the fact that it is a HDAC inhibitor.</p><p>Velcade (bortezomib) for injection prescribing information, Millennium Pharmaceuticals, Inc. August 8, 2014</p><p>Istodax (romidepsin) for injection prescribing information, Celgene Corporation, June 13, 2013</p><p>NCCN Clinical Practice Guidelines in Oncology: Multiple Myeloma, Version 1.2015, August 13, 2014</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Labeling Recommendations</head><p>Discussed throughout review; labeling negotiations are ongoing at the time of this review finalization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9.3</head><p>Advisory Committee Meeting This application is being presented at the FDA Oncologic Drug Advisory Committee meeting in November 2014. <ref type="figure">-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>--This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. <ref type="figure">----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>  Formulation(s) 10 mg, 15 mg, 20 mg capsules Dosing Regimen 20 mg orally, once daily, 3 times a week for 2 weeks of eight repeated 3-week cycles, followed by eight additional cycles for patients with clinical benefit. Indication In combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least 1 prior therapy Intended Population Adults  <ref type="figure">EFFICACY ........................................................................................</ref>... 5  Missing data contributed to the high proportion of censored events in the analysis of PFS; 47% of events were censored in the panobinostat + BD arm compared to 32% in the placebo + BD arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>--</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Tables</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Figures</head><p>Barring these limitations of applicability and reliability, the question remains of whether the effect size of 2 to 4 months progression-free survival is sufficient to justify any risks identified in the trial. An analysis of Overall survival, when the data is mature, may be required to determine the clinical benefit to patients with relapsed multiple myeloma.</p><p>The final clinical assessment of benefit:risk will be discussed in the Cross-Discipline Team Leader review incorporating the separate reviews of efficacy and safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1">Indication</head><p>The Applicant's proposed indication is for Farydak, in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone, for the treatment of patients with multiple myeloma who have received at least one prior therapy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Methods</head><p>This review of efficacy primarily relies on the results of one randomized, placebocontrolled, double-blinded trial (CLBH589D2308, hereafter referred to as Trial 2308) of 768 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma. All patients were given bortezomib and dexamethasone; randomization was 1:1 to the panobinostat arm or placebo arm.</p><p>Treatment on protocol was 48 weeks duration split in two 24-week phases. Treatment phase 1 comprised eight 3-week cycles of panobinostat 20 mg orally 3 times a week for two weeks of 3-week cycles or identical placebo. All patients were given bortezomib 1.3mg/m 2 IV twice weekly for 2 of 3 weeks with dexamethasone 20 mg per day for two days with each dose of bortezomib.</p><p>After 24 weeks, patients with any treatment response or stable disease, and without Grade 2 or higher toxicity, could continue onto treatment phase 2. In treatment phase 2, bortezomib was reduced to two doses every 3 weeks with dexamethasone; panobinostat or placebo were continued as in treatment phase 1. Dose reductions of panobinostat, bortezomib, or dexamethasone were allowed. Refer to Section 5.3 of the full Clinical Review for details of the trial.</p><p>The primary endpoint was PFS based on investigator assessed EBMT criteria <ref type="bibr" target="#b13">(Bladé, Samson, et al. 1998</ref>) modified to include near complete response (nCR). Nearcomplete response has been added to EBMT criteria in other drug trials in patients with relapsed multiple myeloma: a phase 2 trial of bortezomib <ref type="bibr" target="#b25">(Richardson, Barlogie, et al. 2003</ref>), a phase 3 trial of bortezomib vs. high-dose dexamethasone <ref type="bibr" target="#b28">(Richardson, Sonneveld, et al. 2005)</ref>, and a randomized trial of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin with bortezomib vs bortezomib alone <ref type="bibr" target="#b23">(Orlowski, Nagler, et al. 2007</ref>). The descriptive assumptions. The Independent Data Monitoring Committee assessed the dropouts and did not identify a safety issue.</p><p>• After 742 patients were randomized to the trial, the protocol was amended to increase the PFS event fraction for the second interim analysis from 67% to 80%. This was done to provide a better estimate of a treatment effect and increased the probability of detecting a treatment effect. A secondary objective to compare CR and nCR between arms was added. The definition of PFS was clarified as an event of progression, relapse, or death; the definition of an event and the statistical methodology were not changed. • After all patients had enrolled and completed treatment, the Applicant identified missing baseline and response assessments of M-protein as specified in the protocol. This amendment provided for additional data collection of other methods of M-protein monitoring that were done and established an IRC to perform independent response assessments.</p><p>Supporting this application is the multi-center, single arm open label trial CLBH589DUS71 (hereafter referred to as Trial 71) of panobinostat with bortezomib and dexamethasone in 55 patients with relapsed and bortezomib-refractory multiple myeloma. Treatment dosing, schedule, and modifications were similar to that of the randomized Trial 2308. The primary endpoint was ORR, defined as the proportion of patients with CR, nCR, or PR per investigator-assessment based on modified EBMT criteria at the end of 8 cycles. Responses were confirmed after six weeks. Secondary endpoints included MR rate, TTR, DOR, PFS, TTP, and OS.</p><p>The following items from Trials 2308 and 71 submitted by the Applicant were reviewed:</p><p>• Clinical study report (CSR)</p><p>• Protocol and statistical analysis plan • Raw and derived datasets (not CDISC standard)</p><p>• Case report forms • Patient narratives • Applicant responses to FDA information requests • Proposed labeling for Farydak</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Demographics</head><p>Efficacy analyses of Trial 2308 were performed with the intent-to-treat (ITT) population of 768 patients.</p><p>Of the 768 randomized patients, only 54 (7%) were from the United States. Enrollment occurred primarily in European and Asian countries (43% and 29% of patients, respectively). The demographic characteristics in the treatment arms were well balanced.</p><p>- <ref type="figure">----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on Regulatory Action ............................................................. 4 1.2 Benefit-Risk Assessment .................................................................................... 4 1.3 Recommendations for Labeling .......................................................................... 5 1.4 Recommendations for Post-market Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies .. 5 1.5 Recommendations for Post-market Requirements and Commitments ............... 5 2 INTRODUCTION ...</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>..... 8 Efficacy Summary ........................................................................................................ 8 3.1 Methods .............................................................................................................. 9 3.2 Subpopulation: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ................... 9 3.2.1 Demographics .............................................................................................. 9 3.2.2 Results ....................................................................................................... 11 4 REVIEW OF SAFETY ............................................................................................. 13 Safety Summary ........................................................................................................ 13 4.1 Methods ............................................................................................................ 13 4.2 Major Safety Results ........................................................................................ 14 4.2.1 Deaths within 30 days of Treatment ........................................................... 14 4.2.2 Serious Adverse Events ............................................................................. 14 4.2.3 Adverse Events .......................................................................................... 15 4.3 Subpopulation: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ................. 16 4.3.1 Deaths within 30 days of treatment ............................................................ 17 4.3.2 Serious Adverse Events ............................................................................. 17 4.3.3 Adverse Events .......................................................................................... 18 5 APPENDICES ........................................................................................................ 20 5.1 Abbreviations .................................................................................................... 20 Reference ID: 3691291</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Kaplan Meier plot of investigator-assessed Progression-free Survival (PFS) from Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ............. 12</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Kaplan-Meier estimates of Progression Free Survival in Trial 2308 ............... 17 Figure 2 Kaplan-Meier estimates of interim analysis of Overall Survival in Trial 2308 . 19</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table of Contents 1 RECOMMENDATIONS/RISK</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table of Tables</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Table 1 Demographic characteristics of patients in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ............................................................... 10 Table 2 Treatment history of patients in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent .............................................................................................. 11 Table 3 Investigator-assessed Progression-free Survival (PFS) analysis of Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ...................................... 11 Table 4 Response rate and duration of response in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent ............................................................... 12 Table 5 Progression-free Survival (PFS) analysis of Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and lenalidomide ........................................................................................ 13 Table 6 Deaths of patients in Trial 2308 ...................................................................... 14 Table 7 Serious adverse events of patients in Trial 2308 ............................................ 15 Table 8 Adverse events 1 of patients in Trial 2308 ....................................................... 16 Table 9 Deaths of patients in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent .............................................................................................. 17 Table 10 Serious adverse events of patients in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent .................................................................................. 18 Table 11 Adverse events 1 of patients in Trial 2308 subgroup: Prior bortezomib and an immunomodulatory agent .............................................................................................. 19</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>This Addendum supplements the Clinical Review by Adam George dated August 27, 2014 and the Clinical Review of Efficacy by Barry Miller dated August 26, 2014.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Addendum</cell></row><row><cell>Miller, Gormley, Ko</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 205353</cell></row><row><cell>Farydak (panobinostat)</cell></row><row><cell>3 Review of Efficacy</cell></row><row><cell>Efficacy Summary</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table of Contents 1 RECOMMENDATIONS/RISK BENEFIT ASSESSMENT ......................................... 7 1</head><label></label><figDesc>.1 Recommendation on Regulatory Action ............................................................. 7 1.2 Risk Benefit Assessment .................................................................................... 7 1.3 Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies ... 9 1.4 Recommendations for Postmarket Requirements and Commitments ................ 9</figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Drugs approved for the treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma .................... 10 Table 2 Clinical trials submitted to support NDA 205353 ............................................. 16 Table 3 Panobinostat/placebo dose reductions ............................................................ 25 Table 4 Panobinostat dose modification/interruption guidelines trial D2308 ................ 25 Table 5 Panobinostat/placebo dose modification criteria for QTcF abnormalities ........ 27 Table 6 Bortezomib dose modification guidelines for toxicity ....................................... 30 Table 7 Bortezomib dose modification guidelines for neuropathy ................................ 31 Table 8 Dexamethasone dose modification guidelines for toxicity ............................... 32 Table 9 Schedule of ECG assessments trial D2308 .................................................... 39 Table 10 Adverse events in &gt;10% of patients with multiple myeloma who received panobinostat at the recommended dosing schedule ...................................... 47 Table 11 Demographics for safety population trial D2308 ............................................ 50 Table 12 Exposure to therapy trial D2308 .................................................................... 52 Table 13 Dose limiting toxicities in trial B2207 ............................................................. 53 Table 14 Summary of adverse events in dose escalation trial B2207 .......................... 54 Table 15 Summary of adverse events in dose expansion trial B2207 .......................... 55 Table 16 Summary of adverse events trial DUS71 ...................................................... 56 Table 17 Table of deaths within 28 days of last dose in trial D2308 ............................. 58 Table 18 Deaths due to reasons other than disease progression D2308 ..................... 59 Table 19 SAEs in &gt;2% of patients in the panobinostat arm in trial D2308 ................... 75 Table 20 AEs leading to treatment discontinuation in &gt;2% of patients in trial D2308 ... 76 Table 21 AEs requiring treatment interruption or dose modification in &gt;5% of patients trial D2308 ..................................................................................................... 77 Table 22 Grade &gt;3 AEs occurring in &gt;5% of patients in the panobinostat arm D2308 . 78 Table 23 Quality of life assessment for fatigue, trial D2308 ......................................... 80 Table 24 Gastrointestinal toxicity trial D2308 ............................................................... 80 Table 25 Incidence of dehydration in trial D2308 ......................................................... 82 Table 26 Reasons for platelet transfusion trial D2308 .................................................. 83 Table 27 MAED SMQ analysis hemorrhage trial D2308 .............................................. 84 Table 28 Grade &gt;3 infections and infestations trial D2308 ........................................... 86 Table 29 MAED Narrow SMQ ischemic heart disease trial D2308 ............................... 87 Table 30 Adverse reactions 1 reported with &gt;10% incidence, &gt;2% difference between the treatment arms, and higher in panobinostat arm...................................... 90 Table 31 Laboratory adverse events of hematologic toxicity trial D2308...................... 91 Table 32 Laboratory adverse events of chemistry parameters trial D2308 .................. 92 Table 33 Change in body weight during trial D2308 ..................................................... 93 Table 34 ECG abnormalities trial D2308 ...................................................................... 94 Table 35 Most common adverse reactions in &gt;20% of patients age &gt;65 years compared to &lt;65 years who received panobinostat trial D2308 ..................................... 97 Table 36 Adverse events for Asian race compared to Caucasian race, trial D2308 ..... 99</figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table of Figures</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Figure 1 D2308 trial design ........................................................................................... 24 Figure 2 Trial D2308 Schedule of Study Assessments ................................................. 36</figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 1 Drugs approved for the treatment of relapsed multiple myeloma Drug Year Approved Indication</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Cyclophosphamide</cell><cell>1959</cell><cell>Multiple Myeloma</cell></row><row><cell>Melphalan</cell><cell>1964</cell><cell>Palliative treatment of Multiple Myeloma</cell></row><row><cell>Carmustine</cell><cell>1977</cell><cell>Multiple Myeloma in combination with prednisone</cell></row><row><cell>Bortezomib</cell><cell>2005</cell><cell>Multiple Myeloma patients who have received at</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 2 Clinical trials submitted to support NDA 205353 Study ID Study Dates/CSR status Support Design US Sites</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Regimen</cell><cell>Number</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>patients</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>enrolled</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>5.3 Discussion of Individual Studies/Clinical Trials</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>The key review materials and</cell></row><row><cell>activities are outlined below:</cell></row><row><cell> Electronic submission of NDA 205353</cell></row><row><cell> Relevant published literature on patients with relapsed multiple myeloma</cell></row><row><cell> Prior drug approvals in relapsed multiple myeloma</cell></row><row><cell> Applicant responses to clinical reviewer information requests</cell></row><row><cell> Clinical study reports for trials D2308, B2207 and DUS71</cell></row><row><cell> Applicant safety analyses for trials D2308 were reproduced or audited</cell></row><row><cell> Pooled safety analysis of the most common adverse events from trials D2308,</cell></row><row><cell>B2207 and DUS71</cell></row><row><cell> Regulatory background of INDs 69862 67091 for panobinostat were reviewed</cell></row><row><cell> Applicant's proposed labeling was reviewed and revised</cell></row><row><cell>5.3.1 CLBH589D2308 (D2308)</cell></row><row><cell>5.3.1.1 Trial Title</cell></row><row><cell>A multicenter, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled phase III study of</cell></row><row><cell>panobinostat in combination with bortezomib and dexamethasone in patients with</cell></row><row><cell>relapsed multiple myeloma</cell></row><row><cell>5.3.1.2 Trial Design</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Myocardial infarction or unstable angina pectoris &lt;6 months prior to starting study drug k. Symptomatic congestive heart failure (NYHA class III-IV) l. Other clinically significant heart disease and vascular disease (e.g., uncontrolled hypertension) 16. Patient taking medications with relative risk of prolonging the QT interval or inducing Torsade de pointes, if such treatment cannot be discontinued or switched to a different medication prior to starting study drug 17. Patient has impairment of gastrointestinal (GI) function or GI disease that may significantly alter the absorption of panobinostat (e.g., ulcerative disease, uncontrolled nausea, vomiting, malabsorption syndrome, obstruction, or stomach</figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row><row><cell>22</cell></row></table><note>14. Patient has unresolved diarrhea &gt; CTCAE grade 2 15. Patient has impaired cardiac function, including any one of the following: a. LVEF &lt;LLN of institutional normal, as determined by ECHO or MUGA b. Obligate use of a permanent cardiac pacemaker c. Congenital long QT syndrome d. History or presence of ventricular tachyarrhythmia e. Resting bradycardia defined as &lt;50 beats per minute f. QTcF &gt;450 msec on screening ECG g. Complete left bundle branch block, bifascicular block h. Any clinically significant ST segment and/or T-wave abnormalities i. Presence of unstable atrial fibrillation (ventricular response rate &gt;100 bpm). Patients with stable atrial fibrillation can be enrolled provided they do not meet other cardiac exclusion criteria j.and/or small bowel resection) 18. Patient has any other concurrent severe and/or uncontrolled medical conditions (e.g., uncontrolled diabetes, active or uncontrolled infection, chronic obstructive or chronic restrictive pulmonary disease including dyspnea at rest from any</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Table 3 Panobinostat/placebo dose reductions</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Current dosing level</cell><cell>Dose reduction</cell></row><row><cell>20 mg/day</cell><cell>Modify to 15 mg/day</cell></row><row><cell>15 mg/day</cell><cell>Modify to 10 mg/day</cell></row><row><cell>10 mg/day</cell><cell>No further reduction, discontinue</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>permanently</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row></table><note>Panobinostat dose modification/interruption guidelines trial D2308 (Source: Table 6-3 of protocol D2308 amendment 5)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(Source: Table 6-5 of D2308 protocol amendment 5)</cell></row></table><note>Panobinostat/placebo dose modification criteria for QTcF abnormalities</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 6 Bortezomib dose modification guidelines for toxicity</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(Source: Table 6-8 protocol D2308 amendment 5)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 7 Bortezomib dose modification guidelines for neuropathy</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 8 Dexamethasone dose modification guidelines for toxicity</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(Source: Table 6-10 protocol D2308 amendment 5)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>Table 9 Schedule of ECG assessments trial D2308</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(Source: Table 7-3 study D2308 protocol amendment 5)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head>Table 10 Adverse events in &gt;10% of patients with multiple myeloma who received panobinostat at the recommended dosing schedule</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>All trials at</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>recommend</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dosing</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>schedule</cell><cell>Trial D2308</cell><cell>Trial D2308</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 1-4</cell><cell>Grade 1-4</cell><cell>Grade 1-4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pan + Bor +</cell><cell>Pan + Bor +</cell><cell>Pbo + Bor +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dex</cell><cell>Dex</cell><cell>Dex</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term, n (%)</cell><cell>(n=456)</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea</cell><cell>316 (69)</cell><cell>264 (68)</cell><cell>153 (41)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia</cell><cell>296 (65)</cell><cell>249 (65)</cell><cell>151 (41)</cell></row><row><cell>Fatigue</cell><cell>206 (45)</cell><cell>158 (41)</cell><cell>109 (29)</cell></row><row><cell>Anemia</cell><cell>191 (42)</cell><cell>160 (42)</cell><cell>124 (33)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>182 (40)</cell><cell>139 (36)</cell><cell>22 (21)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased appetite</cell><cell>142 (31)</cell><cell>110 (29)</cell><cell>44 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Neuropathy peripheral</cell><cell>141 (31)</cell><cell>119 (31)</cell><cell>132 (36)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral edema</cell><cell>138 (30)</cell><cell>119 (31)</cell><cell>132 (36)</cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia</cell><cell>133 (29)</cell><cell>114 (30)</cell><cell>40 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Constipation</cell><cell>131 (29)</cell><cell>104 (27)</cell><cell>121 (33)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia</cell><cell>125 (27)</cell><cell>106 (28)</cell><cell>52 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell>122 (27)</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>48 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Pyrexia</cell><cell>117 (26)</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Asthenia</cell><cell>103 (23)</cell><cell>85 (22)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Dizziness</cell><cell>101 (22)</cell><cell>73 (19)</cell><cell>60 (16)</cell></row><row><cell>Cough</cell><cell>98 (22)</cell><cell>83 (22)</cell><cell>68 (18)</cell></row><row><cell>Upper respiratory tract infection</cell><cell>92 (20)</cell><cell>68 (18)</cell><cell>55 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Insomnia</cell><cell>90 (20)</cell><cell>73 (19)</cell><cell>61 (16)</cell></row><row><cell>Dyspnea</cell><cell>81 (18)</cell><cell>57 (15)</cell><cell>43 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Pneumonia</cell><cell>75 (16)</cell><cell>65 (17)</cell><cell>48 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Leukopenia</cell><cell>71 (16)</cell><cell>63 (16)</cell><cell>30 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypotension</cell><cell>68 (15)</cell><cell>54 (14)</cell><cell>34 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Headache</cell><cell>65 (14)</cell><cell>53 (14)</cell><cell>39 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Lymphopenia</cell><cell>68 (15)</cell><cell>52 (13)</cell><cell>35 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Back pain</cell><cell>64 (14)</cell><cell>50 (13)</cell><cell>45 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Hyponatremia</cell><cell>58 (13)</cell><cell>49 (13)</cell><cell>19 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased weight</cell><cell>57 (13)</cell><cell>44 (11)</cell><cell>17 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Dysgeusia</cell><cell>54 (12)</cell><cell>36 (9)</cell><cell>26 (7)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypophosphatemia</cell><cell>52 (11)</cell><cell>44 (11)</cell><cell>31 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Pain in extremity</cell><cell>48 (11)</cell><cell>40 (10)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Blood creatinine increased</cell><cell>47 (10)</cell><cell>38 (10)</cell><cell>22 (6)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 11 Demographics for safety population trial D2308 Demographic parameter</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Table 12</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Exposure to therapy trial D2308</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">CSR analysis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">population</cell><cell cols="2">Modified safety set 2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pan + BTZ +</cell><cell>Pbo+BTZ+</cell><cell>Pan+BTZ+</cell><cell>Pbo+BTZ+De</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Dex</cell><cell>Dex</cell><cell>Dex</cell><cell>x</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=381)</cell><cell>(n=377)</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Duration of exposure (days)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean</cell><cell>184</cell><cell>195</cell><cell>184</cell><cell>195</cell></row><row><cell>Standard deviation</cell><cell>125.75</cell><cell>118.33</cell><cell>125.24</cell><cell>118.78</cell></row><row><cell>Median (min, max)</cell><cell>152 (3, 411)</cell><cell>187 (3, 443)</cell><cell>153 (3, 411)</cell><cell>184 (3, 443)</cell></row><row><cell>Exposure categories, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&lt;3 weeks</cell><cell>29 (8)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;3 weeks and &lt;6 weeks</cell><cell>28 (7)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;6 weeks and &lt;12 weeks</cell><cell>60 (16)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;12 weeks and &lt;24 weeks</cell><cell>86 (23)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;24 weeks and &lt;48 weeks</cell><cell>118 (31)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;48 weeks and &lt;56 weeks</cell><cell>55</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;56 weeks</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 13 Dose limiting toxicities in trial B2207</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Dose</cell><cell>Patients</cell><cell>DLTs</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>evaluable</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>for DLTs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 1</cell><cell>Panobinostat 10 mg</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 2</cell><cell>Panobinostat 20 mg</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 3</cell><cell>Panobinostat 20 mg</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 4</cell><cell>Panobinostat 30 mg</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>4 (Grade 3 fatigue, weakness)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>(Grade 4 thrombocytopenia) x 2</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Grade 2 asthenia and decreased</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>appetite)</cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 5</cell><cell>Panobinostat 25 mg</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>2 (Grade 2 tumor lysis syndrome)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>(Grade 4 thrombocytopenia)</cell></row><row><cell>Cohort 6</cell><cell>Panobinostat 20 mg</cell><cell>9</cell><cell>3 (Grade 3 orthostatic hypotension)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bortezomib 1.3 mg/m 2</cell><cell></cell><cell>(Grade 3 vomiting)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Grade 4 thrombocytopenia)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_31"><head>Table 14 Summary of adverse events in dose escalation trial B2207</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>(Source: Table 12-8 of trial B2207 clinical study report)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_32"><head>Table 16</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Summary of adverse events trial DUS71 (Source: Table 12-3 of trial DUS71 clinical study report)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 17 Table of deaths within 28 days of last dose in trial D2308</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>Reviewer categories</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>30 (8)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Due to progressive disease</cell><cell>4 (1)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reasons other than progressive disease</cell><cell>26</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reviewer category</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hemorrhage</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cardiac disorders</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Ischemic cardiac disease</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Cardiac arrest</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Cardiac failure</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gastrointestinal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sudden death</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Renal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Respiratory (non-infectious)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Neurologic</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Drug overdose</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>Table 18 Deaths due to reasons other than disease progression D2308</head><label>18</label><figDesc>This case is confounded by the patient's medical history of diabetes.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Patient ID</cell><cell>Cause of Death (preferred term)</cell><cell>Reviewer</cell><cell>Investigator</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>category</cell><cell>Causality</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_38"><head>Table 19 SAEs in &gt;2% of patients in the panobinostat arm in trial D2308 Preferred term</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_39"><head>Table 20 AEs leading to treatment discontinuation in &gt;2% of patients in trial D2308 Preferred term</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_40"><head>Table 21 AEs requiring treatment interruption or dose modification in &gt;5% of patients trial D2308 Preferred term</head><label>21</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia*</cell><cell>119 (31)</cell><cell>40 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea*</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>33 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Fatigue *</cell><cell>62 (16)</cell><cell>27 (7)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral neuropathy</cell><cell>48 (12)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Pneumonia*</cell><cell>40 (10)</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia*</cell><cell>39 (10)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Anemia*</cell><cell>32 (8)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Asthenia*</cell><cell>32 (8)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Neuralgia</cell><cell>32 (8)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Pyrexia*</cell><cell>30 (8)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Upper respiratory tract infection*</cell><cell>25 (6)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting*</cell><cell>23 (6)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral sensory neuropathy</cell><cell>21 (5)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia*</cell><cell>19 (5)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Platelet count decreased*</cell><cell>18 (5)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head>Table 22 Grade &gt;3 AEs occurring in &gt;5% of patients in the panobinostat arm D2308 Preferred term</head><label>22</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia*</cell><cell>219 (57)</cell><cell>92 (25)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea*</cell><cell>98 (25)</cell><cell>29 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia*</cell><cell>92 (24)</cell><cell>30 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia*</cell><cell>74 (19)</cell><cell>24 (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Anemia</cell><cell>65 (17)</cell><cell>58 (16)</cell></row><row><cell>Fatigue*</cell><cell>65 (17)</cell><cell>33 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Pneumonia</cell><cell>48 (12)</cell><cell>39 (10)</cell></row><row><cell>Lymphopenia*</cell><cell>47 (12)</cell><cell>28 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Asthenia*</cell><cell>37 (10)</cell><cell>14 (4)</cell></row><row><cell>Hyponatremia*</cell><cell>37 (10)</cell><cell>13 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Leukopenia*</cell><cell>35 (9)</cell><cell>12 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Platelet count decreased*</cell><cell>35 (9)</cell><cell>13 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypophosphatemia*</cell><cell>34 (9)</cell><cell>23 (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting*</cell><cell>28 (7)</cell><cell>5 (1)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral neuropathy</cell><cell>26 (7)</cell><cell>21 (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea*</cell><cell>21 (5)</cell><cell>2 (&lt;1)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">*Events that occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequently in the panobinostat arm.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7.3.5 Submission Specific Primary Safety Concerns</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">7.3.5.1 Asthenic conditions (Fatigue, Malaise, Weakness, Asthenia)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head>Table 23 Quality of life assessment for fatigue, trial D2308 Preferred term</head><label>23</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Panobinostat +</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo + bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n=387)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=381)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Baseline</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Mean</cell><cell>Week 12</cell><cell>Baseline</cell><cell>Week 12</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Score</cell><cell>Mean Score</cell><cell>Mean Score</cell><cell>Mean Score</cell></row><row><cell>EORTC-QLQ-C30, mean score 1</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Fatigue</cell><cell>3</cell><cell>48</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>39</cell></row><row><cell>FACT/GOG-NTX, mean score 2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Physical well-being</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>18</cell><cell>21</cell><cell>20</cell></row><row><cell>subscale</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 Higher symptom scores indicate worsening</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2 Higher scores indicate improvement</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7.3.5.2 Gastrointestinal toxicity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Severe gastrointestinal toxicity manifested as nausea, vomiting and diarrhea occurred</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">more frequently in patients receiving panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head>Table 24 Gastrointestinal toxicity trial D2308 Preferred term</head><label>24</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Panobinostat +</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n=386)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4 Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea</cell><cell>264 (68)</cell><cell>98 (25)</cell><cell>153 (41)</cell><cell>29 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>139 (36)</cell><cell>21 (5)</cell><cell>77 (21)</cell><cell>2 (&lt;1)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>28 (7)</cell><cell>48 (13)</cell><cell>5 (1)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_44"><head>Table 26</head><label>26</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Reasons for platelet transfusion trial D2308</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>Reason for platelet transfusion</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Any reason, n (%)</cell><cell>127 (33)</cell><cell>41 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia</cell><cell>115 (30)</cell><cell>36 (10)</cell></row><row><cell>Hemorrhage</cell><cell>10 (3)</cell><cell>5 (1)</cell></row><row><cell>Febrile neutropenia</cell><cell>1 (&lt;1)</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Septic shock</cell><cell>1 (&lt;1)</cell><cell>0</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_45"><head>Table 27 MAED SMQ analysis hemorrhage trial D2308</head><label>27</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>Broad SMQ</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Hemorrhage, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> All grade</cell><cell>79 (20)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Grade 3/4</cell><cell>16 (4)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> SAEs</cell><cell>17</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_46"><head>Table 28 Grade &gt;3 infections and infestations trial D2308</head><label>28</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Panobinostat +</cell><cell>Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell><cell>bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell><cell>dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell>SOC</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term</cell><cell>Grade 3-4</cell><cell>Grade 3-4</cell></row><row><cell>Infections/infestations, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>119 (31)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Pneumonia</cell><cell>48 (12)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sepsis</cell><cell>11 (3)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Septic shock</cell><cell>10</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Upper respiratory tract infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Urinary tract infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Gastroenteritis</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Respiratory tract infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Herpes zoster</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_47"><head>Table 29 MAED Narrow SMQ ischemic heart disease trial D2308</head><label>29</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Panobinostat +</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n=386)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Narrow SMQ</cell><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Grade 3-</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term</cell><cell>1-4</cell><cell>3-4</cell><cell>1-4</cell><cell>4</cell></row><row><cell>Ischemic heart disease, n (%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>14 (4)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Angina pectoris</cell><cell>6 (2)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Myocardial ischemia</cell><cell>3 (</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Acute coronary syndrome</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Myocardial infarction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Acute myocardial infarction</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Arteriosclerosis coronary artery</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Troponin T increased</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_49"><head>Table 30 Adverse reactions reported with &gt;10% incidence, &gt;2% difference between the treatment arms, and higher in panobinostat arm</head><label>30</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Grade 1-4</cell><cell>Grade 1-4</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pan + Bor + Dex</cell><cell>Pbo + Bor + Dex</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term, n (%) *</cell><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea*</cell><cell>264 (68)</cell><cell>153 (41)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia*</cell><cell>249 (65)</cell><cell>151 (41)</cell></row><row><cell>Anemia</cell><cell>160 (41)</cell><cell>124 (33)</cell></row><row><cell>Fatigue*</cell><cell>158 (41)</cell><cell>109 (29)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea*</cell><cell>139 (36)</cell><cell>77 (21)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral neuropathy</cell><cell>119 (31)</cell><cell>132 (35)</cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia*</cell><cell>114 (30)</cell><cell>40(11)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral edema*</cell><cell>111 (29)</cell><cell>70 (19)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased appetite*</cell><cell>110 (29)</cell><cell>44 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia*</cell><cell>106 (27)</cell><cell>52 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Constipation</cell><cell>104 (27)</cell><cell>121 (33)</cell></row><row><cell>Pyrexia*</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting*</cell><cell>99 (26)</cell><cell>48 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Asthenia</cell><cell>85 (22)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Cough</cell><cell>83 (22)</cell><cell>68 (18)</cell></row><row><cell>Dizziness</cell><cell>73 (19)</cell><cell>60 (16)</cell></row><row><cell>Insomnia</cell><cell>73 (19)</cell><cell>61 (16)</cell></row><row><cell>Upper respiratory tract infection</cell><cell>68 (18)</cell><cell>55 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Pneumonia</cell><cell>65 (17)</cell><cell>48 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Leukopenia</cell><cell>63 (16)</cell><cell>30 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Dyspnea</cell><cell>57 (15)</cell><cell>43 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypotension</cell><cell>54 (14)</cell><cell>34 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Headache</cell><cell>53 (14)</cell><cell>39 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Lymphopenia</cell><cell>52 (13)</cell><cell>35 (9)</cell></row><row><cell>Abdominal pain</cell><cell>51 (13)</cell><cell>40 (11)</cell></row><row><cell>Hyponatremia</cell><cell>49 (13)</cell><cell>19 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypophosphatemia</cell><cell>44 (11)</cell><cell>31 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased weight</cell><cell>44 (11)</cell><cell>17 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Platelet count decreased</cell><cell>43 (11)</cell><cell>17 (5)</cell></row><row><cell>Pain extremity</cell><cell>40 (10)</cell><cell>54 (15)</cell></row><row><cell>Blood creatinine increased</cell><cell>38 (10)</cell><cell>22 (6)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">*Events that occurred at a rate &gt;10% more frequently in the panobinostat arm.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_50"><head>Table 31 Laboratory adverse events of hematologic toxicity trial D2308 Hematology parameter</head><label>31</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Panobinostat +</cell><cell cols="2">Placebo +</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell><cell cols="2">bortezomib +</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell><cell cols="2">dexamethasone</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(n=386)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=372)</cell></row><row><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Grade 1-</cell><cell>Grade 3-</cell></row><row><cell>1-4</cell><cell>3-4</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>4</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_51"><head>Table 33 Change in body weight during trial D2308 Visit</head><label>33</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Mean body</cell><cell>Mean body</cell></row><row><cell>weight</cell><cell>weight</cell></row><row><cell>Pan + BTZ + Dex</cell><cell>Pbo + BTZ + Dex</cell></row><row><cell>(n=386)</cell><cell>(n=372)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_52"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>At the time of this review the clinical team has not yet received a response from the QT-IRT team.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Safety Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Adam George, PharmD.</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 203353</cell></row><row><cell>FARYDAK (panobinostat)</cell></row><row><cell>case.</cell></row><row><cell>94</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_53"><head>Table 34 ECG abnormalities trial D2308</head><label>34</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Abnormality type</cell><cell>Pan + BTZ + Dex</cell><cell>Pbo + BTZ + Dex</cell></row><row><cell>Ventricular premature complex</cell><cell>10% (n=370)</cell><cell>6% (n=368)</cell></row><row><cell>Sinus tachycardia</cell><cell>16% (n=373)</cell><cell>7% (n=369)</cell></row><row><cell>ST segment</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Depressed ST segment</cell><cell>22% (n=373)</cell><cell>4% (n=363)</cell></row><row><cell>T-waves (any abnormality)</cell><cell>40% (n=381)</cell><cell>18% (n=377)</cell></row><row><cell>Flat T-waves</cell><cell>34% (n=358)</cell><cell>14% (n=348)</cell></row><row><cell>Inverted T-waves</cell><cell>13% (n=367)</cell><cell>6% (n=364)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_54"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>42%) of patients age &gt;65. In the panobinostat arm 42% of patients were age 65 years or older. With this number of patients it is possible to conduct an analysis to compare the toxicity profile of panobinostat in patients age &lt;65 years to patients age &gt;65 years. Patients age &gt;65 years old experienced higher rates of diarrhea, thrombocytopenia, anemia and fatigue. Most notably patients age &gt;65 years experienced a 10% increase in grade &gt;3 diarrhea, 17% increase in grade &gt;3 thrombocytopenia, 5% increase in grade &gt;3 anemia and 10% increase in grade &gt;3 fatigue.</figDesc><table><row><cell>7.5.3 Drug-Demographic Interactions 7.5.3.1 Age patients age &gt;65 years compared to 30% (n=68) of patients age &lt;65 years who received panobinostat. Adverse reactions leading to treatment interruption and/or dose modification occurred in 91% of patients age &gt;65 years compared to 87% age &lt;65 years who received panobinostat. There were 14 patients (9%) age &gt;65 years compared 12 patients (5%) age &lt;65 years who died due to a reason other than disease Trial D2308 enrolled a significant number (n= 317, Adverse reactions leading to treatment discontinuation occurred in 44% (n=71) of progression in the panobinostat arm.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_55"><head>Table 35 Most common adverse reactions in &gt;20% of patients age &gt;65 years compared to &lt;65 years who received panobinostat trial D2308</head><label>35</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Age &lt;65 years</cell><cell cols="2">Age &gt;65 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Pan + Bor + Dex</cell><cell cols="2">Pan + Bor + Dex</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n=224)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=162)</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term, n (%)</cell><cell cols="4">Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4 Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea</cell><cell>142 (63)</cell><cell>48 (21)</cell><cell>122 (76)</cell><cell>50 (31)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia</cell><cell>132 (59)</cell><cell>111 (50)</cell><cell>117 (73)</cell><cell>108 (67)</cell></row><row><cell>Anemia</cell><cell>82 (37)</cell><cell>33 (15)</cell><cell>78 (48)</cell><cell>32 (20)</cell></row><row><cell>Fatigue</cell><cell>82 (37)</cell><cell>28 (13)</cell><cell>76 (47)</cell><cell>37 (23)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>87 (39)</cell><cell>17 (8)</cell><cell>52 (33)</cell><cell>4 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral edema</cell><cell>60 (27)</cell><cell>4 (2)</cell><cell>51 (32)</cell><cell>4 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell>52 (23)</cell><cell>16 (7)</cell><cell>47 (29)</cell><cell>12 (8)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased appetite</cell><cell>64 (29)</cell><cell>6 (3)</cell><cell>46 (29)</cell><cell>6 (4)</cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia</cell><cell>70 (31)</cell><cell>58 (26)</cell><cell>44 (27)</cell><cell>34 (21)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia</cell><cell>62 (28)</cell><cell>39 (17)</cell><cell>44 (27)</cell><cell>35 (22)</cell></row><row><cell>Pyrexia</cell><cell>57 (25)</cell><cell>2 (1)</cell><cell>42 (26)</cell><cell>3 (2)</cell></row><row><cell>Constipation</cell><cell>63 (28)</cell><cell>2 (1)</cell><cell>41 (26)</cell><cell>2 (1)</cell></row><row><cell>Asthenia</cell><cell>46 (21)</cell><cell>18 (8)</cell><cell>39 (24)</cell><cell>19 (12)</cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral neuropathy</cell><cell>83 (37)</cell><cell>15 (7)</cell><cell>36 (22)</cell><cell>11 (7)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_56"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>AEs) for patients of Asian ethnicity than Caucasian ethnicity in the panobinostat arm of trial D2308 [i.e., thrombocytopenia (Caucasian vs. Asian: 60.7% vs. 70.1%), diarrhea (66.4% vs. 71.7%), fatigue (48.4% vs. 26.8%), hypokalemia (18.4% vs. 44.9%), decreased appetite (20.9% vs. 43.3%), pneumonia (12.7% vs. 26.0%), hypoesthesia (3.7% vs. 15.0%), hepatic function abnormal (0.0% vs. 3.9%), gastroenteritis (2.5% vs. 4.7%), and herpes zoster (2.9% vs. 8.7%].</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_57"><head>Table 36 Adverse events for Asian race compared to Caucasian race, trial D2308</head><label>36</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Asian patients</cell><cell cols="2">Caucasian</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Pan + Bor + Dex</cell><cell cols="2">Pan+ Bor + Dex</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">(n=129)</cell><cell cols="2">(n=245)</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred term, n (%)</cell><cell cols="4">Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4 Grade 1-4 Grade 3-4</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhea</cell><cell>93 (72)</cell><cell>44 (34)</cell><cell>164 (67)</cell><cell>51 (21)</cell></row><row><cell>Thrombocytopenia</cell><cell>91 (71)</cell><cell>82 (64)</cell><cell>149 (61)</cell><cell>130 (53)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypokalemia</cell><cell>58 (45)</cell><cell>42 (33)</cell><cell>46 (19)</cell><cell>31 (13)</cell></row><row><cell>Decreased appetite</cell><cell>57 (44)</cell><cell>5 (4)</cell><cell>52 (21)</cell><cell>7 (3)</cell></row><row><cell>Anemia</cell><cell>53 (41)</cell><cell>27 (21)</cell><cell>101 (41)</cell><cell>35 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell>46 (36)</cell><cell>12 (9)</cell><cell>50 (20)</cell><cell>16</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>46 (36)</cell><cell>7 (5)</cell><cell>89 (36)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Peripheral neuropathy</cell><cell>44 (34)</cell><cell>7 (5)</cell><cell>67 (27)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Neutropenia</cell><cell>40 (31)</cell><cell>34 (26)</cell><cell>71 (29)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Constipation</cell><cell>39 (30)</cell><cell>1 (1)</cell><cell>62 (25)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cough</cell><cell>38 (30)</cell><cell>2 (2)</cell><cell>43 (18)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_60"><head>Table of Contents 6 REVIEW OF</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_61"><head>Table 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Response criteria from Trial 2308 ..................................................................... 7 Table 2 Demographic characteristics of patients in Trial 2308 ..................................... 11 Table 3 Treatment history of patients in Trial 2308 ...................................................... 12 Table 4 Baseline disease characteristics of patients in Trial 2308 ............................... 12 Table 5 Demographic, treatment history, and baseline disease characteristics of patients in Trial 71 ......................................................................................................... 14 Table 6 Screening failures in Trial 2308 ....................................................................... 14 Table 7 Disposition of patients in Trial 2308 ................................................................. 15 Table 8 Reasons for end of treatment in Trial 71 ......................................................... 15 Table 9 Progression-free Survival (PFS) analysis of Trial 2308 ................................... 16 Table 10 PFS censoring in Trial 2308 .......................................................................... 17 Table 11 Summary of PFS sensitivity analyses of Trial 2308 ....................................... 18 Table 12 Response rate analysis of Trial 71 ................................................................ 18 Table 13 Overall Survival (OS) interim analysis of Trial 2308 ...................................... 19 Table 14 Response rates in Trial 2308......................................................................... 20 Table 15 Duration of response analysis of Trial 2308 .................................................. 20 Table 16 QOL assessment completion rates in Trial 2308 ........................................... 21 Table 17 PFS analysis of Trial 2308, by age &lt;65 vs ≥65 years .................................... 21 Table 18 PFS analysis of Trial 2308, by Asian race ..................................................... 22 Table 19 Major protocol deviations in Trial 2308 .......................................................... 23</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 3617167</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3691291</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3617392</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="56">(15) 43 (11) 28(7)17 (4) 15 (4) 15 (4) 12 (3) 11 (3) 11(3)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3617167</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">9</ref> <p>(2) 9 (2) 9 (2) 8 (2) 8 (2) 7 (2) 7 (2) 7 (2) 6 (2) 40 (11) 8 (2) 8 (2) 5 (1) 3 (1) 10 (3) 3 (1) 4 (1) 2 (1) 1 (&lt;1) 7 (2) 2 (&lt;1) 4 (1) 4 (1) 2 (&lt;1) 0 9 (2) 0 * Events that occurred at a rate &gt;2% more frequently in the panobinostat arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.3">Dropouts and/or Discontinuations</head><p>The percentage of patients that discontinued therapy due to an adverse event was higher in the panobinostat arm compared to the placebo arm. Overall 36% (n=139) of patients receiving panobinostat discontinued therapy due to an adverse event compared to 20% of patients (n=76) in the placebo arm. The most common reason for Safety Clinical Review Adam George, PharmD. NDA 203353 FARYDAK (panobinostat)  <ref type="formula">(8)</ref> 21 <ref type="formula">(5)  79 (20)</ref> 7 <ref type="formula">(2)</ref> 22 <ref type="formula">(6)</ref> 72 <ref type="formula">(19)</ref> 55 <ref type="formula">(14)  4 (1)  6 (2)  7 (2)  7</ref> (2) 19 (5) 0 3 (1) 2 (1) 15 (4) 0 1 (&lt;1) 220 <ref type="formula">(60)  173 (47)  145 (39)</ref> 238 <ref type="formula">(64)  137 (37)  156 (42)  99 (27)  125 (34)  152 (41)  79 (21)  57 (15)  86 (23)  50 (13)  81 (22)</ref> 64 <ref type="formula">(17)  54 (15)</ref> 39 <ref type="formula">(10)</ref> 8 <ref type="formula">(2)  46 (12)</ref> 7 <ref type="formula">(2)</ref> 29 <ref type="formula">(8)  26 (7)</ref> 30 <ref type="formula">(8)  7</ref> (2) 5 (1)</p><p>Reviewer comment: The laboratory adverse events observed are consistent with the fact that panobinostat is associated with dehydration, severe vomiting and diarrhea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.3">Vital Signs</head><p>There was no clinically meaningful difference between the treatment groups with regard to increases or decreases in systolic/diastolic blood pressure, heart rate, body temperature or respiratory rate.</p><p>Consistent with the finding of an increased incidence of adverse reactions of decreased body weight in patients treated with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone, there was a decrease (4 kg) in mean body weight from baseline to end of treatment in patients treated with panobinostat + bortezomib + dexamethasone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment:</head><p>In the proposed prescribing information for panobinostat the Applicant has included in section 6 language regarding ECG abnormalities and the findings of changes in T-wave and ST segment depression. It would be reasonable to describe the T-wave changes a (e.g., flat T-waves and inverted T-waves) to inform prescribers of the specific T-wave abnormalities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.5">Special Safety Studies/Clinical Trials</head><p>No special safety trials were submitted to this Application</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.6">Immunogenicity</head><p>No clinical data regarding immunogenicity were submitted to this application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5">Other Safety Explorations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.1">Dose Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>In a response to an IR (SD# 15) from the clinical pharmacology discipline the applicant completed a case-control assessment for FDA selected safety endpoints (thrombocytopenia, fatigue, diarrhea, anemia, neutropenia, hypokalemia, hemorrhage, and ischemic heart disease). The pharmacometrics review discipline is currently reviewing the data and will provide an analysis. Refer to the pharmacometrics review for this analysis.</p><p>The Applicant's executive summary of the response to IR is provided below:</p><p>Novartis has completed the case-control assessment for all selected safety endpoints (thrombocytopenia, fatigue, diarrhea, anemia, neutropenia, hypokalemia, hemorrhage, and ischemic heart disease) and PFS using the reference paper (Yang et al) in order to understand the relationship of dose intensity (DI) and clinical endpoints after adjusting for potentially unbalanced baseline risk factors. The potential relation between the respective endpoint and DI was explored by grouping patients within the panobinostat (PAN) arm by quartiles for DI.</p><p>In summary,  Time to AEs by DI-quartiles showed a trend across all safety endpoints suggesting a possible association between Grade 3-4 AE and a higher DI. In addition, this trend was also observed for thrombocytopenia for all grades. Due to a very small number of events in each quartile of DI for all grades (n=10) and grade 3/4 (n=3) ischemic heart disease and grade 3/4 hemorrhage, no additional assessment was performed. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Summary</head><p>The efficacy of Farydak (panobinostat) was principally evaluated in 768 patients with relapsed multiple myeloma enrolled in a 1:1 randomized, controlled, double-blinded, add-on design trial using bortezomib (B) and dexamethasone (D) as backbone therapy. The primary endpoint was investigator-assessed progression-free survival (PFS); the key secondary endpoint was overall survival (OS).</p><p>A summary of the key efficacy findings based on the data cut-off date of September 10, 2013 follows:</p><p>• Investigator-assessed median PFS difference was 3.9 months: 12.0 months in the panobinostat + BD arm vs. 8.1 months in the placebo + BD arm. The hazard ratio was 0.63 (95% CI: 0.52, 0.76), p-value &lt;0.0001.</p><p>• An interim analysis for OS was not mature.</p><p>• Overall response rate (ORR) was 61% [11% complete response (CR)] on the panobinostat + BD arm with a median duration of response (DOR) of 13.1 months vs. 55% (6% CR) in the placebo + BD arm with median DOR of 10.9 months.</p><p>PFS was also assessed by independent review committee (IRC) in a sensitivity analysis due to large amounts of missing data.</p><p>• IRC-assessed median PFS difference was 2.2 months: 9.9 months in the panobinostat + BD arm vs. 7.7 months in the placebo + BD arm. The hazard ratio was 0.69 (95% CI: 0.58, 0.83), p-value &lt;0.0001.</p><p>The supportive, single-arm trial CLBH589DUS71 enrolled 55 patients with relapsed and bortezomib-refractory multiple myeloma. All received panobinostat, bortezomib, and dexamethasone as given in the randomized trial. At the end of 8 cycles, the ORR was 34.5% with a median DOR of 6 months.</p><p>Limitations to confident interpretation of the randomized controlled trial include: </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">............................... .</forename><surname>Efficacy Summary</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">..................................................................... 5 6.1 Indication ............................................................................................................ 6 6.1.1 Methods ....................................................................................................... 6 6.1.2 Demographics ............................................................................................ 10</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">.</forename><forename type="middle">.</forename><surname>Analysis Of Primary Endpoint</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">................................................................. 15</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Analysis of Secondary Endpoints(s)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">. .</forename><surname>Other Endpoints</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">.................................................................................... 21</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">. . .</forename><surname>Subpopulations</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">................................................................................... 21</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">22 6.1.9 Discussion of Persistence of Efficacy and/or Tolerance Effects</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Analysis of Clinical Information Relevant to Dosing Recommendations</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="middle">. . . .</forename><surname>Appendices</surname></persName>
			<affiliation>
				<orgName type="collaboration">................................................................................................ 24</orgName>
			</affiliation>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<idno>ID: 3617167</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Review of Efficacy B. W. Miller NDA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">205353</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Farydak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>panobinostat</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Review of Efficacy B. W. Miller NDA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">205353</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Farydak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>panobinostat</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Literature Review/References</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinically relevant end points and new drug approvals for myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Anderson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Rajkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">22</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="231" to="240" />
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criteria for evaluating disease response and progression in patients with multiple myeloma treated by high-dose therapy and haemopoietic stem cell transplantation. Myeloma Subcommittee of the EBMT</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Bladé</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Samson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Reece</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Brit J Haematol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">102</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1115</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="1998" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
				<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Dimopoulos</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Fermand</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Consensus recommendations for standard investigative workup: report of the International Myeloma Workshop Consensus Panel 3. Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4701</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International Myeloma Working Group guidelines for serumfree light chain analysis in multiple myeloma and related disorders</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Dispenzieri</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Merlini</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">215</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">International uniform response criteria for multiple myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Durie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J-L</forename><surname>Harousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Miguel</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">1467</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">SEER data submission, posted to the SEER web site</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Howlader</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Noone</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Krapcho</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="http://seer.cancer.gov/csr/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Cancer Statistics Review</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1975" />
		</imprint>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>National Cancer Institute. Bethesda, MD</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criteria for the classification of monoclonal gammopathies, multiple myeloma and related disorders: a report of the International Myeloma Working Group</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">International Myeloma Working Group</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">121</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">749</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Br J Haematol</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Risk of progression and survival in multiple myeloma relapsing after therapy with IMiDs and bortezomib: A multicenter international myeloma working group study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Lee</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Lahuerta</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">149</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Review of 1027 patients with newly diagnosed multiple myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Gertz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Witzig</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Mayo Clin Proc</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">78</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">21</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Criteria for diagnosis, staging, risk stratification and response assessment of multiple myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Kyle</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Rajkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">23</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">New drugs and novel mechanisms of action in multiple myeloma in 2013: a report from the International Myeloma Working Group (IMWG)</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Ocio</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Rajkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Leukemia</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">525</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Randomized phase III study of pegylated liposomal doxorubicin plus bortezomib compared with bortezomib alone in relapsed or refractory multiple myeloma: combination therapy improves time to progression</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">Z</forename><surname>Orlowski</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Nagler</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sonneveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Clin Oncol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">25</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3892</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Consensus recommendations for the uniform reporting of clinical trials: report of the International Myeloma Workshop Consensus Panel 1</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Rajkumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J-L</forename><surname>Harousseau</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Durie</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">117</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">4691</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A phase 2 study of bortezomib in relapsed, refractory myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Barlogie</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Berenson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">26</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2609</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clinical Review of Efficacy B. W. Miller NDA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">205353</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><surname>Farydak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>panobinostat</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bortezomib or high-dose dexamethasone for relapsed multiple myeloma</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Richardson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Sonneveld</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Schuster</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">352</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">24</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2487</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Cancer statistics</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Siegel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Ma</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Zou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Jemal</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">CA Cancer J Clin</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">64</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2014" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization Classification of Tumours of Haematopoietic and Lymphoid Tissues</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Swerdlow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Campo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Harris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
			<publisher>IARC Press</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Lyon</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Racial disparities in incidence and outcome in multiple myeloma: a population-based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Waxman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Mink</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Devesa</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Blood</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">116</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">5501</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2010" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
