<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CLINICAL REVIEW Application Type Application Number(s) Priority or Standard Submit Date(s) Received Date(s) PDUFA Goal Date Division / Office</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">CLINICAL REVIEW Application Type Application Number(s) Priority or Standard Submit Date(s) Received Date(s) PDUFA Goal Date Division / Office</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:36+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="figure">BENEFIT ASSESSMENT .....................................</ref></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1">Recommendations/Risk Benefit Assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.1">Recommendation on Regulatory Action</head><p>From a clinical perspective, the recommended regulatory action for this supplemental NDA is Approval. This sNDA adequately fulfills the postmarketing pediatric research equity act (PREA) requirement in patients under 6 years of age.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Risk Benefit Assessment</head><p>The application contains clinical data from five pediatric trials which enrolled patients under 6 years of age with asthma or reactive airway disease. Because these studies were not part of a planned pediatric development program, the studies were of varying design and utility to the efficacy and safety evaluation. Despite this limitation, the Agency agreed to accept all clinical data available in this age group in order to update the product label accordingly and to fulfill the long-outstanding PREA requirement for pediatric patients less than 6 years of age. The single placebo-controlled trial (051-032) evaluated the effectiveness of levalbuterol inhalation solution 0.31 mg and 0.63 mg three times daily over 3 weeks compared with placebo and racemic albuterol in reducing asthma symptoms as measured by the Pediatric Asthma Questionnaire. Neither dose of levalbuterol inhalation solution demonstrated consistent efficacy in asthmatic patients 2 to 5 years of age. Of the remaining four studies submitted, none were adequately designed to demonstrate substantial evidence of efficacy.</p><p>Regarding safety in patients less than 6 years of age, there was a small but consistent pattern of increased asthma exacerbations, asthma-related treatment-emergent adverse events, and treatment discontinuations due to asthma in patients receiving levalbuterol inhalation solution compared to placebo or racemic albuterol. This along with the lack of consistent efficacy does not support approval for use in pediatric patients under 6 years of age and warrants inclusion in the product label. Based on the submitted data, the Applicant has not requested an indication in the younger age group. The risk benefit profile of Xopenex IS in the approved population of patients 6 years of age and older remains favorable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies</head><p>There are no recommendations for additional postmarketing risk evaluation and mitigation strategies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.6">Other Relevant Background Information</head><p>On October 1, 2014, the Applicant (Sunovion Pharmaceuticals, Inc.) transferred ownership of this NDA (20-837) to Oak Pharmaceuticals, Inc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Ethics and Good Clinical Practices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Submission Quality and Integrity</head><p>The NDA was submitted electronically and included complete study reports, appropriate case report forms, and proposed labeling. The submission was appropriately indexed and organized to permit clinical review. Review of the application did not raise any data integrity concerns, and the majority of studies were conducted greater than 10 years ago. In addition, Xopenex Inhalation Solution is already an approved product for the treatment of bronchospasm. For these reasons, the Division did not request an audit by the Division of Scientific Investigations (DSI) for this supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Compliance with Good Clinical Practices</head><p>The Applicant stated that the clinical trials were conducted in compliance with Good Clinical Practices and submitted a statement certifying that no debarred individuals participated in the conduct of trials included in this NDA. Prior to trial initiation, the clinical study protocols and written informed consent forms were reviewed and approved by an IRB.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Financial Disclosures</head><p>The Applicant has adequately disclosed financial interests/arrangements with clinical investigators as recommended in the guidance for industry Financial Disclosure by Clinical Investigators. None of the principle investigators who participated in the clinical with the protocols and minimize bias of the clinical study results, the investigator and study coordinators attended an investigators' meeting where protocol specifications and regulatory responsibilities were reviewed in detail, and the study site was monitored by trained Clinical Research personnel with a 100% review of source documentation to the case record form data. The financial disclosure checklist is provided below. The disclosed financial interests raise no questions about the integrity of the data and do not affect the approvability of this application. Compensation to the investigator for conducting the study where the value could be influenced by the outcome of the study: 0</p><p>Significant payments of other sorts: 1</p><p>Proprietary interest in the product tested held by investigator: 0</p><p>Significant equity interest held by investigator in sponsor of covered study: 0</p><p>Is an attachment provided with details of the disclosable financial interests/arrangements:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request details from applicant) Is a description of the steps taken to minimize potential bias provided:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request information from applicant) Number of investigators with certification of due diligence (Form FDA 3454, box 3) 0</p><p>Is an attachment provided with the reason:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yes</head><p>No (Request explanation from applicant)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Significant Efficacy/Safety Issues Related to Other Review Disciplines</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Chemistry Manufacturing and Controls</head><p>Levalbuterol HCl inhalation solution is an approved product; therefore, no new quality data was submitted or required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Clinical Microbiology</head><p>Levalbuterol HCl inhalation solution is an approved product; therefore, no new microbiology data was submitted or required.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>12</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Preclinical Pharmacology/Toxicology</head><p>No new pharmacology/toxicology data was submitted or required in this supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Clinical Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Mechanism of Action</head><p>As described in previous reviews, levalbuterol is the (R)-enantiomer of the drug substance racemic albuterol. Levalbuterol is a relatively selective β 2 -adrenergic receptor agonist. Activation of β 2 -adrenergic receptors on airway smooth muscle leads to activation of adenylate cyclase and to an increase in the intracellular concentration of cyclic-3', 5'-adenosine monophosphate (cyclic AMP). The increase in cyclic AMP is associated with the activation of protein kinase A, which in turn inhibits phosphorylation of myosin and lowers intracellular ionic calcium concentrations, ultimately resulting in smooth muscle relaxation in the airways. Increased cyclic AMP concentrations are also associated with inhibited release of mediators from mast cells in the airway.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2">Pharmacodynamics</head><p>No new pharmacodynamic information was submitted or required with this supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.3">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>This supplement included limited data from pharmacokinetic (PK) sampling in pediatric patients, primarily from Studies 051-032 and 051-359. Levalbuterol treatment groups from Study 051-032 had measurable (R)-albuterol plasma concentrations, but also had measurable (S)-albuterol plasma concentrations, albeit at lower levels than observed in the racemic albuterol group. Similarly, in Study 051-359, measurable (R)-albuterol concentrations were present in both levalbuterol treatment groups and in the placebo treatment group, although at much lower levels in the latter. These findings may reflect use of rescue albuterol or potentially contamination. Given the limitations of the sampling and the findings, no conclusions can be drawn from the PK data, </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Population</head><p>A total of 211 subjects were randomized to study treatment: 58 to Lev IS 0.31 mg, 51 to Lev IS 0.63 mg, 52 to racemic albuterol, and 50 to placebo.</p><p>Key Inclusion Criteria 1. Male or female between the ages of 2 and 5 years (inclusive) at the time of consent. 2. Physician-diagnosis of asthma for a minimum of 30 days prior to Visit 1.</p><p>(Investigators were allowed to enroll subjects under their direct supervision with newly diagnosed asthma.) 3. Overall good health with the exception of asthma 4. Chest x-ray (within the past 12 months) with no evidence of pneumonia, atelectasis, pulmonary fibrotic disease, pneumothorax, etc. 5. Parent/legal guardian able to reliably complete diary cards and medical event calendars on a daily basis.</p><p>Key Exclusion Criteria 1. History of hospitalization for asthma within 30 days prior to Visit 1 or scheduled for in-patient hospitalization, including elective surgery, during the trial. 2. Life-threatening asthma, defined as a history of asthma episodes requiring intubation, associated with hypercapnia, respiratory arrest, or hypoxic seizures within 12 months prior to Visit 1. 3. Disallowed medication use or expected use during the trial 4. Clinically significant abnormalities that may interfere with metabolism or excretion of study drug or diseases (e.g., hyperthyroidism, diabetes, hypertension, cardiac disease, seizures) that were not well-controlled by medication or that may interfere with completion of study 5. History of cancer 6. Bronchopulmonary aspergillosis or any form of allergic alveolitis 7. Purulent respiratory tract infection in the 14 days prior to Visit 1 or during the study 8. Clinically significant laboratory or 12-lead ECG abnormality</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Withdrawal Criteria</head><p>Subjects may have been discontinued from study treatment for any of the following reasons:</p><p>o Ampule Inhalation Solution, 0.083% (w/v), 1.25 mg/3 mL or 2.5 mg/3 mL in 0.9% saline o Placebo: 0.9% saline/3 mL Rescue medication consisted of 1.25 mg Lev IS for all subjects during the placebo runin period. Blinded rescue medication during the double-blind treatment period consisted of 1.25 mg Lev IS for both levalbuterol groups and 2.5 mg racemic albuterol for the racemic albuterol and placebo groups.</p><p>Study medication was administered using a PARI LC PLUS™ nebulizer with a mouthpiece or face mask and a PARI DURA-NEB™ 3000 compressor three times daily (minimum 4 hours in between doses) for 3 weeks.</p><p>Dose selection for this age group was based on data from previous studies demonstrating that the peak change in FEV 1 produced by 0.31 mg and 0.63 mg of Lev IS was similar to 1.25 mg and 2.5 mg of racemic albuterol, respectively. In addition, an investigator-initiated study (051-SRC038) had administered Lev IS doses as high as 1.25 mg every 20 minutes for up to 6 doses in children ages 1-18 years of age with no significant adverse events reported.</p><p>Compliance was measured by the number of study drug ampules dispensed, returned, and lost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy</head><p>The primary efficacy variable was the total score from the Pediatric Asthma Questionnaire (PAQ) which consisted of eight questions regarding difficulty breathing, cough, wheeze, activity limitation, level of activity limitation, overall symptom score, and nighttime asthma awakenings (see Error! Reference source not found.). Parents/legal guardians completed the PAQ on a daily basis. The daytime asthma questions were rated on a scale of 0 to 4, while the nighttime asthma questions were rated on a scale of 0 to 3 and 0 to 2; higher scores indicated greater symptom severity (maximum score=29). The primary efficacy endpoint was the mean change in the PAQ total score during the third week of treatment (Week 3) relative to the placebo run-in period (Week -1). The primary efficacy analysis was performed on the intent-to-treat (ITT) population, which included all subjects who received at least one dose of doubleblind study medication, using an ANOVA model with effects for treatment, investigator, and weight group.</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution up to 3 hours 4 . Subjects who subsequently required hospitalization or did not meet discharge criteria 5 within 24 hours were discontinued from the study. After discharge from the ED/physician's office, subjects entered Period II of the study and were instructed to administer double-blind study medication TID for the next 7-10 days and to return to clinic for Visit 2 at that time. After Visit 2, subjects entered Period III and were instructed to administer double-blind study medication PRN to TID for an additional 7-10 days and to return to clinic for Visit 3. A follow-up safety evaluation was conducted by telephone 14 days after Visit 3. Rescue medication during Periods II and III consisted of blinded 1.25mg Lev IS for the levalbuterol treatment groups and blinded 2.5 mg racemic albuterol for the racemic albuterol treatment group. A study schematic and schedule of assessments are shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 3</ref> and <ref type="table">Table 7</ref>. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> Investigators were allowed to administer additional doses of blinded study medication to subjects who were not discharged after 3 hours. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> Based on diminished wheezing, good air exchange, no supraclavicular or intercostal retractions, O 2 saturation ≥95% on room air, minimum 25% improvement in Section III RSS total score, and investigator's clinical judgment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>22</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Amendments</head><p>There were two protocol amendments. Amendment #1, dated October 18, 2007, reduced the number of lab collections and volume of blood drawn and added a minimum weight requirement and extra vital sign assessments between doses. Amendment #2, dated February 14, 2008, lowered the reversibility inclusion criteria from 15% to 12% and clarified timing of study assessments.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The primary objective of this study was to compare the safety and tolerability of cumulative dosing with arformoterol tartrate inhalation solution versus levalbuterol HCl inhalation solution (3 cumulative nebulizations in one hour) in pediatric subjects with asthma. Secondary objectives were to characterize the pharmacokinetic profile of (R,R)formoterol and to investigate the FEV 1 response in children 6 years of age and older.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Design</head><p>This was a randomized, double-blind, two-way crossover study evaluating three cumulative doses of arformoterol (7.5 mcg per nebulization) and levalbuterol IS (0.63 mg per nebulization) administered over a 1-hour period, followed by a single open-label treatment day with three cumulative doses of arformoterol 15 mcg per nebulization in subjects 2 to 11 years of age with asthma. The study was divided into five periods as shown in <ref type="figure">Figure 5</ref>. Study Schematic: 091-029 Period I (Visits 1 and 2) consisted of a screening visit and a 7-day washout period during which LABAs were withheld. Subjects received either Lev IS 0.63 mg or Lev HFA 45 mcg/actuation as needed for rescue medication for the duration of the study. Period II (Visits 3 and 4) and Period III (Visits 5 and 6) consisted of the blinded active treatment days during which subjects received three cumulative doses of either arformoterol 7.5 mcg per nebulization or Lev IS 0.63 mcg per nebulization. Period IV (Visits 7-9) consisted of the open-label arformoterol (15 mcg per nebulization) treatment day. On each treatment day, the study medication was administered every 30 minutes over 1 hour (at 0, 30, and 60 minutes). Following each treatment, subjects were monitored for 6 hours after dosing, and then followed at 12 and 24 hours by phone and in clinic, respectively. The three treatment days were separated by a 7-day washout period and safety review for each subject. Period V (Visit 10) occurred 5 days after arformoterol open-label treatment and consisted of the final clinical study evaluation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>29</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution Source: Module 5.3.5.4, Study 091-029 CSR, <ref type="table">Table 9</ref>.1-1, p24</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Population</head><p>A total of 53 subjects were enrolled in the study. Randomization was stratified by age group (2-5 years and 6-11 years); fourteen of the subjects were in the 2-5 year old age group.</p><p>Key Inclusion Criteria 1. Male and female subjects between the ages of 2 to 11 years, inclusive, at the time of consent and weight ≥15 kg 2. Negative serum pregnancy test at Visit 1 for females ≥8 years of age 3. Physician-diagnosed asthma of at least 2 years duration for children ≥6 years of age and for at least 1 year duration for children ≤5 years of age 4. Baseline FEV 1 of 65-85% predicted for subjects ≥6 years of age (and for subjects ≤5 years of age who could perform spirometry) 5. Demonstration of ≥12% reversibility of airflow obstruction within 15-30 minutes following inhalation of levalbuterol 0.63 mg inhalation solution in subjects ≥6 years of age (and any subjects ≤5 years of age who could perform spirometry) 6. Stable asthma with use of a β-adrenergic agonist, and/or asthma antiinflammatory medication, and/or over-the-counter asthma medication for at least 6 months prior to Visit 1 7. Good health with the exception of reversible airways disease 8. Physical examination that was not suggestive of a pulmonary condition other than asthma Key Exclusion Criteria 1. Expected to require any disallowed medications 2. Pregnancy or lactation 3. Inability to take first daily dose of study medication and/or to start study visits before 9 AM 4. History of hospitalization of asthma within 1 year prior to Visit 1 or scheduled for in-patient hospitalization, including elective surgery, during the course of the trial 5. History of life-threatening asthma defined as asthma episodes requiring intubations, associated with hypercapnia, respiratory arrest, or hypoxic seizures 31</p><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution 6. Unstable asthma, change in asthma therapy, or visit to the ED/hospital for worsening asthma within 6 weeks 7. History of cigarette smoking or use of any tobacco products 8. Clinically significant abnormalities that may interfere with metabolism/excretion of study drug 9. Hyperthyroidism, diabetes, hypertension, cardiac disease, or seizure disorders 10. History of cancer 11. Bronchopulmonary aspergillosis or any form of allergic alveolitis 12. Clinically significant upper or lower respiratory tract infection in the 6 weeks prior to Visit 1 or during the study 13. Clinically significant laboratory or 12-lead ECG abnormality 14. Weight less than 15kg</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Withdrawal Criteria</head><p>Subjects may have been discontinued from the study for any of the following reasons:</p><p>o Adverse event o Protocol violation o Voluntary withdrawal o Lost to follow-up o No longer met entry criteria o Other Subjects who prematurely discontinued from the study were not replaced, and, regardless of cause, were required to be seen for a final early termination evaluation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prohibited Medications</head><p>The following medications were disallowed for the duration of the study and must have been withheld for the specified time period prior to Visit 1. Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution of abnormal lab values that was inadvertently removed in the previously amended protocol. Amendment #4, dated February 11, 2010, removed the minimum number of patients required to perform PEF due to difficulty with recruitment, and clarified target enrollment numbers (30 patients aged 0 to 11 months and no more than 30 subjects aged 12 to 23 months).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The objectives were to examine the safety, tolerability, and efficacy of levalbuterol HFA MDI using a facemask and holding chamber in subjects aged birth to 47 months with asthma.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Design</head><p>This was a modified-blind, randomized, placebo-controlled, multicenter, parallel-group trial. Subjects were screened at Visit 1 after which eligible subjects entered a 7-day placebo washout period and returned for randomization at Visit 2. Subjects who had no clinically significant adverse events and disallowed medication use during the washout period were randomized equally to one of three study treatments: Lev HFA 45-90 mcg (1-2 actuations) MDI, Lev IS 0.31 mg, or placebo 1-2 actuations MDI. All study treatments were administered three times daily for 4 weeks. The MDI dose was based on age; subjects 0 to 23 months received 1 actuation (45 mcg levalbuterol) TID while subjects 24 to 47 months received 2 actuations (90 mcg levalbuterol) TID. The MDI treatment arms were double-blind while the Lev IS treatment arm was open-label with the same 0.31 mg dose administered regardless of age. Approximately 65 subjects were to be randomized to each treatment (195 subjects total) with the following distribution by age: 45 subjects aged 24 to 47 months and 20 subjects aged 0 to 23 months with at least half being under 12 months of age.</p><p>Subjects received their first dose of study medication in clinic. Parents/legal guardians were instructed to complete the Pediatric Asthma Caregiver Assessments (PACA) questionnaire daily. Subjects 24 to 47 months of age who were capable of performing acceptable and reproducible PEF maneuvers were instructed to perform PEF maneuvers throughout the study. Follow-up visits occurred at 2-week intervals during the 28-day treatment period (Visits 3 and 4) and then 7 days after end of study drug treatment (Visit 5). A study schematic and schedule of assessments are shown below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>35</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Population</head><p>A total of 197 subjects were randomized to study treatment: 65 to Lev HFA MDI, 64 to Lev IS, and 68 to placebo MDI. Of the 64 patients within the Lev IS treatment group, 9 patients were under 12 months of age, 22 patients were between 12 and 23 months of age, and 41 patients were between 24 and 47 months of age.</p><p>Main Inclusion Criteria 1. Male or female between the ages of birth and 47 months at the time of consent 2. For subjects 24 to 47 months of age, a physician diagnosis of asthma (defined as at least 3 episodes of respiratory symptoms consistent with asthma symptoms including, but not limited to, cough, wheeze, or dyspnea) 3. For subjects 0 to 23 months of age, a history of 3 episodes of respiratory symptoms that in the judgment of the investigator could be consistent with asthma or reactive airways disease 4. No other chronic conditions other than asthma 5. No evidence of chronic cardiopulmonary conditions other than asthma on chest radiograph Rescue medication consisted of Lev IS 0.31 mg for use as needed for all treatment groups.</p><p>MDI treatments were administered via the Monaghan AeroChamber MAX™ with face mask with instructions for the face mask to be held in place for 1 minute. Levalbuterol IS was administered via mouthpiece or facemask with the TREK-S™ compressor and PARI LC PLUS™ nebulizer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy</head><p>Evaluating the efficacy of Lev HFA MDI in pediatric patients under 4 years of age was a secondary objective of this study. Efficacy assessments included daily Pediatric Asthma Caregiver Assessments (PACA), Pediatric Asthma Questionnaire (PAQ), Pediatric Asthma Quality of Life Questionnaire (PACQLQ), PEF maneuvers in subjects 24 to 47 months of age, investigator and caregiver global evaluations, and rescue medication use. The primary efficacy variable was the PACA, a questionnaire consisting of five domains that was completed by parents/legal guardians daily (see <ref type="table">Table 15</ref>. Pediatric Asthma Caregiver Assessments (PACA) below). The maximum score was 19, with higher scores indicating greater symptom severity. The primary endpoint was the change in mean daily composite PACA score from baseline to Visit 4 between treatment groups. Baseline was defined as the mean of the daily composite scores during the placebo washout period from Visit 1 to 2, and Visit 4 was defined as the mean of the daily composite scores in the week prior to Visit 4. However, because the Lev IS treatment arm was unblinded, the only relevant comparison was between the blinded Lev HFA MDI and placebo MDI treatment groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>39</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution ) via facemask (&lt; 6 years of age) or mouthpiece (≥6 years of age).</p><p>Additional treatments administered during intensification therapy consisted of the following:</p><p> Ipratropium bromide 500 mcg (0.5 mg/2.5 mL) inhalation solution  Subcutaneous epinephrine 0.01mL/kg (1:1000 injection ampules), max dose 0.5 mg  Double dose of blinded study drug (2.5 mg Lev IS or 5 mg racemic albuterol)  Supplemental oxygen  Corticosteroids (oral prednisone 2 mg/kg or IV methylprednisolone 1 mg/kg)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy</head><p>Primary efficacy variables were hospital admission rates and total length of stay (LOS). Secondary efficacy variables included ED length of stay, Asthma Care Path length of stay, number of aerosols required before discharge criteria were met, number of subjects with LOS &lt;24 hours in each group, number of subjects requiring intensification therapy, requirement for supplemental oxygen, concurrent medication in the ED, and rates of acute visits or readmissions to the hospital for worsening asthma. Although patients were stratified by age, the study did not prespecify or power for separate analyses of patients less than 6 years of age.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety</head><p>Safety assessments included vital signs (heart rate, respiratory rate, and oxygen saturation) and unexpected adverse events. Because asthma-related events were expected, these were not captured during the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer Comment:</head><p>Despite enrolling the highest number of patients, Study 051-SRC038 provides no meaningful efficacy or safety information, and thus is not relevant to this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>44</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Review of Efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Summary</head><p>The Applicant submitted two Phase 3 pediatric studies (051-032 and 051-033) to evaluate the efficacy of levalbuterol inhalation solution for the treatment and prevention of bronchospasm in patients less than 6 years of age with reversible obstructive airway disease. In Study 051-032, subjects received one of four double-blind medications three times daily for 3 weeks: levalbuterol inhalation solution 0.31 mg or 0.63 mg, racemic albuterol, or placebo. The primary efficacy endpoint was the mean change in Pediatric Asthma Questionnaire (PAQ) total score from run-in to its mean during Week 3 compared to placebo. In Study 051-033, subjects received one of three double-blind medications for treatment of an acute asthma exacerbation: low dose or high dose levalbuterol inhalation solution or racemic albuterol. The primary efficacy endpoint was the maximum decrease in the Respiratory Status Scale (RSS) total score from pre-dose to each post-dose measurement during the acute exacerbation treatment period.</p><p>Both studies failed to demonstrate a statistically significant benefit of levalbuterol inhalation solution for the prevention or treatment of asthma or reactive airway disease in this age group. In Study 051-032, the levalbuterol inhalation solution treatment groups experienced the greatest numerical decrease in PAQ total score over the 3 week treatment period; however, the overall difference between treatment groups was not statistically significant. Furthermore, this numerical advantage disappears when the analysis is adjusted for the higher baseline PAQ scores in the levalbuterol inhalation solution treatment groups. Study 051-033 evaluated a non-validated respiratory symptom score as its primary endpoint and did not include a placebo control or a prespecified non-inferiority margin to the active control, racemic albuterol. Even if these design flaws are dismissed, levalbuterol inhalation solution performed worse than an equivalent racemic albuterol dose, and the low dose of levalbuterol outperformed the high dose.</p><p>Although the Applicant included a third study, 051-SRC038, which compared levalbuterol with racemic albuterol in children 2 to 17 years of age experiencing an acute asthma exacerbation, this study did not prespecify nor power for separate efficacy analyses of patients less than 6 years of age.</p><p>The Applicant submitted this supplement to comply with PREA regulations, but based on the results from these studies, is not seeking to expand the indication to patients less than 6 years of age. It is of note, however, that while the submitted studies failed to meet their primary endpoints, it is often difficult to demonstrate efficacy in younger patients by means of caregiver symptom assessments, particularly when asthma symptoms are mild at baseline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution which was higher in the Lev IS groups. For further details see the original Biometrics Review from supplement 011 completed by Dr. James Gebert on February 21, 2003. Study 051-033 The primary endpoint for Study 051-033 was the maximum decrease in RSS total score during Period I, from initial pre-dose at screening and each post-dose measurement. The RSS total score was based solely on the sum of the Section III scores comprised of grunting/coughing, nasal flaring, wheezing, air exchange, and accessory muscle use (refer to Section 5.3, <ref type="figure">Figure 4)</ref>. A lower RSS total score indicated improved respiratory status (maximum score=12). As noted in Section 5.3, the RSS is not a validated endpoint to quantitatively measure acute reactive airway disease activity, and the study design did not include a placebo control or a pre -specified non-inferiority margin to the presumably effective active control, racemic albuterol. The statistical methodology was the same as in Study 051-032, but as noted in the Biometrics Review of this submission by Dr. Robert Abugov, this study was improperly designed due to its comparison of Lev IS to an equivalent racemic albuterol mixture using a test for superiority rather than noninferiority. Therefore, Dr. Abugov revised the primary efficacy analysis in his statistical review to evaluate the superiority of HD Lev IS to LD Lev IS for maximum change from baseline in RSS total score.</p><p>The baseline RSS total scores were similar between both Lev IS treatment groups with means and medians of 7.0. The baseline RSS total score was slightly higher in the racemic albuterol group with a mean and median of 7.7 and 8.0, respectively. The results for the primary efficacy analysis, as performed by Dr. Abugov, are shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_4">Table 20</ref> (note a higher decrease indicates greater benefit). The improvements in RSS Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution total score from baseline were statistically significantly less for HD Lev IS compared to LD Lev IS. Although the Applicant analyzed additional efficacy endpoints (See Section 5.3), these were not reviewed in detail given the lack of statistical significance of the primary endpoints and the Applicant's decision to seek no further indication based on the results of these studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.7">Subpopulations</head><p>Because neither study showed effectiveness for Lev IS, differences by gender, race, age, or geographic region were not examined for this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.8">Analysis of Clinical Information Relevant to Dosing Recommendations</head><p>The Applicant evaluated Lev IS doses of 0.31 mg and 0.63 mg in Study 051-032 as well as high and low Lev IS doses for weight in Study 051-033. Although neither study demonstrated effectiveness for any Lev IS dose, the higher dose groups consistently performed more poorly than the lower dose groups. Whether this is due to a differential tachyphylaxis effect after chronic dosing in Study 051-032 or perhaps a potentially a harmful effect from Lev IS, as will be discussed in Section 7, is unclear. 6.1.9 Discussion of Persistence of Efficacy and/or Tolerance Effects Current guidelines recommend that these short-acting β 2 -adrenergic agonists be used as-needed rather than continuously due to known tolerance or tachyphylaxis to the bronchodilator effects that occurs with long term, scheduled use. In Study 051-032, the mean baseline change in PEF (measured 30-45 minutes postdose at weekly clinic visits) diminished over the course of 3 weeks in the Lev 0.63 mg treatment group, but not the Lev 0.31 mg or racemic albuterol treatment groups (data not shown). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Review of Safety</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Summary</head><p>This sNDA submission contains adequate data to update the product label regarding use in patients less than 6 years of age. The majority of safety data in this age group is based on three of the five studies included in this submission: 051-032 (3-week chronic dosing trial in patients 2 to 5 years), 051-033 (acute exacerbation trial with 2-week follow up period in patients birth to 48 months), and 051-359 (4-week chronic dosing trial in patients birth to 47 months).</p><p>No deaths were reported in any study, and nonfatal serious adverse events (SAEs) were rare overall. Although there is no apparent imbalance among treatment groups, the SAEs that did occur primarily involved hospitalization for asthma or other respiratory illnesses such as pneumonia. Data from the three primary safety studies revealed a small but consistent pattern of increased asthma exacerbations, asthma-related treatment-emergent adverse events, and treatment discontinuations due to asthma in patients receiving levalbuterol inhalation solution compared to placebo or racemic albuterol. This safety information will be added to the product label. Additionally, even though a decrease in β 2 -agonist associated side effects is an often touted safety benefit of levalbuterol use, there was no substantial difference in the occurrence of hypokalemia, cardiovascular effects, or hyperglycemia among treatment groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.1">Studies/Clinical Trials Used to Evaluate Safety</head><p>The clinical trials used to evaluate safety are described in <ref type="table">Table 3</ref> in Section 5.1 and primarily include studies 051-032, 051-033, and 051-359. For studies 091-029 and 051-SRC038, which enrolled pediatric subjects up to 11 and 17 years of age, respectively, only the subset of subjects under 6 years of age were included in this safety review; however, these two studies contributed very little evaluable safety data given the short duration and small size of Study 091-029 and limited amount of safety data captured in Study 051-SRC038. It is also worth noting that one study site (#0183), which enrolled 25 subjects (~20% of all subjects) in Study 051-033 did not report any adverse events.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.2">Categorization of Adverse Events</head><p>Adverse events (AEs) were defined as any reaction, side effect, or other undesirable event that occurred in conjunction with the use of study medication, whether or not the event was considered related to study medication. Adverse events were considered serious if the event was fatal or life-threatening, permanently disabling, required or prolonged hospitalization, represented a congenital anomaly, or required intervention to prevent permanent damage. Adverse events were collected from time of informed 51 Across the five studies, Lev IS doses ranging from 0.15 mg to 1.25 mg were evaluated; however, the majority of evaluable safety data is derived from treatment administration with 0.31 mg and 0.63 mg doses. Following chronic dosing, there was no appreciable dose response in terms of efficacy or safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.3">Special Animal and/or In Vitro Testing</head><p>No special animal or in vitro testing was submitted as part of this application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.4">Routine Clinical Testing</head><p>The safety evaluation in the Sponsor-initiated studies included monitoring of adverse events, vital signs, physical exam, and clinical laboratory tests. The methods used and the frequency of assessments provided an adequate assessment of the safety of Lev IS in the treatment of asthma or reactive airway disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.5">Metabolic, Clearance, and Interaction Workup</head><p>Appropriate studies to assess the absorption, distribution, metabolism, and clearance of levalbuterol inhalation solution were submitted by the Applicant in support of the original NDA for the use of levalbuterol inhalation solution to treat adult and adolescent patients with reversible obstructive airway disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.6">Evaluation for Potential Adverse Events for Similar Drugs in Drug Class</head><p>As mentioned in Section 2.4, β 2 -adrenergic agonists have to potential to cause paradoxical bronchospasm, particularly with continued or scheduled use. The Sponsor assessed for protocol-defined asthma exacerbations as a secondary endpoint in Study 051-032 and for β 2 -agonist related TEAEs, treatment failures, and asthma-related TEAEs in Study 051-359; these findings are discussed in Section 7.3.5. In addition, the Sponsor included vital signs, clinical labs, and EKG to assess for common side effects such as tachycardia and hypokalemia as well as other cardiovascular effects; these results are discussed in Section 7.4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Major Safety Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1">Deaths</head><p>There were no deaths in any of the five studies reviewed in this supplemental NDA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>54</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286 days after the last dose of study medication for treatment of pneumonia (and concurrent sinusitis).</p><p>Subject 1652163 (RA 2.5 mg): This was a 3-year-old male with history of eczema, SAR, and PAR. He experienced wheeze and cough of moderate severity on Day 4 of double-blind study treatment, and received four doses of rescue medication on that day.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(b ) (4)</formula><p>On Day , he presented to the ED for persistent symptoms and was hospitalized for treatment with albuterol, ipratropium, oral corticosteroids, and oxygen. He was subsequently transferred to another hospital on the following day for continuing <ref type="bibr">(b) (4)</ref> treatment and was discharged on Day . Study medication was discontinued due to this event.</p><p>Subject 1732074 (RA 2.5 mg):</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(b) (4)</formula><p>This was a 3-year-old male with history of eczema, food allergy, SAR, and PAR. days after completing the double-blind treatment period, he experienced an asthma exacerbation of moderate severity resulting in hospitalization.</p><p>Study 051-033 Subject 03313152 (HD Lev IS, 1.25 mg): This was a 23-month-old male weighing 12.8 kg upon presentation to the ED for an asthma exacerbation. He had a history of reactive airway disease and "respiratory issues" since birth, but had not received controller medications (albuterol nebulizer and Pulmicort) for the past 3 days. He was afebrile with a respiratory rate of 32 breaths/minute, O2 saturation of 92% on room air, and RSS score of 5. He received three nebulized doses of 1.25 mg Lev IS and oral prednisone while in the ED before planned discharge. However, before leaving the ED, his condition worsened (O2 sat 85%, decreased air entry, and increased wheeze); therefore, he was subsequently admitted to the hospital and was treated with continuous albuterol nebulization, atrovent, and prednisone. This event was assigned to Period I, and the subject was discontinued from the study due to this event. The event was considered resolved <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref> (4) days later.</p><p>Subject 00274082 (RA 1.25 mg): This was a 2-month-old male weighing 7.1 kg upon presentation to the ED for an asthma exacerbation. He had a history of asthma treated <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref>  <ref type="formula">(4)</ref> with PRN albuterol. days prior to presentation, he was evaluated for cough and wheeze and noted to have bronchiolitis and a red tympanic membrane for which he was started on albuterol, Pediazole, and a 5-day course of Prelone before being sent home. In the ED, his RSS score was 6, and he received four doses of RA 1.25 mg before discharge home. During the follow-up period, he received protocol-specified oral (b) (4) corticosteroids.</p><p>days after discharge, he presented to the ED with irritability, shortness of breath, cough, congestion, low-grade fever, tachypnea, and tachycardia. A chest x-ray revealed pneumonia, and he was subsequently hospitalized for treatment with IV cefotaxime, Solu-Medrol, albuterol, and supplemental oxygen. Sputum culture returned positive for H. influenzae and Staphylococcus. He was discharged <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref> (4) days later, and discontinued from the study due to this event.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>56</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution Subject 01783129 (HD Lev IS, 1.25 mg): This was a 29-month-old-male (11.5 kg) with a history of asthma, IgG subclass and IgA deficiency, and RSV who presented to the ED for an asthma exacerbation. He had a familial history of febrile seizures and epilepsy. Upon arrival his RSS score was 5, and he received one nebulized dose of 1.25 mg Lev IS before discharge. He continued to take oral prednisone and study <ref type="bibr">(b) (4)</ref> medication during the follow-up period.</p><p>days after presentation to the ED, he experienced a fever and decreased oral intake followed by tonic-clonic seizures. He was hospitalized for a hypoglycemic seizure (last dose of study medication <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref> (4) days prior). After an extensive evaluation, the etiology was felt to be iatrogenic adrenal suppression from oral and inhaled glucocorticoid. The subject was discontinued from the study due to this event.</p><p>Subject 02592025 (HD Lev IS, 0.63 mg): This was a 6-month-old female (weight 8.2 kg) with a history of gastroesophageal reflux and bronchiolitis who presented to the ED with an acute asthma exacerbation. She received 4 doses of study medication prior to discharge. After <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref> (4) days of treatment with blinded study medication during Period II, she was hospitalized for hypoxia and respiratory distress secondary to bronchiolitis. She was discontinued from the study due to this event.</p><p>(Period II), he received three doses of study medication and one dose of rescue medication for wheeze and cough without improvement. He was hospitalized for observation of respiratory distress, apnea, and hypoxia and was treated with albuterol, (b ) (4) amoxicillin, and erythromycin. He was discharged Subject 02592027 (LD Lev IS 0.31 mg): This was a 9-month-old male (weight 9.8 kg) with a history of recurrent otitis media who presented to the ED with an acute asthma exacerbation. He reported having had one asthma exacerbation within the past 30 days. He received two doses of study medication in the ED prior to discharge. The (b) (4) days later and discontinued from the study due to this event.</p><p>Subject 02593145 (HD Lev IS 1.25 mg): This was a 35-month-old male (weight 15.5 kg) who presented to the ED with an acute asthma exacerbation. He was received four doses of study medication prior to discharge and continued to receive blinded study medication TID to PRN in Periods II and III. Six days after completing the study, he experienced sudden onset of wheezing, cough, tachypnea and retractions. He presented to the ED and was subsequently Study 051-359 Subject 0032/S013 (Lev IS 0.31 mg): This was a 27-month old male with a history of exomphalos, asthma, and eczema who was not on concomitant inhaled corticosteroid <ref type="bibr">(b)</ref> (4) controller therapy. On Day , he experienced an acute asthma exacerbation which did not improve with ipratropium/albuterol and prednisolone treatment in the ED. He was admitted to the hospital for continued treatment and started on inhaled budesonide. Study medication was interrupted during the hospitalization, and he was subsequently</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>on Regulatory Action ............................................................. 7 1.2 Risk Benefit Assessment.................................................................................... 7 1.3 Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies ... 7 1.4 Recommendations for Postmarket Requirements and Commitments ...............</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Figure 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Study Schematic: 051-032 ............................................................................. 16 Figure 2. Pediatric Asthma Questionnaire (PAQ).......................................................... 20 Figure 3. Study Schematic: 051-033 ............................................................................. 23 Figure 4. Respiratory Status Scale (RSS) ..................................................................... 27 Figure 5. Study Schematic: 091-029 ............................................................................. 30 Figure 6. Study Schematic: 051-359 ............................................................................. 36 Figure 7. Emergency Department Asthma Care Algorithm: Study 051-SRC038........... 42 Figure 8. Asthma Care Path Algorithm: Study 051-SRC038 ......................................... 42 Figure 9. Asthma Exacerbations: Study 051-032 .......................................................... 60 Figure 10. Asthma-related TEAEs: Studies 051-032, 051-033, 051-359....................... 62 Figure 11. Post-dose Serum Potassium: Study 051-032............................................... 64 Figure 12. Post-dose Serum Potassium: Study 051-359............................................... 64 Figure 13. Post-dose Serum Glucose: Study 051-359 .................................................. 65 Figure 14. Heart Rate 20 minutes Post-dose: Study 051-032 ....................................... 66 Figure 15. Heart Rate 15-30 minutes Post-dose: Study 051-359 .................................. 66 Figure 16. Systolic and Diastolic Blood Pressure 20 minutes Post</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table of Contents 1 RECOMMENDATIONS/RISK</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table of Tables</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Table 1. Products Available for Treatment of Bronchospasm ......................................... 8 Table 2. Financial Disclosure Checklist......................................................................... 11 Table 3. Sources of Clinical Data .................................................................................. 14 Table 4. Schedule of Assessments: Study 051-032 ...................................................... 16 Table 5. Disallowed Medications: Study 051-032.......................................................... 18 Table 6. Concomitant Medications: Study 051-032 ....................................................... 18 Table 7. Schedule of Assessments: 051-033 ................................................................ 23 Table 8. Disallowed Medications: Study 051-033.......................................................... 25 Table 9. Concomitant Medications: Study 051-033 ....................................................... 25 Table 10. Schedule of Assessments: Study 091-029 .................................................... 30 Table 11. Disallowed Medications: Study 091-029........................................................ 32 Table 12. Concomitant Medications: Study 091-029 ..................................................... 33 Table 13. Schedule of Assessments: Study 051-359 .................................................... 36 Table 14. Disallowed Medications: Study 051-359........................................................ 38 Table 15. Pediatric Asthma Caregiver Assessments (PACA) ....................................... 40 Table 16. Schedule of Assessments: Study 051-SRC038 ............................................ 43 Table 17. Subject Demographics of ITT Population: Studies 051-032 and 051-033 ..... 46 Table 18. Disposition of Subjects: Studies 051-032 and 051-033 ................................. 47 Table 19. PAQ Total Score Results: Study 051-032 ..................................................... 49 Table 20. Maximum Decrease from Baseline RSS Total Score: Study 051-033 ........... 50 Table 21. Demographics of Overall Exposure............................................................... 52 Table 22. Extent of Exposure ........................................................................................ 53 Table 23. Nonfatal Serious Adverse Events.................................................................. 55 Table 24. Subject Discontinuations due to AEs by Study and Treatment Group........... 59 Table 25. Asthma Exacerbations and Treatment Discontinuations: Study 051-033 ...... 61 Table 26. Asthma-related TEAEs and Treatment Discontinuations: Study 051-359 ..... 61 Table 27. Common TEAEs by Study and Treatment .................................................... 62 5</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell></row><row><cell>Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table of Figures</head><label>of</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>-dose: Study 051-032 ...................................................................................................................................... 67 6</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell></row><row><cell>Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 2 . Financial Disclosure Checklist</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="4">trials referenced in this sNDA disclosed receiving significant financial compensation</cell></row><row><cell>from Sunovion. One sub-investigator for Study</cell><cell>(b) (6)</cell><cell>(b) (6)</cell><cell>reported</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">receiving a consultation fee of &gt;$25,000 after study initiation. To ensure full compliance</cell></row><row><cell>Was a list of clinical investigators provided: Yes</cell><cell>No</cell><cell cols="2">(Request list from</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>5 Sources of Clinical Data 5.1 Tables of Studies/Clinical Trials As</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell></row><row><cell>Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>(4)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note>previously agreed upon, the Applicant submitted data from five clinical trials in patients under 6 years of age to fulfill PREA. An overview of the trials are provided in the table below. 13</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Levalbuterol 0.31 mg: (R)-albuterol HCl Ampule Inhalation Solution, 0.0105% (w/v), 0.312 mg/3 mL in 0.9% saline o Racemic albuterol 1.25 mg (&lt;33 lbs) or 2.5 mg (≥33 lbs): (R,S)-albuterol HCl</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell></row><row><cell>Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>o</cell></row><row><cell>Adverse event</cell></row><row><cell>o Intercurrent illness</cell></row><row><cell>o Protocol violation</cell></row><row><cell>o Use of disallowed medications</cell></row><row><cell>o Administrative reasons</cell></row><row><cell>o Withdrawal of consent</cell></row><row><cell>17</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>117 subjects were randomized: 42 to low dose Lev IS, 40 to high dose Lev IS, and 35 to racemic albuterol.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD Stacy Chin, MD</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041 sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>Study Population Sites 12 clinical study sites in the U.S.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>IND A total of Key Inclusion Criteria 55,302 IRB (Site)</cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1. Males or females from birth to 48 months of age (inclusive) at the time of</cell></row><row><cell>informed consent</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2. At least one previous episode of acute bronchospasm or previous history of</cell></row><row><cell>reactive airway disease</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">3. Oxygen saturation ≥90% at room air or ≤2 L/min supplemental oxygen</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">4. Section III Respiratory Status Scale total score ≥5</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">5. Good health with the exception of acute reactive airway disease</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6. For participation in Periods II/III, subjects must have required further dosing after</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">completion of Period I (at the discretion of the investigator)</cell></row><row><cell>Key Exclusion Criteria</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1. Prematurity (born at ≤32 weeks gestational age) or chronic lung disease of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">prematurity and/or required supplemental oxygen for ≥28 days after birth</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">2. Concurrently required use of supplemental oxygen</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">3. History of airway obstruction that required intubation, associated with</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">hypercapnia, respiratory arrest, or hypoxic seizures within 12 months prior to</cell></row><row><cell>Visit 1</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">4. Disallowed medication use or expected use during the trial</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">5. Clinically significant abnormalities that could interfere with metabolism or</cell></row><row><cell>excretion of study drug</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6. History of cystic fibrosis, bronchopulmonary dysplasia, bronchopulmonary</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">aspergillosis or any form of allergic alveolitis</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7. Clinically significant 12-lead ECG abnormality</cell></row><row><cell>8. History of cancer</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>For Period II only</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">9. Development of a clinically significant purulent respiratory tract infection</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">10. Scheduled for in-patient hospitalization, including elective surgery, during the</cell></row><row><cell>course of the trial</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Withdrawal Criteria</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Subjects may have been discontinued for any of the following reasons:</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">o Life-threatening event precluding compliance with the protocol</cell></row><row><cell>o Withdrawal of consent</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Hospital admission</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Adverse event</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Intercurrent illness</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Protocol violation</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Use of disallowed medications</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>o Administrative reasons</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 11 . Disallowed Medications: Study 091-029</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Module 5.3.5.4, Study 091-029 CSR, Table 9.4.7.1-1, p33</cell></row><row><cell>32</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The following concomitant medications were allowed at the investigator's discretion if the dose had been stable for the month prior to Visit 1 (if applicable): leukotriene inhibitors, inhaled or nasal corticosteroids, topical corticosteroids, mucolytics and expectorants, antihistamines, immunotherapy, antibiotics, and other medications to treat chronic conditions.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Stacy Chin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>sNDA 20-837/S-041</cell></row><row><cell>Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</cell></row><row><cell>Treatments/Dose Rationale</cell></row><row><cell>The study included three treatment groups:</cell></row><row><cell>o Levalbuterol HFA 45mcg or 90 mcg (1-2 actuations) TID</cell></row><row><cell>o Levalbuterol IS 0.31 mg TID</cell></row><row><cell>o Placebo MDI (1-2 actuations) TID</cell></row><row><cell>The MDI dose was based on age: subjects 0 to 23 months received 1 actuation (45 mcg</cell></row><row><cell>levalbuterol) TID while subjects 24 to 47 months received 2 actuations (90 mcg</cell></row><row><cell>levalbuterol) TID. Although the MDI treatment arms were double-blind, the Lev IS</cell></row><row><cell>treatment arm was open-label with the same 0.31 mg dose administered regardless of</cell></row><row><cell>age.</cell></row><row><cell>Main Exclusion Criteria</cell></row><row><cell>1. Requires or may require disallowed medications</cell></row><row><cell>2. History of hospitalization for asthma, reactive airway disease, or bronchospasm</cell></row><row><cell>within 4 weeks prior to Visit 1 or scheduled in-patient hospitalization, including</cell></row><row><cell>elective surgery, during the study period</cell></row><row><cell>3. Clinical diagnosis of cystic fibrosis</cell></row><row><cell>4. Premature birth, defined as less than 38 weeks gestational birth and under 1</cell></row><row><cell>year of age at Visit 1</cell></row><row><cell>37</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 16 . Schedule of Assessments: Study 051-SRC038</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Module 5.3.5.1, Study 051-SRC038 CSR, Table 9.5.1.1-1, p24</cell></row><row><cell>Study Population</cell></row><row><cell>A total of 483 patients were enrolled in the study; randomization was stratified by age</cell></row><row><cell>(&lt;6 years, ≥6 years). Of the patients under 6 years of age, 111 were randomized to Lev</cell></row><row><cell>IS and 102 to racemic albuterol.</cell></row><row><cell>Key Inclusion Criteria</cell></row><row><cell>1. Male or female between 2 and 17 years of age</cell></row><row><cell>2. History of physician-diagnosed asthma or reactive airway disease and presenting</cell></row><row><cell>to the pediatric ED at Rainbow Babies &amp; Children's Hospital for treatment of</cell></row><row><cell>acute asthma</cell></row><row><cell>Key Exclusion Criteria</cell></row><row><cell>1. Chronic disease such as cystic fibrosis, cyanotic or uncorrected congenital heart</cell></row><row><cell>disease, active bronchopulmonary dysplasia, or chronic obstructive pulmonary</cell></row><row><cell>disease</cell></row><row><cell>2. Pregnancy</cell></row><row><cell>3. Sensitivity to racemic albuterol</cell></row><row><cell>Withdrawal Criteria</cell></row><row><cell>Subjects were withdrawn from the study for any of the following reasons:</cell></row><row><cell>o Protocol violation</cell></row><row><cell>o Administrative reasons</cell></row><row><cell>o Investigator decision</cell></row><row><cell>o Withdrawal of consent</cell></row><row><cell>o Admission to PICU, ward, or other facility</cell></row><row><cell>43</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3676286</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 19 . PAQ Total Score Results: Study 051-032</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Medical Officer Review of NDA 20-837, Supplement 011 by Howard Birenbaum, MD (February</cell></row><row><cell>25, 2003)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 20 . Maximum Decrease from Baseline RSS Total Score: Study 051-033</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">Maximum Decrease RSS</cell><cell cols="3">Difference Between Treatments (P-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(N)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Value)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>LL</cell><cell>HL</cell><cell>RA</cell><cell>HL -LL</cell><cell>HL -RA</cell><cell>LL -RA</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">5.3 (42) 4.1 (40) 5.3 (35) 1.1 (0.0127) 1.2 (0.0102) 0.1 (0.8467)</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Source: Biometrics Review by Dr. Robert Abugov</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">6.1.5 Analysis of Secondary Endpoints(s)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3676286</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Review</head><p>Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution discontinued from the study due to receiving disallowed medications (prednisone) during the hospitalization.</p><p>Subject 0060/S008 (Lev IS 0.31 mg): This was a 43-month old male with history of recurrent otitis media, food allergy, allergic rhinitis, and asthma. Concomitant <ref type="bibr">(b) (4)</ref> medications included montelukast but not an inhaled corticosteroid. On Day , he presented to the ED with an acute asthma exacerbation with fever and hypoxia (94% on room air) and found to have bi-basilar pneumonia on chest x-ray. Due to continued hypoxia despite continuous nebulization treatments in the ED, he was hospitalized for</p><p>further treatment. He was discharged days later, and these events led to discontinuation from the study.</p><p>Subject 0065/S001 (Lev IS 0.31 mg): This was a 37-month-old female with history of (b) (4) recurrent otitis media, recurrent UTI, GERD, and asthma. On Day , she developed an</p><p>E.coli UTI of moderate intensity that was treated with Bactrim. On Day , she presented to the ED with persistent fever and ill appearance; a clean-catch urine culture revealed E.coli resistant to Bactrim. She was hospitalized for treatment of her UTI, and discharged</p><p>days later once afebrile. She received her last dose of study medication on Day and completed the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject 0060/S041 (Lev HFA):</head><p>This was an 18-month-old female with a history of asthma, RSV infection, GERD, and pneumonia on concomitant inhaled corticosteroid</p><p>therapy. On Day she experienced fever, respiratory distress, cough, post-tussive emesis, and decreased activity/alertness. She was hospitalized for treatment of status asthmaticus with hypoxia (92% on room air) secondary to a meta-pneumovirus infection. A chest x-ray showing perihilar and peribronchiolar infiltrates was consistent with her diagnosis. No action was taken with the study medication due to the SAEs; however, she was discontinued from the study due to receiving disallowed medications (prednisolone) during the hospitalization.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.3">Dropouts and/or Discontinuations</head><p>The number of subjects who discontinued study medication early due to an adverse event are displayed in the table below. None of the subjects under 6 years of age in Studies 091-029 and 051-SRC038 discontinued study medication due to an adverse event; thus these studies are not included in the table below. Also, note that the Lev HFA treatment group from Study 051-359 is not displayed in the table due to space considerations. However, this study is reviewed in detail under NDA 21-730, supplement 36.</p><p>A reviewer analysis of the Applicant's datasets did not reveal any additional adverse dropouts. Although the numbers are small, there appears to be more adverse drop-outs in the Lev IS treatment groups across studies when compared to the control groups.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>58</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution smaller number of patients receiving higher Lev IS doses may have blunted any apparent dose response.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.2">Time Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>As mentioned previously regarding tachyphylaxis and paradoxical bronchospasm, the risk for experiencing an asthma-related TEAE was higher for subjects enrolled in chronic dosing studies of 3-4 weeks duration. Although only 12 subjects less than 6 years of age were treated in Study 091-029, there were few adverse events reported following cumulative dosing with Lev IS over the course of 1 hour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.3">Drug-Demographic Interactions</head><p>There were no apparent drug-demographic interactions based on subgroup analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.4">Drug-Disease Interactions</head><p>There was no assessment of drug-disease interactions in this submission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.5">Drug-Drug Interactions</head><p>No drug-drug interaction studies were included in this submission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6">Additional Safety Evaluations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.1">Human Carcinogenicity</head><p>No carcinogenicity studies were included in this submission. Levalbuterol has demonstrated no carcinogenic potential in nonclinical studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.2">Human Reproduction and Pregnancy Data</head><p>The use of levalbuterol hydrochloride during pregnancy and lactation has not been evaluated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.6.3">Pediatrics and Assessment of Effects on Growth</head><p>No growth studies were included in this submission as no growth effects are known to occur with the use of levalbuterol hydrochloride.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>68</head><p>Reference ID: 3676286</p><p>Clinical Review Stacy Chin, MD sNDA 20-837/S-041 Xopenex (levalbuterol HCl) Inhalation Solution</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Labeling Recommendations</head><p>At the time of this review, labeling discussions between the Applicant and the Agency were ongoing. Major labeling recommendations include updating Section 8.4 with efficacy and safety data for pediatric patients &lt;6 years of age, specifically with information regarding the increased number of asthma-related adverse reactions in the Xopenex treatment groups. The Office of Prescription Drug Promotion (OPDP) and the Division of Medical Policy Programs (DMPP) had no further recommendations following review of the revised label and package insert.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3">Advisory Committee Meeting</head><p>An Advisory Committee Meeting was not held for this supplemental NDA. Xopenex Inhalation Solution is already approved for the treatment or prevention of bronchospasm in adults, adolescents, and children 6 years of age and older with reversible obstructive airway disease, and the Applicant is not seeking to expand the indication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>71</head><p>Reference <ref type="figure">ID: 3676286   ------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>----------------------------------------------------This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
