<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 210303Orig1s000 CLINICAL REVIEW(S)</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date>Review Completion Date 6/13/2018</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 210303Orig1s000 CLINICAL REVIEW(S)</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">Review Completion Date 6/13/2018</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note type="submission">Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs CLINICAL REVIEW</note>
					<note>NDA 210303/Clinical Review Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection CDER Clinical Review Template 1 Division/Office Division of Anti-Infective Products (DAIP)/Office of Antimicrobial Products (OAP) Reviewer Name Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
				<date type="submission" when="210303" />
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The Applicant has proposed a dosing regimen in cUTI adjusted according to renal function and serum trough concentrations. For those with normal renal function, the initial dose is 15 mg/kg daily. For BSI, the applicant is again proposing an initial dose of 15 mg/kg daily for those with normal renal function, and this will be adjusted according to a therapeutic drug management (TDM) algorithm that takes into account periodic measured serum concentrations of plazomicin.</p><p>The drug is a semi-synthetic new molecular entity (NME) although it is part of the wellrecognized aminoglycoside antimicrobial class.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Conclusions on the Substantial Evidence of Effectiveness</head><p>See text below in Benefit-Risk Assessment 1.3. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-Risk Assessment</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-Risk Integrated Assessment</head><p>Plazomicin is a semi-synthetic aminoglycoside that brings promise of a new therapy to treat serious infectious diseases. Its clinical development includes a randomized, comparator controlled phase 2 and 3 cUTI trial and a small, randomized, open label phase 3 trial targeting CRE-associated bloodstream and HABP/VABP infections. For both indications, subjects with limited treatment alternatives are targeted. The cUTI data provides compelling evidence of noninferiority to a commonly used comparator (meropenem in the phase 3 trial) on accepted primary endpoints such as composite microbiologic eradication and clinical response at Day 5 and at TOC. Plazomicin's effect seems adequate even with resistant pathogens such as those resistant to one or more aminoglycosides and organisms containing extended spectrum betalactamases. The safety database, though small, identifies expected risks of an aminoglycoside, such as nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity, as well as more general adverse effects seen often in drug development trials, such as headaches, nausea, and vomiting. Serum plazomicin trough monitoring should be used to prevent nephrotoxicity; currently a plasma trough level of 3 mcg/ml has been set. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Therapeutic Context</head><p> Analysis of Condi cUTI generally involves a urinary tract infection in the setting of some other physical or functional deficit that predisposes to the development of infection. Such predisposing factors might include an indwelling catheter, renal calculi, vesicoureteral reflux, or diabetes. Subjects generally can be of any age or gender and typically have some combination of urinary symptoms along with urine culture data showing the growth of the offending pathogen. Untreated, the infection may progress to more severe complications such as abscess development, metastatic infection, sepsis, or even death. Pathogens tend to be more varied than in uncomplicated UTI and consist of gram-negative organisms such as Escherichia coli (E. coli), Klebsiella pneumoniae (KP), Enterobacter species, Proteus species, etc. Many of these organisms are acquired in health care facilities and carry significant resistance mechanisms to currently used antimicrobials. Broad spectrum antimicrobials (either intravenous or oral depending on the clinical status of the patient) such as fluoroquinolones, carbapenems, beta lactam-beta lactamase inhibitors are generally used empirically to start treatment and then adjusted once susceptibilities are known. Treatment is anywhere between 7-10 days.</p><p>Acute pyelonephritis is a severe urinary tract infection in which the upper urinary tract has been affected. Patients, which can include young females as well as older adults, generally have some combination of systemic and localized symptoms, including flank pain, and also have corresponding microbiological data on urine culture. As with cUTI, the natural history of AP is unknown (particularly as regards self-resolution), however, bacteremia, sepsis, and death are possible complications. Typical pathogens are gram-negative bacilli, particularly E. coli. Therapy typically involves supportive measures such as fluid resuscitation as well as antimicrobial therapy for ~7 days. The choice of therapy is dependent on factors such as patient status and possibility of resistance and includes fluoroquinolones, trimethoprimsulfamethoxazole (TMP-SMX), aminoglycosides, and extended spectrum cephalosporins. Initial intravenous therapy is recommended for those unable to tolerate oral medications and with unstable medical status.</p><p>BSI is a condition associated with another source of infection such as central line or hospital acquired pneumonia/ventilator-associated pneumonia. It is generally a serious condition (occurring often in subjects in the ICU) and can lead to sepsis, metastatic infection, and death. Numerous gram-positive and negative organisms can be the cause, and treatment generally includes 7 to 14 days of broad spectrum therapy which is narrowed based on susceptibilities It should be noted that though these indications are being discussed here broadly, the Applicant plans to pursue a limited use indication, essentially restricting use to patients with limited or no treatment alternatives. In practice, this means primarily targeting subjects with highly resistant organisms or intolerant of available therapies. These highly resistant organisms include Carbapenem Resistant Enterobacteriaceae (CRE) and gram-negative organisms containing Extended Spectrum Beta Lactamases (ESBL); these organisms tend to simultaneously carry resistance to multiple therapeutics. In the case of CRE, though currently more prevalent overseas, such as in locations in Greece, numerous cases in the US have been reported (particularly Klebsiella pneumoniae Carbapenemase (KPC) producing organisms), and are rapidly becoming more prevalent domestically. These organisms not only increase the chance for inappropriate initial treatment but also limit treatment to medications with significant toxicity profiles, such as colistin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Analysis of Current Treatment Options</head><p>As noted above, given the limited use indication of this drug, its comparators primarily include drugs that are expected to still retain an effect on highly-resistant gram-negative organisms, such as ESBL-containing organisms and CREs. Thus, such comparators include the carbapenems, other aminoglycosides such as amikacin and gentamicin, colistin, tigecycline, as well as recently approved combination agents such as ceftazidime/avibactam and meropenem/vaborbactam. These comparators are only partially able to meet the need of affected subjects. They can be affected by shortages and thus have limited availability. They may be bacteriostatic, such as in the case of tigecycline, or may have uncertain efficacy benefit, such as in the case of colistin treatment for CRE infection. Importantly, as in the case of colistin-induced nephrotoxicity, they may have significant adverse effects that limit use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Regulatory Background</head><p>3.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U.S. Regulatory Actions and Marketing History</head><p>Plazomicin is an NME and it is not currently marketed in the US. December 12, 2014: Qualified Infectious Disease Product (QIDP) designation was granted for the indications of hospital-acquired bacterial pneumonia (HABP), ventilator-associated bacterial pneumonia (VABP), complicated intra-abdominal infections (cIAIs), cUTI, and catheter-related BSI.</p><p>February 26, 2015: A Type A Clinical Development Meeting was held between the Applicant and the Agency. The Applicant discussed use of a new primary endpoint for Study 007, based on a composite of all-cause mortality or significant disease-related complications. The applicant and the Agency also discussed April 28, 2015: Protocol Amendment 1 for Study 007 was submitted to the Agency. This amendment changed the primary efficacy endpoint from all-cause mortality to the composite of all-cause mortality or significant disease-related complications. The definition of significant disease-related complications had been previously proposed by the applicant, and feedback from the Agency had been received. The amendment did not change the planned sample size or planned superiority test at the one-sided α = 0.05 statistical significance level for the primary efficacy analysis.</p><p>May 15, 2015: The applicant submitted a protocol for the Phase 3 cUTI noninferiority Study ACHN-490-009 (Study 009) to the Agency.</p><p>July 15, 2015: Protocol Amendment 2 for Study 007 was submitted to the Agency with a request for comment, adding the nonrandomized, descriptively analyzed Cohort 2 of plazomicin-treated patients. These patients were ineligible for the randomized Cohort 1 due to resistance to the colistin comparator, polymicrobial infection, cUTI as the source of CRE infection, or APACHE II score &lt;15.</p><p>January 11, 2016: The Phase 3 cUTI Study 009 was initiated.</p><p>March 4, 2016: A Type A Clinical Development Meeting was held between the applicant and the Agency. The applicant discussed enrollment challenges in Study 007. The Applicant stated that "current enrollment projections suggest that the study will be unable to achieve the originally planned enrollment for an adequately powered test of the primary endpoint in a clinically meaningful or operationally feasible timeframe." The Applicant discussed the possibility of changing the primary analysis to a noninferiority analysis,  September 30, 2016: The Applicant submitted a statistical analysis plan for Study 007, which as noted above had completed enrollment. Due to the premature study termination, the hypothesis testing for superiority was removed from the primary efficacy analysis. The Applicant communicated that "While the protocol-specified primary and secondary efficacy endpoints will be analyzed and traditional statistical inference measures such as p-values and/or confidence intervals will be included for descriptive purposes, no formal hypothesis testing is to be performed in this limited sample size."</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">Reference ID: 4282865 (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4)</formula><p>March 29, 2017: The Applicant submitted a Breakthrough Therapy Designation Request for plazomicin for the treatment of bloodstream infection in patients with limited or no alternative treatment options. The request was granted by the Agency on May 17, 2017.</p><p>April 14, 2017: A pre-NDA meeting was held between the Applicant and the Agency. The Applicant notified the Agency that due to the small number of patients with HABP/VABP in Study 007 that it was considering only using this study to support a BSI indication rather than both BSI and HABP/VABP indications.</p><p>October 25, 2017: The Applicant submitted the New Drug Application.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Foreign Regulatory Actions and Marketing History</head><p>[Not Applicable-the drug has no approved foreign marketing application] </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Significant Issues from Other Review Disciplines Pertinent to Clinical</head><p>Conclusions on Efficacy and Safety 4.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Office of Scientific Investigations (OSI)</head><p>was Inspected by OSI and no data integrity issues for plazomicin measurements were noted for Study 002 and 009. However, there was concern that a "carryover" effect may overestimate serum concentration measurement and complicate TDM.</p><p>Inspection of clinical sites in Poland, Hungary, Estonia, and Greece have concluded; the sites were found to be acceptable. OSI's conclusions are as follows:</p><p>"Studies ACHN-490-007 and ACHN-490-009 were identified for on-site audit at good clinical practice (GCP) inspections of four foreign clinical investigator (CI) sites and the sponsor site. A Form FDA 483 was issued at Site 6801 <ref type="bibr">(CI Michal Nowicki)</ref> in Study ACHN-490-009 for minor GCP deficiencies unlikely to be significant to the study outcome. For all remaining sites, no significant deficiencies were observed and a Form FDA 483 was not issued. For both studies at all inspected sites, study conduct appeared adequately GCP-compliant, including sponsor oversight of study conduct. All audited data were acceptably verifiable against source records and case report forms (CRFs). The data from the inspected sites appear reliable as reported in the NDA."</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Product Quality</head><p>The CMC assessment is as follows:</p><p>"The NDA, as amended, has provided sufficient CMC information to assure the identity, strength, purity, and quality of the proposed drug product, plazomicin injection. All information requests and review issues have been addressed and there are no pending approvability issues. The manufacturing and testing facilities for this NDA are deemed acceptable as documented in the Facility Chapter <ref type="bibr">(dated May 17, 2018)</ref>. The overall manufacturing inspection recommendation in Panorama is still pending however, this inspection recommendation does not impact the NDA recommendation. Based on the above assessments, this NDA is currently recommended for Approval by the Office of Pharmaceutical Quality (OPQ).</p><p>Reference ID: 4282865 The drug product is supplied as a 10-mL sterile, aqueous solution for intravenous infusion, containing 500 mg of plazomicin in a single-dose vial with a rubber stopper and a flip top cap.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4)</formula><p>The only excipients in the formulation are sodium hydroxide, NF and Water for Injection, USP, which are both compendial. There are no novel excipients or excipients of human or animal origin in the drug product formulation.</p><p>For the most part the analytical methods are compendial.</p><p>. The HPLC method for assay and impurities is described in reasonable detail and has been validated. The HPLC method was verified by an FDA laboratory and found to be acceptable. Satisfactory batch analysis data are provided for 13 batches including three primary registration stability batches. A risk assessment has been performed for elemental impurities following the recommendations of ICH Q3D.</p><p>The drug product plazomicin sulfate in water for injection, with sodium hydroxide used to adjust the pH of the solution to a target of 6.5. Production of plazomicin injection, 500 mg/10 mL, Stability data has been provided for drug product to support stability out to 36 months (2°-8°C). Please see the review by Dr. Dorota Matecka, CMC Team Leader, for further details.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Clinical Microbiology/Nonclinical Pharmacology Toxicology Clinical Microbiology</head><p>Plazomicin is an aminoglycoside antibacterial drug with in vitro activity against certain gramnegative and gram-positive bacteria. Plazomicin contains structural modifications that allow it to maintain activity in the presence of the common aminoglycoside modifying enzymes (AMEs) that inactivate some currently marketed agents in this class. Mechanism of action studies demonstrated that, as with other aminoglycosides, the antibacterial action of plazomicin is mediated through inhibition of protein synthesis. In surveillance studies, plazomicin was active against Enterobacteriaceae, including isolates encoding common resistance mechanisms conferring resistance to other aminoglycosides, as well as organisms with ESBL and/or carbapenem-resistant phenotypes. The drug is not active against the 16S RNA methyltransferase mechanism of aminoglycoside resistance.</p><p>Pharmacokinetic/pharmacodynamic data derived from in vivo animal models and an in vitro chemostat model was used to determine that the ratio of the total-drug plasma area under the concentration-time curve from 0 to 24 hours (AUC0-24h) to minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), [(AUC0-24h:MIC)], was the PK/PD index most closely associated with plazomicin efficacy.</p><p>In Study 009, emergence of decreased plazomicin susceptibility occurred in 7 isolates from 6 plazomicin-treated patients and decreased meropenem susceptibility in one isolate from 1 meropenem-treated patient during the study. Among the 7 isolates that developed decreased susceptibility to plazomicin, all 7 were considered resistant based on the resistance breakpoint of &gt;4 mcg/mL. Of the isolates, 6 contained panresistance to amikacin, tobramycin, and gentamicin while one isolate maintained susceptibility to gentamicin and was intermediate to tobramycin and amikacin Five of the 7 isolates with decreased plazomicin susceptibility were obtained on or before the EOIV visit; the remaining 2 were detected at the TOC and LFU, after demonstrating eradication at the EOIV visit. All patients with a uropathogen(s) that developed decreased susceptibility to plazomicin were clinical cures at the Day 5 and EOIV visits. Two patients were clinical failure at TOC, of which both had E. cloacae as the baseline infecting pathogen:</p><p>-Patient had unresolved frequency that met the programmatic definition for clinical failure and was not treated with nonstudy antibacterial drugs -Patient was treated with nonstudy antibacterial drugs prior to the TOC visit.</p><p>Of the 6 plazomicin treated subjects who possessed isolates with decreased susceptibility, in 4 of them 16S RMT mechanisms of resistance were detected (though other resistance mechanisms may have also been present).</p><p>Reference ID: 4282865 </p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (4)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_3">Enterobacter cloacae 2 (1.0) 0 (0.0) Escherichia coli 1 (0.5) 1 (0.5) Klebsiella pneumoniae 3 (1.6) 0 (0.0) Proteus mirabilis 1 (0.5) 0 (0.0) Patients with Resistance b 6 (3.1) 1 (0.5) Enterobacter cloacae 2 (1.0) 0 (0.0) Escherichia coli 1 (0.5) 1 (0.5) Klebsiella pneumoniae 3 (1.6) 0 (0.0)</formula><p>Proteus mirabilis 1 (0.5) 0 (0.0) MIC=minimum inhibitory concentration; mMITT=microbiological modified intent-to-treat; N=number of patients in the specified population; n=number of patients with a uropathogen in the specified category.</p><p>Notes: Percentages are calculated as 100×(n/N). Patients with &gt;1 of the same uropathogen within each type of uropathogen were counted once for that uropathogen. a Decreased susceptibility is defined as a postbaseline MIC &gt;4 µg/mL and a ≥4-fold increase in MIC relative to that of the baseline pathogen. b Development of resistance to plazomicin is defined as postbaseline nonsusceptibility to plazomicin (i.e., MIC &gt;4 mcg/mL) in pathogens susceptible to plazomicin (i.e., MIC ≥4 mcg/mL) at baseline; development of resistance to meropenem will be defined as postbaseline nonsusceptibility to meropenem (i.e., MIC &gt;1 mcg/mL) in pathogens susceptible to meropenem (i.e., MIC ≤1 mcg/mL) at baseline. Source: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Pharmacology</head><p>The Clinical Pharmacology issues were broad and required significant internal/external discussion. Some of the central issues involved the following:</p><p>1.</p><p>2. Serum trough monitoring is used with aminoglycosides to prevent toxicity (particularly nephrotoxicity). The Clinical Pharmacology review team has concluded that a serum plazomicin trough of ≥3 mcg/ml is associated with the development of nephrotoxicity in subjects being treated for cUTI with a baseline creatinine clearance ≤90 ml/min. This value was based on modeling done with serum PK measurements from Study 009 (since trough monitoring was not done in the trial itself). Adjustments made due to trough measurements would involve changes to dosing intervals.</p><p>Please see the reviews of Drs. Kunyi Wu and Luning Zhang for further details Plazomicin has a half-life of 4 to 5 hours in cUTI and BSI patients, and does not accumulate with once-daily dosing in healthy subjects. Plazomicin clearance (CL) was 4.08 L/h and the volume of distribution at steady-state (Vss) was 24.0 L in healthy subjects. The Vss tended to be larger in cUTI/AP patients (31.5 L) and larger still in BSI patients (52.9 L). In patients, CL was typically within 35% of healthy subjects. The mean binding of plazomicin to human plasma proteins is approximately 20%, ranging between 13.9% and 24.2%. Unchanged plazomicin was the only plazomicin-related component detected in any of the pooled clinical plasma samples analyzed by high-resolution mass spectrometry, indicating no significant circulating metabolites of plazomicin in human (this was confirmed by the mass balance study; Study 010). Plazomicin is primarily eliminated by the kidneys. Approximately 90% of administered plazomicin is excreted in urine following a single dose of 15 mg/kg in subjects with normal renal function. The renal clearance of plazomicin was similar to plasma clearance and similar to the glomerular filtration No dosage adjustment is required in patients with CLcr &gt;60 mL/min based on results from a dedicated renal impairment study and the population PK analysis. Dosage adjustment is required in patients with moderate renal impairment (CLcr &gt;30 to 60 mL/min), as plasma clearance of plazomicin significantly decreases with increasing renal impairment. Dosing in those with severe renal impairment (≤30 ml/min) is based on information obtained from the dedicated renal impairment study (Study 004); very few such subjects were enrolled in the Studies 002 and 009.</p><p>No dosage adjustment is required on the basis of age, sex, race, or infection type based on the population PK analysis. Plazomicin does not undergo hepatic metabolism and has low plasma protein binding; therefore, the systemic clearance of plazomicin is not expected to be affected by hepatic impairment.</p><p>Plazomicin is considered unlikely to have significant clinical drug interactions. In vitro data show that plazomicin is not a substrate of P-glycoprotein (P-gp) or breast cancer resistance protein (BCRP) transporters. In addition, as plazomicin is mostly excreted as unchanged drug in urine, metabolism by any of the major drug-metabolizing enzymes is considered to be unlikely. Based on in vitro assessments, plazomicin is unlikely to be an in vivo inhibitor of the following CYP450 enzymes: CYP1A2, CYP2B6, CYP2C8, CYP2C9, CYP2C19, CYP2D6, or CYP3A4/5. Plazomicin is unlikely to be an in vivo inducer of CYP1A2, CYP2B6, or CYP3A4. In addition, plazomicin is unlikely to be an in vivo inhibitor of the following hepatic and renal transporters: P-gp, BCRP, bile salt export pump, multidrug resistance protein 2, organic anion-transporting polypeptide (OATP) 1B1, OATP1B3, organic anion transporter (OAT) 1, OAT3, organic cation transporter (OCT) 1, OCT2, or multidrug and toxin extrusion (MATE) 1. Plazomicin selectively inhibited MATE2-K in vitro, and the potential for clinical interactions cannot be completely excluded. However, a clinical DDI study with a MATE substrate (metformin) did not appear to show any clinically relevant drug-drug interaction with plazomicin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Devices and Companion Diagnostic Issues</head><p>Effectively, this TDM was expected to minimize overdosing (thus minimizing toxicity) and minimize underdosing (thus ensuring therapeutic effect). Currently the applicant is developing the to-be-marketed plazomicin assay with another company, Thermo Fisher.</p><p>Reference ID: 4282865 Please note also that the applicant is proposing plazomicin trough monitoring for cUTI in order to minimize the development of nephrotoxicity. No formal trough monitoring was done in study 009, but the applicant submitted post-hoc analyses (based on population modeling using PK data from Study 009) to show the potential merits of setting plazomicin trough cutoffs in reducing nephrotoxicity. Clinical Pharmacology has proposed a plazomicin trough cutoff level of 3 µg/ml for TDM-based dosing interval adjustments (based on their own analyses).</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4)</formula><p>Please see the CDRH review by Dr. Eveline Arnold (Team Lead Dr. James Mullaly) for further details. 4.6. Consumer Study Reviews <ref type="bibr">[Not applicable]</ref>  -Six phase 1 type studies, including a PK study in healthy volunteers, TQT study, mass balance study, metformin drug interaction study, PK study in subjects with renal impairment, and lung penetration study (Studies 001, 003,004,006,010,011) -One phase 2 study in cUTI (Study 002)    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Sources of Clinical Data and Review Strategy</head><formula xml:id="formula_5">Reference ID: 4282865 (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2.">Review Strategy</head><p>For efficacy purposes, review emphasis was placed on the phase 3 studies (Study 007 and 009) and, to a lesser extent, the phase 2 study (Study 002). For safety purposes, Study 009 was given the most review emphasis, with some attention given to all the other clinical development studies, including the phase 1 studies. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overview and Objective</head><p>Note: This section combines many elements of the statistical review, sponsor analyses and this reviewer's analyses. Because the applicant is pursuing two indications, each section is generally divided into two sections -first the CRE BSI and HABP/VABP (Study 007) findings are described followed by the cUTI (Study 009) findings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 007</head><p>A Phase 3, Multicenter, Randomized, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Plazomicin Compared With Colistin in Patients With Infection Due to Carbapenem-Resistant Enterobacteriaceae (CRE). The primary objective for this study was to demonstrate the superiority of plazomicin over colistin (plus background therapy of either meropenem or tigecycline) in the treatment of BSI, HABP, and VABP due to CRE.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>A Phase 3, Randomized, Multicenter, Double-Blind Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Plazomicin Compared with Meropenem followed by Optional Oral Therapy for the Treatment of Complicated Urinary Tract Infection (cUTI), including Acute Pyelonephritis (AP), in Adults.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Trial Design</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 007</head><p>Study ACHN-490-007 was initiated in September 2014 and completed in September 2016. This was a randomized, multicenter, multinational, double-blind study evaluating the efficacy and safety of plazomicin compared with meropenem followed by optional oral (PO) therapy in the treatment of cUTI, including AP, in adults. In general, the study design was consistent with the guidance on cUTI. Upon meeting inclusion criteria, patients were randomized 1:1 into either receiving IV plazomicin 15 mg/kg daily or meropenem 1 gm every 8 hours (dosing was adjusted daily based on renal function). Subjects had to receive at least four days of IV therapy and no more than 7 days of IV therapy at which point they could be switched to oral levofloxacin 500mg daily for 3 to 6 days. The total treatment duration was 7 to 10 days. If a subject needed more than 7 days of IV therapy, the subject was discontinued from the study and switched to alternative IV therapy. All study doses were to be given as 30 minute infusions of a 50ml solution. A Test-of Cure assessment occurred on Day 17 (Day 1 was first day of study drug), and a Late Follow Up (LFU) visit occurred between Days 24-32. The dose for plazomicin chosen for this study was based on efficacy findings in the Phase 2 study, predicted concentrations in the urine (relative to expected pathogen MICs), as well as study 004 which helped assess plazomicin dosing in subjects with renal impairment. Though meropenem is not approved for treatment of cUTI in the US, the choice of meropenem at 1 gm q 8 hours as the comparator in this study was thought to be acceptable based on its spectrum of activity, particularly with resistant organisms such as ESBLs, its approval for use in this indication in Europe, its common use for this indication in the US, as well as ease of dosing and similarities to plazomicin dosing that facilitated blinding.</p><p>Renal function (based on creatinine clearance) was estimated daily and dose/dose interval adjustments made accordingly. Important exclusion criteria included GU conditions requiring prolonged treatment (such as abscess or chronic bacterial prostatitis), use of any therapeutic antibacterial agent within 48 hours of starting study drug (exceptions included if prior therapy was directed at gram positives or anaerobes only, organisms resistant to prior therapy, etc.), known fungal or gram positive UTI at time of randomization, known pathogen resistant to meropenem at time of randomization, known nonurinary source of infection, pregnant subjects, and an unwillingness to use appropriate contraceptive measures.</p><p>The primary objective of the study was to demonstrate the noninferiority (NI) of plazomicin compared with meropenem based on the difference in the composite microbiological eradication and clinical cure rate in the microbiological Modified Intent-To-Treat (mMITT) population at both the Day 5 and test-of-cure (TOC) visits, using a NI margin of 15%, at a onesided 0.025 significance level. Though this NI margin is larger than what is proposed in the Agency guidance on cUTI, it was deemed acceptable given the applicant's intent to pursue a limited use indication.</p><p>Premorbid symptoms (present on an ongoing basis prior to the current infection) and current urinary symptoms (present in the past 36 hours as the baseline for the current infection) status were documented at baseline according to assessments based on a patient's provided response (example in the table below).   Programmatic improvement in Clinical Response was designated as follows:</p><p>Post Baseline Symptom Response:   The coprimary efficacy endpoints were the composite microbiological eradication and programmatically derived clinical cure rate in the mMITT population at Day 5 and the TOC visit. To test the null hypothesis, a two-sided 95% CI for the observed difference in composite cure rates (plazomicin treatment group minus meropenem treatment group) for each timepoint was calculated using a continuity corrected Z-statistic for the mMITT population. If the lower limit of the 95% CI for the difference in composite cure rate in the mMITT population was greater than -15% at both Day 5 and the TOC visit, then the null hypothesis was to be rejected and the NI of plazomicin to meropenem would be declared. If the lower limit of the 95% CI for difference in composite cure rate in the mMITT population was less than or equal to ≤15% at either Day 5 or the TOC visit, then the null hypothesis was not to be rejected, and NI of plazomicin to meropenem could not be declared. The ITT population was considered as all randomized patients.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis Plan</head><p>The MITT population was considered as all randomized patients who received any amount of study drug.</p><p>The mMITT Population consisted of all patients in the ITT Population who received any amount of study drug and had at least one qualified baseline pathogen from a study-qualifying baseline urine culture against which meropenem and plazomicin have antibacterial activity, and no pathogens against which either meropenem or plazomicin do not have antibacterial activity. A study-qualifying baseline urine culture specimen must have been obtained within 36 hours before the start of administration of the first dose of study drug and have been collected by an acceptable method (which included midstream clean catch, sample taken after replacement of the indwelling catheter, sterile catheterization, sterile suprapubic aspiration, etc.). A qualified baseline pathogen was a pathogen that grew from a study-qualifying baseline urine culture at ≥ 10 5 CFU/mL and against which meropenem and plazomicin have antibacterial activity. For meropenem, only baseline pathogens with meropenem MIC of ≤1 μg/mL were considered qualifying baseline pathogens. For plazomicin, only baseline pathogens with an MIC of ≤4 μg/mL were considered qualifying, consistent with the tentative susceptibility breakpoint for plazomicin. Any patients with one or more pathogens confirmed from the last blood culture obtained prior to the first dose of study drug were defined as having bacteremia at baseline. All Enterobacteriaceae were considered pathogens, while all Pseudomonas aeruginosa, Acinetobacter species, Enterococcus species, fungi, and coagulase-negative staphylococcus species at baseline were not considered pathogens.</p><p>The Clinically Evaluable population (CE) must have met important key requirements including inclusion criteria, avoidance of prohibited concomitant antimicrobial therapy, and reception at least 3 days of IV therapy in case of cure.</p><p>The Safety Population included all randomized patients who received any amount of IV study drug. Only one protocol amendment occurred in Dec 2015 to allow for the inclusion of patients with moderate renal impairment, defined as a CLcr of &gt;30 to ≤60 mL/min as estimated by the Cockcroft-Gault equation. This change occurred after data were available from safety/PK Phase 1 study of plazomicin in subjects with renal impairment (Study 004).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2.">Study Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance with Good Clinical Practices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>The applicant declared that the study was conducted in accordance with the US Food and Drug Administration (FDA) regulations, the International Council on Harmonisation (ICH) E6 Guidelines for Good Clinical Practice (GCP), the Declaration of Helsinki <ref type="bibr">(October 1996)</ref>, and applicable local, state, and national laws.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Financial Disclosure</head><p>Reference ID: 4282865 For study 009, no financial interests were noted for all investigators and subinvestigators. One year follow-up disclosures for all investigators were submitted in May 2018. No new disclosures were noted, though several sub-investigators in site and one sub investigator in site were lost to follow up.</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(b) (4) (b) (4) (b)<label>(</label></formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Patient Disposition</head><p>Reference ID: 4282865  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>A total of 609 patients were randomized and included in the ITT Population: 306 randomized to plazomicin and 303 randomized to meropenem. In general, patient disposition was comparable between treatment groups. Approximately 97% of patients in both groups completed the LFU visit. The most common reason for withdrawal from the study was patient's withdrawal of consent (1.1%, overall) and loss to follow-up (0.7% overall). Less than 1% of patients (3 in the plazomicin group and 2 in the meropenem group) were randomized but not treated, which was also most frequently due to patient's withdrawal of consent. Almost 75% of subjects in each arm completed IV study drug. The vast majority of those who did not (roughly 20% in each arm), did so because of lack of a study qualifying culture at baseline. 1-2% of subjects discontinued IV study drug due to adverse events. There was very little discontinuation of the oral study drug (around 1% in each arm).  Three and two subjects did not receive study drug in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively, leaving an MITT population of 303 and 301 in those arms. Slightly over 100 subjects from each arm (112 and 104 from plazomicin and meropenem, respectively) were excluded from the mMITT population, almost overwhelmingly due to lack of a qualifying study pathogen (whether due to the pathogen itself or its resistance pattern). The mMITT population thus included 191 and 197 subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively. Relatively few exclusions occurred due to clinical and microbiological evaluability; plazomicin ME-Day 5 and ME-TOC populations were 188 and 179, respectively and meropenem ME -Day 5 and ME-TOC populations of 190 and 177, respectively. Almost all subjects (96%) were enrolled under the amended protocol.  </p><formula xml:id="formula_7">2 (0.7) 1 (0.3) 1 (0.3) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 4 (1.3) 2 (0.7) 1 (0.3) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 1 (0.3) 8 (1.3) 4 (0.7) 2 (0.3) 1 (0.2) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 0 (0) 1 (0.2) Completed</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protocol Violations/Deviations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>Roughly 40% and 30% of subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms (ITT Population), respectively were found to have protocol deviations. In the plazomicin arm, 17% of subjects had "Unblinded Issues" which constituted errors by unblinded personnel regarding dosing and dose preparation. This might be due to errors in weight calculations, creatinine clearance calculations, rounding errors, and errors in study drug reconstitution. Only 6% of subjects in the meropenem arm had similar errors, likely due to the relatively easy and familiar dosing regimen for this drug. 12% and 10% of subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively had a deviation related to timing of a study visit. The visit in question was usually the TOC visit though when using criteria set out in the SAP for when this visit should occur (had a slightly larger post Day 17 visit window than the protocol) then much fewer subjects were noted to have deviations (7 only). 9% and 6% of subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively had deviations related to continuing in the study despite not having a qualifying baseline urine culture, receiving a prolonged course of study drug (oral or IV or both), or being unblinded to treatment (3 such students in each arm). Other protocol deviations were small in number and essentially equivalent between both arms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Demographic Characteristics</head><p>Reference ID: 4282865 The majority of subjects in the mMITT population (roughly 60%) in each arm had cUTI (rather than AP) and were generally well balanced between treatment arms. The overwhelming majority of subjects (roughly 98%) in both arms came from Region 2 which primarily consisted of Eastern European countries and former Soviet Republics along with Russia. As concerns gender, while the meropenem arm was evenly split between the sexes, there were more females than males in the plazomicin arm. Virtually all enrolled subjects except 2 subjects were White. The mean age in both arms was around 60 years though the meropenem arm had slightly more subjects (relative to plazomicin) that were ≥65 years old. Interestingly, roughly 40% of subjects in each arm had a TBW/IBW ratio ≥125%; this had consequences in terms of plazomicin dosing and estimation of creatinine clearance. The mean creatinine clearance for both arms was around 75 mL/min. When looking at distribution by creatinine clearance, the two arms were generally evenly matched though the plazomicin arm had slightly more subjects with clearance &gt; 120 mL/min and the meropenem arm had slightly more subjects with clearance between 30 and 60 mL/min. Most subjects had monomicrobial infections, and slightly more than a quarter of patients in each arm were infected with ESBL pathogens. Importantly, only two subjects took an antimicrobial in the 48 hrs. prior to starting therapy.  The most common pathogens isolated at baseline were E. coli followed by K. pneumoniae. Roughly a fifth of the E. Coli were ESBLs whereas almost 2/3rds of the K. pneumoniae were ESBLs. Among Enterobacteriaceae from the baseline urine cultures in the mMITT population, the plazomicin MIC50 and MIC90 were 0.5 mcg/mL and 1 mcg/mL, respectively (range: 0.06 to 4 mcg/mL). The MIC50/90 for plazomicin against aminoglycoside-resistant and ESBL-producing Enterobacteriaceae were 0.25/2 mcg/mL and 0.25/0.5 mcg/mL.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatment Compliance, Concomitant Medications, and Rescue Medication Use</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>In the mMITT population, the mean duration of IV plus oral study drug therapy was 9.2 and 8.9 calendar days in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively. Only 6 mMITT patients (4 in meropenem and 2 in plazomicin) received &gt;12 calendar days of IV plus oral study drug Overall, 78.6% of patients switched to oral therapy. The proportion of patients who switched to oral therapy and the study day of oral switch was comparable across treatment arms. In general, the switch was made to levofloxacin.</p><p>Virtually all subjects (except 2) had not received any antibacterial drugs in the 48 hours prior to start of study drug.</p><p>In the mMITT population, the proportion of patients with any prior and/or concomitant systemic antibacterial medication (from 14 days prior to randomization to LFU) was low and was similar between the treatment groups (11 [5.8%] patients in the plazomicin group vs 12 1%] patients in the meropenem group). Quinolones were the most commonly used class of concomitant antibacterial drugs. The proportion of patients with any prior and/or concomitant medication other than systemic antibacterial medication was similar between treatment groups: 244 (80.5%) patients in the plazomicin group vs 240 (79.7%) patients in the meropenem group. In the Safety population, overall, the three most frequent ATC Class Level 3 medications across treatment groups were other analgesics and antipyretics (27.6%; predominantly paracetamol and/or the nonsteroidal anti-inflammatory drug [NSAID] metamizole), IV solution additives (22.5%), and beta blocking agents (22.2%). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Results -Primary Endpoint</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>As mentioned above, the coprimary efficacy endpoints were the composite microbiological eradication and programmatically determined clinical cure rate in the mMITT population at both Day 5 and the TOC visit. For noninferiority to be declared, the lower end of the 95% confidence interval for the difference between the composite cure in the two arms would have to be ≥ -15% at BOTH Day 5 and at the TOC.</p><p>At Day 5, the difference in composite cure (plazomicin -meropenem) was -3.4% (-10.0, -3.1)]. At TOC, the difference in composite cure was 11.6% (2.7, 20.3). Because the lower end of the 95% confidence interval of the difference in composite cure on both days was ≥ -15%, noninferiority of plazomicin to meropenem in the treatment of cUTI could be declared. Similar findings were noted at EOIV.</p><p>When looking at the composite cure rates for the ME population, similar trends were noted for Day 5 and TOC.  unclear what could account for this precipitous drop in microbiologic eradication. There were slight imbalances between the arms in terms of gender, infection type (cUTI vs. AP), and presence of DM but it is not clear why these would negatively impact meropenem's microbiologic eradication so heavily. The number of subjects who switched to oral therapy was relatively comparable between the arms, however there was a slight imbalance between the arms in terms of subjects receiving levofloxacin despite having a levofloxacin resistant pathogen (roughly 5% more in the meropenem arm). It is also plausible the plazomicin may have some intrinsic benefit with regards to microbiologic eradication (post-antibiotic effect, concentrating in the urine) though the TOC/LFU visits seem somewhat further than expected for such an effect to persist.</p><p>Whether this disparity in microbiologic eradication is of relevance clinically is also unclear. At the LFU visit, there were more clinical relapses in the meropenem arm <ref type="bibr">(14/197; 7.1%)</ref> compared to the plazomicin arm (3/169; 1.6%), but does not fully reflect the disparity in microbiologic eradication seen in TOC (it should also be noted that at LFU, there were more microbiologic recurrences in the meropenem arm compared to plazomicin).</p><p>The composite cure rates and their 95% CIs at each visit in the ME population were similar to the mMITT population.  For the Day 5 outcomes, in general, subpopulation estimates tracked along with the overall findings in that plazomicin performed worse (according to point estimates) than meropenem, particularly in females, subjects ≥ 65 years of age, subjects with ESBL pathogens, subjects with DM, subjects bacteremic at baseline, subjects with mild to moderately impaired renal function, subjects with an indwelling Foley, and subjects who switched to oral therapy. At the TOC visit, plazomicin seemed to perform better than meropenem in almost all subgroups. Interestingly, subjects with DM did not do better (by point estimate) with plazomicin at either visit. Given the small sample size of many of these subgroups (including the DM subgroup), post-randomization factors, etc., these findings should be viewed as purely exploratory.</p><p>Of note, of the 51 plazomicin subjects noted to have aminoglycoside-nonsusceptible isolates, almost all had resistance to either tobramycin alone, gentamicin alone, or combined tobramycin/gentamicin resistance. Amikacin "resistance" was only noted in one subject (had isolate that was intermediate to amikacin and resistant to tobramycin and gentamicin).</p><p>Microbiological eradication rates at TOC visit by baseline pathogen in the mMITT population are presented in <ref type="table" target="#tab_16">Table 11</ref>. As can be noted, eradication rates for the most frequent pathogens (E. coli and K. pneumoniae) were generally better for plazomicin than for meropenem. For other pathogens, the sample size is too limited to draw any real conclusions. Plazomicin's activity seemed at least comparable to that of meropenem for pathogens containing aminoglycoside resistance or ESBLs (please note that in this study, aminoglycoside resistance was defined as having intermediate or resistant susceptibility to either amikacin, tobramycin, OR gentamicin). Of note, Aminoglycoside resistance meant a baseline uropathogen had resistance to either tobramycin, gentamicin, or amikacin (or some combination thereof  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Data Quality and Integrity</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>The statistical reviewer found several subjects (11) who may have been mistakenly coded as Cures at either Day 5 or TOC. However, a sensitivity analysis in which these patients were reclassified as Failures still showed an NI margin ≥ 15% at Day 5 and TOC. However, it should be noted that reclassification did shift margins to the left so that superiority of plazomicin at TOC was eliminated (95% CI crossed zero Microbiological eradication for this study was assessed using criterion as bacteria growth at less than 10 4 CFU/mL. As this criterion may change to 10 3 CFU/mL in future guidances, additional analysis was done at the TOC visit (based on the data availability) for microbiological eradication rate at ≤ 10 3 CFU/mL. Compared to the results with criterion 10 4 CFU/mL, the new results favors plazomicin even more. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 002</head><p>As has been noted earlier, though the phase 3 trial only examined one dose of plazomicin (15 mg/kg daily), a phase 2 study was conducted in which several subjects took a 10mg/kg daily plazomicin dose until the protocol was amended and all subjects were switched to the 15mg/kg dose. Thus, there was a dose response comparison, albeit of imbalanced sample size.</p><p>This was a multicenter, multinational, double-blind, randomized, comparator-controlled, Phase 2 study of the safety and efficacy of plazomicin compared to levofloxacin (both administered as IV infusions) in patients with cUTI or AP. The coprimary efficacy endpoints were the microbiological eradication (MBE) rates at the test-of-cure (TOC) visit in the modified intent-to-treat (MITT) population and in the microbiologically evaluable (ME) population. The study consisted of a screening period (Day 1), a treatment period (Days 1-5), and a follow-up period (from EOT through Day 40).</p><p>The follow-up period consisted of the TOC (or early termination) visit and the long-term follow-up (LTFU) visit. The TOC visit and assessments occurred 7 (±2) days after the last dose of study drug (i.e., on Day 12 ±2). The LTFU visit (the final study visit) occurred 35 (±7) days after the last dose of study drug (i.e., on Day 40 ±7). At both the TOC and LTFU visits, the investigators assessed and recorded clinical outcome.</p><p>The study was comparator-controlled, and levofloxacin 750 mg for 5 consecutive days was chosen as the comparator drug for this study. Levofloxacin is approved for treatment of cUTI and AP.</p><p>At study entry, patients were to have a bacterial pathogen identified in urine culture at ≥10 5 CFU/mL as well as signs and symptoms of cUTI or AP.</p><p>Please note that beyond the small sample size of this study, demographic characteristics, including race, gender distribution, as well as microbiologic susceptibility differed considerably from Study 009.  Despite these demographic differences, it is still instructive to look at the phase 2 study results in order to see any possible implication of dose on outcomes. Difference (95% CI) a −7.6 (−31.3-16.0) Difference is for the difference in microbiological eradication rates between plazomicin 15 mg/kg and levofloxacin and is calculated as levofloxacin -plazomicin 15 mg/kg. The 95% CI for the difference is based on a normal approximation with a continuity correction. Source: Study 002, Clinical Study Report</p><p>As can be seen, there did appear to be a trend toward higher eradication in the 15 mg/kg arm, though the number of indeterminates in the MITT analysis set (which the applicant attributed to poor sample collection and tracking), small and imbalanced sample size, etc. make these results difficult to interpret)]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Durability of Response</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>Composite cure was tracked out to the LFU visit. Results did not differ from the TOC visit. Again, note that microbiological eradication drove the positive response at TOC and LFU.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Integrated Review of Effectiveness</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated Assessment of Effectiveness</head><p>The plazomicin clinical development plan was intended to pursue treatment of an unmet need through two distinct tracks. One track involved pursuing a traditional indication (cUTI) using a supportive Phase 2 study and a single Phase 3 study. A larger NI margin (15%) than is usually accepted for an cUTI NI trial was used as plazomicin had the potential to address an unmet medical need. The other track involved pursuing a BSI and HABP/VABP indication A clear understanding of these differing approaches is needed to determine if the standards for efficacy have been met for both indications.</p><p>In the case of cUTI, the evidentiary standard was adequately met. An initial small cUTI study (study 002) supported the efficacy of plazomicin compared to a commonly used comparator (levofloxacin) in the treatment of cUTI (descriptive analyses only; no NI margin was prespecified in this study) and provided the basis for Study 009. Study 009 was an, active controlled, doubleblind trial conducted using a trial design essentially in line with FDA guidance. An adequate comparator was chosen in meropenem. Noninferiority, as defined by composite cure rates at Day 5 and at TOC, was demonstrated in the mMITT population and supported by similar findings in the ME population. At TOC and LFU, plazomicin trended toward better composite cure rates than meropenem, though this was driven primarily by microbiological eradication findings. It is unclear what the clinical significance of this is, nor is it clear what the underlying reason (chance, confounding by demographics, true plazomicin effect, etc.) is for this finding. Subgroup analyses were generally in line with the mMITT population results; subgroups such as those with bacteremia and those with diabetes mellitus at baseline were difficult to interpret given the very small subgroup sample size. For the most part, the findings are generalizablesubjects had Foley catheters replaced, they were often switched to oral therapy after several days of IV therapy, and they represented an adequate mix of cUTI and AP. Importantly, patients could not have antibacterial therapy 48 hours prior to starting study drug, thus minimizing confounding. Also, almost all patients in the study continued in the study until the LFU visit.</p><p>However, it should be noted that there were some factors affecting generalizability. First, the racial makeup of the trial was overwhelmingly White as the trial was conducted primarily in Eastern European countries. Considering the racial diversity in the United States, this is not ideal. However, the Phase 2 study, Study 002, had a more diverse racial makeup and the efficacy findings there provides at least some assurance that the study medication effect seen in Study 009 is applicable to a broad swath of the US population. The other thing to note is that the primary efficacy analysis of Study 009 did not evaluate plazomicin activity against potential (though much less common) cUTI pathogens such as Acinetobacter and Pseudomonas. Due to concerns from prior nonclinical studies about plazomicin's activity against these pathogens, these pathogens were excluded from the mMITT population. Thus, clinical scenarios where such pathogens are expected to be the source of a cUTI may require an alternative therapy to plazomicin. However, plazomicin did appear to show activity against Enterobacteriaceae, the most common cause of cUTI. Importantly, it appeared to show adequate efficacy in Enterobacteriaceae carrying common resistance patterns such as ESBLs and appeared to provide an alternative aminoglycoside option in cases where there was aminoglycoside resistance (particularly tobramycin and gentamicin resistance). Finally, it should be noted that subjects with severe renal impairment were not studied. Considering that it is very likely that patients with severely impaired renal function at baseline are likely to be treated post market, dosing in this population should be appropriately evaluated. Where relevant, findings from phase 1 studies will also be discussed. Of note, this safety discussion will flow by topic rather than by trial. Thus, deaths in Study 002, Study 009, A total of 612 subjects were exposed to plazomicin including 479 subjects who received the therapeutic dose of 15mg/kg. Excluding TDM-adjusted doses, the highest clinical dose evaluated was a single dose of 20 mg/kg in the TQT study. The longest duration evaluated in the absence of TDM was 7 dosing days in Study 009.   In the case of the cUTI trials, there is a slight decrease in equitable distribution in the pooled safety database particularly when it comes to gender, race and age. However, when looking at Study 009 alone, there is better distribution of these factors with the exception of race (which was overwhelmingly white).  Typically, a baseline of at least 300 exposed subjects at the expected dose and duration for a proposed indication is expected. In the question of the cUTI indication, there is an acceptable numerical safety database, considering the planned usage for an unmet need. However, it should be noted that this database is not ideal. Typically, a phase 3 development program includes two adequate and well-controlled trials. Moreover, it is expected that adequate racial and geographic diversity is present so that findings can be generalized. From this perspective, the cUTI safety database does not meet those criteria. Generally, the data submission related to safety was adequate. In particular, the applicant did convey information related to aminoglycoside class-associated effects effectively. There was some confusion regarding study drug exposure, particularly in the phase 1 studies, but these concerns were relatively minor and were addressed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.2.">Categorization of Adverse Events</head><p>The categorization and assessment of adverse events by the applicant was adequate. MedDRA version 19.0 and CTCAE version 4.0 were used to categorize events. AE monitoring was typical for a phase 3 clinical trial. Importantly, the applicant did try to assess adverse events related to nephrotoxicity and ototoxicity-toxicities of particular interest with aminoglycosides See section 8.5 below).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.3.">Routine Clinical Tests</head><p>The safety assessments, which included typical laboratory measurements, vital signs measurements, physical examinations, etc. were appropriate and as expected for a phase 3 clinical development program.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.">Safety Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.1.">Deaths cUTI studies -Studies 009 and 002</head><p>There were no deaths in the meropenem arm and only one death in the plazomicin arm. This death involved a 63-year-old White woman who was admitted for pyelonephritis. She received one dose of plazomicin and then was discontinued from study drug due to acute kidney injury (switched to piperacillin-tazobactam and then meropenem). At the time of discontinuation, she was found to have metastatic uterine cancer with possible involvement of the lungs and liver. She continued to have worsening renal function (Day 7 creatinine 8.6 mg/dL) and eventually needed hemodialysis. She underwent six sessions of hemodialysis but on Day 17 refused further sessions due to difficulties in tolerating the procedure. On Day 18 she died due to asystole and bradycardia. The cause of death is unlikely study drug related though a relationship cannot be fully excluded; acute kidney injury may have partially been related to study drug, and worsening renal failure could have led to electrolyte disturbances that could have triggered arrhythmias and death. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Studies 009 and 002</head><p>The rate of SAEs was low and comparable between study arms. In study 009, five subjects in each arm had Serious Adverse Events (SAEs). In the plazomicin arm, the SAEs were acute kidney injury and metastatic neoplasm (in one subject), acute kidney injury, pneumonia, urosepsis, and calculus urinary. Review of the narratives of each of the five plazomicin cases revealed only possible relatedness of both acute kidney injury cases. In both cases, decreases in creatinine clearance were noted after only one dose of plazomicin. One subject eventually required hemodialysis and passed away, while another had recovery of renal function. Though other nephrotoxic confounders were present, given what is known about the nephrotoxic potential of aminoglycosides, a relationship between plazomicin and these acute kidney injury events is certainly plausible.  The rate of discontinuations was low and comparable between study arms. There were 10 subjects total between the plazomicin arms that had an AE leading to discontinuation. The vast majority of events were related to renal injury; in study 009 all the discontinuations were related to renal injury. The applicant noted that the study 009 protocol required discontinuation of IV study drug in patients with two successive creatinine clearance  In Study 009, nine subjects (3.0%) in the plazomicin arm and 14 subjects (4.7%) in the meropenem arm had Grade ≥ 3 TEAEs. In the plazomicin arm, there was some clustering of such AEs around renal injury, which is not surprising given the nephrotoxic ability of aminoglycosides. In Study 002, two plazomicin subjects had severe events; in one case the patient experienced hypotension and had plazomicin discontinued, however it is unclear whether the hypotensive episode was more related to the plazomicin infusion or placebo infusion (episode happened 30 minutes after placebo infusion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.4.">Treatment Emergent Adverse Events and Adverse Reactions cUTI trials-Study 009</head><p>There was little difference in the frequency of TEAEs between treatment groups in Study 009. A total of 59 (19.5%) and 65 (21.6%) subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively were noted to have TEAEs. In looking at TEAEs that occurred in at least 1% of subjects in either treatment group, frequencies of individual PTs were comparable between both arms and not atypical for a clinical trial. Diarrhea, hypertension, headache, nausea, and vomiting were the most frequent AEs for plazomicin, though they occurred at a level comparable to that of the meropenem arm. It should be noted that TEAEs associated with kidney injury were more concentrated in the plazomicin arm.  In study 009, there were 2 AEs coded to anemia in the plazomicin arm. None of these AEs were considered related to the study drug. As regards changes in typical hematology parameters in study 009, increases in at least 2 Grades (by CTCAE criteria) were few and comparable between treatment arms; missing data between the two arms was also similar. When looking at median changes from baseline to the EOIV, TOC, and LFU visits in WBC, neutrophils, hemoglobin (hgb), and platelets, changes were clinically insignificant and comparable between arms and generally did not have extremes that tended in one direction or another. In Study 009, there were 4 AEs coded to LFT elevations and 1 AE coded to hypokalemia in the plazomicin arm. All were considered not related to study drug. As regards blood chemistry, subjects with at least two grade increases were generally few and similar between both treatment arms though such increases in potassium and serum creatinine occurred slightly more in the plazomicin arm. In the case of potassium, there were 16 (5.8%) such subjects in the plazomicin arm versus 9 (3.2%) in the meropenem arm. However, 6.1mmol/L was the highest potassium level recorded in these 16 plazomicin subjects, and the highest change recorded in these subjects was an increase of 1.9 mmol/L from baseline. In the plazomicin arm, median changes in blood chemistry parameters from baseline to EOIV, TOC, and LFU visits were clinically insignificant and comparable in both arms.  In Study 009, LFT elevations were minimal in both arms. At the EOIV visit, one plazomicin subject had an ALT &gt; 3X ULN and at the TOC visit, one plazomicin subject had AST &gt; 5 X ULN. For the first subject, ALT increased from 17 to 167 at the EOIV visit but then decreased back to normal in the ensuing visits; the event was considered as not related to study drug and was nonserious; the patient was on some slightly hepatotoxic concomitant medications as well (calcium channel blocker, nsaid, etc.). In the second case, AST increased from 11 to 314 at the TOC visit, however this was 13 days after stopping plazomicin. This patient only got a single dose of plazomicin because of deterioration of renal function; the patient had AST of 14 at the EOIV visit. No patients in the plazomicin group met Hy's Law.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vital Signs</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>[In study 009, vital signs (including respiratory rate, heart rate, systolic/diastolic blood pressure, and temperature) were measured roughly 15 minutes prior to and after study drug infusion and during follow up (TOC/LFU) visits (if they occurred in person). There were no clinically significant mean changes from baseline to EOIV, TOC, and LFU visits in vital signs for both arms; mean changes were comparable between arms. In terms of potentially clinically significant (prespecified) postbaseline values, there was a slight trend toward increased incidences of low SBP and DBP in the plazomicin arm, however this trend was not necessarily seen in conjunction with the EOIV, TOC or LFU visits. Also, a trend for decreased temperature was also seen in the plazomicin arm overall postbaseline and at the EOIV, TOC, and LFU visits. Three plazomicin subjects actually low SBPs that were PCS that were associated with the plazomicin infusion. In one subject the drop was 20mm Hg only and occurred with placebo infusions as well. In another case, the incident occurred on Day 1 only, was associated with a 20 mm Hg drop, and also occurred with placebo infusion. In a third case, this hypotension occurred in conjunction with suspected urosepsis and stent placement for hydronephrosis and was not seen at the EOIV therapy visit. It is notable that only 4 AEs related to hypotension were seen in the plazomicin arm and none were temporally related to plazomicin infusion or thought to be related to study drug. All other vital signs saw comparable incidences of PCS postbaseline values. It should be noted that in the phase 1 study-Study 003 (Lung penetration study), 5 subjects who received a 15 mg/kg dose had episodes of hypotension soon after the plazomicin infusion was finished. Though these episodes required normal saline in some cases, they generally resolved within a few minutes to hours. Of importance, is that all of these subjects received a 10 minute plazomicin infusion. Subsequent to this study, all studies used a 30-minute infusion time, and no events of decreased blood pressure temporally associated with plazomicin infusions were subsequently observed in the subsequent completed Phase 1 studies. In study 009, there were slightly more TEAEs associated with nephrotoxicity that occurred in the plazomicin arm relative to the meropenem arm (11 cases (3.6%) in the plazomicin arm and 4 cases (1.3%) in the meropenem arm). In the plazomicin arm 7/11 (63.6%) cases involved were mild to moderate in severity and 6/11 (54.5%) cases required discontinuation of IV plazomicin (primarily due to protocol mandates as explained earlier). Interestingly, in the plazomicin arm all such TEAEs occurred in patients with Creatinine Clearance &lt; 90 ml/min.). There were two subjects who had a nephrotoxic serious adverse event, only one of whom's renal function recovered after discontinuation of plazomicin IV. Of the 11 plazomicin associated-nephrotoxic cases, only 2 were considered as not recovered by end of study.</p><p>The applicant also evaluated increases (at any time postbaseline) in serum creatinine ≥ 0.5mg/dl. These changes happened with more frequency in the plazomicin arm (7.0%; 21/300) than the meropenem arm (4.0%12/297); a slightly increased trend was also noted for the plazomicin arm when evaluating increases ≥ 1.0mg/dl, 2.0mg/dl, 3.0mg/dl, or 4.0 mg/dl. In general, though, increases were mild. Only 1.7% (5/300) and 1.0% (3/297) of patients had increases of ≥1.0 mg/dL in the plazomicin and meropenem groups, respectively. As expected, not all increases occurred while on IV therapy; increases could manifest post study drug administration as well.  The applicant also evaluated changes in serum creatinine relative to RIFLE criteria. In general, post-baseline changes were increased in the "Risk" category but comparable relative to meropenem for all other categories The applicant noted that most cases of creatinine increase recovered (recovery being defined as a visit creatinine value &lt; 0.5 mg/dl above baseline value). The table below shows that recovery from creatinine increases that occurred while on IV therapy was common. Importantly, the applicant noted that increases in serum creatinine were directly associated with decreasing renal function and increased duration of therapy. The following table shows incidences of serum creatinine increases in Study 009 in relation to baseline renal function.  Aminoglycosides have been associated with permanent ototoxicity, manifested as both audiometric losses as well as vestibulotoxicity. In the applicant's clinical development plan, ototoxicity was evaluated in the phase 1 trials and cUTI trials.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>cUTI-Study 009</head><p>In Study 009, ototoxicity could not practically be assessed through typical measurements such as audiometric tests or Romberg testing because of the hospitalized status of most of the Per the applicant, hearing was assessed using the HHIA at baseline, EOIV and LFU. Patients were asked if they had a history of hearing problems or if they currently had a problem with hearing. If "yes", the HHIA was administered to determine how much the hearing problem impacted the patient's daily activities. The HHIA consists of 25 questions, which are answered as yes, sometimes, or no. A total score is derived as follows: Total HHIA score = (number of 'Yes' responses ×4) + (number of 'Sometimes' responses ×2). Patients indicating "no" in response to the initial screening question were assigned a score of 0 for that visit. Patients who answered "yes" to the initial screening question, but did not answer all 25 questions, were considered to have missing data and were excluded from the analysis for that visit. The total score was also categorized into perceived hearing handicap categories as follows: Tinnitus was assessed using the THI at baseline, EOIV, and LFU. Patients were asked if they had a history of hearing any noises such as ringing or buzzing in their ears or currently had noises such as ringing or buzzing in their ears. If "yes", the THI was administered to determine how much the tinnitus impacted the patient's daily activities. The THI consists of 25 questions which are answered as yes, sometimes, or no. A total score is derived as follows: Total THI score = (number of 'Yes' responses ×4) + (number of 'Sometimes' responses ×2). Patients indicating "no" in response to the initial screening question were assigned a score of 0 for that visit. Patients who answered "yes" to the initial screening question, but did not answer all 25 questions were considered to have missing data and were excluded from the analysis for that visit. The total score was also categorized into perceived tinnitus handicap categories as follows:  Dizziness was assessed using the DHI at baseline, EOIV and LFU. Patients were asked if they had a history of dizziness or problems with their balance or were currently experiencing dizziness or problems with their balance. If "yes", the DHI was administered to determine how much the dizziness impacted the patient's daily activities. The DHI consists of 25 questions which are answered as yes, sometimes, or no. A total score is derived as follows: Total DHI score = (number of 'Yes' responses ×4) + (number of 'Sometimes' responses ×2) Patients indicating "no" in response to the initial screening question were assigned a score of 0 for that visit. Patients who answered "yes" to the initial screening question, but did not answer all 25 questions, were considered to have missing data and were excluded from the analysis for that visit. The total score was also categorized into perceived dizziness handicap categories as follows:  The HHIA criteria for referral to an audiologist required a 12-point increase from baseline accompanied by an associated shift in handicap category. The THI criteria for referral to an ENT required a 20-point increase from baseline accompanied by an associated shift in handicap category. The DHI criteria for referral to an ENT required an 18-point increase from baseline accompanied by an associated shift in handicap category.</p><p>For the HHIA, only one plazomicin subject had a shift in handicap category. However, the shift was mild (a two-point change to move from no handicap at baseline to mild handicap at EOIV), and then reverted to baseline by the LFU visit. Only one subject in the meropenem arm had a handicap change.</p><p>A single patient in the plazomicin group experienced a one-category handicap increase in THI at the LFU visit. The subject had pre-existing tinnitus in both ears and experienced a one-category shift in THI at the LFU visit (from 22 [mild handicap] at screening and EOIV to a score of 40 [moderate handicap] at the LFU visit). This change did not meet the criteria for referral to an audiologist and was not reported as a TEAE. She received four doses of plazomicin.</p><p>One female subject experienced a one handicap category increase in DHI. The DHI score at EOIV was 20 (Mild Handicap), increased from the baseline score of 0 (No Handicap). Although the change at EOIV met protocol-specified criteria for otolaryngology referral, the DHI score returned to 0 at the LFU visit, and the patient was not referred. The subject had a TEAE of dizziness on Study Day 3 but recovered on the same calendar day following treatment with intramuscular dexamethasone. The dizziness was considered moderate and unrelated to blinded IV study drug. The patient's scores for the HHIA and THI were 0 at all three visits.</p><p>There was one plazomicin subject who reported a TEAE of hypoacusis. This involved an 83 y/o male who received four doses of plazomicin. At screening and at the end-of-intravenoustherapy, the subject did not report any prior or current problems with dizziness or balance, Handicap Inventory, and Hearing Handicap Inventory for Adult (HHIA) scores were each 0 for these visits. Three days following the test-of-cure visit, an AE of Grade 1 hypoacusis (verbatim: decrease of hearing; continuous course) was reported. At the late follow-up visit (Study Day 28), the patient reported hearing problems affecting both ears, and the HHIA score was 8 on a scale of 0 to 100. This HHIA score is categorized as "No handicap"; thus, this score change did not meet the protocol-specified criteria for an audiologist referral. At an unscheduled visit 3 months later, the AE of Grade 1 hypoacusis was reported as fully recovered/resolved. A relationship with study drug cannot be ruled out but given the short course of aminoglycoside treatment and full recovery, it's unlikely an association exists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phase 1 Studies</head><p>In the phase 1 studies, five subjects had reports of transient tinnitus following a single dose of plazomicin (one of the five subjects also reported transient nystagmus). Another subject had an abnormal vestibular function test.</p><p>In the phase 2 and 3 cUTI trials, there were three reports of adverse events associated with cochlear or vestibular function. These were reports of hypoacusis, tinnitus, and vertigo. These events were somewhat atypical for aminoglycoside-related ototoxicity in that the hypoacusis and vertigo events resolved and the tinnitus event was unilateral.</p><p>Pure tone audiometry (PTA) was performed in phase 1 and phase 2 studies. These procedures varied by study in terms of the frequencies measured, duration of follow up, etc. The applicant conducted an independent expert analysis of the PTA data. Their findings are reported as below.</p><p>"The criteria applied to individual Phase 1 and 2 studies for interpretation of potentially clinically meaningful changes in audiometry findings differed, rendering an overall assessment of this data challenging. As such, an external expert assessment of all Phase 1 and 2 audiometry data was conducted in order to apply widely accepted, uniform criteria for meaningful change in hearing thresholds as defined by the American Speech-Language-Hearing Association <ref type="bibr">(ASHA;</ref><ref type="bibr">1994)</ref> and to confirm the findings from individual Phase 1 and 2 studies.</p><p>Based on this expert review, of the 203 plazomicin-exposed and 56 comparator-exposed adults <ref type="bibr">(levofloxacin, moxifloxacin, and/or placebo only)</ref> with PTA data across 4 Phase 1 studies and 1 Phase 2 study, <ref type="bibr">182/203 (89.7%) and 49/56 (87.5%)</ref>, respectively, had evaluable data. Four of the 182 plazomicin-exposed individuals (2.2%) and 1 of the 49 comparator-exposed individuals (2.0%) were assessed as having findings for which study drug-related ototoxicity could not be definitively excluded. Overall, the expert review concluded that there were no widespread signs of study drug-related ototoxicity as determined by PTA across Phase 1 and 2 studies. Given the known ototoxic potential of aminoglycosides, the small number of individuals with longer-term NDA 210303/Clinical Review Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection CDER Clinical Review Template 123 Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs follow-up (e.g., at 6 months following treatment) as recommended by ASHA, and findings in a small number of individuals for which ototoxicity could not be definitively excluded, ototoxicity remains an identified risk for plazomicin." Also in the phase 1 studies, a mix of electronystagmography, modified Romberg testing, and Dynamic Visual Acuity testing was performed; modified Romberg testing was also performed in the phase 2 study. Electronystamography (ENG) data was submitted by the applicant to outside experts for evaluation and their findings are summarized as follows:</p><p>"Expert review was limited to ENG data obtained in the SAD/MAD and lung penetration studies (Studies ACHN-490-001 and ACHN-490-003 respectively), as this testing was felt to be the most objective method used. Overall, no standard behavioral assessment scale for vestibular function has been universally accepted and approved for use in clinical trials as these tests in general are fairly unreliable and only detect vestibular toxicity if the damage is very severe. Further, results of this type of testing should be interpreted in the context of clinical findings. There were 31 plazomicin-dosed subjects and 11 placebo-dosed subjects for whom ENG data were reviewed. Of these, 4/31 plazomicin subjects (12.9%) and 1/11 placebo subjects (9.1%) had a change in vestibular function as evidenced by abnormal findings on caloric symmetry. It is unclear whether these were unilateral or bilateral changes, based on the available data. Per expert review, if vestibulotoxicity had been present, the subjects should have experienced imbalance or oscillopsia. No AEs of that nature were reported by these subjects; therefore, it was concluded that, in spite of the limitations in the ENG available, no clear sign of vestibulotoxicity can be inferred based on this testing."</p><p>The Agency does not have in-house expertise to evaluate this PTA and ENG data, however given the outside expert conclusions (essentially not ruling out ototoxicity), this is not needed given that class warnings related to ototoxicity are likely to be placed in labelling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.6.">Safety Analyses by Demographic Subgroups</head><p>[Given the large size of Study 009 and much smaller sizes of Studies 002 demographic analyses were analyzed primarily for Study 009. Also, subgroup comparisons are made primarily within the plazomicin arm. TEAEs, including related TEAEs, occurred with more frequency in the elderly (≥ 65 years old) population relative to the similar age group in the comparator arm and relative to the 18 to &lt;65-year-old age group in the plazomicin arm. Some of this disparity can be related to TEAEs related to renal function, but not all. See the table below (Note: most elderly subjects were in Study 009).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Glossary ..........................................................................................................................................9 1. Executive Summary ...............................................................................................................11 1.1. Product Introduction......................................................................................................11 1.2. Conclusions on the Substantial Evidence of Effectiveness.............................................11 1.3. Benefit-Risk Assessment ................................................................................................11 1.4. Patient Experience Data.................................................................................................15 2. Therapeutic Context..............................................................................................................15 2.1. Analysis of Condition......................................................................................................16 2.2. Analysis of Current Treatment Options .........................................................................17 3. Regulatory Background .........................................................................................................17 3.1. U.S. Regulatory Actions and Marketing History.............................................................17 3.2. Summary of Presubmission/Submission Regulatory Activity ........................................17 3.3. Foreign Regulatory Actions and Marketing History .......................................................20 4. Significant Issues from Other Review Disciplines Pertinent to Clinical Conclusions on Efficacy and Safety ................................................................................................................20 4.1. Office of Scientific Investigations (OSI) ..........................................................................20 4.2. Product Quality ..............................................................................................................21 4.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>8.</head><label></label><figDesc>Review of Safety....................................................................................................................91 8.1. Safety Review Approach ................................................................................................91 8.2. Review of the Safety Database ......................................................................................91 8.2.1. Overall Exposure.....................................................................................................91 8.2.2. Relevant characteristics of the safety population: .................................................97 8.2.3. Adequacy of the safety database: ..........................................................................98 8.3. Adequacy of Applicant's Clinical Safety Assessments....................................................99 8.3.1. Issues Regarding Data Integrity and Submission Quality........................................99 8.3.2. Categorization of Adverse Events ...........................................................................99 8.3.3. Routine Clinical Tests ..............................................................................................99 8.4. Safety Results.................................................................................................................99 8.4.1. Deaths.....................................................................................................................99 8.4.2. Dropouts and/or Discontinuations Due to Adverse Effects..................................102 8.4.3. Significant Adverse Events....................................................................................103 8.4.4. Treatment Emergent Adverse Events and Adverse Reactions .............................104 8.4.5. Laboratory Findings ..............................................................................................108 8.4.6. Electrocardiograms (ECGs) ...................................................................................112 8.4.7. QT .........................................................................................................................112 8.4.8. Immunogenicity ....................................................................................................113 8.5. Analysis of Submission-Specific Safety Issues ..............................................................113 8.5.1. [Nephrotoxicity]....................................................................................................113 8.5.2. Ototoxicity ............................................................................................................116 8.6. Safety Analyses by Demographic Subgroups ...............................................................121 8.7. Specific Safety Studies/Clinical Trials ...........................................................................122 8.8. Additional Safety Explorations .....................................................................................122 8.8.1. Human Carcinogenicity or Tumor Development ..................................................123 8.8.2. Human Reproduction and Pregnancy...................................................................123 8.8.3. Pediatrics and Assessment of Effects on Growth .................................................123 8.8.4. Overdose, Drug Abuse Potential, Withdrawal, and Rebound ..............................124 8.9. Safety in the Postmarket Setting .................................................................................124 8.9.1. Safety Concerns Identified Through Postmarket Experience ...............................124 Reference ID: 4282865</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>April 28, 2016: The Applicant proposed to terminate enrollment due to enrollment challenges in Study 007, and proposed a prospective stopping rule such that the end of enrollment would coincide with the completion of the Phase 3 cUTI Study 009.July 18, 2016: The Applicant revised the prospective stopping rule for Study 007, such that new enrollment would be terminated on August 1, 2016 regardless of enrollment in Study 009.September 15, 2016: The Phase 3 CRE Study 007 was completed. The last patient had been enrolled on July 22, 2106. The primary analysis population of patients in the randomized cohort with CRE contained 17 patients in the plazomicin group and 20 patients in the colistin group.September 22, 2016: The Phase 3 cUTI Study 009 was completed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>6. 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Study 007 (CRE) and Study 009 (cUTI) 6.1.1. Study Design</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Figure 2</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Study Design Schema and Overview of Study Schedule, Study 009 Source: Study 009 Clinical Study Report</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Figure 4</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Efficacy Endpoints by Visit, mMITT Population, Study 009 Note: Red vertical lines respresent the NI margin of -15%. Source: Statistical reviewer Additional Analyses Conducted on the Individual Trial</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>Figure 5 :</head><label>5</label><figDesc>HHIA Categorization, Study 009Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Figure 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>THI Categorization, Study 009Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Figure 7 :</head><label>7</label><figDesc>DHI Categorization, Study 009 Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table of Contents</head><label>of</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>3. Clinical Microbiology/Nonclinical Pharmacology Toxicology.........................................22 4.4. Clinical Pharmacology ....................................................................................................24 4.5. Devices and Companion Diagnostic Issues ....................................................................26 4.6. Consumer Study Reviews...............................................................................................26 5. Sources of Clinical Data and Review Strategy .......................................................................27 5.1. Table of Clinical Studies .................................................................................................27 5.2. Review Strategy .............................................................................................................33 6. Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy .............................................33 6.1. Study 007 (CRE) and Study 009 (cUTI) ...........................................................................33 6.1.1. Study Design ...........................................................................................................33 6.1.2. Study Results ..........................................................................................................49 7. Integrated Review of Effectiveness .......................................................................................87</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs 8.9.2. Expectations on Safety in the Postmarket Setting................................................124 8.9.3. Additional Safety Issues From Other Disciplines ..................................................125 8.10. Integrated Assessment of Safety..............................................................................125 9. Advisory Committee Meeting and Other External Consultations .......................................126 10. Labeling Recommendations ................................................................................................127 10.1. Prescription Drug Labeling .......................................................................................127 10.2. Nonprescription Drug Labeling.................................................................................127 11. Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies (REMS) ..............................................................127 12. Postmarketing Requirements and Commitments...............................................................128</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>4 5</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table of Tables</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Table 1-Patients with Uropathogens that Developed Decreased Susceptibility or Resistance to Study Drug Received by Pathogen-mMITT Population, Study 009 .......................23 Table 2 -Completed Phase 2 and Phase 3 Clinical Studies of Plazomicin in Patients With Complicated Urinary Tract Infection, Including Acute Pyelonephritis..........................................28 Table 3 -Completed Phase 3 Clinical Study of Plazomicin in Patients With Carbapenem-Resistant Enterobacteriaceae Infection .......................................................................................29 Table 4 -Phase 1 Completed Studies (Pre NDA Submission) of Plazomicin in Heathy Subjects or Otherwise Healthy Subjects With Renal Impairment ...................................................................29 Table 5 -Phase 1 Completed Studies (Post NDA Submission) of Plazomicin in Heathy Subjects.30 Table 6 Overview of Study Drug Dosing, Study 009 .....................................................................41 Table 7 Core Symptoms of cUTI, Study 009..................................................................................42 Table 8 Clinical Response Categories and Corresponding Criteria at Day 5 and EOIV Visits, Study 009................................................................................................................................................42 Table 9 Clinical Response Categories and Corresponding Criteria at the TOC Visit, Study 009....43 Table 10 -Postbaseline Symptom Response Relative to Baseline Status, Study 009 ...................43 Table 11 Per-Pathogen Microbiological Outcome Categories at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC, Study 009 ......................................................................................................................................................43 Table 12 Per-Patient Microbiological Outcome Categories at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC, Study 009 44 Table 13 Clinical Response categories for BSI patients in Study 007............................................45 Table 14 Clinical Response categories for HABP/VABP patients in Study 007 .............................46 Table 15: Patient Disposition -ITT Population, Study 009............................................................52 Table 16 Study Populations Overall and by Randomization Stratification Factors, Study 009.....54 Table 17 Reviewer's summary of baseline characteristics, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007 ...............................................................................................................57 Table 18 Investigator Site Locations, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007................................................................................................................................................58 Table 19 Medical/surgical history, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007 ......................................................................................................................................................59 Table 20 Summary of baseline CRE bacteremia based on blood cultures collected within 24 hours prior to initiation of study drug and postbaseline cultures, mMITT population, Cohort 1, BSI subgroup, Study 007...............................................................................................................59 Table 21 Antibacterial therapy received within 96 hours prior study drug, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007...................................................................................60 Table 22 Reviewer's summary of baseline characteristics, mMITT population, Study 009..........61 Table 23 Most frequent Uropathogens Identified from Baseline Urine Cultures -mMITT Population, Study 009 ..................................................................................................................62 Table 24 All-cause mortality at Day 28 or SDRCs, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 008 ...............................................................................................................66 Table 25 Day 28 all-cause mortality or SDRCs by subgroups of interest, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007...................................................................................68</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>6</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 26</head><label>26</label><figDesc>All-cause mortality at Day 28 or SDRCs, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI subgroup), Study 007......................................................................................................................................69 Table 27 Summary of demographic subgroup results, mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007 ...............................................................................................................70 Table 28 Day 28 all-cause mortality or SDRCs in subgroups defined by baseline plazomicin minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007......................................................................................................................................71 Table 29 Summary of Day 28 all-cause mortality or SDRCs in subgroups defined by baseline colistin minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC), mMITT population, Cohort 1 (BSI and HABP/VABP), Study 007 ...............................................................................................................71 Table 30 Composite of Microbiological Eradication and Clinical Cure Rate, and Individual Components at Day 5 and TOC Visits, mMITT Population, Study 009..........................................72 Table 31: Composite of Microbiological Response and Clinical Response at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC Visits, ME Population, Study 009 ..........................................................................................74 Table 32 cUTI Composite Cure Rate, mMITT subgroup analysis, Study 009 ................................74 Table 33: Microbiological Eradication Rate at TOC by Baseline Pathogen, mMITT Population, Study 009......................................................................................................................................76 Table 34: Microbiological Eradication Rate at TOC, Based on Two Different Criteria, mMITT Population, Study 009 ..................................................................................................................79 Table 35 Demographics and Baseline Characteristics (ITT Population), Study 002......................81 Table 36: Microbiological Response at TOC (MITT and ME Populations), Study 002...................82 Table 37: Source Workup in 7 Plazomicin Subjects with Primary Bacteremia, BSI Subgroup, Study 007......................................................................................................................................84 Table 38: Plazomicin Subjects With Negative or No Blood Cultures at Baseline who Remained Culture Negative Throughout the Rest of Study, BSI Subgroup, Study 007 .................................86 Table 39 Adult Plazomicin Exposure by Dose and Duration of Exposure in Completed Phase 1, 2, and 3 Studies ................................................................................................................................93 Table 40 Plazomicin Exposure in Healthy Subjects by Dose and Dosing Regimen, Studies 002 and 009................................................................................................................................................94 Table 41 Intravenous Study Drug Exposure-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009) ..............95 Table 42 Study Drug Exposure-Safety Population, Study 007....................................................96 Table 43: Demographics and Baseline Characteristics-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009 ......................................................................................................................................................97 Table 44 Fatal Serious Adverse Events by System Organ Class and Preferred Term-Safety Population, Study 007 ................................................................................................................100 Table 45 Incidence of Serious Adverse Events by Preferred Term-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009 ................................................................................................................................102 Table 46: Adverse Events Leading to Premature Discontinuation of Intravenous Study Drug-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009 .....................................................................................103 Table 47: Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in at Least 1% of Patients in Either TreatmentGroup by PT (by Decreasing Frequency in Plazomicin Group) -Safety Population, Study 009....................................................................................................................................104</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 48</head><label>48</label><figDesc>Incidence of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Related to IV Study Drug by PT (By Decreasing Overall Incidence) -Safety Population, Study 009...................................................106 Table 49:Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Assessed as Related to IntravenousStudy Drug by System Organ Class and Preferred Term-Safety Population, Study 007 ..................................108 Table 50 Patients with at Least a Two-Grade Increase from Baseline in CTCAE Grade by Hematology Central Laboratory Parameter -Safety Population, Study 009..............................109 Table 51 Patients with at Least a Two-Grade Increase from Baseline in CTCAE Grade by Chemistry Central Laboratory Parameter -Safety Population, Study 009 .................................111 Table 52 Patients With Any Serum Creatinine Increase of 0.5 mg/dL or Greater Above Baseline-Safety Population, Studies 002, 007, and 009 ...........................................................114 Table 53 RIFLE Classification of Renal Injury, Safety Population, Studies 002, 007, and 009.....115 Table 54 Renal Recovery for Patients With Any Serum Creatinine Increase of 0.5 mg/dL or Greater Above Baseline While on Intravenous Study Drug-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009).............................................................................................................................................116 Table 55 Patients with any &gt;= 0.5 mg/dL Increase from Baseline in Serum Creatinine by Baseline CLcr Category -Safety Population, Study 009 ............................................................................117 Table 56 Overall Summary of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events, by Age Group, for the Pooled Complicated Urinary Tract Infection Studies-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009 ....................................................................................................................................................123 Table 57: Planned Pediatric Studies ...........................................................................................125</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Table of Figures</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Figure 1: Design schema and overview of study schedule in Study 007 ......................................37 Figure 2 Study Design Schema and Overview of Study Schedule, Study 009 ...............................40 Figure 3: Disposition flow diagram for Study 007 ........................................................................50 Figure 4 Efficacy Endpoints by Visit, mMITT Population, Study 009 ............................................82 Figure 5: HHIA Categorization, Study 009 ..................................................................................117 Figure 6: THI Categorization, Study 009 .....................................................................................118 Figure 7: DHI Categorization, Study 009.....................................................................................119</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell></row><row><cell>OPQ</cell><cell>Office of Pharmaceutical Quality</cell></row><row><cell>Glossary OSE</cell><cell>Office of Surveillance and Epidemiology</cell></row><row><cell>OSI</cell><cell>Office of Scientific Investigation</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">AC PBRER 1. Executive Summary Periodic Benefit-Risk Evaluation Report advisory committee AE PD pharmacodynamics adverse event AR adverse reaction BLA PI prescribing information or package insert PK 1.1. Product Introduction pharmacokinetics biologics license application BPCA PMC postmarketing commitment Best Pharmaceuticals for Children Act BRF PMR postmarketing requirement Plazomicin (Zemdri™), is a newly developed semi-synthetic aminoglycoside with the proposed Benefit Risk Framework CBER PP per protocol indications of treatment of complicated urinary tract infections (cUTI) and acute pyelonephritis Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research CDER PPI patient package insert (AP) and blood stream infection (BSI), both in cases where limited or no treatment alternatives Center for Drug Evaluation and Research CDRH CDTL CFR CMC COSTART CRF CRO CRT CSR clinical study report TEAE treatment emergent adverse event clinical review template SOC standard of care contract research organization SGE special government employee case report form SAP statistical analysis plan Coding Symbols for Thesaurus of Adverse Reaction Terms SAE serious adverse event chemistry, manufacturing, and controls REMS risk evaluation and mitigation strategy Code of Federal Regulations PSUR Periodic Safety Update report Cross-Discipline Team Leader PRO patient reported outcome Center for Devices and Radiological Health PREA Pediatric Research Equity Act are available.</cell></row><row><cell>CSS</cell><cell>Controlled Substance Staff</cell></row><row><cell>DMC</cell><cell>data monitoring committee</cell></row><row><cell>ECG</cell><cell>electrocardiogram</cell></row><row><cell>eCTD</cell><cell>electronic common technical document</cell></row><row><cell>ETASU</cell><cell>elements to assure safe use</cell></row><row><cell>FDA</cell><cell>Food and Drug Administration</cell></row><row><cell>FDAAA</cell><cell>Food and Drug Administration Amendments Act of 2007</cell></row><row><cell>FDASIA</cell><cell>Food and Drug Administration Safety and Innovation Act</cell></row><row><cell>GCP</cell><cell>good clinical practice</cell></row><row><cell>GRMP</cell><cell>good review management practice</cell></row><row><cell>ICH</cell><cell>International Council for Harmonization</cell></row><row><cell>IND</cell><cell>Investigational New Drug Application</cell></row><row><cell>ISE</cell><cell>integrated summary of effectiveness</cell></row><row><cell>ISS</cell><cell>integrated summary of safety</cell></row><row><cell>ITT</cell><cell>intent to treat</cell></row><row><cell>MedDRA</cell><cell>Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities</cell></row><row><cell>mITT</cell><cell>modified intent to treat</cell></row><row><cell>NCI-CTCAE</cell><cell>National Cancer Institute-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Event</cell></row><row><cell>NDA</cell><cell>new drug application</cell></row><row><cell>NME</cell><cell>APPEARS THIS WAY ON ORIGINAL new molecular entity</cell></row><row><cell>OCS</cell><cell>Office of Computational Science</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CDER Clinical Review Template CDER Clinical Review Template CDER Clinical Review Template CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>9 10 11 12</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>NDAs and BLAs Benefit-Risk Dimensions Dimension Evidence and Uncertainties Conclusions and Reasons Analysis of Condition</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dimension Dimension 1.4.</cell><cell>Evidence and Uncertainties Evidence and Uncertainties Patient Experience Data</cell><cell>Conclusions and Reasons Conclusions and Reasons</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">(b) (4) 14 Complicated UTI is a serious bacterial infection most (b) (4) commonly caused by gram-negative bacteria of the family Enterobacteriaceae. BSI and HABP/VABP caused by CRE are serious infections associated with high mortality. Treatment options for CRE infections are limited. Plazomicin may offer a treatment alternative for infections which have limited treatment options currently. 15 Plazomicin shows noninferiority (using a composite of clinical and microbiological response) to a commonly used therapy for cUTI that persists to the TOC visit. (b) (4) 16 Plazomicin contains risk due to typical aminoglycoside-associate adverse effects. 17 Validated (from the Agency perspective) PRO's were not part of this application. However, as CDER Clinical Review Template individuals with some functional or physical deficit in the lower or upper urinary tract, predisposing to infection.  Infections are generally from Enterobacteriaciae, though theoretically could be the result of a broad array of pathogens  Treatment courses are generally for 7-10 days.  CRE-associated BSI and HABP/VABP generally are associated with high mortality.  Current therapies, such as colistin can have significant toxicities  Treatment courses can last from 7 to 14 days. Current Treatment Options  cUTI Examples: levofloxacin, meropenem, piperacillin-tazobactam, cephalosporins.  CRE -associated infections BSI Examples: ceftazidime/avibactam, meropenem vaborbactam, colistin, tigecycline, aminoglycosides, carbapenems. HABP/VABP Examples: colistin, meropenem, tigecycline, aminoglycosides. CDER Clinical Review Template Note: Includes off label usage Benefit  cUTI Plazomicin had a composite cure rate of 168/191 (88.0%) and 156/191 (81.7%) at Day 5 and TOC, respectively in the mMITT population. For meropenem, the values were 180/197 (91.4%) and 138/197 (70.1%). The noninferiority margin of 15% was met for both time points Day 5 Margin (plazomicin -meropenem): -3.4% (-10.0, 3.1%) TOC Margin: 11.6% (2.7%, 20.3%) BSI (b) (4) CDER Clinical Review Template Risk and Risk Management Major safety findings: Plazomicin does show increased nephrotoxicity relative to a non-nephrotoxic comparator (meropenem). Its nephrotoxicity relative to a potent nephrotoxic agent (such as colistin) may be less, though assessments are limited by a small study population Plazomicin cannot be excluded from having ototoxic effects based on outside assessment of pure tone audiometry and electronystagmography results. CDER Clinical Review Template part of the Clinical Response in study 009 (cUTI trial), patients were asked about improvement/ worsening in their urinary symptoms. Also, several inventories were used to assess ototoxicity in the same trial. See sections 6.1.1 and 8.5.2 for more details Patient Experience Data Relevant to this Application (check all that apply) □ The patient experience data that was submitted as part of the application include: Section where discussed, if applicable □ Clinical outcome assessment (COA) data, such as x □ Patient reported outcome (PRO) □ Observer reported outcome (ObsRO) □ Clinician reported outcome (ClinRO) □ Performance outcome (PerfO) □ Qualitative studies (e.g., individual patient/caregiver interviews, focus group interviews, expert interviews, Delphi Panel, etc.) □ Patient-focused drug development or other stakeholder meeting summary reports □ Observational survey studies designed to capture patient experience data □ Natural history studies □ Patient preference studies (e.g., submitted studies or scientific publications) □ Other: (Please specify) □ Patient experience data that were not submitted in the application, but were considered in this review: □ Input informed from participation in meetings with patient stakeholders □ Patient-focused drug development or other stakeholder meeting summary reports □ Observational survey studies designed to capture patient experience data □ Other: (Please specify) □ Patient experience data was not submitted as part of this application. CDER Clinical Review Template 18 Version date: September 6, 2017 for all  cUTI is generally found in Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865 Reference ID: 4282865 Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, if possible. The diagnosis is made through a combination of symptoms/signs, positive blood cultures, and culture data that help to identify a source (such as a urine or sputum culture or blood culture from an indwelling central line).</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>and patient condition</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>19</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Summary of Presubmission/Submission Regulatory Activity</head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs completed Phase 2 cUTI Study ACHN-490-002 (Study 002), which had completed enrollment in April, 2012.</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3.2.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">This subsection describes significant regulatory interactions between the Applicant and the</cell></row><row><cell>Agency relating to the design and analysis of Study 007 and 009.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">June 4, 2012: A Type B Clinical Development Meeting was held between the Applicant and the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Agency. The Agency provided general input on a clinical development plan to study plazomicin</cell></row><row><cell>for the treatment of CRE infections.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">August 12, 2012: Fast Track designation was granted for the treatment of serious and life-</cell></row><row><cell>threatening infections due to CRE.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">December 17, 2012: An End-of-Phase 2 Meeting was held between the Applicant and the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Agency. A general agreement was reached on a Phase 3 study design to support approval of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">plazomicin for patients with bloodstream infections or ventilated nosocomial pneumonia due</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">to CRE. This included agreement on the proposed plazomicin and colistin comparator dosing</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">regimens, and agreement with therapeutic drug management to support plazomicin dosing.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">April 5, 2013: A Special Protocol Assessment (SPA) request was submitted for the Phase 3 CRE</cell></row><row><cell>Study ACHN-490-007 (Study 007).</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">July 29, 2013: The SPA request for Study ACHN-490-007 was resubmitted based on Agency</cell></row><row><cell>feedback.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>September 12, 2013: The Agency communicated agreement with the Special Protocol</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Assessment to the Applicant.</cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>September 16, 2014: Study 007 was initiated.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">November 4, 2014: A Type B Clinical Development Meeting was held between the Applicant</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">and the Agency. The Applicant proposed to conduct an uncontrolled study in parallel with Study</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">007, in patients who were ineligible for this randomized trial due to resistance to the colistin</cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>20 21</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865 Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>comparator or infection at an excluded body site. The Agency provided input on an alternative development pathway based on a single Phase 3 cUTI trial in conjunction with data from the</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs is responsible for drug substance manufacturing, packaging, release testing and stability testing, and is responsible for drug product manufacturing, packaging, labeling, release and stability testing. In addition, several other sites are involved in the drug substance testing, and the drug product testing, labeling and secondary packaging.</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>24</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 1 -Patients with Uropathogens that Developed Decreased Susceptibility or Resistance to Study Drug Received by Pathogen -mMITT Population, Study 009</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 42 ;</head><label>42</label><figDesc>Study 009 CSR</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs rate for the unbound fraction, indicating plazomicin is eliminated primarily via glomerular filtration and active renal secretion is not a major elimination pathway.</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>28</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table of Clinical Studies</head><label></label><figDesc>Please note the following sponsor Table of Studies which highlight all the studies to date with plazomicin. These include:</figDesc><table><row><cell>5.1. [</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs -Two phase 3 studies; one in cUTI and the other in subjects with CRE-associated BSI and HABP/VABP infections (Studies 007 and 009)</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>Table 2 -Completed Phase 2 and Phase 3 Clinical Studies of Plazomicin in Patients With Complicated Urinary Tract Infection, Including Acute Pyelonephritis</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note>Source: Table 1, Applicant Tabular Listing of Clinical Studies</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head>Table 3 -Completed Phase 3 Clinical Study of Plazomicin in Patients With Carbapenem- Resistant Enterobacteriaceae Infection SourceTable 4 -Phase 1 Completed Studies (Pre-NDA Submission) of Plazomicin in Heathy Subjects or Otherwise Healthy Subjects with Renal ImpairmentTable 3 ,</head><label>343</label><figDesc>: Table 2, Applicant Tabular Listing of Clinical Studies Applicant Tabular Listing of Clinical Studies Note: Clinical Study Reports for two studies were submitted after the NDA had been submitted to the Agency -Study 010 (Mass Balance Study) and Study 011 (Metformin Drug Interaction Study). See the table below.</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head>Table 5 -Phase 1 Completed Studies (Post NDA Submission) of Plazomicin in Heathy Subjects</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Site Location</cell><cell>Number of</cell><cell>Study Design</cell><cell>Dose</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Subjects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Study 010</cell><cell>Celerion,</cell><cell>6 subjects</cell><cell>Non-randomized</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell></row><row><cell>Mass Balance</cell><cell>Nebraska, USA</cell><cell>enrolled and</cell><cell>mass balance</cell><cell>15mg/kg single</cell></row><row><cell>Study</cell><cell></cell><cell>completed study</cell><cell>study</cell><cell>30-minute</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>infusion</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(radiolabeled)</cell></row><row><cell>Study 011</cell><cell>Celerion,</cell><cell>16 subjects</cell><cell>Two sequence,</cell><cell>Metformin 850</cell></row><row><cell>Metformin Drug</cell><cell>Nebraska, USA</cell><cell>enrolled and</cell><cell>two period,</cell><cell>mg(Period 1)</cell></row><row><cell>Interaction</cell><cell></cell><cell>completed study</cell><cell>crossover study</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Study</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Metformin 850</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>mg + Plazomicin</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>15mg/kg single</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>30-minute</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>infusion (period</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>2) Or vice versa</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>Table 6 Overview of Study Drug Dosing, Study 009</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Estimated CLcr (mL/min)</cell><cell>Plazomicin IV</cell><cell>Meropenem IV</cell><cell>Levofloxacin PO</cell></row><row><cell>˃60</cell><cell>15 mg/kg q24h</cell><cell>1.0 g q8h</cell><cell>500 mg q24h</cell></row><row><cell>˃50 to 60</cell><cell>12 mg/kg q24h</cell><cell>1.0 g q8h</cell><cell>500 mg q24h</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;40 to 50</cell><cell>10 mg/kg q24h</cell><cell>1.0 g q12h</cell><cell>250 mg q24h</cell></row><row><cell>&gt;30 to 40</cell><cell>8 mg/kg q 24h</cell><cell>1.0 g q12h</cell><cell>250 mg q24h</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell><cell></cell><cell>Discontinue Study Drug</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>CLcrcreatinine clearance; IVintravenous; POoral; q8hevery 8 hours; q12hevery 12 hours; q24hevery 24 hours. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report Important inclusion criteria included age ≥ 18 years old, IBW≤ 150 kg, pyuria, signs and symptoms of cUTI or AP (included fever, flank pain, lower abdominal pain, CVA tenderness on exam, dysuria, nausea or vomiting), predisposing condition in case of cUTI (such as BPH or presence of indwelling catheter), creatinine clearance &gt; 30 ml/min, and a urine culture taken within 36 hours of starting of study drug.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 7 Core Symptoms of cUTI, Study 009</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>eCRF Field</cell><cell>Absent</cell><cell>Mild</cell><cell>Moderate</cell><cell>Severe</cell></row><row><cell>Flank pain</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Suprapubic pain</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Dysuria</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Frequency</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row><row><cell>Urgency</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>3</cell></row></table><note>eCRFelectronic Case Report Form. Source: Study 009 Clinical Study Report Efficacy was based on Clinical and Microbiological response at both the Day 5 and TOC visits. Clinical response at the various timepoints was assessed as noted in the following Applicant tables.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_31"><head>Table 8 Clinical Response Categories and Corresponding Criteria at Day 5 and EOIV Visits, Study 009</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Patients meeting any of the following criteria will be classified as failure:  Lack of improvement in core baseline symptoms of cUTI or development of new core symptoms of cUTI  AE requiring the discontinuation of study drug and the patient required alternative nonstudy antibiotic therapy for the current cUTIIndeterminate: Insufficient data are available to allow an evaluation of clinical outcome for any reason AEadverse event; EOIVend of intravenous therapy. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_32"><head>Table 9 Clinical Response Categories and Corresponding Criteria at the TOC Visit, Study 009</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_33"><head>Table 10 -</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Postbaseline Symptom Status</cell></row></table><note>Postbaseline Symptom Response Relative to Baseline Status, Study 009Subjects who discontinued IV therapy due to an AE or use of nonstudy systemic antimicrobial therapy for the cUTI/AP were designated as failures regardless of clinical symptom change. Microbiologic responses were based on both per pathogen and per patient response</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 11 Per-Pathogen Microbiological Outcome Categories at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC, Study 009</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell></row></table><note>CFUcolonyforming-units; EOIVend of intravenous therapy; TOCtest of cure. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>Table 12</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Category</cell></row></table><note>Per-Patient Microbiological Outcome Categories at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC, Study 009</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_40"><head>Table 15 : Patient Disposition -ITT Population, Study 009</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell cols="2">Meropenem All Patients</cell></row><row><cell>Disposition</cell><cell>(N306)</cell><cell>(N303)</cell><cell>(N609)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Completed study drug treatment a</cell><cell>229 (74.8)</cell><cell>227 (74.9)</cell><cell>456 (74.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Randomized but not treated</cell><cell>3 (1.0)</cell><cell>2 (0.7)</cell><cell>5 (0.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Prematurely discontinued study drug (IV or oral)</cell><cell>74 (24.2)</cell><cell>74 (24.4)</cell><cell>148 (24.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Prematurely discontinued IV study drug</cell><cell>70 (22.9)</cell><cell>70 (23.1)</cell><cell>140 (23.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Primary reason for prematurely discontinuing IV study drug</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lack of study-qualifying baseline urine culture</cell><cell>60 (19.6)</cell><cell>61 (20.1)</cell><cell>121 (19.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Adverse event</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>6 (2.0)</cell><cell>10 (1.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Investigator decision</cell><cell>2 (0.7)</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>3 (0.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Withdrawal of consent</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>2 (0.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Insufficient therapeutic effect</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>1 (0.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Pregnancy or nursing</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>1 (0.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Significant patient noncompliance</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>2 (0.7)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>2 (0.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Death</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head>Table 16 Study Populations Overall and by Randomization Stratification Factors, Study 009</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell><cell>All Patients</cell></row><row><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row></table><note>AP=acute pyelonephritis; CE=clinically evaluable; cUTI=complicated urinary tract infection; IV=intravenous; IXRS= interactive voice-or web-based response system; PK=pharmacokinetic; ME=microbiologically evaluable; N=Number of patients randomized; n=Number of patients in the specified category; TOC=test of cure. Note: Percentages are calculated as 100×(n/N).a A patient was considered randomized when a randomization transaction was recorded in the IXRS. b Randomized patients who received any amount of study drug. c Patients in the MITT Population who had ≥1 qualified pathogen from a study- qualifying baseline urine culture. d Randomized patients who received any amount of IV study drug. e Randomized patients who received ≥1 dose of plazomicin and had ≥1 quantifiable plasma concentration(s)available. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_46"><head>Table 22 Reviewer's summary of baseline characteristics, mMITT population, Study 009</head><label>22</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell></row><row><cell>Demographic Parameters</cell><cell>(N=191)</cell><cell>(N=197)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>84 (44.0%)</cell><cell>99 (50.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>107 (56.0%)</cell><cell>98 (49.8%)</cell></row><row><cell>Age</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean years (SD)</cell><cell>58.8</cell><cell>60.0</cell></row><row><cell>Median (years)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Min, max (years)</cell><cell>18,88</cell><cell>18, 87</cell></row><row><cell>Age Group</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>≥ 18 -&lt; 65 years</cell><cell>101 (52.9%)</cell><cell>95 (48.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>≥ 65 years</cell><cell>90 (47.1%)</cell><cell>102 (51.8%)</cell></row><row><cell>Race</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>189 (99%)</cell><cell>197 (100%)</cell></row><row><cell>Black or African American</cell><cell>1 (0.5%)</cell><cell>0 (0%)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>1 (0.5%)</cell><cell>0 (0%)</cell></row><row><cell>Multiple</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Ethnicity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Hispanic or Latino</cell><cell>2 (1.0%)</cell><cell>3 (1.5%)</cell></row><row><cell>Not Hispanic or Latino</cell><cell>188 (98.0%)</cell><cell>193 (98.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>Not Reported</cell><cell>1 (0.5%)</cell><cell>1 (0.5%)</cell></row><row><cell>Region</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Region 1</cell><cell>4 (2.1%)</cell><cell>2 (1%)</cell></row><row><cell>Region 2</cell><cell>187 (97.9%)</cell><cell>195 (99%)</cell></row><row><cell>Infection Type</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AP</cell><cell>84 (44%)</cell><cell>78 (39.6%)</cell></row><row><cell>cUTI</cell><cell>107 (56%)</cell><cell>119 (60.4%)</cell></row><row><cell>Indwelling Catheter</cell><cell>25 (13.1%)</cell><cell>26 (13.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Males with history of urinary retention</cell><cell>47.7%</cell><cell>46.2%</cell></row><row><cell>TBW:IBW</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&lt;125%</cell><cell>120 (62.8%)</cell><cell>117 (59.4%)</cell></row><row><cell>≥125%</cell><cell>71 (37.2%)</cell><cell>80 (40.6%)</cell></row><row><cell>Creatinine Clearance (mL/min)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>≤30</cell><cell>0 (0%)</cell><cell>3 (1.5%)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Region 1-Mexico, Spain, United States; Region 2-Bulgaria, Czech Republic, Estonia, Georgia, Hungary, Latvia, Poland,Romania, Russia, Serbia, Ukraine. Resistant, based on central laboratory Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute breakpoints.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_47"><head>Table 23 Most frequent Uropathogens Identified from Baseline Urine Cultures -mMITT Population, Study 009</head><label>23</label><figDesc>Baseline clinical signs and symptoms were as expected for a cUTI trial. Interestingly, 20% and 17% of plazomicin and meropenem subjects, respectively had urosepsis at baseline (as determined by SIRS criteria). 13% and 12% of subjects had bacteremia at baseline. Subjects in the meropenem arm had slightly more systemic signs of AP at baseline (such as nausea, vomiting, chills, rigors, and fever) than did plazomicin.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell></row><row><cell>Baseline Uropathogen</cell><cell>(N191)</cell><cell>(N197)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Gram-negative aerobes</cell><cell>189 (99.0)</cell><cell>193 (98.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Enterobacteriaceae</cell><cell>189 (99.0)</cell><cell>193 (98.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-R</cell><cell>51 (27.0)</cell><cell>50 (25.9)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>50 (26.5)</cell><cell>57 (29.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R</cell><cell>9 (4.8)</cell><cell>6 (3.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Escherichia coli</cell><cell>126 (66.0)</cell><cell>137 (69.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-R</cell><cell>23 (18.3)</cell><cell>26 (19.0)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>20 (15.9)</cell><cell>28 (20.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell></row><row><cell>Klebsiella pneumoniae</cell><cell>33 (17.3)</cell><cell>43 (21.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-R</cell><cell>18 (54.5)</cell><cell>20 (46.5)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>20 (60.6)</cell><cell>26 (60.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>1 (2.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Enterobacter cloacae</cell><cell>15 (7.9)</cell><cell>3 (1.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-R</cell><cell>5 (33.3)</cell><cell>2 (66.7)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>7 (46.7)</cell><cell>2 (66.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell><cell>0 (0)</cell></row><row><cell>Proteus mirabilis</cell><cell>11 (5.8)</cell><cell>7 (3.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-R</cell><cell>5 (45.5)</cell><cell>3 (42.9)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>3 (27.3)</cell><cell>1 (14.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R</cell><cell>7 (63.6)</cell><cell>5 (71.4)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Resistant, based on central laboratory Clinical and Laboratory Standards Institute breakpoints. Aminoglycoside-R=Not</cell></row><row><cell>susceptible to any of amikacin, gentamicin, or tobramycin.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-R=Not susceptible to imipenem or doripenem.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">ESBL defined as a minimum inhibitory concentration =2 mcg/mL to any of ceftazidime, aztreonam, or ceftriaxone based on</cell></row><row><cell>central laboratory testing; Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Prior medical conditions and/or surgical procedures were reported in approximately 90% of</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">patients in the mMITT. Overall, the nature of medical and surgical histories was comparable</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">between treatment groups and consistent with an older population with cUTI. The most</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">common medical conditions (by PT) were hypertension (156/388 [40.2%]) and benign prostatic</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">hyperplasia (BPH; 104/388 [26.8%]). Nineteen [10.0%] and 39 [19.8%] patients in the</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">plazomicin and meropenem groups, respectively, had type 1 or type 2 diabetes mellitus.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_51"><head>Table 30 Composite of Microbiological Eradication and Clinical Cure Rate, and Individual Components at Day 5 and TOC Visits, mMITT Population, Study 009</head><label>30</label><figDesc>As can be noted from above, at Day 5, the small difference in Composite Cure is reflective of similar Clinical Cure and Microbiological Eradication rates in both arms. At TOC, the large difference in Composite Cure is primarily driven by a large drop off in Microbiologic Eradication in the meropenem arm. The reason behind this drop in microbiological eradication is unclear though not necessarily without precedent. In the cUTI trial for meropenem-vaborbactam, there was a 20% drop in composite cure rates from the EOIV visit to the TOC visit, again driven mostly September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs https://www.accessdata.fda.gov/drugsatfda_docs/nda/2017/209776Orig1s000MedR.pdf). Still, it's</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Timepoint Response</cell><cell>(N=191)</cell><cell>(N=197)</cell><cell>Difference (95% CI)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Day 5</cell><cell>Composite</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cure</cell><cell>168 (88.0)</cell><cell>180 (91.4)</cell><cell>-3.4 (-10.0, 3.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Failure</cell><cell>20 (10.5)</cell><cell>15 (7.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>3 (1.6)</cell><cell>2 (1.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Clinical</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cure</cell><cell>171 (89.5)</cell><cell>182 (92.4)</cell><cell>-2.9 (-9.1, 3.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Failure</cell><cell>17 (8.9)</cell><cell>13 (6.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>3 (1.6)</cell><cell>2 (1.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Microbiological</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Eradication</cell><cell>188 (98.4)</cell><cell>193 (98.0)</cell><cell>0.5 (-3.1, 4.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Persistence</cell><cell>3 (1.6)</cell><cell>2 (1.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 (1.0)</cell></row><row><cell>TOC</cell><cell>Composite</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cure</cell><cell>156 (81.7)</cell><cell>138 (70.1)</cell><cell>11.6 (2.7, 20.3)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Failure</cell><cell>29 (15.2)</cell><cell>51 (25.9)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>6 (3.1)</cell><cell>8 (4.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Clinical</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cure</cell><cell>170 (89.0)</cell><cell>178 (90.4)</cell><cell>-1.4 (-7.9, 5.2)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Failure</cell><cell>17 (8.9)</cell><cell>12 (6.1)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>4 (2.1)</cell><cell>7 (3.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Microbiological</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Eradication</cell><cell>171 (89.5)</cell><cell>147 (74.6)</cell><cell>14.9 (7.0, 22.7)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Persistence</cell><cell>14 (7.3)</cell><cell>41 (20.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate</cell><cell>6 (3.1)</cell><cell>9 (4.6)</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Notes: Difference = difference in proportion (plazomicin -meropenem). Confidence interval is calculated</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">using the Newcombe method with continuity correction. Missing outcomes are categorized as</cell></row><row><cell>indeterminate.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: Statistical reviewer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">by microbiologic recurrence (FDA Clinical Review;</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_52"><head>Table 31 : Composite of Microbiological Response and Clinical Response at Day 5, EOIV, and TOC Visits, ME Population, Study 009</head><label>31</label><figDesc>Source: Study 009 Clinical Study Report, .</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_53"><head>Table 32 cUTI Composite Cure Rate, mMITT subgroup analysis, Study 009</head><label>32</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell><cell cols="2">Difference Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Day 5</cell><cell>Day 5</cell><cell></cell><cell>TOC</cell><cell>TOC</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N=191</cell><cell>N=197</cell><cell></cell><cell>N=191</cell><cell>N=197</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>All</cell><cell cols="3">168 (88%) 180 (91.4%) -3.4%</cell><cell>156</cell><cell cols="2">138 (70.1%) 11.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(81.7%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Age (years)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&lt; 65</cell><cell>93/101</cell><cell>88/95</cell><cell>-0.5%</cell><cell>90/101</cell><cell>68/95</cell><cell>17.5%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(92.1%)</cell><cell>(92.6%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(89.1%)</cell><cell>(71.6%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>≥ 65</cell><cell>75/90</cell><cell>92/102</cell><cell>-6.9%</cell><cell>66/90</cell><cell>70/102</cell><cell>4.7%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(83.3%)</cell><cell>(90.2%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(73.3%)</cell><cell>(68.6%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Sex</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>73/84</cell><cell>87/99</cell><cell>-1.0%</cell><cell>65/84</cell><cell>68/99</cell><cell>8.7%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(86.9%)</cell><cell>(87.9%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(77.4%)</cell><cell>(68.7%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>95/107</cell><cell>93/98</cell><cell>-6.1%</cell><cell>91/107</cell><cell>70/98</cell><cell>13.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(88.8%)</cell><cell>(94.9%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(85.0%)</cell><cell>(71.4%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ESBL</cell><cell>43/50</cell><cell>53/57</cell><cell>-7.0%</cell><cell>36/50</cell><cell>37/57</cell><cell>7.1%</cell></row><row><cell>Pathogens</cell><cell>(86%)</cell><cell>(93.0%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(72%)</cell><cell>(64.9%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CRE</cell><cell>8/9</cell><cell>6/6 (100%)</cell><cell>-11.1%</cell><cell>6/9</cell><cell cols="2">4/6 (66.7%) 0%</cell></row><row><cell>Pathogens</cell><cell>(88.9%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(66.7%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Bacteremia</cell><cell>19/25</cell><cell>21/23</cell><cell>-15.3%</cell><cell>18/25</cell><cell>13/23</cell><cell>15.5%</cell></row><row><cell>at baseline</cell><cell>(76%)</cell><cell>(91.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(72%)</cell><cell>(56.5%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AG Non-</cell><cell>47/51</cell><cell cols="2">47/50 (94%) -1.8%</cell><cell>35/51</cell><cell cols="2">30/50 (60%) 8.6%</cell></row><row><cell>susceptible</cell><cell>(92.2%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(68.6%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Renal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Function</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(mL/min)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>≤30</cell><cell>0/0</cell><cell>2/3 (66.7%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>0/0</cell><cell>2/3 (66.7%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;30-60</cell><cell>51/61</cell><cell>65/71</cell><cell>-7.9%</cell><cell>43/61</cell><cell>47/71</cell><cell>4.3%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(83.6%)</cell><cell>(91.5%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(70.5%)</cell><cell>(66.2%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;60-90</cell><cell>61/70</cell><cell cols="2">69/75 (92%) -4.9%</cell><cell>59/70</cell><cell>52/75</cell><cell>15%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(87.1%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(84.3%)</cell><cell>(69.3%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;90-120</cell><cell>38/40</cell><cell>33/35</cell><cell>0.7%</cell><cell>37/40</cell><cell cols="2">28/35 (80%) 12.5%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(95%)</cell><cell>(94.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(92.5%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>&gt;120</cell><cell>16/17</cell><cell>9/10 (90%)</cell><cell>4.1%</cell><cell>16/17</cell><cell>7/10 (70%)</cell><cell>24.1%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(94.1%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(94.1%)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Missing?</cell><cell>2</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell><cell>1</cell><cell>2</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>AP</cell><cell>73/84</cell><cell>72/78</cell><cell>-5.4%</cell><cell>72/84</cell><cell>56/78</cell><cell>13.9%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(86.9%)</cell><cell>(92.3%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(85.7%)</cell><cell>(71.8%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>cUTI</cell><cell>95/107</cell><cell>108/119</cell><cell>-2.0%</cell><cell>84/107</cell><cell>82/119</cell><cell>9.6%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(88.8%)</cell><cell>(90.8%)</cell><cell></cell><cell>(78.5%)</cell><cell>(68.9%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_55"><head>Table 33 : Microbiological Eradication Rate at TOC by Baseline Pathogen, mMITT Population, Study 009</head><label>33</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Pathogen</cell><cell>Plazomicin n/N (%)</cell><cell>Meropenem n/N (%)</cell></row><row><cell>All Enterobacteriaceae</cell><cell cols="2">177/198 (89.4) 157/208 (75.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-non-susceptible</cell><cell>41/52 (78.9)</cell><cell>35/51 (68.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-non-susceptible</cell><cell>7/9 (77.8)</cell><cell>5/6 (83.3)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL-producing</cell><cell>42/51 (82.4)</cell><cell>45/60 (75.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Escherichia coli</cell><cell cols="2">120/128 (93.8) 106/142 (74.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-non-susceptible</cell><cell>20/23 (87.0)</cell><cell>16/26 (61.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-non-susceptible</cell><cell>---</cell><cell>---</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL-producing</cell><cell>18/20 (90.0)</cell><cell>19/28 (67.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Klebsiella pneumoniae</cell><cell>27/33 (81.8)</cell><cell>32/43 (74.4)</cell></row><row><cell>Aminoglycoside-non-susceptible</cell><cell>14/18 (77.8)</cell><cell>15/20 (75)</cell></row><row><cell>Carbapenem-non-susceptible</cell><cell>---</cell><cell>1/1 (100)</cell></row><row><cell>ESBL-producing</cell><cell>15/20 (75)</cell><cell>20/26 (76.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Proteus mirabilis</cell><cell>9/11 (81.8)</cell><cell>4/7 (57.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Proteus vulgaris</cell><cell>1/1 (100)</cell><cell>0/1 (0)</cell></row><row><cell>Enterobacter cloacae</cell><cell>13/16 (81.3)</cell><cell>3/3 (100)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Note: Aminoglycoside-non-susceptible: not susceptible to amikacin, gentamicin, or tobramycin. Carbapenem-non-</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">susceptible: not susceptible to imipenem or doripenem (while susceptible to meropenem).</cell></row><row><cell>Source: Statistical reviewer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_57"><head>Table 34 : Microbiological Eradication Rate at TOC, Based on Two Different Criteria, mMITT Population, Study 009 Microbiological Eradication</head><label>34</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(N=191)</cell><cell>(N=197)</cell><cell>Difference (95% CI)</cell></row><row><cell>Criterion</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10 4 CFU/mL</cell><cell>171 (89.5)</cell><cell>147 (74.6)</cell><cell>14.9 (7.0, 22.7)</cell></row><row><cell>10 3 CFU/mL</cell><cell>167 (87.4)</cell><cell>142 (72.1)</cell><cell>15.4 (7.5, 23.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Source: Statistical reviewer</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Dose/Dose Response</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_59"><head>Table 35 Demographics and Baseline Characteristics (ITT Population), Study 002</head><label>35</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Levofloxacin</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10 mg/kg</cell><cell>15 mg/kg</cell><cell>750 mg</cell><cell>All Patients</cell></row><row><cell>(N=22)</cell><cell>(N=76)</cell><cell>(N=47)</cell><cell>(N=145)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_60"><head>Table 36 : Microbiological Response at TOC (MITT and ME Populations), Study 002</head><label>36</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>By-Patient</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Population</cell><cell>Microbiological</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Levofloxacin</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Response</cell><cell>10 mg/kg</cell><cell>15 mg/kg</cell><cell>750 mg</cell></row><row><cell>MITT</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>12</cell><cell>51</cell><cell>29</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Eradication, n (%)</cell><cell>6 (50.0)</cell><cell>31 (60.8)</cell><cell>17 (58.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>(21.1-78.9)</cell><cell>(46.1-74.2)</cell><cell>(38.9-76.5)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Non-eradication, n (%)</cell><cell>1 (8.3)</cell><cell>5 (9.8)</cell><cell>4 (13.8)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Indeterminate, n (%)</cell><cell>5 (41.7)</cell><cell>15 (29.4)</cell><cell>8 (27.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Difference (95% CI) a</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>−2.2 (−272-22.9)</cell></row><row><cell>ME</cell><cell>N</cell><cell>7</cell><cell>35</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Eradication, n (%)</cell><cell>6 (85.7)</cell><cell>31 (88.6)</cell><cell>17 (81.0)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>95% CI</cell><cell>(42.1-99.6)</cell><cell>(73.3-96.8)</cell><cell>(58.1-94.6)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Non-eradication, n (%)</cell><cell>1 (14.3)</cell><cell>4 (11.4)</cell><cell>4 (19.0)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_66"><head>Table 39 Adult Plazomicin Exposure by Dose and Duration of Exposure in Completed Phase 1, 2, and 3 Studies</head><label>39</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_67"><head>Table 40 Plazomicin Exposure in Healthy Subjects by Dose and Dosing Regimen, Studies 002 and 009cUTI Studies-Study 002 and Study 009</head><label>40</label><figDesc>In the safety population of the cUTI studies, the median duration of plazomicin therapy was 5 days. 12% of plazomicin subjects received &lt; 4 days of therapy. No subject received &gt; 7 days of therapy. Most durations of therapy were either 4 or 7 days, corresponding with general switches to oral therapy. See the table below.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_68"><head>Table 41 Intravenous Study Drug Exposure-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009)Relevant characteristics of the safety population: cUTI studies-Study 002 and Study 009</head><label>41</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_70"><head>Table 43 : Demographics and Baseline Characteristics-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009Adequacy of the safety database: cUTI studies -Study 002 and 009</head><label>43</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_74"><head>Table 45 Incidence of Serious Adverse Events by Preferred Term-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009Dropouts and/or Discontinuations Due to Adverse Effects cUTI Studies-Studies 009 and 002</head><label>45</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row><row><cell>8.4.2.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_75"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs measurements &lt;30 mL/min during IV treatment. Of the 6 renal discontinuations in the plazomicin arm, four of the subjects started with baseline creatinine clearance between 30-40 mL/min. See the discussion of nephrotoxicity in section 8.5</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>104</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_76"><head>Table 46 : Adverse Events Leading to Premature Discontinuation of Intravenous Study Drug- Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009Significant Adverse Events cUTI studies -Studies 009 and 002</head><label>46</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (6)</cell></row><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_78"><head>Table 47 : Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events Reported in at Least 1% of Patients in Either Treatment Group by PT (by Decreasing Frequency in Plazomicin Group) -Safety Population, Study 009</head><label>47</label><figDesc>3%) subjects in the plazomicin and meropenem arms, respectively, were noted to have TEAEs thought to be possibly related to study drug. In terms of such TEAEs, in the plazomicin arm they were concentrated within a few categories-typical adverse events (diarrhea, headache, etc.), renal injury (blood creatinine increased, renal failure, etc.) and possible allergic /local reactions (injection site phlebitis and erythema, papular rash, etc.).</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell><cell>All Patients</cell></row><row><cell>Preferred Term</cell><cell>(N=303)</cell><cell>(N=301)</cell><cell>(N=604)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Patients with any TEAE</cell><cell>59 (19.5)</cell><cell>65 (21.6)</cell><cell>124 (20.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypertension</cell><cell>7 (2.3)</cell><cell>7 (2.3)</cell><cell>14 (2.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Headache</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>9 (3.0)</cell><cell>13 (2.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Diarrhoea</cell><cell>7 (2.3)</cell><cell>5 (1.7)</cell><cell>12 (2.0)</cell></row><row><cell>Nausea</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>8 (1.3)</cell></row><row><cell>Vomiting</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>3 (1.0)</cell><cell>7 (1.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Anaemia</cell><cell>1 (0.3)</cell><cell>4 (1.3)</cell><cell>5 (0.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Dizziness</cell><cell>2 (0.7)</cell><cell>3 (1.0)</cell><cell>5 (0.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Hypotension</cell><cell>3 (1.0)</cell><cell>2 (0.7)</cell><cell>5 (0.8)</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">N=number of patients in the Safety Population; n=number of patients in the specified category; PT=preferred term;</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">TEAE=treatment-emergent adverse event. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Only 18 (5.9%) and 16 (5.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_79"><head>Table 50 Patients with at Least a Two-Grade Increase from Baseline in CTCAE Grade by Hematology Central Laboratory Parameter -Safety Population, Study 009</head><label>50</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</cell></row><row><cell>Serum Chemistry/Liver Function</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_81"><head>Table 51 Patients with at Least a Two-Grade Increase from Baseline in CTCAE Grade by Chemistry Central Laboratory Parameter -Safety Population, Study 009</head><label>51</label><figDesc>Terminology Criteria for Adverse Events (version 4.0); N=Number of patients in the Safety Population; N1=Number of patients with a baseline and postbaseline value specified for the specified laboratory parameter; n=Number of patients in the specified category; SGOT=serum glutamic oxaloacetic transaminase; SGPT=serum glutamic pyruvate transaminase. Notes: Percentages are calculated as 100×(n/N1). Baseline is defined as the last laboratory measurement from the central laboratory prior to the first dose of study drug administered. Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</figDesc><table><row><cell>CTCAE=Common</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_84"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ECGs were performed pre-dose and 10-20 minutes after study drug infusion. In general, ECGs remained stable over the course of drug infusion. In study 002, ECGs were performed pre-and post Day 1 dose and as needed at STFU. No clinically significant ECG changes were noted No ECGs were performed in Study 009.] 8.4.7. QT[The applicant conducted a TQT study in which 15mg/kg and 20mg/kg doses of plazomicin were compared to a positive control (moxifloxacin) as well as placebo in 56 healthy subjects. This study was evaluated by the Agency's Interdisciplinay Review Team for QT studies. This committee concluded that the study was adequate and that at the doses tested plazomicin did not prolong the QTc interval to any clinically relevant extent.]</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>8.5.</cell><cell>Analysis of Submission-Specific Safety Issues</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">8.5.1. Nephrotoxicity</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">[Aminoglycosides as a class have long been associated with nephrotoxicity, particularly with</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">increased duration of dose/larger dose amounts. The applicant attempted to quantify the</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">risk/degree of nephrotoxicity with a combination of assessments, including recording of</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">nephrotoxic adverse events and following/categorizing changes in serum creatinine levels.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">cUTI Study 009</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">8.4.6. Electrocardiograms (ECGs)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">[In Study 004, 8.4.8. Immunogenicity</cell><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">[Not Applicable]</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>115</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Version date: September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_86"><head>Table 52 Patients With Any Serum Creatinine Increase of 0.5 mg/dL or Greater Above Baseline-Safety Population, Studies 002, and 009</head><label>52</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Study 002</cell><cell></cell><cell>Study 009</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>cUTI</cell><cell></cell><cell>cUTI</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Serum</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Levofloxacin</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell></row><row><cell>Creatinine</cell><cell>N=74,</cell><cell>N=44,</cell><cell>N=303;</cell><cell>N=301;</cell></row><row><cell>Increase</cell><cell>N1=72</cell><cell>N1=41</cell><cell>N1=300</cell><cell>N1=297</cell></row><row><cell>mg/dL</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell></row><row><cell>≥0.5</cell><cell>4 (5.6%)</cell><cell>1 (2.4%)</cell><cell>21 (7.0%)</cell><cell>12 (4.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>≥1.0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>5 (1.7%)</cell><cell>3 (1.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>≥2.0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 (0.7%)</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>≥3.5</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1 (0.3%)</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>≥4.0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1 (0.3%)</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">N1=number of patients with a baseline value and a value at the specified time point for serum</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">creatinine from the central laboratory</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Source: Adapted from Summary of Clinical Safety</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_87"><head>Table 53 RIFLE Classification of Renal Injury, Safety Population, Studies 002, and 009 Study 002 cUTI Study 009 cUTI RIFLE Classification Worst Postbaseline</head><label>53</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Levofloxacin</cell><cell>Plazomicin</cell><cell>Meropenem</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N=74,</cell><cell>N=44,</cell><cell>N=303;</cell><cell>N=301;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N1=72</cell><cell>N1=41</cell><cell>N1=300</cell><cell>N1=297</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell><cell>n/N1 (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Risk</cell><cell>8 (11.1%)</cell><cell>2 (4.9%)</cell><cell>16 (5.3%)</cell><cell>9 (3.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>Injury</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>1(2.4%)</cell><cell>3 (1.0%)</cell><cell>3 (1.0%)</cell></row><row><cell>Failure</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 (0.7%)</cell><cell>2 (0.7%)</cell></row><row><cell>Loss of</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Function</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ESRD</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">N1=number of patients with a baseline value and a value at the specified time point for serum</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">creatinine from the central laboratory</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Source: Adapted from Summary of Clinical Safety</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_88"><head>Table 54 Renal Recovery for Patients With Any Serum Creatinine Increase of 0.5 mg/dL or Greater Above Baseline While on Intravenous Study Drug-Safety Population, Studies 002 and 009)</head><label>54</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Summary of Clinical Safety</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_90"><head>Table 55 Patients with any &gt;= 0.5 mg/dL Increase from Baseline in Serum Creatinine by Baseline CLcr Category -Safety Population, Study 009</head><label>55</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Study 009, Clinical Study Report</cell></row><row><cell>8.5.2. Ototoxicity</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_91"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs subjects. Thus, the applicant attempted to gauge ototoxicity through the use of several inventories, including the Hearing Handicap Inventory Assessment (HHIA), the Tinnitus Handicap Inventory (THI), and Dizziness Handicap Inventory.</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>119</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_94"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>September 6, 2017 for all NDAs and BLAs ringing or buzzing in ears, or hearing. The patient's Dizziness Handicap Inventory, Tinnitus</figDesc><table><row><cell>NDA 210303/Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template</cell><cell>122</cell></row><row><cell>Version date:</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4282865</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 4282865</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 4282865 (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4) (b) (4)</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2">Page(s) has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">Page(s) has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7">Page(s) has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Page has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4">Page(s) has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 4282865 (b) (4)1 Page has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Page has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1">Page has been Withheld in Full as b4 (CCI/TS) immediately following this page</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>When looking at sex, TEAEs were comparable in incidence between the males and females in the plazomicin arm. Race could not be appropriately evaluated given that the vast majority of the subject population was white. In terms of disparities by baseline BMI, none were noted in the plazomicin arm between those with baseline BMI 18.5 -&lt;30 kg/m 2 and those with BMI ≥30 kg/m 2, and disparities between cUTI and AP were minimal in the plazomicin arm as well. Unsurprisingly, the incidence of TEAE increased in the plazomicin arm with increasing renal impairment. A similar trend was noted in the meropenem arm though to a lesser degree.] 8.7.</p><p>Specific Safety Studies/Clinical Trials <ref type="bibr">[</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Additional Safety Explorations</head><p>The phase 1 studies were briefly reviewed; notable findings are discussed below.</p><p>I both the drug interaction study with metformin (Study 011) as well as the lung penetration study (Study 003), dizziness was noted. In the metformin DDI study, three subjects had an onset of dizziness 9, 18, and 41 minutes, respectively, following start of concurrent dosing with plazomicin and metformin and had fasting blood glucose values of 91, 78, and 88 mg/dL measured within 20 minutes of onset of dizziness. These values were considered by the PI to be normal for fasting blood glucose via finger stick (greater than or equal to 70 mg/dL). Though hypoglycemia and/or hypotension may have contributed to the symptoms, a relationship to plazomicin cannot be excluded. In the 003 study, dizziness, somnolence and oral hypoaesthesia AEs were noted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.8.1.">Human Carcinogenicity or Tumor Development</head><p>[Not Applicable given the short duration of usage of aminoglycosides. Also, aminoglycosides as a class have not been associated with malignancy.]</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.8.2.">Human Reproduction and Pregnancy</head><p>[Per the protocol of study 009, pregnant subjects were not to be enrolled in the study. One 41year-old female subject with pyelonephritis was randomized to the plazomicin arm; she had a negative urine pregnancy test at baseline but then was found to have a positive serum pregnancy test on Day 3. Plazomicin was discontinued on Day 3, and the patient underwent a therapeutic abortion on Day 10 (was an unwanted pregnancy  Integrated Assessment of Safety [Plazomicin hails from the aminoglycoside class of antibiotics. This class has been extensively used for decades, and, thus, there is at least a general sense of some of the safety issues that may be anticipated with plazomicin.</p><p>Plazomicin's safety findings are in line with what was expected. In Study 009, diarrhea, headache, nausea, and vomiting were the most common adverse events and were present at rates similar to the comparator. These adverse events are typical of drug development trials and though they are certainly a source of discomfort for patients, they are also not particularly worrisome in a setting where a drug is expected to provide some basic benefit. Other "general" adverse events noted with plazomicin included dizziness and hypoaesthesia, particularly in the earlier phase 1 trials. It should be noted that early in clinical development, a possible link between hypotension and a rapid 10 minute plazomicin infusions was noted. Thus, the plazomicin infusion time was increased to 30 minutes, and subsequently the infusion was generally tolerated well.</p><p>Plazomicin does not appear to have any clinically significant QTc prolonging effects, and its effects on clinical laboratory parameters are expected (namely its effects on renal function parameters). It does not appear to have any significant hepatotoxic effects.</p><p>Plazomicin does appear to have a slight nephrotoxic effect. It appeared to be associated with creatinine increases/nephrotoxic adverse events at a rate higher than meropenem in Study 009, though most of the serum increases were mild and reversible.</p><p>Regardless, nothing was noted in the safety profile that suggested either bolstering or lessening the nephrotoxicity 'Warnings' labelling language typically associated with aminoglycosides. As has been discussed earlier, the Clinical Pharmacology review team has set a serum plazomicin trough cutoff of 3 mcg/ml for nephrotoxicity monitoring and subsequent dosing interval adjustments.</p><p>Plazomicin also cannot be ruled out of having ototoxic effects. The use of hearing inventories in study 009 did not highlight any real plazomicin-associated ototoxic effects, however outside analysis of PTA and ENG testing from the phase 1 studies could not definitively exclude ototoxic effects. Thus, typical class labelling language related to ototoxicity should likely remain.</p><p>Plazomicin was noted to have a disproportionate incidence of TEAEs in the elderly relative to the younger population and this should be noted in labelling Overall, nothing unexpected was noted in the safety profile of plazomicin and would not preclude approval of the drug, assuming the drug was associated also with significant clinical benefit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Advisory Committee Meeting and Other External Consultations</head><p>An Advisory Committee meeting was held on May 2, in which both the applicant and Agency presented the Study 009 and 007 findings in detail to a committee of experts composed of pediatric and adult Infectious Diseases physicians, statisticians, pharmacologists, and patient/industry representatives. Multiple public speakers also presented their viewpoints.</p><p>The committee was asked to consider two questions:</p><p>1. Has the applicant provided substantial evidence of the safety and effectiveness of plazomicin for the treatment of complicated urinary tract infections in patients with limited or no treatment options? If yes, please provide any recommendations regarding labeling. If no, what additional studies/analyses are needed?</p><p>The committee voted 15-0 in favor of plazomicin on this question. In general, members felt that substantial evidence was presented (NI margin met), particularly in the setting of an unmet need. However, there was concern by many members that the issues regarding plazomicin trough measurements for the prevention of nephrotoxicity had not been fully explored/resolved and would need to be explicitly explained in labelling. Some members advocated for trough monitoring in all subjects to simplify use and one member suggested usage of the drug be restricted to Infectious Diseases physicians. There were also recommendations to consider a PMR in order to address the trough issue. Members also pointed out that labelling should mention that safety data (such as ototoxicity data) was limited and highlight limitations of the trial, including the homogenous racial makeup. Members pointed out that pediatric data and data in immunosuppressed individuals was necessary.</p><p>2. Has the applicant provided substantial evidence of the safety and effectiveness of plazomicin for the treatment of bloodstream infections in patients with limited or no treatment options? If yes, please provide any recommendations regarding labeling. If no, what additional studies/analyses are needed?</p><p>The committee voted 11-4 against plazomicin on this question. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>12.Postmarketing Requirements and Commitments</head><p>The following post marketing studies are suggested:  <ref type="figure">------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>--This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. <ref type="figure">---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">for all NDAs and BLAs Table 56 Overall Summary of Treatment-Emergent Adverse Events, by Age Group, for the Pooled Complicated Urinary Tract Infection Studies-Safety Population</title>
		<idno>ID: 4282865</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2017-09-06" />
			<biblScope unit="page">9</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>NDA 210303/Clinical Review Shrimant Mishra, MD MPH Zemdri (plazomicin) Injection CDER Clinical Review Template 124 Version date</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">N1=number of patients with a baseline and postbaseline value for serum creatinine from the central laboratory; n=number of patients in the specified category. Percentages are calculated as 100 × (n/N) for AEs. Patients reporting a particular adverse event (Preferred Term) more than once are counted only once by Preferred Term. a Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Event. b Percentages are calculated as 100 × (n/N1) for serum creatinine increase ≥ 0.5 mg/dL above baseline</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Note: N=number of patients in the Safety Population</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Summary of Clinical Safety</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
