<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="figure">BENEFIT ASSESSMENT ....................................</ref> <ref type="figure">................................................................................................</ref> <ref type="figure">...............................................................................................................</ref> <ref type="figure">........................................................................................</ref> <ref type="figure">...........................................................................</ref> <ref type="figure">Guidelines....................................................................</ref></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Figures</head> <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1: Study Design ..........................................................................................</ref> <ref type="figure">................................................................................................</ref><p>. This recommendation is based on the Applicant failing to demonstrate efficacy in an</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">( b ) ( 4 )</formula><p>adequate and well-controlled study. However, this study does fulfill Pfizer's pediatric postmarketing requirements for NDA 21446 (LYRICA capsules) and NDA 22488 (LYRICA oral solution).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2">Risk Benefit Assessment</head><p>Risk Benefit Assessment efficacy was not demonstrated in adolescent patients with</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">(b) (4)</formula><p>fibromyalgia. The safety profile for pregabalin in the fibromyalgia studies in pediatric patients was generally consistent with the known profile for pregabalin in fibromyalgia adult studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit</head><p>Efficacy was not demonstrated in Study A0081180 (hereafter referred to as Study 1180), a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled, flexible-dose, 15-week study of pregabalin in 107 pediatric patients with fibromyalgia, age 12 to 17 years, at LYRICA total daily doses of 75-450 mg/day. The primary efficacy endpoint of change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain intensity (derived from an 11-point daily pain numeric rating scale) showed numerically greater improvement for the pregabalin-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients, but did not reach statistical significance. Based on Pfizer's prespecified analysis, a treatment difference of was reported by the Applicant for pregabalin relative to placebo in endpoint mean pain score. Although sensitivity analyses (BOCF, mBOCF, LOCF, (b) (4) MMRM at Week 15) also showed greater numerical improvements for pregabalin compared to placebo, they were not statistically significant. The secondary endpoint Patient Global Impression of Change at Week 15 trended in favor of the pregabalin group. The FDA statistician, confirmed the Sponsor's overall findings and determined a (b) (4) treatment difference of for the primary endpoint.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk</head><p>In the LYRICA pediatric development program for fibromyalgia, a total of 84 patients were exposed to at least one dose of pregabalin during efficacy Study 1180 and openlabel extension safety Study A0081231 (hereafter referred to as Study 1231). In Study 1180, 54 patients were treated with pregabalin and in extension Study 1231 of the 63 patients treated with pregabalin, 33 subjects had previously been treated with pregabalin and 30 subjects with placebo. The safety data obtained from this limited number of patients revealed no new safety concerns in adolescents. The currently approved label for LYRICA for adults states that antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including LYRICA, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication. During Study 1180, there did not appear to be a significant difference in the incidence of suicidal ideation between the placebo and LYRICA treatment arms and no suicidal behavior was reported in either treatment group but given the small size of the study a treatment difference would not be expected. LYRICA treatment may cause weight gain in adults. During Study 1180, approximately 22% of subjects treated with pregabalin had weight gain compared to no subjects in the placebo arm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.3">Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.4">Recommendations for Postmarket Requirements and Commitments</head><p>Not applicable 2 Introduction and Regulatory Background</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Product Information</head><p>Pregabalin is described chemically as (S)-3-(aminomethyl)-5-methylhexanoic acid. The molecular formula is C 8 H 17 NO 2 and the molecular weight is 159.23. The chemical structure of pregabalin is:</p><p>Pregabalin binds with high affinity to the alpha-2-delta site (an auxiliary subunit of voltage-gated calcium channels) in central nervous system tissues. Although the mechanism of action of pregabalin has not been fully elucidated, results with genetically modified mice and with compounds structurally related to pregabalin (such as 9</p><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) gabapentin) suggest that binding to the alpha-2-delta subunit may be involved in pregabalin's anti-nociceptive and antiseizure effects in animals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Tables of Currently Available Treatments for Proposed Indications</head><p>There are currently no FDA approved products for the treatment of fibromyalgia in adolescents. FDA products approved for the treatment of fibromyalgia in adults include: pregabalin (Lyrica), duloxetine hydrochloride (Cymbalta) and milnacipran HCI (Savella).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Availability of Proposed Active Ingredient in the United States</head><p>Pregabalin is currently available in the United States as an approved treatment in adults for the management of neuropathic pain associated with diabetic peripheral neuropathy, postherpetic neuralgia, adjunctive therapy for adult patients with partial onset seizures, fibromyalgia, and neuropathic pain associated with spinal cord injury.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.4">Important Safety Issues With Consideration to Related Drugs</head><p>Lyrica is associated with the potentially serious safety issues of increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior (this risk applies to all antiepileptic drugs used for any indication), peripheral edema, dizziness and somnolence, angioedema (e.g. swelling of the throat, head and neck), hypersensitivity reactions (e.g. hives, dyspnea, and wheezing), and increased seizure frequency in patients with seizure disorders if Lyrica is rapidly discontinued.    patients there may only be two patients with monitoring by the C-SSRS. • The Division stated, "However, as an approved product that is already labeled with a suicide warning, the data you have will be sufficient to support filing your application and the adequacy of the data collected on suicidal ideation and behavior will be a review issue. If, after review of the data, we believe additional data on suicidality is needed for this patient population, we may consider available options such as a new postmarketing requirement." June 15, 2015 Submission of CSR study A0081180</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5">Summary of Presubmission Regulatory Activity Related to Submission</head><p>• Final CSR for Study A0081180 to fulfill the pediatric post marketing requirement submitted. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Ethics and Good Clinical Practices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Submission Quality and Integrity</head><p>This NDA was submitted in Electronic Common Technical Document (eCTD) format. There were no issues with the quality of the submission that affected my ability to complete this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Compliance with Good Clinical Practices</head><p>Randomized, double-blind efficacy Study 1180 and open-label safety Study 1231 were conducted in accordance with Good Clinical Practice (GCP) guidelines and in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki.</p><p>No inspections of clinical sites were requested. It was decided that inspections were unlikely to be informative for this application because no specific safety or efficacy concerns were identified in the failed efficacy study or open-label safety extension study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Financial Disclosures</head><p>Pfizer has submitted financial disclosure information on Study 1180 for the time period from the start of the study through one year after the completion of the study. Pfizer submitted Debarment Certification and FDA form 3454 certifying that none of the financial interests or arrangements described in 21 CFR Part 54 exists for 109 of the 114 clinical investigators who participated in the covered study listed above. Pfizer was unable to obtain a completed Financial Disclosure Form for three Clinical Investigators (Cathy Henderson, Caitlyn Eliza Toffler and Jesdit Diaz), despite multiple attempts. For those investigators no longer at the institution where the study was conducted, Pfizer is certifying that it has conducted reasonable efforts to contact the Clinical Investigator to obtain disclosable financial information. Pfizer identified no clinical investigators who $25,000.</p><p>A copy of the completed Clinical Investigator Financial Disclosure Review form follows.</p><p>were full-time or part-time employees of the sponsor of the covered study. Pfizer identified two clinical investigators that had financial information to report and provided FDA Form 3455, Disclosure Statement, for each of these clinical investigators who received payment in excess of (b) (6)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>13</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) Discuss whether the applicant has adequately disclosed financial interests/arrangements with clinical investigators as recommended in the guidance for industry Financial Disclosure by Clinical Investigators. Also discuss whether these interests/arrangements, investigators who are sponsor employees, or lack of disclosure despite due diligence raise questions about the integrity of the data:</p><p>-If not, why not (e.g., study design (randomized, blinded, objective endpoints), clinical investigator provided minimal contribution to study data) -If yes, what steps were taken to address the financial interests/arrangements (e.g., statistical analysis excluding data from clinical investigators with such interests/arrangements) Briefly summarize whether the disclosed financial interests/arrangements, the inclusion of investigators who are sponsor employees, or lack of disclosure despite due diligence affect the approvability of the application. investigators, received payments from Pfizer exceeding $25,000 for consulting and as honorarium. The FDA statistician repeated the analysis of the primary efficacy endpoint without subjects from these two investigators and the three investigators without a completed Financial Disclosure Form and found similar results with a numerically greater improvement for pregabalin compared to placebo. Therefore, it can be concluded that investigators with financial disclosure problems did not favorably influence the efficacy findings. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">Significant Efficacy/Safety Issues Related to Other Review Disciplines</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Chemistry Manufacturing and Controls</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Clinical Microbiology</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Preclinical Pharmacology/Toxicology</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Clinical Pharmacology</head><p>A detailed discussion of the pharmacology issues is contained in the review by Dr. Srikanth Nallani, the pharmacology reviewer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Mechanism of Action</head><p>Pregabalin (LYRICA) is an alpha-2-delta ligand that binds with high affinity to this auxiliary subunit of voltage-gated calcium channels in central nervous system tissues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.2">Pharmacodynamics</head><p>Not applicable Study A0081180 confirmed the findings from a previous PK study in pediatric subjects with epilepsy that for the same mg dose, pregabalin exposure in pediatric patients 12 to 16 years of age is similar to adults. It is recommended that this information be included in the label (refer to Section 9.2 Labeling Recommendations).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Sources of Clinical Data</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Tables of Studies/Clinical Trials</head><p>The LYRICA clinical development program for fibromyalgia in adolescents includes two Phase 3 clinical studies: Study A0081180 a double-blind randomized efficacy and safety study and Study A0081231 an open-label extension safety study <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 2)</ref>.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>The primary objective was to have been:</p><p>• To evaluate the safety and efficacy of pregabalin (75-450 mg/day) compared with placebo in an adolescent fibromyalgia population.</p><p>The secondary objective was to have been:</p><p>• To evaluate the pharmacokinetics (PK) of pregabalin in an adolescent fibromyalgia population. follow-up/taper (1 week). At Visit 1 (screening), subjects were to be given a pain and quality of sleep diary which they were instructed to complete on a daily basis. At Visit 2 (randomization), at least 4 pain diaries were to be completed satisfactorily within the last 7 days and the average pain score had to be ≥4. Subjects who met the eligibility criteria at randomization were to receive blinded treatment of either placebo or pregabalin in a ratio of 1:1. Subjects were to initiate dosing at 75 mg/day and have their dose optimized over a 3 week period, based on tolerability and response, to a dose of 75 mg/day, 150 mg/day, 300 mg/day or 450 mg/day ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). Guidelines for dose escalation are described in <ref type="table" target="#tab_20">Table 4</ref>. Study drug dose could only be increased at scheduled visits but could be decreased at, or between the visits, up to and including Day 21. The dose could only be changed by one step up or down at a time (eg, 75 mg/day to 150 mg/day or 450 mg/day to 300 mg/day etc.). After this 3 week optimization period, subjects were to remain at the optimized dose for 12 weeks with no further dose adjustment allowed. Subjects unable to tolerate the fixed dose of study medication were to discontinue from the study. At the end of the 12 week period, subjects were to taper their study medication over a 1-week period and given the option to enter into an open-label extension study. The initial planned sample size of 162 subjects was reduced in Protocol Amendment 3 to a minimum of 106 subjects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Figure 1: Study Design</head><p>Source: CSR 1180. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref> • Pain modulation by anxiety or stress If 5 of the above minor criteria are present, 4 tender points will satisfy the criteria. 5. At screening (Visit 1) and randomization (Visit 2), patients must have a score of ≥4 on the Weekly Pain Numeric Rating Scale. 6. At randomization, at least 4 pain diaries must be completed satisfactorily within the preceding 7 days and the average daily pain score must be ≥4.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exclusion Criteria:</head><p>Patients were to have been excluded if any of the following applied: 3. Previous participation in a clinical trial with pregabalin, failed pregabalin treatment due to lack of efficacy, intolerance to pregabalin or any pregabalin ingredient, or taking pregabalin within the last 30 days for any condition. 4. Subjects with unstable depressive disorders, unstable Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD), or any history of bipolar (mania or hypomania) or psychotic disorder, as assessed by structured interview using the Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview (MINI-KID) assessment. Subjects with any clinically significant psychiatric disorder that in the judgment of the investigator would make the patient inappropriate for this trial. For subjects with a current DSM diagnosis of a depressive disorder, anxiety disorder, or ADHD (or who meet criteria for one of these conditions based upon the MINI-KID), the following criteria must have been met to be eligible:</p><p>• Subjects with an anxiety disorder or depressive disorder: Must have stable symptoms that do not require pharmacologic treatment, OR be treated for these symptoms for at least 3 months, with the last 2 months prior to Visit 1 at a stable dose and not considering a further increase in dose at study entry. • Subjects with ADHD: Must have stable symptoms that do not require pharmacologic treatment, OR must be on a pharmacologic treatment for ADHD for at least 3 months with the last 2 months at a stable dose and unlikely to require a dose adjustment during the study. • Any non-pharmacological treatments must be stable. 5. Any subject at risk of suicide or self-harm based on investigator judgment and/or details of a risk assessment by a qualified mental health professional. 6. Subjects with serious hepatic, respiratory, neurologic (epilepsy, multiple sclerosis), cardiovascular, hematologic or immunologic illnesses, or any other severe acute or chronic medical or laboratory abnormality that may increase the risk associated with study participation or study drug administration. 7. Pregnant or nursing females; patients who are unwilling or unable to use an acceptable method of contraception (or abstinence) from screening until completion of follow-up procedures. Females must have a negative serum pregnancy at screening prior to randomization. 8. Subjects with active malignancy of any type or any history of a malignancy. 9. Subjects who are immunocompromised. 10. Subjects with a history of illicit drug or alcohol abuse within the last 2 years.</p><p>Subjects will not be randomized if a urine drug screen for non-therapeutic drugs is positive at screening. Subjects testing positive for opioid use may have a repeat urine drug screen at the discretion of the investigator, and may be randomized if the repeat test is negative. 11. Creatinine clearance (CLcr) ≤80 mL/min (Cockroft-Gault equation). 12. Platelet count &lt;100x 10 9 /L; white blood cell (WBC) count &lt;2.5 x 10 9 /L; neutrophil count &lt;1.5 x 10 9 /L. 13. C-reactive protein ≥2.00 mg/L. 14. Rheumatoid factor (RF&gt;80 IU/mL).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>20</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) 15. Abnormal (clinically relevant) 12-lead electrocardiogram (ECG); must be reviewed/confirmed by investigator. 16. Subjects taking any other investigational drugs within 30 days of screening. 17. Subjects with active gastrointestinal disease (GI) including any GI surgery that in the opinion of the investigator would interfere with the absorption. 18. Subjects with difficulty swallowing capsules or unable to tolerate oral medication. 19. Unwilling or unable to comply with the Life Style Guidelines including not having elective surgery or consuming alcohol during the study. 20. Use of certain medications for pain, sleep or the treatment of fibromyalgia are prohibited, as listed in <ref type="table" target="#tab_22">Table 5</ref>. Certain antidepressants, sleep medications, and medications for the treatment of ADHD are allowable under specific conditions (refer to section on allowable medications). Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDS) and selective COX-2 inhibitors are permitted. Acetaminophen (up to 3 g/day) as rescue medication is permitted. 21. Clinically significant or unstable medical or psychological conditions that, in the opinion of the investigator, would compromise participation in the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomization Criteria</head><p>For randomization at Visit 2 and entry into the double-blind period, subjects were to have met the following criteria:</p><p>1. At Visit 2 at least 4 pain diaries must have been completed satisfactorily within the preceding 7 days, and the average daily pain score had to be ≥4. 2. No subject was to be randomized until confirmed ECG and lab reports had been received from the central ECG reader and central laboratory by the site and verified by the Investigator that the subject met all eligibility criteria. 3. Females of child-bearing potential must have had a negative serum pregnancy test prior to randomization. 4. Prior to randomization, the need for a risk assessment by a qualified mental health professional (MHP) was to be determined based on results of screening suicidality assessment. If a subject met criteria for a risk assessment, the subject could not be randomized until the risk assessment had been completed and eligibility determined by the investigator in conjunction with the MHP (or investigator alone if qualified).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>21</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Procedures</head><p>The Schedule of Activities <ref type="table" target="#tab_18">(Table 3)</ref> provides an overview of the visits and procedures. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Washout (Visit 0)</head><p>Informed consent and child assent was to have been obtained prior to undergoing any washout of prohibited medications <ref type="table" target="#tab_27">(Table 7)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Screening (Visit 1)</head><p>Visit 1 was to have occurred between 21 days and 7 days prior to Visit 2 (randomization). The following procedures were to have been conducted at this visit:</p><p>• Written Informed Consent and assent obtained unless previously at Visit 0.</p><p>• • Physical examination (including height, weight, pulse, blood pressure).</p><p>• Abbreviated neurological examination (muscle strength, gait and reflexes).</p><p>• Assessment of pubertal status (Tanner Staging) and menstrual history-females only. • Mini International Neuropsychiatric Interview-KID (MINI-KID).</p><p>• Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS).</p><p>• Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) (added Amendment 3)</p><p>• Suicide Behaviors Questionnaire-Revised (SBQ-R).</p><p>• Assessment of need to complete a risk assessment.</p><p>• Weekly Pain Numeric Rating Scale (Pain-NRS).</p><p>• 12-lead ECG.</p><p>• Clinical laboratory tests (hematology, chemistry with estimated serum creatinine clearance (CLcr), C-reactive protein, urinalysis, drug testing and serum pregnancy. • Reproductive hormone evaluations -females only.</p><p>• Subjects instructed in proper completion of daily diaries for pain and sleep.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suicidality Risk Assessment During Screening</head><p>If the subject had suicide ideation with actual intent, method, or plan at any time in their lifetime or any previous lifetime history of suicide behaviors, or current major psychiatric disorders that were not explicitly permitted in the inclusion/exclusion criteria, a subject should have been excluded based on the judgment of the investigator, or a risk assessment by a clinically qualified mental health professional should have been done. Subjects meeting the following criteria were to have been excluded from the study or may have been allowed to proceed if deemed appropriate after a documented risk assessment:</p><p>1. The subject has had suicide ideation associated with actual intent and/or plan at any time in their lifetime, or any positive response (score ≥1) on STS items 1a, 1b, both 3 and 4, or 5 or "yes" response to C-SSRS items 4 or 5; or 2. A score ≥8 on the SBQ-R, or 3. Any previous lifetime history of suicide behaviors:</p><p>• any positive response on STS items 1a, 1b, 6 or 8; or • an answer of "yes" to any of the suicidal behavior items of the C-SSRS; or 4. The presence of any current major psychiatric disorder that is not explicitly permitted in the inclusion/exclusion criteria. If a subject has a DSM anxiety disorder, DSM depressive disorder, or ADHD (or meet criteria for one of these conditions based on the MINI-KID) and is stable (treated or untreated), the subject will be eligible to participate in the study without a risk assessment for suicidality if no risk assessment criteria have been met. However, if the investigator feels anxiety, depressive symptoms or impulsive behaviors are significant enough to warrant a risk assessment, this approach would be supported by the sponsor; or 24</p><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) 5. In the investigator's judgment a risk assessment or exclusion is required.</p><p>It was recommended that the risk assessment be done by a clinically-qualified child and adolescent Mental Health Professional (MHP).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Randomization (Visit 2)</head><p>Subjects were to have been randomized in a ratio of 1:1 to receive either placebo or active treatment. Pregabalin or matching placebo capsules were to have been administrated orally, BID for 15 weeks (3 week dose optimization phase and 12 weeks fixed-dose phase).</p><p>Study Drug LYRICA Capsules were supplied in the following strengths: 25mg, 50mg, 75mg, 150mg and 225mg. Study drug was supplied as blinded capsules of pregabalin and matching placebo. On the day of randomization, drug supply consisting of 4 blister packages, was provided to the subject's parent/guardian/caregiver, as follows:</p><p>• Pregabalin 75 mg/day (25 mg morning and 50 mg evening) or placebo.</p><p>• Pregabalin 150 mg/day (75 mg BID) or placebo.</p><p>• Pregabalin 300 mg/day (150 mg BID) or placebo.</p><p>• Pregabalin 450 mg/day (225 mg BID) or placebo.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dose Titration</head><p>Subjects were to initiate dosing at 75 mg/day with pregabalin or matching placebo the morning after randomization (Visit 2). Subjects were to take one capsule in the morning and one capsule in the evening. During the dose optimization phase (Weeks 1, 2, and 3), the dose was escalated in a blinded fashion (ie, the investigator and subject were unaware as to whether active or placebo was being administered) in order to reach the optimal dose for each subject. Study drug dose could only be increased at scheduled visits (including phone visits) but could be decreased at, or between the visits, up to and including Day 21. Based on tolerability and response, the dose could be titrated from the initiating dose of 75 mg/day to 150 mg/day, 300 mg/day or 450 mg/day ( <ref type="figure" target="#fig_0">Figure 1</ref>). Guidelines for dose escalation are described in <ref type="table" target="#tab_22">Table 5</ref>. Patients were to have remained on these doses for an additional 12 weeks without further dose adjustment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>25</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) items 1a, 1b, both 3 and 4, 5, 6, or 8 (score of ≥1) on more than one occasion during a trial must have their potential suicidality managed appropriately by the investigator together with a qualified MHP (or the investigator alone if the investigator is a qualified MHP), or be discontinued from the trial. The investigator should consult with the Pfizer medical monitor regarding this issue.</p><p>Anytime a subject came into the clinic, including an unscheduled clinic visit, suicidality assessments (Sheehan Suicidality Tracking Scale -since last visit version and Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale -since last visit version) were to have been administered. Beginning with Visit 2, if there are any positive responses on items 4, 5, or on any behavioral question of the C-SSRS (Since Last Visit version), a risk assessment must be done by a qualified MHP to determine whether it is safe for the subject to continue in the trial. A suicidality narrative must be constructed for subjects who receive study treatment who have undergone any risk assessment as part of the study (baseline or during the study), using information from the STS assessment, C SSRS assessment, the MHP assessment(s), and prior screening and baseline information, utilizing the supplemental relevant case report forms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visits 3, 4, 5 (Day 3, Wk 1, and Wk 2) -Phone Visits</head><p>If the subject was tolerating the study medication, these visits could be completed by phone. Subjects unable to tolerate a dose of 75 mg were to have been discontinued from the study. Dose adjustment was to have been discussed during this visit and the dose confirmed at this time should be administered at the next dose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visit 6 (Week 3) -Clinic Visit</head><p>The following procedures were to have been conducted at this visit:</p><p>• Vital signs (pulse, blood pressure and weight).</p><p>• Clinical laboratory tests (hematology, chemistry, urinalysis, and serum pregnancy). • Collection of pharmacokinetic samples.</p><p>• Review concomitant medications and nondrug treatments.</p><p>• Daily pain and sleep quality diary review and reminder to complete diaries until the next scheduled visit. • Assess and record adverse events.</p><p>• Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS). • Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).</p><p>• Assess need to complete a risk assessment.</p><p>• Collection of blister packs (used and unused). Review of study medication compliance and dosing diary. Discuss potential dose adjustment. Subjects unable to tolerate a dose of 75 mg/day were to have been discontinued from the study. This was to have been the last opportunity for dose optimization; after this visit no further dose changes were allowed.</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visit 7 (Week 4) -Phone Visit</head><p>If the subject was tolerating the study medication, this visit may have been completed by phone. The following procedures were to have been completed at this visit:</p><p>• Documentation of pain and other fibromyalgia symptoms over the past week.</p><p>• Daily pain and sleep quality diary review.</p><p>• Assess and record adverse events.</p><p>• Review of study medication compliance and dosing diary.</p><p>• Review concomitant medications and nondrug treatments.</p><p>• Study personnel to confirm study medication dose.</p><p>• Review with parent/guardian/caregiver that an adult must be closely involved in supervising the administration of study medication.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Visit 8 (Week 7) -Clinic Visit</head><p>The following procedures were to have been conducted at this visit:</p><p>• Vital signs (pulse, blood pressure and weight).</p><p>• Review concomitant medications and nondrug treatments.</p><p>• Daily pain and sleep quality diary review.</p><p>• Assess and record adverse events.</p><p>• Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS).</p><p>• Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).</p><p>• Assess need to complete a risk assessment.</p><p>• Collection of blister pack with unused capsules and dispensing of new blister pack. • Review of study medication compliance and dosing diary.</p><p>• Study personnel to confirm study medication dose to be administered Visit 9 (Week 11) -Clinic Visit The following procedures were to have been conducted at this visit:</p><p>• Vital signs (pulse, blood pressure and weight).</p><p>• Review concomitant medications and nondrug treatments.</p><p>• Daily pain and sleep quality diary review.</p><p>• Assess and record adverse events.</p><p>• Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS).</p><p>• Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).</p><p>• Assess need to complete a risk assessment.</p><p>• Collection of blister pack with unused capsules and dispensing of new blister pack. • Review of study medication compliance and study medication dosing diary.</p><p>• Introduce the open-label extension study A0081231 to the subject and parent/guardian and provide a copy of the Informed Consent/Assent. • Parent Global Impression of Change (Parent-GIC).</p><p>• Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC).</p><p>• Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire for Children (FIQ-C).</p><p>• Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS).</p><p>• Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS).</p><p>• Assess need to complete a risk assessment.</p><p>• Daily pain and sleep quality diary review.</p><p>• Record and assess adverse events.</p><p>• Review concomitant medications and nondrug treatment.</p><p>• Collection of blister pack with unused medication.</p><p>• Review study medication compliance and dosing diary.</p><p>• Study personnel to confirm study medication dose to be administered and dispense medication for study medication taper.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drug Taper</head><p>Following the treatment phase, all patients were to have tapered study medication over 1 week as shown in <ref type="table" target="#tab_23">Table 6</ref> below and be given the option to enter the open-label extension study. For subjects who have not taken study medication for the past 24 hours or more, there was no requirement to dispense the taper medication. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rescue Medication</head><p>Acetaminophen up to 3 g/day as rescue medication was permitted. <ref type="table" target="#tab_27">Table 7</ref> lists concomitant medications that might affect the pain or sleep disturbance associated with fibromyalgia that were to have been discontinued prior to Visit 1. Also, consumption of alcohol was to be avoided during the study. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Prohibited Pain/Sleep Medications</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Allowable Medications/Nonpharmacologic Therapies</head><p>The following medications and nonpharmacologic therapies were to have been allowed:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Antidepressants</head><p>The use of one antidepressant for anxiety or depressive symptoms, either a selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) or bupropion (Wellbutrin), was permitted if it had been taken for at least 3 months prior to Screening (Visit 1) and at a stable dose for the 2 months prior to Visit 1. The use of other antidepressants was not permitted <ref type="table" target="#tab_27">(Table 7)</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Attention Deficit Hyperactivity Disorder (ADHD) Medications</head><p>The use of one pharmacologic treatment for ADHD (a psychostimulant, or the nonstimulant atomexetine/Straterra only) was to have been permitted if the dose had been taken for at least 3 months prior to screening (Visit 1) and at a stable dose for the 2 months prior to Visit 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sleep Medications</head><p>Bedtime use of the following medications for sleep was to have been allowed if the pattern of use had been stable for the 30 days prior to Screening (Visit 1) and the conditions below were met:</p><p>• Zolpidem (Ambien) and eszopiclone (Lunesta), if used 3 nights or fewer per week. • Over the counter sleep medications allowed if used 3 nights or fewer per week.</p><p>• The daily use of herbal sleep aids such as melatonin and valerian root permitted.</p><p>Diphenhydramine (Benadryl) for topical use was to have been permitted. Acute use of oral Benadryl as per product labeling was to have been allowed not more than 3 days weekly for allergies and allergic reactions and as a sleep aid.</p><p>Use of anxiolytics including benzodiazepines (eg, alprazolam) and barbiturates for sleep was not to have been permitted <ref type="table" target="#tab_27">(Table 7)</ref>. Sleep medications should not have been initiated during the Double-Blind Phase of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pain Relief or Cardiovascular Prophylaxis</head><p>The following medications were to have been permitted for additional pain relief or cardiovascular prophylaxis:</p><p>• Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory agents (NSAIDs) or selective COX-2 inhibitors.</p><p>• Aspirin.</p><p>• Acetaminophen, 3 grams/day maximum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nonpharmacologic Therapies</head><p>Subjects were permitted to continue with stable (ie, for at least 30 days before Visit 1) nonpharmacologic therapy (ie, physical and psychological therapy, massage, chiropractic care, exercise program, etc.) during the study. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contraceptive Measures</head><p>Males and females of childbearing potential were to have used an acceptable method of contraception from screening until completion of follow-up procedures. Acceptable methods of contraception included:</p><p>• Oral contraceptive agents, intrauterine devices, implantable contraceptives, transdermal hormonal contraceptives, and injectable contraceptives. • Barrier methods of contraception (eg, condom and/or diaphragm) with concomitant use of a spermicide. • Abstinence during the entire study period.</p><p>• Vasectomy.</p><p>Male subjects were to agree that female spouses/partners would use adequate contraception (as defined above) or were of non-childbearing potential (ie, surgically sterile).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Compliance</head><p>Lack of study compliance was to have included any of the following:</p><p>• Missing 3 or more consecutive days of study drug.</p><p>• Less than 80% or greater than 120% study drug compliance for &gt;2 clinic and/or phone visits; if this occurred, this was to be recorded as a protocol deviation (except if doses were missed due to an AE). • Missing a required study visit (or 2 phone contacts).</p><p>• Starting any prohibited treatment.</p><p>• If a capsule count of returned medication at any clinic visit indicated that the subject had not taken all prescribed study drug, the subject was to be counseled about the importance of compliance and reminded of the instructions for taking study drug. • If the subject had been non-compliant in any area as defined above, the subject's participation in the study was to be re-evaluated. Any discontinuation was to be done in consultation with Pfizer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject Withdrawal</head><p>Subjects were to have been allowed to withdraw from the study at any time at their own request, or withdrawn at any time at the discretion of the investigator for safety or behavioral reasons, or inability to comply with the protocol. Subjects were to have been withdrawn for the following reasons:</p><p>• If a female subject became pregnant during the study.</p><p>• If alanine aminotransferase (ALT) or aspartate aminotransferase (AST) was above 3 times ULN repeatedly during 2 weeks, or above 5 times ULN.</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Endpoints</head><p>Primary Efficacy Endpoint The primary efficacy endpoint was to have been the following:</p><p>• Change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain intensity (derived from an 11 point daily pain numeric rating scale).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Secondary Efficacy Endpoints</head><p>The following secondary efficacy endpoints were to have been measured:</p><p>• Weekly mean pain score at each week derived from the daily pain numeric rating scale (NRS) (24-hour recall). • 30% and 50% pain responders.</p><p>• Weekly pain NRS at Week 15 (1-week recall).</p><p>• Weekly mean sleep quality score (from the daily sleep diary) at end of study using the mean of the last 7 diary entries prior to Week 15. • Weekly mean sleep quality score at each week, from the daily sleep diary.</p><p>• Patient Global Impression of Change (PGIC) at Week 15.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Exploratory Efficacy Endpoints</head><p>The following exploratory efficacy endpoints were to have been measured:</p><p>• Parent Global Impression of Change (Parent-GIC) at Week 15.</p><p>• Fibromyalgia Impact Questionnaire for children (FIQ-C) at Week 15.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Assessments</head><p>Safety was to have been assessed by the following:</p><p>• Incidence and severity of AEs.</p><p>• Physical and neurological examinations.</p><p>• Vital signs.</p><p>• Electrocardiogram (ECG) at V1 and V10.</p><p>• Laboratory assessment.</p><p>• Tanner staging at V1 and V10.</p><p>• Reproductive hormones (LH, FSH, and Estradiol) collected at V1 and V10 for female patients only. • Suicidality assessment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Clinical Laboratory Tests</head><p>The following serum chemistry, hematology and urinalysis tests were to have been obtained at V1, V6 and V10 unless otherwise specified:</p><p>Serum Chemistry: Aspartate Aminotransferase (AST), Alanine Aminotransferase (ALT), Albumin, Alkaline Phosphatase, Amylase, Blood Urea Nitrogen, Creatine Kinase, Serum Creatinine, Estimated Creatinine Clearance (Calculated at V1 and V10 only), Sodium, Potassium, Chloride, Calcium, C-reactive protein (V1 Only), Glucose, Pregnancy Test, </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reproductive Hormones</head><p>The following reproductive hormone levels were to have been obtained in female patients at V1 and V10: luteinizing hormone (LH), follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and, Estradiol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Electrocardiogram</head><p>A 12-lead ECG was to have been obtained at Visit 1 (Screening) and Visit 10/Termination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pharmacokinetic Endpoint</head><p>Two pharmacokinetic (PK) samples were to have been collected at Visit 6 (Week 3). The first sample was to be collected as soon as possible upon arrival at the clinic, and the second sample just prior to leaving the clinic. Subjects with a clinic visit scheduled in the morning should not have taken their morning dose until immediately after the first PK sample was drawn. The dose taken in the clinic was to be taken from the previously dispensed blister pack. Subjects with a clinic visit scheduled in the afternoon should have taken their morning dose at the usual time, collect the PK samples upon arrival and departure, and no dose was to be administered during the clinic visit. Subjects with a clinic visit scheduled in the evening should not have taken their evening dose until immediately after the first PK sample was drawn. The dose taken in the clinic was to be taken from the previously dispensed blister pack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Statistical Analysis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Full Analysis Set (FAS)</head><p>The FAS includes all randomized subjects who received at least one dose of study drug. The FAS population was the primary population for efficacy analyses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary Analysis</head><p>The primary analysis of change from baseline to endpoint in weekly mean pain scores was carried out based on the FAS population using analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) with baseline mean pain score, center and treatment. Baseline was defined as the mean of the daily pain scores recorded in the 7 days prior to randomization. Endpoint Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) was defined as the mean of the daily pain scores recorded in the 7 days prior to final dose of study drug.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sensitivity Analyses of the Primary Endpoint</head><p>The following sensitivity analyses were performed to assess the robustness of the primary analysis:</p><p>• Mixed model repeated measures (MMRM) analysis without any imputation for missing data • ANCOVA model with BOCF imputation method • ANCOVA model with LOCF imputation method • ANCOVA model with modified BOCF imputation method where BOCF was applied for subjects discontinued due to AEs and LOCF was applied for subjects discontinued due to any other reasons</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method of Imputation for Missing Data</head><p>The method of imputation for missing data will be derived using the following methods:</p><p>• For subjects who discontinue for reasons other than tolerability or lack of efficacy, the Week 15 mean pain score will be assigned based on the distribution of post randomization weekly mean pain scores. • For subjects who withdraw due to an adverse event or discontinue due to lack of efficacy, the Week 15 mean pain scores will be assigned according to the distribution of baseline mean pain scores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protocol Amendments</head><p>Original Protocol, January 28, 2008</p><p>No patients were enrolled under the original protocol.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Amendment 1, October 29, 2009</head><p>Amendment 1 was issued prior to enrolling any subjects in the study. This amendment revised the study from a short-term (6-week) safety and tolerability study to a 12-week efficacy and safety study (as requested by the FDA).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Amendment 2, April 24, 2012</head><p>The following were changes made in Amendment 2:</p><p>• The patient population age range was expanded from 12-16 years to 12-17 years.</p><p>• Narratives for risk assessments required.</p><p>• Time between screening to randomization increased to 21 days.</p><p>• Certain antidepressants, sleep meds, ADHD meds allowed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Amendment 3, March 14, 2014</head><p>The following were changes made to the protocol in Amendment 3:</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p><p>• Secondary endpoints were clarified to include weekly pain scores and weekly sleep quality scores at each week • Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) added in addition to the STS.</p><p>(Reviewer's Note: Only 3 patients actually completed this assessment) • Sample size changed from 162 randomized patients (81 in each treatment arm) to 106 patients based on ongoing Study 1180 blinded database and the previously completed placebo-controlled studies in adults with fibromyalgia. • Analysis of primary efficacy endpoint modified and sensitivity analyses added.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Results</head><p>A detailed discussion of the efficacy results is presented in Section 6.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Primary Efficacy Endpoint</head><p>The primary efficacy endpoint of change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain intensity (derived from an 11-point daily pain numeric rating scale) was not statistically significant but showed numerically greater improvement for the pregabalin-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients. Based on Pfizer's prespecified analysis, a treatment difference of was reported by the Applicant for pregabalin relative to placebo in endpoint mean pain score. The FDA statistician, confirmed the Sponsor's overall findings and determined a treatment difference of for the primary endpoint.</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">(b) (4) (b) (4)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Safety Results</head><p>A detailed discussion of the safety findings is presented in Section 7.</p><p>The following is a summary of Protocol A0081231.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Title: A 6-MONTH, OPEN-LABEL, SAFETY TRIAL OF PREGABALIN IN ADOLESCENT PATIENTS WITH FIBROMYALGIA</head><p>Dates Conducted: The first patient enrolled September 1, 2010 and the last patient completed June 1, 2015.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objective:</head><p>The objective of this study was to evaluate the safety of pregabalin at doses of 75-450 mg/day (taken twice daily) in subjects who participated in double-blind study A0081180 and who wished to receive open-label pregabalin therapy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Overall Design:</head><p>This was a 6-month (25-week) open-label extension study of the double-blind randomized fibromyalgia study A0081180. After the termination visit and study drug taper in study A0081180, subjects had an option of starting pregabalin at a dose of 75 mg/day under open-label conditions. The study consisted of 3 phases: dose Subjects initiated pregabalin dosing at 75 mg/day and had their dose optimized over a 3-week period, based on tolerability and response, to a dose of 75 mg/day, 150 mg/day, 300 mg/day, or 450 mg/day. The dose could only be changed by 1 step (up or down) at a time. After the initial 3-week optimization period, the dose could be adjusted for the remainder of the study to optimize pain control and to minimize AEs. The minimum daily dose of pregabalin was 75 mg/day and the maximum daily dose was 450 mg/day. At the end of the study, subjects tapered the dose over a 1-week period. A maximum of 12 visits were scheduled in the study; 5 visits conducted in the clinic and 7 visits by telephone <ref type="table" target="#tab_29">(Table 8</ref>). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key Eligibility Criteria:</head><p>• Subject and 1 parent were able to comply with scheduled visits, treatment plan, laboratory tests, and other study procedures. • Subject and 1 parent signed written informed assent and consent. • Subjects must have met the inclusion criteria for the preceding fibromyalgia study 1180 (12-17 years old at time of enrollment in Study 1180, and have met the Yunus and Masi criteria for fibromyalgia), have received study drug under double-blind conditions, and have completed study 1180. • Subjects who experienced a serious adverse event during study 1180 which was considered related to study medication were not eligible to participate. • Subjects with white blood cell count &lt;2.5 x 10 9 /L, neutrophil count &lt;1.5 x 10 9 /L, platelet count &lt;100 x 10 9 /L, or creatinine clearance &lt;80 mL/min were not eligible to participate. • Female subjects were to continue to use adequate birth control methods and have a negative pregnancy test at open-label Visit 1 (Visit 10/early termination of study 1180) and at the indicated intervals during the open-label study. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study Drug</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Results</head><p>A detailed discussion of the safety findings is presented in Section 7.</p><p>Enrollment: A total of 63 subjects were enrolled in this open-label extension study and treated with pregabalin. Of these 63 subjects, 33 had previously been treated with pregabalin and 30 subjects with placebo.</p><p>Disposition: Of the 14 subjects that discontinued, 7 subjects had been treated in study 1180 with pregabalin, and 7 subjects with placebo. Two subjects discontinued due to adverse events, 3 subjects due to lack of efficacy, 5 subjects no longer willing to participate, 1 subject lost to follow-up and 3 subjects other.</p><p>Deaths: There were no deaths.</p><p>Serious Adverse Events: There were 3 (4.8%) subjects who had SAEs during the study. These resulted in hospitalization due to migraine, appendicitis, and joint instability. The SAE of severe migraine may have been related to the study drug but the patient had a history of headaches.</p><p>Discontinuations due to AEs: There were 2 (3.2%) subjects who discontinued study drug due to adverse events. Dizziness, fatigue and nausea in 1 subject were considered related to the study drug, and spinal stenosis in 1 subject was not considered related to the study drug.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Common Adverse Events:</head><p>A total of 45 (71.4%) subjects experienced at least one adverse event. The most frequently reported adverse events were dizziness and fatigue.</p><p>Weight Gain: A weight gain of at least 7% was reported for 18 (29.0%) subjects.</p><p>Suicidality: There were no suicide attempts or completed suicides during the study. No suicidal behavior was reported. During the study, 6 (9.5%) subjects reported suicidal ideation, without plan or intent; these subjects all had a history of suicidal ideation noted at the time of screening for study 1180.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>39</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6">Review of Efficacy</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Efficacy Summary</head><p>Statistical significance was not demonstrated with the primary efficacy endpoint of change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain score, derived from the daily pain NRS (24-hour recall) but the results were numerically in favor of pregabalin. The patient global impression of change also showed greater improvement rates in the pregabalin group compared to the placebo group. The reason the study failed to demonstrate efficacy is unclear but the FDA statistician noted that the study was not adequately powered to demonstrate efficacy with respect to the primary efficacy endpoint.</p><p>(b) (4)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.1">Methods</head><p>This study was an adequate and well-controlled (i.e., randomized, double-blind, placebocontrolled) study in subjects with fibromyalgia. The primary efficacy endpoint was change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain intensity (derived from an 11-point daily pain numeric rating scale). The study design and primary endpoint meet the Division's standards.</p><p>The Applicant submitted one efficacy study (Study 1180) (b) (4)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Demographics</head><p>The demographic characteristics for the pregabalin and placebo treatment groups were similar with respect to age, sex, race and weight <ref type="table" target="#tab_30">(Table 9</ref>). In the pregabalin treatment group the mean age was 14.6 years and in the placebo group 14.7 years. Most subjects were 14 to 16 years old with only a few subjects (1.9%) 17 years old, likely due to this age group being added with Amendment 2 after initiation of the study. The majority of subjects were White (57%) or Asian (34%). In the pregabalin group 89% of the subjects were female and in the placebo group 83% of the subjects were female. All but two of the female subjects (2.2%) were in menarche.</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) disposition in Study 1180. Within the pregabalin group, 10 (18.5%) subjects discontinued study drug early for the following reasons: adverse event 7.4% (4/54), lack of efficacy no subjects, no longer willing to participate 9.3% (5/54), other 1.9% (1/54) and protocol violation no subjects. Within the placebo group, 17 (32.1%) subjects discontinued study drug early for the following reasons: adverse event 7.5% (4/53), lack of efficacy 5.7% (3/53), no longer willing to participate 13.2% (7/53), other 1.9% (1/53) and protocol violation 3.8% (2/53). As expected there were more discontinuations due to lack of efficacy in the placebo group. Discontinuations due to adverse events were numerically similar in both groups but the specific adverse events resulting in study discontinuation were more likely due to study drug in the pregabalin group where two subjects discontinued due to weight gain (Section 7.3.3). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protocol Violations</head><p>Protocol deviations included subjects who did not meet all inclusion/exclusion criteria, deviations in the conduct of the study (eg, incorrect dosing of investigational product, prohibited concomitant medication), deviations from study assessments as required by the protocol, deviations due to adverse events, informed consent deviations, and deviations due to other criteria. Major protocol deviations were defined as those deviations from the protocol likely to have an impact on the subject's rights, safety, or well-being, and/or on the validity of the data for analysis. A summary of protocol violations is provided in <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 11</ref>. A total of 22% (23/107) of randomized subjects had a protocol violation. The incidence was similar in the pregabalin group 24% and placebo group 19%. Across all subjects, the most common category for major protocol deviations was a deviation related to study drug administration/study treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>42</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Primary Efficacy Endpoint</head><p>The primary endpoint was change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain score derived from the daily pain numeric rating scale (24-hour recall) from the daily pain diary. Based on the prespecified analysis using the full analysis set (FAS) population, the</p><formula xml:id="formula_3">(b) (4) (b) (4)</formula><p>Applicant reported a placebo-adjusted treatment difference of favoring pregabalin, which was not a statistically significant difference . The FAS population consisted of all randomized subjects who received at least one dose of study drug. Pregabalin-treated subjects experienced an improvement in LS mean changes of point improvement from baseline <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">(Table 12</ref>). The FDA statistician, Dr. Yan Zhou, confirmed</p><formula xml:id="formula_4">(b) (4)</formula><p>the Sponsor's overall findings and determined a treatment difference of (   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sensitivity Analyses of Primary Endpoint</head><p>The Applicant reports results of sensitivity analyses of the primary endpoint using alternate imputation approaches or based on the per protocol analysis were not statistically significant but treatment differences favored pregabalin treatment <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">(Table  14)</ref>. The FDA statistician confirmed that using alternate imputation approaches were similar in nature to the primary efficacy analysis, numerically favoring pregabalin but not statistically significant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>44</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rescue Medication Use</head><p>The number of doses and milligrams of rescue medication taken during the study was not collected. Pfizer did collect information regarding the number of subjects taking concomitant medications and the duration of use but this limited information on rescue medication makes it impossible to assess study drug efficacy based on rescue medication use. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 18</ref> summarizing the mean duration and number of patients taking concomitant medications during the Double-Blind Phase, with similar information provided for the Baseline Phase as reference. The most commonly used medications during the Double-Blind Phase were ibuprofen and paracetamol. Ibuprofen was used by 23 (42.6%) pregabalin-treated subjects for an average of 5.7 days/week and 18 (34.0%) placebo-treated subjects for an average of 6.2 days per week. Paracetamol was used by 19 (35.2%) of pregabalin-treated subjects for an average of 5.5 days/week and 19 (35.8%) of placebo treated subjects for an average of 5.2 days/week. Overall, the number of subjects taking rescue medication and duration of treatment appeared similar but without knowing the actual dose this information is of limited value.  Efficacy Study 1180 failed to demonstrate efficacy in adolescents based on the primary prespecified endpoint. Several possible factors were considered as to why this study comparisons. Subgroup analyses of the other factors listed above were performed by the statistician.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pfizer provided</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subgroup Analysis by Fibromyalgia Diagnostic Criteria</head><p>Subjects must have met the Yunus and Masi criteria for diagnosing fibromyalgia to be eligible for participation in Study 1180. These criteria required: generalized musculoskeletal aching at 3 or more sites for 3 or more months, 5 or more tender points, and 3 or more of the following 10 minor criteria:</p><p>• may have failed to demonstrate efficacy in adolescents while in adults efficacy has been demonstrated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(b) (4)</head><p>The FDA statistician believes that this study was not adequately powered to detect statistically significant differences in treatment group Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p><p>• Numbness • Pain modulation by physical activities • Pain modulation by weather factors • Pain modulation by anxiety or stress</p><p>The 1990 American College of Rheumatology (ACR) criteria used to determine eligibility in adult studies was not a requirement for entry into Study 1180 in adolescents. ACR criteria require a history of widespread pain present for at least 3 months with pain in 11 of 18 tender point sites on digital palpation.</p><p>Of the 107 randomized subjects, 95 (88.8%) subjects met the ACR fibromyalgia diagnostic criteria in addition to the Yunus and Masi criteria, which were a study eligibility requirement. In the pregabalin group 92.6% (50/54) met the ACR diagnostic criteria at screening and in the placebo group 84.9% (45/53) met the criteria. When the FDA statistician excluded subjects who did not meet the ACR criteria the efficacy results (b) (4) appeared similar (treatment difference ).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subgroup Analysis by Dose</head><p>In adults the recommended dose of LYRICA for fibromyalgia is 300 to 450 mg/day. In Study 1180 doses of 75 mg/day and 150 mg/day were included to allow for smaller, lowweight adolescents. There was lower exposure compared to adults with pediatric subjects dosed with 75 mg and 150 mg/day. Approximately half of the patients in Study 1180 received doses that are lower than the doses demonstrated to be effective in adults. <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 19</ref> presents subgroup analyses results by dose group performed by the FDA statistician. The results were only numerically in favor of the lowest and highest dose of pregabalin. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subgroup Analysis by Country</head><p>In Study 1180, 67 patients were enrolled in sites in the U.S. and 40 patients were enrolled in three countries outside the U.S. <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">Table 20</ref> presents subgroup analyses results by country. The results were similar between the U.S. and the other countries.  <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 21</ref>. A total of 44 patients were exposed to pregabalin for greater than 90 days. The mean and median pregabalin doses during the fixed dose period were 244.5 mg/day and 262.3 mg/day, respectively. Mean and median doses were higher for male subjects and for subjects weighing at least 50 kg. During the fixed dose period approximately 40% of subjects were treated with 450 mg/day, 15% of subjects were treated with 300 mg/day, 19% with 150 mg/day, and 25% with 75 mg/day. A total of 29 subjects approximately 55% were treated at a dose level of 300-450 mg/day, the approved dose range for adult fibromyalgia subjects in the US.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>53</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)  <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">Table 22</ref>. In Study 1180, 54 subjects were randomized to pregabalin treatment and 53 to placebo. A total of 63 subjects were subsequently treated with pregabalin in Study 1231, 33 (52.4%) of whom had previously been treated in Study 1180 with pregabalin, and 30 (47.6%) with placebo. A total of 84 subjects were treated with pregabalin across studies 1180 and 1231, for a median duration of treatment of 172 days. A total of 5 (6%) subjects received pregabalin for 2-28 days, 11 (13%) subjects for 29-90 days, 37 (44%) subjects for 91-180 days, and 31 (37%) subjects for 181-300 days <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 22)</ref>.</p><p>depression. Her last dose of pregabalin 75 mg/day was taken 10 days earlier on (Study Day 63). The subject's mother reported that the subject had been doing</p><formula xml:id="formula_5">(b) (6) (b) (6)</formula><p>was taken with regard to the study drug. The event resolved on Study Day 47</p><formula xml:id="formula_6">(b) (6)</formula><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p><p>Inventory of Depressive Symptomatology (QIDS), and Suicide Behavior Questionnaire -Revised (SBQ-R), all met protocol criteria requiring a mental health risk assessment (MHRA). The subject had a score of 11 on the QIDS, which reflects clinically significant depression. The subject also had a score of 8 on the SBQ-R, reporting that "I have attempted to kill myself, but did not want to die." The STS score met protocol criteria for MHRA based on items 3 and 4. The MHRA conducted on 08-Jul-2010 found that she denied suicidal ideation, her mood was good and she denied any current depressive episode. Based on the outcome of the MHRA, the investigator considered the subject</p><formula xml:id="formula_7">(b) (6)</formula><p>appropriate to enter the study. The subject completed subsequent STS assessments on (at randomization), 02-Sep-2010, and 12-Oct-2010 with no report of suicidal ideation or behavior, and the subject did not require MHRA based on these evaluations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>On</head><p>(Study Day 41), the subject experienced the SAE of cholelithiasis requiring hospitalization. At that time her pregabalin dose was 150 mg/day. The subject took morphine on , hydromorphone on , and Vicodin for abdominal pain from through Study Day 35 to 66. No action</p><formula xml:id="formula_8">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula><p>after removal of the gallbladder. The subject had several risks factors for gallstones including being female, overweight and metabolic syndrome. The investigator considered the event of cholelithiasis unrelated to study drug.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>On</head><p>(Study Day 73), the subject was admitted to the hospital due to major well and went to her homecoming dance the night of . The next day ( ), the subject reported increased pain and fatigue. On , the subject</p><formula xml:id="formula_9">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula><p>took 10 pills of an over the counter cold medicine (name unknown) to try to alleviate her pain. The subject became concerned about taking that much medicine and made herself vomit. She asked her mother in the morning to take her to the hospital for help. The mother reported that the subject denied suicidal ideation and did not take the medication to hurt herself. She was assessed by the physician at the hospital as having major depression and was admitted for observation. and behavior were not reported during the subject's hospitalization or after . On Study Day 76 , the subject was discharged from the hospital and the SAE of major depression was considered resolved but she continued to have depression of moderate intensity which required ongoing treatment (escitalopram and psychotherapy); the event was still present at last reporting.</p><p>The investigator and sponsor considered the event of major depression related to study drug. The subject was lost to follow-up and was contacted multiple times with no response. The subject was permanently discontinued from the study on 15-Nov-2010 due to the event of depression.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>57</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>The SAE of cholelithiasis in a 14-year old is unusual but the patient had several known risk factors for cholelithiasis. However, pregabalin cannot be excluded as a contributing factor considering the current label includes cholelithiasis in the list of infrequent treatment-emergent adverse reactions (occurring in 1/100 to 1/1000 patients). Her SAE of depression may be due to her history of depression and suicidal ideation but LYRICA cannot be completely excluded as a contributing factor. It is noted that no suicidal ideation was reported with her SAE of depression and she denied suicidal ideation, but since no formal suicidal assessment was completed in the hospital it may have been missed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject Number: 10071001 (Pregabalin) Study Number: A0081231 Serious Adverse Events: Migraine</head><p>This 14-year-old white female subject, treated with placebo in double-blind study 1180,</p><formula xml:id="formula_10">(b) (6) (b) (6)</formula><p>started treatment with pregabalin in study 1231 on (Study Day 1). She completed the study and treatment was stopped on (Study Day 175).</p><p>Medical history present at study entry included acne, asthma, cough, fatigue, headache, hypermobility syndrome, osteochondrosis, paraesthesia, seasonal allergy, sinus arrhythmia, somnambulism, and syncope. Treatments at study entry included benzaclin topical, fexofenadine, fluticasone, minocycline, montelukast, paracetamol, salbutamol, and tretinoin. The subject had a history of headaches which had not previously been diagnosed as migraine. The subject had a known allergy to celebrex with reactions of headache.</p><p>On Study Day 4 , when the subject was on pregabalin 150 mg/day, she reported a headache that led to hospitalization; the diagnosis was first time migraine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>(b) (6)</head><p>This had occurred on a background of daily headaches associated with fibromyalgia. The subject was given intravenous (IV) ketorolac and metoclopramide and was discharged after 12 hours. The migraine had improved, but not fully resolved. This event was considered an SAE due to hospitalization. No action was taken with regard to the study drug. The subject increased the dose of study drug to 225 mg/day twice daily (BID) on  The subject was discharged on (Study Day 105) and was instructed to take amitriptyline 10 mg for 1 week and 20 mg for another week, but then stopped as it</p><formula xml:id="formula_11">(b) (6)</formula><p>was not helping the migraine. The subject continued to receive study drug pregabalin As of the investigator's conversation with subject's mother on (Study Day 127), the investigator considered that this subject still had a constant migraine. The investigator and sponsor considered there was a reasonable possibility that the event of migraine was related to pregabalin. The subject had a history of headaches, which had not previously been diagnosed as migraine; the migraine diagnosis was made after the headache increased in intensity and did not respond to multiple interventions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>Pregabalin cannot be excluded as a cause of her migraine headache based on the temporal relationship (headache started on Day 4 of treatment). However, the patient had a prior history of daily headaches associated with fibromyalgia. This raises the possibility that some of her previous headaches may have been migraine headaches but attributed to her fibromyalgia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary of Serious Adverse Events</head><p>There were two serious adverse events (SAEs) in one patient on LYRICA in Study 1180 and three SAEs in Study 1231. LYRICA cannot be completely excluded as the cause of the serious adverse events of cholelithiasis, depression and migraine headache. Depression and cholelithiasis are adverse events listed in the current label. The etiology of the cholelithiasis is unclear but pregabalin cannot be completely excluded as a cause considering cholelithiasis is listed in the current label as an adverse event. Although migraine headache is not listed in the label, headache is included in the label. It is possible that migraine headaches were previously present in this patient with a history of headaches prior to starting pregabalin but not diagnosed as migraine headaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.3">Dropouts and/or Discontinuations</head><p>A summary of subject disposition during placebo-controlled, double-blind Study 1180 is provided in <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">Table 23</ref>. As expected a larger percentage of placebo group subjects (5.7%) discontinued due to lack of efficacy compared with pregabalin group (0%). Discontinuation from the study due to adverse events was similar in the placebo group 59 Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) and pregabalin group (7.5% vs 7.4%). However, in the pregabalin group the adverse events appeared related to pregabalin and are discussed below. Four (7.4%) patients in the pregabalin group and four (7.5%) patients in the placebo group reported adverse events causing discontinuation form the study <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 24</ref>). In the pregabalin group weight increased was reported by two patients and depression and loss of consciousness were each reported by one patient. All AEs causing discontinuation in the pregabalin group were reviewed and considered possibly related to study drug. A summary of these SAEs is provided below. Depression was also reported by one patient in the placebo group. This 15-year-old white female subject with fibromyalgia started treatment with pregabalin on 11-Dec-2010. Following dose escalation, the subject was taking pregabalin 150 mg/day as of 04-Jan-2011. Her medical history was significant for increased triglycerides, depression, diarrhea, headache, and insomnia. Prior medications continued during the study were azelastine hydrochloride, fluoxetine, and marvelon.</p><p>On Study Day 52 (31-Jan-2011), the subject experienced weight increased of mild intensity. The subject weighed 163 lb. at screening on 02-Dec-2010, and was 65 inches in height. On 10-Dec-2010, the day of randomization, the subject weighed 167 lb. On 03-Jan-2011, the subject's weight was 169 lb., and on 31-Jan-2011 she weighed 172 lb. On 28-Feb-2010 and 07-Mar-2011, she weighed 174 lb., for a weight gain since randomization of approximately 7 lb. The investigator considered the event of weight increased as related to study drug. The study drug was permanently discontinued and the subject withdrawn from the study on 07-Mar-2011 due to this AE. The duration of treatment was 87 days. The event was still present at last reporting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>This subject gained 7 lb. (4%) while on LYRICA over a period of 11 weeks from the time of randomization. It is possible that some of the weight gain may not be related to Lyrica, considering she gained 4 lb. in eight days while not on study drug from the day of screening to randomization. On 13-Jun-2011 (Study Day 63), the subject first experienced loss of consciousness which resolved the same day. On the same date, she also experienced dizziness and vomiting. The investigator stated that "the patient had one syncope episode on 13-Jun 2011." Study drug dose at the time was 450 mg. The subject temporarily stopped study drug from 14 to 19 June 2011 (Study Days 64-69) due to the vomiting AE and due to the loss of consciousness for which study drug was initially stopped temporarily and subsequently permanently discontinued. After the investigator saw her on 20-Jun-2011, she restarted the medication that afternoon. The subject also took difenidol hydrochloride for dizziness from 20-Jun-2011 to 27-Jun-2011.</p><p>The investigator reported another episode of syncope happened on 21-Jun-2011 at school (Study Day 71), and that subsequently the patient decided to drop out of the trial. The event was reported as loss of consciousness, which the investigator considered of mild severity. The site reported that the subject fell down "in a swoon for few seconds at school." The subject's teacher called her name many times but there was no response. The subject awoke "after 5-10 seconds." In addition on 21-Jun-2011, the subject experienced mild headache and mild memory loss. The patient totally recovered soon after this episode in school. The study drug was permanently discontinued due to the second event of loss of consciousness</p><p>The patient saw the investigator on 30-Jun-2011 (Study Day80) with no sequelae. It is noted that the subject experienced a 5-kg weight loss between Study Days 52 and 80, during the timeframe of the episodes of syncope. Physical and neurological examination, vital signs (pulse and blood pressure), and electrocardiogram (ECG) performed at this visit on 30-Jun-2011 were otherwise normal. Throughout the study, laboratory assessments were normal with the exception of elevated eosinophils on Study Day 24, which were normal at the next evaluation on Study Day 80.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>The exact etiology of her adverse event coded as loss of consciousness but characterized by the investigator as syncope is unclear. Pregabalin cannot be excluded as the cause of the event. She had dizziness and vomiting on the day of the first event which is consistent with a syncopal episode. These categories increase the granularity for tracking suicidal ideation and behavior, following the C-SSRS structure. The more fine-grained subcategories (eg, ideation with method and intent, but no plan) are not part of the STS. However, the STS has good accuracy for identifying broad categories of suicidal ideation and behavior. Given the limited number of subjects enrolled in the study and few subjects identified with suicidal ideation, the difference in the two scales would not result in any significant overall difference in results and interpretation of the findings. Since the LYRICA label already contains a suicide warning and there were no unexpected findings, there is no need for the Applicant to collect additional safety information on suicidality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4">Supportive Safety Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.1">Common Adverse Events</head><p>Of the 107 patients enrolled in Study 1180, there were 38 (70%) subjects in the pregabalin group and 34 (64%) subjects in the placebo group, who had at least 1 treatment-emergent adverse event (TEAE) during the study (includes 1 subject in the pregabalin group with a SAE). An overview of the most common treatment-emergent adverse events for Study 1180 and study 1231 is provided in <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">Table 25</ref>. The most common adverse events in placebo-controlled study 1180 were: dizziness, 30% in the pregabalin group and 13% in the placebo group; nausea 22% in the pregabalin group and 9% in the placebo group; headache, 19% in the pregabalin group and 19% in the placebo group; weight increased, 17% in the pregabalin group and no subjects in the placebo group; fatigue, 15% in the pregabalin group and 8% in the placebo group and; somnolence 9% in the pregabalin group and 4% in the placebo group. investigator. The events which were not study drug-related were attributed by the investigator to other illness, co-occurrence with migraine or menstrual cramps, or situational concerns such as school stress. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.2">Laboratory Findings</head><p>Serum chemistry, hematology and urinalysis tests were obtained at V1 (Screening), V6 (Week 3) and V10 (Week 15/Early Termination). The median changes in laboratory data from baseline to last observation did not appear to be clinically relevant for any of the parameters studied. However, it is noted that median platelet levels decreased from baseline by 7 x 10 3 /mm 3 in pregabalin-treated subjects and by 4 x 10 3 /mm 3 in placebotreated subjects. Two subjects on pregabalin experienced thrombocytopenia considered related to study drug. One of these subjects, 10331006, had baseline thrombocytopenia (platelet value of 106 x 10 9 /L, reference range 140-450 x 10 9 /L) and an increase to 267 x 10 9 /L (Day 21) before dropping to a low of 85 x 10 9 /L (Day 105) and ending the study at 166 x 10 9 /L (Day 116). Subject 10331010 had a baseline platelet value of 147 x10 9 /L which dropped to 85 x10 9 /L (Day 52) and ended the study at 108 x10 9 /L (Day 121). There was no evidence of a pancytopenia in either of these patients. The finding of decreased platelets is consistent with the warning in the approved label below:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>67</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p><p>LYRICA treatment was associated with a decrease in platelet count. LYRICA-treated subjects experienced a mean maximal decrease in platelet count of 20 × 10 3 /µL, compared to 11 × 10 3 /µL in placebo patients. In the overall database of controlled trials, 2% of placebo patients and 3% of LYRICA patients experienced a potentially clinically significant decrease in platelets, defined as 20% below baseline value and less than 150 × 10 3 /µL. A single LYRICA treated subject developed severe thrombocytopenia with a platelet count less than 20 × 10 3 / µL. In randomized controlled trials, LYRICA was not associated with an increase in bleeding-related adverse reactions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reproductive Hormone Levels</head><p>Due to nonclinical findings that pregabalin could have a negative effect on female fertility and possibly also affect sexual maturation, the Division requested that the Applicant measure reproductive hormones in their clinical studies.</p><p>The Applicant previously conducted two reproductive developmental toxicology studies in the juvenile rat. In the first study (RR 745-03267) conducted in male rats, sexual development was delayed, epididymal weight and sperm motility were reduced and when treated males were mated with untreated females decreased numbers of implants and live fetuses were seen. Female rat fertility was significantly lower than expected in all groups including controls (~60-70%). Therefore another study conducted only in juvenile females was undertaken (RR 745-03471). This study reported that when female rats were given pregabalin at doses of 50, 250 or 500 mg/kg for up to 9 weeks, vaginal opening was delayed, diestrus prolonged and fertility decreased. A NOAEL was not determined for these reproductive effects. The 50 mg/kg/day dose level concern was mainly driven by decreased fertility in females. This decrease was not statistically significant but appeared to be a trend which is dose-dependent in severity. Median laboratory values (estradiol, FSH, LH) were found to be within normal ranges following treatment in both studies (including both pregabalin and placebo treatment groups in Study 1180) <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 26</ref>). Generally, hormone evaluations at last observation either fell within normal limits by Tanner stage or were closer to normal ranges than for the same Tanner stage at baseline. It is noted that there are few subjects at earlier Tanner stages (e.g., 1-2 subjects at Tanner stages 1 and 2 in Study 1180).</p><p>Subjects whose reproductive hormone values were outside of the normal ranges appeared to reflect high mid-cycle levels (refer to <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">Table 28</ref> for mid-cycle reference ranges). Estradiol changes from baseline were not accompanied by substantive changes in FSH and LH <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 26</ref>), suggesting that these were reflective of inter-and intrasubject variability and menstrual cycle timing; thus, none of the findings were considered to be clinically relevant.   Pfizer in their discussion below noted a variety of factors complicating the interpretation of their data.</p><p>There are a variety of factors influencing reproductive hormone levels, resulting in a more complex interpretation. The results cover a wide range due to innate variability in the normal ranges. Between individuals, there are differences in hormone concentrations reflecting variations in the advancement of puberty. For patients who have experienced the onset of menarche, hormone levels fluctuate considerably during the menstrual cycle, with mid-cycle spikes of FSH and LH preceded by elevation of estrogen (e.g., estradiol)…Menstrual cycles are often irregular in adolescents (48% in one study), lending uncertainty to when peaks in hormone levels would be anticipated. Additionally, hormone levels vary across the day for any given individual…Lastly, there is inherent variability in Tanner staging by self-report compared with physical examination, particularly in younger adolescents. Recognizing these variables, the results obtained in the 2 studies are compatible with normal puberty and fluctuations in hormone levels throughout the menstrual cycle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Division of Bone, Reproductive and Urologic Products Consult</head><p>The Division of Bone, Reproductive and Urologic Products (DBRUP) was consulted to determine whether the reproductive hormone laboratory assessments demonstrated any clinically relevant findings related to reproductive health. DBRUP concluded that the serum hormone laboratory data obtained are not clinically interpretable and provided the following additional comments. The rat reproductive system is significantly different than the human reproductive system. Rat reproduction is very heavily prolactin dependent. For example, many of the SSRI/SSNRIs have clinical effects on serum prolactin that can significantly affect rat reproductive behavior and fertility. In this reviewer's opinion, prolactin levels should have been evaluated in the rats and in humans. If there were effects of pregabalin on prolactin in rats and not in humans, that would lend support to a species-specific effect of pregabalin on the reproductive system.</p><p>Although the Applicant provided publications with ranges of serum hormone levels in puberty in their response to a clinical request (See Applicant's response dated July 22,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>70</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) 2016), it is not possible to compare serum hormone levels because the publications were done many years ago with different laboratory kits that have different methodology and levels of detection. Also, the serum hormone data were not obtained with regard to the phase of the menstrual cycle. Even if the menstrual cycle data had been obtained, however, the hormone data may still be difficult to interpret as many adolescents girls have anovulatory or irregular cycles in early puberty resulting in unpredictable hormonal levels. The lack of menstrual diaries preclude the ability to detect increased rates of anovulation or oligovoluation. Finally, it is unknown whether most girls can accurately self-report Tanner stage which further complicates interpretation.</p><p>Seven subjects reported reproductive adverse events, five with dysmenorrhea, one with vaginal spotting and one with an ovarian cyst. These events are commonly reported in adolescents, especially within two to three years after initiation of menses.</p><p>It is not possible to identify infertility in adolescent girls. From this reviewer's perspective, the primary clinical conditions that could be monitored that could alter future fertility include anovulation, delayed puberty or premature ovarian failure. These conditions can be identified through menstrual diaries and serial visits over years to document whether the girls have normal menstrual cycles and are reaching appropriate milestones in development through Tanner staging. Also, growth charts and bone age could be useful if pubertal delay is identified. Since these evaluations often take several years of measurement, whether there are long-term effects of pregabalin on anovulation, pubertal milestones or premature ovarian failure is unknown with the available evidence. An important missing gap in assessing the relevance of the animal findings to humans is the drug's effect on prolactin. For example, if there were effects of pregabalin on prolactin in rats but not in humans, that would lend support to a species-specific effect of pregabalin on the reproductive system, and reduce the likelihood of clinical relevance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Summary</head><p>The reproductive hormone data and self-reported Tanner staging are inconclusive and inadequate for determining whether there is an effect of pregabalin on future fertility and pubertal development. Although it is not possible to identify infertility in adolescent girls, it would be possible to monitor anovulation, delayed puberty or premature ovarian failure which could alter future fertility, but this would require documenting menstrual cycles and developmental milestones in a study lasting years. The approved label provides the nonclinical findings related to fertility in Section 8.4 Pediatric Use:</p><p>In studies in which pregabalin (50 to 500 mg/kg) was orally administered to young rats from early in the postnatal period (Postnatal Day 7) through sexual maturity, neurobehavioral abnormalities (deficits in learning and memory, altered locomotor activity, decreased auditory startle responding and habituation) and reproductive impairment (delayed sexual maturation and decreased fertility in males and females) were observed at doses ≥50 mg/kg. The neurobehavioral changes of acoustic startle persisted at ≥250 mg/kg and locomotor activity and water maze performance at ≥500 mg/kg in animals tested after cessation of dosing and, thus, were considered to represent long-term effects. The low effect dose for developmental neurotoxicity and reproductive impairment in juvenile rats (50 mg/kg) was associated with a plasma 71</p><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) pregabalin exposure (AUC) approximately equal to human exposure at the maximum recommended dose of 600 mg/day. A no-effect dose was not established.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.3">Vital Signs</head><p>For placebo-controlled study 1180, vital signs including blood pressure, pulse and weight were obtained at screening, randomization and visits at weeks 3, 7, 11 and 15. Height was done at screening and week 15 only. Review of the vital signs revealed no clinically relevant changes except for weight gain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Weight Gain</head><p>During Study 1180, a total of 11 subjects had a weight gain of at least 7% compared to no patients in the placebo group <ref type="table" target="#tab_14">(Table 29)</ref>. Two subjects (3.7%) discontinued treatment during Study 1180 due to weight gain.   The observed weight gain in adolescents is not unexpected since it is known that LYRICA may cause weight gain in adults. In LYRICA controlled clinical trials of up to 14 weeks, a gain of 7% or more over baseline weight was observed in 9% of LYRICAtreated patients and 2% of placebo-treated patients.</p><p>During Study 1180 there were no clinically significant differences in mean or median systolic or diastolic blood pressure or pulse rate between treatment groups. The number of subjects with a 30% or greater increase or decrease in pulse rate from baseline to last visit was similar in both treatment groups. A 30% increase in pulse rate was reported in 2 (3.8%) pregabalin subjects and 2 (4.0%) placebo patients and a 30% decrease was reported in no pregabalin patients and 1 (2.0%) placebo patient.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4.4">Electrocardiograms (ECGs)</head><p>Electrocardiograms were recorded at screening and end of study or early termination. There were no clinically relevant changes in ECG parameters. The Applicant assessed</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Recommendation on Regulatory Action ............................................................. 8 1.2 Risk Benefit Assessment.................................................................................... 8 1.3 Recommendations for Postmarket Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies ... 9 1.4 Recommendations for Postmarket Requirements and Commitments ................ 9 Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) 8 POSTMARKET EXPERIENCE............................................................................... 759 APPENDICES ...</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>..... 75 9.1 Literature Review/References .......................................................................... 75 9.2 Labeling Recommendations ............................................................................. 75 9.3 Advisory Committee Meeting...........................................................................</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>..... 26 Table 6: Study Drug Taper Schedule......................................................................... 29 Table 7: Prohibited Medications ................................................................................ 30 Table 8: Schedule of Activities Study 1231............................................................... 37 Table 9: Demographic Characteristics for Pregabalin and Placebo Treatment Groups .......................................................................................................... 41 Table 10: Subject Disposition (Study 1180) .............................................................. 42 Table 11: Protocol Deviations (Randomized Subjects)............................................ 43 Table 12: Applicant's Analysis of Primary Endpoint -Change from Baseline to Week 15 in Weekly Mean Pain Score -Daily Pain NRS............................. 44 Table 13: FDA Analysis of Primary Efficacy Endpoint............................................. 44 Table 14: Summary of Applicant's Sensitivity Analyses -Change from Baseline to Week 15 in Weekly Mean Pain Score -Daily Pain NRS (24-Hour Recall) 45 Table 15: Analysis of Changes from Baseline to Weekly Mean Pain Scores-Daily Pain NRS (24-Hour Recall) .......................................................................... 46 Table 16: Applicant's Analysis of 30% and 50% Mean Pain Score Responders at Week 15 ........................................................................................................ 47 Table 17: Analysis of Patient Global Impression of Change at Week 15................ 49 Table 18: Applicants Analysis of Duration of Use of NSAIDs, COX-2 Inhibitors, and Acetaminophen-and Aspirin-Containing Medications .................... 50 Table 19: FDA Subgroup Analyses by Dose Group ................................................. 51 Table 20: FDA Subgroup Analyses by Country........................................................ 52 Table 21: Duration of TreatmentStudy 1180 ............................................................ 54 Table 22: Duration of Treatment by Dose, Combined Controlled and Uncontrolled Studies (A0081180 and A0081231) ............................................................. 55 Table 23: Patient Disposition by Treatment Group for Study1180......................... 60 Table 24: Adverse Events Causing Discontinuation During Study 1180 ............... 60 Table 25: Common Adverse Events Study 1180 and Study 1231 (Experienced by at least 4 subjects in the Pregabalin Treatment Group in Study 1180) ... 67 Table 26: Study 1180 Hormone Levels: Median Changes from Baseline to Last Observation ..................................................................................... 69 Table 27: Study 1231 Hormone Levels: Median Changes from Baseline to Last Observation ............................................ 69 Table 28: Normal Ranges for Estradiol, FSH, and LH by Age and Phase .............. 70 Table 29: Summary of Weight Gain from Baseline to Last Visit (Study A0081180) ....................................................................................................................... 72 Table 30: Summary of ElectrocardiogramInterpretation (Study 1180) .................</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>..... 18 Figure 2: FDA Analysis of Weekly Average Pain Scores (observed and imputed) 46 FDA Responder Curve of Percent Improvement in Pain from Baseline at Week 15 ...</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>disclosed financial arrangements with clinical investigators. Two</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>endpoint of change from baseline to Week 15 in average pain intensity. Safety Safety findings from the double-blind study (Study 1180) and the open-label extension study (Study 1231) are discussed in Section 7 on Safety. 5.3 Discussion of Individual Studies/Clinical Trials the Applicant conducted Study A0081180, (b) (4) hereafter referred to as Study 1180. The following summary of the design of Study 1180 was derived from Final Protocol Amendment 3, dated March 14, 2014. Important modifications to the original protocol are summarized at the end of the protocol. Title: A 15 WEEK, RANDOMIZED, DOUBLE BLIND, PARALLEL-GROUP, PLACEBO-CONTROLLED, FLEXIBLE-DOSE, SAFETY AND EFFICACY STUDY OF PREGABALIN IN ADOLESCENTS (12-17 YEARS OLD) WITH FIBROMYALGIA Dates Conducted: The first patient enrolled May 7, 2010 and last patient completed December 8, 2014.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(b) (4) points from baseline while placebo-treated subjects experienced a (b) (4)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>day BID from (b) (6) (Study Day 51) to (Study Day 170), and then started a taper until the medicine was stopped on (Study Day 175).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>28: Summary of Weight Gain from Baseline to Last Visit (Study A0081180) a post-baseline weight measurement are included in this</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Table of Contents 1 RECOMMENDATIONS/RISK</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table of Tables</head><label>of</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 1 : Presubmission Regulatory Interactions between FDA and the Applicant ...</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>..... 10 Table 2: Phase 3 Studies</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>.... 16 Table 3: Schedule of Activities ...</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>.... 22 Table 5: Dose Escalation</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Risk Benefit Assessment 1.1 Recommendation on Regulatory Action</head><label></label><figDesc>..... 48 I recommend approving this labeling supplement for LYRICA (pregabalin) with the modified language shown in Section 9.2 (Labeling Recommendations) of this review.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>1 Recommendations/</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 1 displays</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>highlights of the regulatory activity that occurred during the clinical development program for Lyrica for the treatment of fibromyalgia in adolescents.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 1 : Presubmission Regulatory Interactions between FDA and the Applicant</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Date</cell><cell>Topics</cell></row><row><cell>June 21, 2007</cell><cell>• Lyrica approved for the management of fibromyalgia in</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446 approved</cell><cell>adults</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Pediatric study requirements waived for ages 0 to 12 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Pediatric study requirements deferred for ages 13 to 16</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>years with a final report submission date of January 31,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2012</cell></row><row><cell>January 30, 2008</cell><cell>Pfizer submitted a new pediatric protocol (A0081180) for fulfill</cell></row><row><cell>New protocol</cell><cell>their required pediatric study requirement</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>10</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 1 : Presubmission Regulatory Interactions between FDA and the Applicant</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>January 9, 2009</cell><cell>The Division made the following comments about Protocol</cell></row><row><cell>FDA Advice Letter</cell><cell>A0081180:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Your proposed pediatric study is primarily a safety and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>tolerability study and is not designed to demonstrate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>efficacy. Demonstration of efficacy and safety are</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>necessary.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• You will need to demonstrate efficacy with at least 12</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>weeks of double-blind therapy.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• The Yunus and Masi criteria are acceptable for</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>diagnosing juvenile fibromyalgia syndrome.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Flexible dosing with of 75 to 450 mg/day is acceptable.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Enroll patients ages 12 to 16 years old, inclusive.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Female reproductive hormone levels should be monitored.</cell></row><row><cell>January 4, 2010</cell><cell>• Lyrica Oral Solution approved for neuropathic pain</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 22488 approved</cell><cell>associated with DPN and PHN, adjunctive therapy of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>patients with partial onset seizures and fibromyalgia.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Pediatric study requirement waived for ages 0 to 16 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>for patients with neuropathic pain associated with DPN</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>and PHN</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Pediatric study requirement waived for ages 0 to 12 years</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>in patients with fibromyalgia because pediatric</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>fibromyalgia studies are impossible or highly impracticable</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>to conduct due to the low incidence of this condition.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• Pediatric study requirement deferred for ages 13 to 16</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>years with a final report submission date of January 31,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2012</cell></row><row><cell>December 19, 2012</cell><cell>Pfizer requested a deferral extension for the clinical study</cell></row><row><cell>Deferral extension</cell><cell>report for Study 1180 to December 31, 2017 due to the slow</cell></row><row><cell>request</cell><cell>recruitment of adolescent fibromyalgia patients.</cell></row><row><cell>January 8, 2013</cell><cell>The Division made the following comments and</cell></row><row><cell>FDA Advice Letter</cell><cell>recommendations for Protocol A0081180:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• We note that you plan to monitor subjects for suicidality</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>using the Suicidality Tracking Scale. This instrument does</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>not adequately capture key categories of suicidal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>ideations and behaviors.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• We recommend use of the Columbia-Suicide Severity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Rating Scale (C-SSRS) or another instrument that will</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>capture the information described in the Draft Guidance.</cell></row></table><note>• You propose to use LOCF imputation for the efficacy pain measure for all patients who discontinue for any reason. Single imputation methods such as LOCF are not</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 1 : Presubmission Regulatory Interactions between FDA and the Applicant</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>currently preferred for efficacy analyses. Consult the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>National Academy of Sciences report on missing data. We</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>favor approaches that attribute poor outcomes to those</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>patients that discontinue prior to the end of the study.</cell></row><row><cell>April 8, 2013</cell><cell>The Division revised the Final Report Submission date to</cell></row><row><cell>New Postmarketing</cell><cell>December 31, 2017 and included 17 year olds in the</cell></row><row><cell>Requirement Date</cell><cell>population to be evaluated.</cell></row><row><cell>March 4, 2014</cell><cell>The Division provided the following written responses to</cell></row><row><cell>Type C Written</cell><cell>Pfizer's request for a Type C Meeting:</cell></row><row><cell>Response</cell><cell>• The Division agreed with the proposed imputation and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>analyses.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>• The Division agreed with the proposed change in sample</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>size of 106 subjects.</cell></row></table><note>• The Division noted that if Pfizer plans to enroll only 106</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 2 : Phase 3 Studies Study Title Number of Subjects/Dose 1180 Efficacy</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>A 15 Week, Randomized, Double-</cell><cell>107 subjects treated: 54 pregabalin</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Blind, Parallel-Group, Placebo-</cell><cell>and 53 placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Controlled, Flexible-Dose, Safety and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Efficacy Study of Pregabalin in</cell><cell>Pregabalin 75, 150, 300, or 450</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Adolescents (12-17 Years Old) with</cell><cell>mg/day (dosed BID)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Fibromyalgia</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>A 6-Month, Open-Label, Safety Trial</cell><cell>63 subjects continued from Study</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of Pregabalin in Adolescent Patients</cell><cell>1180 into the open-label study</cell></row><row><cell>81231 Safety</cell><cell>with Fibromyalgia</cell><cell>(33 subjects previously treated with pregabalin and 30 subjects with placebo)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Pregabalin 75, 150, 300, or 450</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>mg/day (dosed BID)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 3 : Schedule of Activities 22</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note>Source: CSR 1180. Schedule of Activities, p. 43-45</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 4 : Dose Escalation Guidelines</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row></table><note>Source: CSR 1180. Table 1, p. 29 Suicidality Risk Assessment During the Clinical Trial At the baseline (randomization) and post-baseline visits, if there is any positive response on STS items 1a, 1b, both 3 and 4, 5, 6, or 8 (score of ≥1), a risk assessment must be done by a qualified MHP to determine whether it is safe for the subject to continue to participate in the trial. Subjects who have a positive response on STS</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The following procedures were to have been conducted at this visit: • For subjects entering open-label extension Study A0081231, Informed Consent/Assent must be obtained. • Physical examination (including height, weight, pulse, blood pressure). • Abbreviated neurological examination (muscle strength, gait and reflexes). • Assessment of pubertal status (Tanner Staging) -females only. • 12-lead ECG. • Clinical laboratory tests: (hematology, chemistry with estimated serum CLcr, urinalysis, drug testing and serum pregnancy tests). • Reproductive hormone evaluations for females only.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>Visit 10 Termination Visit (Week 15) -Clinic Visit</cell></row></table><note>• Weekly Pain Numeric Rating Scale (Pain-NRS).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>Table 5 : Study Drug Taper Schedule</head><label>5</label><figDesc>If the subject was not entering open-label extension Study 1231, this visit may have been completed by phone. If the subject was entering the open-label extension study, this visit was to have been conducted in the clinic and was considered V1.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note>Source: Study 1180 Clinical Study Report. Table 5, p. 39 29</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_23"><head>Table 6 : Prohibited Medications</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: CSR1180. Table 1, p. 41</cell></row><row><cell>30</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Rheumatoid Factor (V1 Only), Thyroid-Stimulating Hormone (TSH) and T4 (V1 Only), Total Protein, Total Bilirubin, Uric Acid</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>Hematology: Hemoglobin, Hematocrit, Red Blood Cell (RBC) Count, Platelet Count,</cell></row><row><cell>White Blood Cell (WBC) Count, Differential (Neutrophils, Lymphocytes, Monocytes,</cell></row><row><cell>Eosinophils, Basophils)</cell></row><row><cell>Urinalysis: pH, Specific Gravity, Glucose, Microscopic Sediment Examination (if</cell></row><row><cell>indicated), Drug screen (V1 and V10 only and as indicated)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>weeks), flexible dose (21 weeks), and follow-up/taper (1 week). Day 1 of this open-label study (Visit 1) was the same day as Visit 11 in study A0081180.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>optimization (3</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head>Table 7 : Schedule of Activities Study 1231 37</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note>Source: CSR A0081231. Table 4, p.33</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Subjects who met the eligibility criteria received open-label treatment with pregabalin. Subjects optimized their dose based on efficacy and tolerability over a 3-week period to one of the following pregabalin doses: 75 mg/day (minimum allowable dose), 150 mg/day, 300 mg/day, or 450 mg/day (maximum allowable dose). At the end of the study, all subjects tapered their dose over a 1-week period.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>Safety Assessments</cell></row><row><cell>Duration of Treatment: Up to 25 weeks</cell></row><row><cell>Efficacy Assessments</cell></row><row><cell>• Pain Numeric Rating Scale (NRS)</cell></row></table><note>• Frequency and severity of adverse events (AEs)• Physical and neurological examinations• Vital signs• Electrocardiogram (ECG)• Laboratory assessment• Tanner staging• Suicidality assessment</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Table 8 :</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Demographic Characteristics for Pregabalin and Placebo Treatment Groups</figDesc><table><row><cell>Demographic Characteristic</cell><cell>Pregabalin</cell><cell>Placebo</cell><cell>Total</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(N=54)</cell><cell>(N=53)</cell><cell>(N=107)</cell></row><row><cell>Gender</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Male</cell><cell>6 (11)</cell><cell>9 (17)</cell><cell>15 (14)</cell></row><row><cell>Female</cell><cell>48 (89)</cell><cell>44 (83)</cell><cell>92 (86)</cell></row><row><cell>Premenarchal</cell><cell>1 (2.2)</cell><cell>1 (2.3)</cell><cell>2 (2.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Menarche</cell><cell>47 (97.9)</cell><cell>43 (97.7)</cell><cell>90 (97.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Age (years)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>14.6 (1.2)</cell><cell>14.7 (1.2)</cell><cell>14.7 (1.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell>12-17</cell><cell>12-16</cell><cell>12-17</cell></row><row><cell>Age group</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12 years</cell><cell>4 (7.4)</cell><cell>3 (5.7)</cell><cell>7 (6.5)</cell></row><row><cell>13 years</cell><cell>5 (9.3)</cell><cell>6 (11.3)</cell><cell>11 (10.3)</cell></row><row><cell>14 years</cell><cell>15 (27.8)</cell><cell>8 (15.1)</cell><cell>23 (21.5)</cell></row><row><cell>15 years</cell><cell>18 (33.3)</cell><cell>21 (39.6)</cell><cell>39 (36.4)</cell></row><row><cell>16 years</cell><cell>10 (18.5)</cell><cell>15 (28.3)</cell><cell>25 (23.4)</cell></row><row><cell>17 years</cell><cell>2 (3.7)</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 (1.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Race</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>White</cell><cell>29 (53.7)</cell><cell>32 (60.4)</cell><cell>61 (57)</cell></row><row><cell>Black</cell><cell>2 (3.7)</cell><cell>3 (5.7)</cell><cell>5 (4.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Asian</cell><cell>21 (38.9)</cell><cell>15 (28.3)</cell><cell>36 (33.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>2 (3.7)</cell><cell>3 (5.7)</cell><cell>5 (4.7)</cell></row><row><cell>Weight (kg)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>60.4 (21.4)</cell><cell>59.7 (17.7)</cell><cell>60.1 (19.6)</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell>28.5-154.7</cell><cell>39.0-127.6</cell><cell>28.5-154.7</cell></row><row><cell>Height (cm)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Mean (SD)</cell><cell>160 (7.6)</cell><cell>162 (8.2)</cell><cell>161 (7.9)</cell></row><row><cell>Range</cell><cell>141-178</cell><cell>147-183</cell><cell>141-183</cell></row><row><cell>Source: CSR 1180. Table 13, p.77</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6.1.3 Subject Disposition</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Subject Disposition</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="4">Enrollment/Randomization: Of the 147 subjects screened for this study, 107 subjects</cell></row><row><cell cols="4">were randomized to treatment, 54 patients to receive pregabalin and 53 patients to</cell></row><row><cell>receive placebo.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Double-blind Treatment Period: All 107 randomized subjects took at least one dose of study drug. A total of 44 (81.5%) subjects in the pregabalin group and 36 (67.9%) subjects in the placebo group completed the study. Table 10 summarizes subject</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>Table 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">: Subject Disposition (Study 1180)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pregabalin</cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>n (%*)</cell><cell>n (%*)</cell></row><row><cell>Randomized</cell><cell>54</cell><cell>53</cell></row><row><cell>Completed Study</cell><cell>44 (81.5%)</cell><cell>36 (67.9%)</cell></row><row><cell>Discontinued Study</cell><cell>10 (18.5%)</cell><cell>17 (32.1%)</cell></row><row><cell>Adverse Event</cell><cell>4 (7.4%)</cell><cell>4 1 (7.5%)</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of Efficacy</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3 (5.7%)</cell></row><row><cell>No longer willing to participate</cell><cell>5 (9.3%)</cell><cell>7 (13.2%)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>1 (1.9%)</cell><cell>1 (1.9%)</cell></row><row><cell>Protocol Violation</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 2 (3.8%)</cell></row><row><cell>* Percent of randomized subjects</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Source: CSR 1180. Modified from Table 10, p.73</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_31"><head>Table 10 : Protocol Deviations (Randomized Subjects)</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: CSR 1180. Table 11, p74</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.4 Analysis of Primary Endpoint(s)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_32"><head>Table 13</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>).</cell></row><row><cell>43</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_33"><head>Table 11 : Applicant's Analysis of Primary Endpoint -Change from Baseline to Week 15 in Weekly Mean Pain Score -Daily Pain NRS</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>Source: CSR 1180. Table 17, p.81</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>Table 12 : FDA Analysis of Primary Efficacy Endpoint</head><label>12</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>Table 13 : Summary of Applicant's Sensitivity Analyses -Change from Baseline to Week 15 in Weekly Mean Pain Score -Daily Pain NRS (24-Hour Recall)Secondary Efficacy Endpoints The</head><label>13</label><figDesc>Division does not consider any of the secondary efficacy endpoints to be statistically significant since the study failed to demonstrate statistical evidence of efficacy with the prespecified primary endpoint.</figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_36"><head>Table 16 : Analysis of Patient Global Impression of Change at Week 15</head><label>16</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_38"><head>Table 17 : Applicants Analysis of Duration of Use of NSAIDs, COX-2 Inhibitors, and Acetaminophen-and Aspirin-Containing Medications</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: Study 1180. Pfizer Response to Information Request. Table 1, p.2</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.6 Other Endpoints</cell></row><row><cell>Not Applicable</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.7 Subpopulations</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_40"><head>Table 18 : FDA Subgroup Analyses by Dose Group</head><label>18</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head>Table 19 : FDA Subgroup Analyses by Country</head><label>19</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head>Table 20 : Duration of Treatment Study 1180</head><label>20</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Source: CSR 1180. Table 26, p.94 Combined Exposure for Studies 1180 and 1231 The combined duration of treatment for Study 1180 and Study 8123 including the 3 week dose optimization for each study, 12-week fixed dose phase in Study 1180, 21 week flexible dosing phase in Study 81231, and 1-week taper for each study is summarized in</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Study Day 100), the subject was admitted to the children's medical center to receive a dihydroergotamine (DHE) protocol for her migraine. She received a total of 14 doses of DHE and her migraine improved.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(On (b) (6)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>(Study Day 17), but then started tapering on</cell><cell>b) (6)</cell><cell>(Study Day 27)</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">to determine if the study drug was causing the migraine. The subject decreased the</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">dose to 75 mg/day, but this made no difference to the migraine, however, fibromyalgia</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">pain was worsening. The subject therefore increased the dose back up to 225 mg/day (Study Day 51). on (b) (6)</cell></row><row><cell>58</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_44"><head>Table 22 :</head><label>22</label><figDesc>Patient Disposition by Treatment Group for Study 1180</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Pregabalin</cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N=54</cell><cell>N=53</cell></row><row><cell>Analysis Group</cell><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row><row><cell>Discontinued study</cell><cell>10 (18.5)</cell><cell>17 (32.1)</cell></row><row><cell>Adverse event</cell><cell>4 (7.4)</cell><cell>4 (7.5)</cell></row><row><cell>Lack of efficacy</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>3 (5.7)</cell></row><row><cell>No longer willing to participate</cell><cell>5 (9.3)</cell><cell>7 (13.2)</cell></row><row><cell>Protocol violation</cell><cell>0</cell><cell>2 (3.8)</cell></row><row><cell>Other</cell><cell>1 (1.9)</cell><cell>1 (1.9)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">N=number of patients; n=number of patients in subgroup.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Source: CSR Protocol 1180. Table 10, p73</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_45"><head>Table 23 : Adverse Events Causing Discontinuation During Study 1180 MedDRA Preferred Term Pregabalin</head><label>23</label><figDesc>nausea considered related to study drug and a summary of this patient is provided below. Subject 10531004 developed low back pain secondary to spinal stenosis considered unrelated to pregabalin.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Placebo</cell></row><row><cell>N=54</cell><cell>N=53</cell></row><row><cell>n (%)</cell><cell>n (%)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_48"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Of the 63 patients enrolled in Study 1231, there were 45 (71%) subjects on pregabalin who had at least 1 TEAE during the study. The most commonly reported TEAEs by preferred term were: dizziness 22%, fatigue 8%, headache 10%, nausea 8%, abdominal pain 8%, abdominal pain upper 8%. The most common adverse events in the openlabel study were similar to the double-blind study.The most common AEs in the adolescent studies were dizziness, nausea, headache, weight gain, fatigue and somnolence. These adverse events are consistent with the adverse events observed in the adult studies except for nausea which was reported at a greater frequency in Study 1180. The Applicant provides the following additional details for Study 1180; 12 pregabalin-treated subjects and 5 placebo subjects reported nausea. In each treatment group, 4 of the events were considered study drug-related by the 66</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_49"><head>Table 24 : Common Adverse Events Study 1180 and Study 1231 (Experienced by at least 4 subjects in the Pregabalin Treatment Group in Study</head><label>24</label><figDesc>CSR A0081180 Table 14.3.1.2.3.1 and Table 14.3.1.2.3.2 and CSR A008123 Table 14.3.1.2.3</figDesc><table><row><cell>1180)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_50"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The 83.3% (at 50 mg/kg/day) vs. 89.5% in the controls appeared to be a marginal decline. Based on these findings, the Division requested that the Applicant include measurement of reproductive hormones in their clinical studies.Estradiol, follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and luteinizing hormone (LH) levels were obtained at screening and end of study for placebo-controlled Study 1180 and at screening of Study 1231 if not previously performed at Week 15 of Study 1180, and at end of Study 1231.Pfizer's Analysis of Reproductive HormonesPfizer submitted (July 22, 2016) a summary of their findings and concluded that no clinically relevant changes in reproductive hormones or Tanner stage were observed, and no reproductive system adverse events were reported suggestive of pregabalin induced alternations in reproductive hormones. Pfizer provided the following interpretation of the hormone levels but noted a variety of factors could influence the reproductive hormone levels.68Median changes from baseline to last observation in estradiol, FSH, and LH were determined for Study 1180 (pregabalin and placebo groups;Table 26below) and Study 1231(Table 27below) across all subjects evaluated…</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Robert A. Levin, MD</cell></row><row><cell>NDA 21446</cell></row><row><cell>Lyrica (Pregabalin)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_51"><head>Table 25 : Study 1180 Hormone Levels: Median Changes from Baseline to Last Observation</head><label>25</label><figDesc>: Pfizer July 22, 2016 Response to IR. Module 5.3.5.1 Table 1.2</figDesc><table><row><cell>Source</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_52"><head>Table 26 : Study 1231 Hormone Levels: Median Changes from Baseline to Last Observation Source</head><label>26</label><figDesc>: Pfizer July 22, 2016 Response to IR. Module 5.3.5.2 Table 2.2 69</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 4018670</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_53"><head>Table 27 : Normal Ranges for Estradiol, FSH, and LH by Age and Phase</head><label>27</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>Source: Pfizer July 22, 2016 Response to IR.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_54"><head>Table</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_55"><head>table Source :</head><label>Source</label><figDesc>Study A0081180 Clinical Study Report. Table 14.3.4.2.5</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 4018670</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2.6">Evaluation for Potential Adverse Events for Similar Drugs in Drug Class</head><p>Pregabalin is approved in adults and the adverse event profile in this population is well known.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Major Safety Results</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.1">Deaths</head><p>There were no deaths during the LYRICA development program for fibromyalgia in adolescents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.2">Nonfatal Serious Adverse Events</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Serious Adverse Events</head><p>Of the 107 patients (54 on pregabalin and 53 on placebo) enrolled in double-blind Study 1180, one patient on pregabalin (2%) had 2 SAEs (cholelithiasis and major depression resulting in hospitalization). No patient on placebo in Study 1180 had an SAE. In openlabel safety Study 1231, three of 63 patients on pregabalin (5%) each had one SAE (migraine, joint instability and appendicitis). Narratives of all SAEs were reviewed. Pregabalin cannot be excluded as a contributing factor to the SAEs of major depression, cholelithiasis, and migraine. Summaries of the two patients with these three SAEs are provided below. and stopped treatment after 60 days on . Following dose escalation, the subject was taking pregabalin 150 mg/day as of 14-Aug 2010 and throughout the rest of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Individual Patient Summaries of Nonfatal Serious Adverse Events</head><p>Her medical history at study entry included gastroesophageal reflux, insomnia, metabolic syndrome, migraine, tension headache, polycystic ovaries, restless leg syndrome, and vitamin D deficiency. Past medical history was significant for depression. Treatments ongoing at study entry included ergocalciferol, ibuprofen, metformin hydrochloride, riboflavin, and vitamin B complex.</p><p>At screening, the subject's scores on self-reported suicidal ideation and behavior questionnaires, which included the Sheehan Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS), Quick Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) Her medical history included fibromyalgia symptoms since 2009 and headache. Prior treatments ongoing at study entry were meloxicam and paracetamol. Concomitant treatments during the study were cetirizine hydrochloride (stopped on Study Day 1), fexofenadine hydrochloride, gabapentin, and herbal preparation (butterbur).</p><p>On Study Day 22 (10-Jun-2011), the subject experienced increased weight of moderate intensity and study drug was permanently discontinued on 22-Aug-2011 after 82 days of treatment due to a 10 lb. weight gain.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>This subject's weight gain of 10 lb. from baseline was likely related to pregabalin. The weight gain was first noticed on Day 22 of treatment with pregabalin. This 13 year old white female discontinued pregabalin on Study Day 10 due to the adverse events of dizziness, fatigue, and nausea. She was treated with placebo in the preceding double-blind study A0081180 and started treatment with pregabalin in study A0081231 on 15-Oct-2011 (Study Day 1) and stopped treatment on 24-Oct-2011 (Study Day 10).</p><p>Medical history present at study entry included arthralgia and acne. Past medical history included cataract, gastroenteritis viral, ligament sprain, and wrist fracture. Prior treatments ongoing at study entry included adapalene, benzoyl peroxide/clindamycin, minocycline hydrochloride, sulfacet, and tretinoin.</p><p>On Study Day 4 (18-Oct-2011), the subject experienced AEs of dizziness, fatigue, and nausea, all of moderate intensity while on pregabalin 150 mg/day. The study drug was permanently discontinued due to these events on Study Day 10. The events resolved on Study Day 12 (26-Oct-2011), 2 days after study drug was discontinued.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Impression</head><p>The adverse events of dizziness, fatigue, and nausea resulting in study drug discontinuation were likely related to pregabalin. The onset of symptoms was on Day 4 of treatment and symptoms resolved two days after study drug was discontinued.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.4">Significant Adverse Events</head><p>Discussed in Section 7.3.2.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>63</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3.5">Submission Specific Primary Safety Concerns</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suicidal Behavior and Ideation</head><p>Approved Label: The currently approved label for LYRICA contains the following warning on suicidal behavior and ideation:</p><p>Antiepileptic drugs (AEDs), including LYRICA, increase the risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior in patients taking these drugs for any indication… The increased risk of suicidal thoughts or behavior with AEDs was observed as early as one week after starting drug treatment with AEDs and persisted for the duration of treatment assessed.</p><p>Background: The Division made the following comment on the preferred assessment to use for monitoring suicidal behavior and ideation in an Advice Letter dated January 18, 2013.</p><p>We note that you plan to monitor subjects for suicidality using the Suicidality Tracking Scale. This instrument does not adequately capture key categories of suicidal ideations and behaviors that are noted in the Draft Guidance for Industry on Suicidal Ideation and Behavior: Prospective Assessment of Occurrence in Clinical Trials and is not acceptable. We recommend use of the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C SSRS) or another instrument that will capture the information described in the Draft Guidance.</p><p>Based on the Division's recommendation, Pfizer added the Columbia-Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) to the ongoing study. However, the Division noted that if Pfizer planned to enroll only 106 patients in Study 1180 and given the enrollment at the time, this might result in at most, two patients with monitoring by the C-SSRS. Therefore, the Division provided the following comment to Pfizer on March 4, 2014 on how this might impact the filing and review of the proposed NDA: …However, as an approved product that is already labeled with a suicide warning, the data you have will be sufficient to support filing your application and the adequacy of the data collected on suicidal ideation and behavior will be a review issue. If, after review of the data, we believe additional data on suicidality is needed for this patient population, we may consider available options such as a new postmarketing requirement.</p><p>Suicidality Screening: During Study 1180 patients completed a suicidality risk assessment at screening, randomization, and weeks 3, 7, 11 and 15. The "lifetime" version of the Sheehan Suicidality Tracking Scale (STS) was completed at screening only and all other visits used STS for suicidality risk assessment "since last visit". The STS was administered any time the subject came in for a clinic visit, including unscheduled clinic visits. The Columbia Suicide Severity Rating Scale (C-SSRS) "Lifetime" was to be performed at screening, and the C-SSRS "since last visit" was to be performed at all subsequent visits and any time the subject came in for an unscheduled clinic visit. The timing of the suicidality assessments at baseline and at each clinic visit 64 Reference ID: 4018670</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) is considered adequate. For Study 1180, two of the 54 patients randomized to pregabalin were assessed using the C-SSRS and one of the 53 patients randomized to placebo was assessed using the C-SSRS. The adequacy of the suicidal assessments used is reviewed in the discussion section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Results</head><p>There were no completed suicides, suicide attempts or reports of suicidal behavior during Study 1180 or Study 1231. During placebo-controlled Study 1180 suicidal ideation was reported by 3 subjects (5.6%) in the pregabalin group and by 2 subjects (3.8%) in the placebo group. All the subjects with suicidal ideation during the study reported suicidal ideation during the screening assessment. At screening, 8 subjects in each treatment group reported suicidal ideation. During open-label safety study 1231, 6 (9.5%) subjects reported suicidal ideation, without plan or intent; these subjects all had a history of suicidal ideation noted at the time of screening for study 1180. No positive responses for suicidal ideation or behavior were recorded in the three subjects assessed with the C-SSRS. All of the required narratives based on mental health assessments were reviewed in both studies and no unexpected findings were noted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Discussion</head><p>During placebo-controlled study 1180, there did not appear to be a significant difference in the incidence of suicidal ideation between the placebo and LYRICA treatment arms and no suicidal behavior was reported in either treatment group but given the small size of the study a treatment difference would not be expected. During open-label safety study 1231, the six subjects with suicidal ideation all had a history of suicidal ideation at the time of screening. The frequency of suicidality assessments performed during the studies was adequate. The C-SSRS scale is the preferred assessment of the FDA. The FDA Guidance for Industry Suicidal Ideation and Behavior: Prospective Assessment of Occurrence in Clinical Trials (Draft 2012) describes the preferred terms that the FDA considers important and include five levels of suicidal ideation, five levels of suicidal behavior, and the category self-injurious behavior, no suicidal intent. The 11 categories are listed below:</p><p>Clinical Review Robert A. Levin, MD NDA 21446 Lyrica (Pregabalin) the number of "normal" and "abnormal, not clinically significant" ECGs at screening and end of treatment and found no significant difference <ref type="table">(Table 30)</ref>. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5">Other Safety Explorations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5.1">Dose Dependency for Adverse Events</head><p>The number of patients participating in the pediatric clinical development program for fibromyalgia was too small to for an analysis of dose dependency and adverse events. However, from the adult studies some of the adverse events appear to be dose dependent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>73</head><p>Reference ID: 4018670 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8">Postmarket Experience</head><p>There is no postmarket experience with LYRICA for the treatment of fibromyalgia in adolescents.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Appendices</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1">Literature Review/References</head><p>Not applicable</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.2">Labeling Recommendations</head><p>The existing label in Section 8.4 Pediatric Use contains the following clinical statement:</p><p>The safety and efficacy of pregabalin in pediatric patients have not been established.</p><p>The Applicant proposes adding the following language to Section 8.4:</p><p>frequently observed adverse reactions in the clinical trial included dizziness, nausea, headache, weight increased, and fatigue. The overall safety profile in adolescents was similar to that observed in adults with fibromyalgia.</p><p>The Division proposes modifying the Applicant's language by including a statement noting that the primary efficacy endpoint showed numerically greater improvement for pregabalin-treated patients but this did not reach statistical significance. The Division proposes the following language for Section 8.4:</p><p>Fibromyalgia A 15-week, placebo-controlled trial was conducted with 107 pediatric patients with fibromyalgia, ages 12 through17 years, at LYRICA total daily doses of 75-450 mg/day. The primary efficacy endpoint of change from baseline to Week 15 in mean pain intensity (derived from an 11-point numeric rating scale) showed numerically greater improvement for the pregabalin-treated patients compared to placebo-treated patients, but did not reach statistical significance. The most frequently observed adverse reactions in the clinical trial included dizziness, nausea, headache, weight increased, and fatigue. The overall safety profile in adolescents was similar to that observed in adults with fibromyalgia.</p><p>The Division proposes the following changes for Section 12. Add the following language under Pediatric Pharmacokinetics:</p><p>In the pediatric age group of 12 years of age and older, systemic exposure of pregabalin is similar to adults at any given dose of LYRICA [see Pediatric Use, (8.4)].</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.3">Advisory Committee Meeting</head><p>No Advisory Committee Meeting was held for this product.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>76</head><p>Reference <ref type="figure">ID: 4018670   ---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>---------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</head><p>----------------------------------------------------This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Passive suicidal ideation: wish to be dead 2. Active suicidal ideation: nonspecific (no method, intent</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>or plan</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Active: suicidal ideation: method and intent but no plan 5. Active: suicidal ideation: method, intent and plan Suicidal behavior 1. Completed suicide 2. Suicide attempt 3</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Active: suicidal ideation: method, but no intent or plan 4. Interrupted suicide attempt 4. Aborted suicide attempt</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
