<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 761025Orig1s000 MEDICAL REVIEW(S) CLINICAL REVIEW Application Type New BLA</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2015-08-10">Date August 10, 2015</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<addrLine>900 Ridgebury Road</addrLine>
									<postBox>P.O. Box 368 Ridgefield</postBox>
									<postCode>06877</postCode>
									<region>CT</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">CENTER FOR DRUG EVALUATION AND RESEARCH APPLICATION NUMBER: 761025Orig1s000 MEDICAL REVIEW(S) CLINICAL REVIEW Application Type New BLA</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2015-08-10">Date August 10, 2015</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Division/Office Division of Hematology Products Reviewer Name(s) Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Review Completion Established Name Idarucizumab (Proposed) Trade Name Praxbind Applicant Boehringer Ingelheim Pharmaceuticals</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
				<date type="submission" when="761025-2-19" />
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="table" target="#tab_2">Table of Tables   Table Number  Table Title  1  Table of</ref> <p>• Praxbind® (idarucizumab) is a humanized monoclonal antibody fragment (Fab) indicated in patients treated with dabigatran (Pradaxa®) when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding.</p><p>However, the proposed indication should be changed to remove the wording, "anticoagulant effect" and replaced with the wording "pharmacodynamic effect" which more accurately reflects that the demonstrated effect of idarucizumab in clinical trials is on pharmacodynamic clotting parameters. Therefore, the idarucizumab indication should read as follows and incorporate the recommendations of reviewers as shown in Section 10.2 Patient Labeling in this review.</p><p>• Praxbind® (idarucizumab) is a humanized monoclonal antibody fragment (Fab) indicated in patients treated with dabigatran (Pradaxa®) when rapid reversal of the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.2.">Conclusions on the Substantial Evidence of Effectiveness</head><p>The sponsor has provided substantial evidence to support the approval of idarucizumab from two phase 1 pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic studies which demonstrated that idarucizumab is able to reverse the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran, based on coagulation tests, in adult normal healthy volunteers at steady state. Support for this conclusion is demonstrated in two phase 1 studies (studies 1321.1 and 1321.2 described in detail below in section 4.5 Clinical Pharmacology). These were randomized, placebo controlled, double-blind, studies in which dabigatran 220mg was administered orally twice daily for 3 days with an additional 220mg dose administered on day 4 followed by single or divided intravenous idarucizumab infusions of up to 8g. These studies demonstrated that there was a dose dependent reversal of the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran by idarucizumab in normal healthy volunteers who received intravenous single or split doses of idarucizumab ranging from 20mg to 8g administered over up to 1 hour or two 2.5g infusions over 5 minutes up to 1 hour apart following dabigatran administration. From a clinical perspective, the reversal of the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran by idarucizumab was established using several different coagulation tests, e.g., dilute thrombin time (dTT), thrombin time (TT), ecarin clotting time (ECT) and activated partial thromboplastic time (aPTT). In these two studies 159 subjects were exposed to idarucizumab. Additional supportive safety and efficacy data comes from an ongoing phase 3 (study 1321.3 described in detail below (see the Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy) which has enrolled 123 adult patients who are being treated with dabigatran and require emergency surgery or procedures for other morbidities or are being treated with dabigatran and present with life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. Data from this interim analysis demonstrates that administration of two doses of idarucizumab 2.5 mg intravenously can rapidly reverse and sustain the reversal of the pharmacodynamic anticoagulant effect of dabigatran for at least 24 hours after the last administration of idarucizumab.</p><p>The Clinical Pharmacology Review by Dr. Martina Shahre, final signature date August 10, 2015 states that the Office of Clinical Pharmacology has determined that, pending the inspection results for one of the analytical sites and labeling agreement, there is sufficient clinical pharmacology information provided in the NDA to support approval of idarucizumab for the rapid reversal of the anticoagulant activity of dabigatran in emergency surgery/urgent procedures and life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. The Clinical Pharmacology Review States that Administration of 5 g of idarucizumab at steady-state exposures of dabigatran causes an immediate decrease of unbound dabigatran concentrations in most patients. Coagulation markers, e.g., dilute thrombin time (dTT), thrombin time (TT), and activated partial thromboplastic time (aPTT) follow the pharmacokinetics of unbound dabigatran closely and thereby lead to immediate reversal of dabigatran mediated anticoagulant activity.</p><p>The sponsor requests waiver of the requirement for pediatric studies in 21 CFR Section 314.55(a). Dabigatran is not approved in pediatric patients in the US. The sponsor states idarucizumab is not likely to be used in a substantial number of pediatric patients treated with dabigatran who require emergency surgery/procedures or who have uncontrolled bleeding or life-threatening bleeding requiring urgent intervention, when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required. The sponsor should complete study 1321.3 and submit a final study report as a Post Marketing Requirement (PMR) to support the application's approval. Completion and submission of final study results for study 1321.3 will allow identification and assessment of any unexpected serious risk related to the use of idarucizumab in patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Benefit-Risk Summary and Assessment</head><p>In two studies in normal healthy volunteers (studies 1321.1 and 1321.2) treated with dabigatran 220mg orally twice daily for 3 days followed by one 220mg dose on day 4 a rapid, dose dependent, reversal of the dabigatran pharmacodynamic effect was observed within 30 minutes of the administration of idarucizumab at doses ranging from 20mg to 8g administered over up to 1 hour or two 2.5g infusions over 5 minutes up to 1 hour apart. The sponsor determined that a 5 g dose or two 2.5 g doses of idarucizumab were the lowest doses of idarucizumab that would be able to neutralize dabigatran for a projected 99% of patients with moderate renal failure from the RE-LY trial, i.e., the pivotal trial used to support the initial marketing application approval for dabigatran. Based on a population pharmacokinetic (PK) model of data from RE-LY the 99th percentiles of trough and peak concentrations of dabigatran in patients with moderate renal failure were 543 and 861 ng/mL. In an interim analysis of an ongoing study (1321.3) in patients who are being treated with dabigatran and require reversal of the dabigatran pharmacodynamic effect due to serious bleeding or the requirement for urgent surgery or procedures idarucizumab administered as two 2.5g intravenous infusions separated by 15 minutes or as a single bolus was able to reverse the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran. The reversal of the pharmacodynamic effect by idarucizumab was established using several different coagulation tests such as dilute thrombin time (dTT), thrombin time (TT), ecarin clotting time (ECT), activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT) and activated clotting time (ACT). This pharmacodynamic reversal effect was sustained for a period of at least 24 hours after the last dose of idarucizumab. A dose of 5 g of idarucizumab was calculated by the sponsor to be sufficient for full reversal of dabigatran anticoagulant effect in 99% of patients, based on dabigatran plasma concentrations observed in previous studies of dabigatran used to support its marketing approval. The complete dose of 5 g is administered intravenously as two consecutive infusions over 5 to 10 minutes. The reversal of elevated anticoagulation tests in dabigatrantreated patients is a surrogate for clinical efficacy. The coagulation tests, e.g., aPTT, dTT, pre-and post-treatment, may help the treating physician determine whether reversal of dabigatran has occurred. The data from studies 1321.1 and 1321.2 document the pharmacologic effect and in these normal healthy volunteer studies there were no discontinuations due to adverse events (AEs) and no serious adverse (SAEs). AEs that were observed were of mild-moderate severity. Similarly data from study 1321.3 supports the idarucizumab reversal of the pharmacodynamic anti-coagulant effect of dabigatran in the target population, i.e., when rapid reversal of the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. In This study among 123 patients treated with idarucizumab adverse events appeared to be unrelated to treatment. In this study 26 patients died primarily due to complications related to their serious medical conditions, i.e., serious bleeding or causes for the need for urgent surgery/procedures, e.g., trauma or abdominal surgery. The mortality rate was not unexpected in a high risk population with life-threatening events. Two patients developed thrombotic events, these occurred 9 and 13 days after treatment with idarucizumab and in the absence of any antithrombotic treatment. There is no evidence of worsening renal function when idarucizumab is given to patients with renal impairment and full efficacy is The clinical outcome, i.e., a decrease in the risk of bleeding, is difficult to assess. In many cases, bleeding is not visible and cannot be readily measured, e.g. in patients with intracranial hemorrhage (ICH). Other clinical outcomes such as mortality are also significantly confounded by the severity of the underlying clinical situation, e.g., trauma or duration and complications of surgery. A control group to compare outcomes would not be ethical to determine whether mortality rates are impacted by administration of idarucizumab. The target patient population is dabigatran treated patients who require emergency surgery or other invasive intervention where anticoagulation may increase the risk of bleeding, and dabigatran treated patients with life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding requiring urgent intervention. The sponsor estimates that the incidence of these conditions based on observations in the pivotal trials for dabigatran that the major bleeding rate for patients treated with dabigatran is approximately 3% and is estimated by the sponsor to be &lt;2.5% per year for life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding during or emergency surgery. Idarucizumab is not intended for use in patients with minor bleeding or other bleeding where standard supportive care is sufficient. It is expected that usage of this drug would be confined to Emergency Departments or other critical care facilities. In summary, 5 g of idarucizumab (administered as 2, 2.5 g infusions separated by 15 minutes) appears to be safe and effective in the reversal of dabigatran anticoagulant pharmacodynamic effect in patients treated with dabigatran who require emergency surgery or other invasive procedure or who present with life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. The sponsor should complete study 1321.3 in order to support the approval of idarucizumab for this indication. require emergency surgery or other invasive procedure or who present with lifethreatening or uncontrolled bleeding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimension Evidence and Uncertainties Conclusions and Reasons</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis of Condition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Current</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Treatment Options</head><p>• Currently there are no approved therapies for the reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran. The dabigatran product label states that the half-life of dabigatran in healthy subjects is 12 to 17 hours. Recommendations for patients who bleed while receiving dabigatran are based on the mechanism of action of dabigatran, i.e., to administer agents that may possibly overwhelm the inhibited coagulation cascade. Administration of activated prothrombin complex concentrates (PCCs, e.g. FEIBA) or recombinant Factor VIIa, or concentrates of coagulation factors II, IX, or X could be considered, however, these agents have their effects at points in the cascade prior to thrombin. Other, management approaches that could be considered include supportive care with blood products such as fresh frozen plasma, fresh or packed red blood cell (RBCs) transfusions or packed platelet transfusions. However, even with these agents thrombin is a critical factor for coagulation. Dabigatran can be hemodialyzed out of a patient's circulation. Approximately 60% of the drug can be removed over 2-3 hours.</p><p>(Hankey, G. J. and Eikelboom, J.W.: Dabigatran: a new oral thrombin inhibitor. 2011. Circulation. 123:1436-1450) However, this approach may not be optimal in a situation that requires rapid anticoagulant reversal. The phase 3 study is ongoing. To date 123 of a planned 300 patients have been enrolled. A decrease in the risk of bleeding is difficult to assess. In many cases, bleeding is not visible and cannot be readily measured, e.g. in patients with intracranial hemorrhage (ICH).</p><p>Other clinical outcomes such as mortality are also significantly confounded by the severity of the underlying clinical situation, e.g., trauma or duration and complications of surgery. A control group to compare outcomes would not be ethical to determine whether mortality rates are impacted by administration of idarucizumab. The target patient population is dabigatran treated patients who require emergency surgery or other invasive intervention where anticoagulation may increase the risk of bleeding, and dabigatran treated patients with life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeds that require urgent intervention.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk</head><p>• The data from studies 1321.1 and 1321.2 document the pharmacologic effect and in these normal healthy volunteer studies there were no discontinuations due to adverse events (AEs) and no serious adverse (SAEs </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dimension Evidence and Uncertainties Conclusions and Reasons</head><p>idarucizumab reversal of the pharmacodynamic anti-coagulant effect of dabigatran in the target population, i.e., when rapid reversal of the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. In 123 patients treated with idarucizumab adverse events appeared to be unrelated to treatment. In this study 26 patients died due to their underlying serious medical conditions. The mortality rate was not unexpected in a high risk population with life-threatening events. Two patients developed thrombotic events, these occurred 9 and 13 days after treatment with idarucizumab and in the absence of any antithrombotic treatment.</p><p>There is no evidence of worsening renal function when this drug is given to patients with renal impairment and full efficacy is maintained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Risk Management</head><p>• Idarucizumab is a targeted antidote for dabigatran.</p><p>The sponsor should complete study 1321.3 in order to support the approval of idarucizumab and to enhance the idarucizumab safety database. The purpose for this study is to demonstrate the efficacy and safety of idarucizumab for the reversal of the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran in patients who require an urgent surgical procedure or who have serious bleeding. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Analysis of Condition</head><p>Idarucizumab is a humanized antigen-binding fragment (Fab) against the direct thrombin inhibitor dabigatran. The proposed indication for idarucizumab is as follows.</p><p>• Praxbind® (idarucizumab) is a humanized monoclonal antibody fragment (Fab) indicated in patients treated with dabigatran (Pradaxa®) when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding.</p><p>Dabigatran was approved for marketing on October 19, 2010. Dabigatran is approved for the following indications.</p><p>• To reduce the risk of stroke and systemic embolism in patients with non-valvular atrial fibrillation. • For the treatment of deep venous thrombosis (DVT) and pulmonary embolism (PE) in patients who have been treated with a parenteral anticoagulant for 5-10 days.</p><p>• To reduce the risk of recurrence of DVT and PE in patients who have been previously treated.</p><p>The recommended dose of dabigatran ranges from 75mg orally twice daily to 150mg orally twice daily and depends on the indication for which dabigatran is prescribed and the patient's creatinine clearance (CrCl), e.g., for the treatment of deep vein thrombosis (DVT) or for the reduction in risk of stroke and systemic embolism in non-valvular atrial fibrillation in a patient with CrCl &gt;30mL/min the recommended dose is 150mg orally twice daily. However, if the CrCl is &lt; 30mL/min in these patients the recommended dose of dabigatran is 75mg orally twice daily for the reduction in risk of stroke indication. Dosing recommendations for dabigatran in patients with DVT and CrCl &lt;30mL/min are not provided in the dabigatran product label.</p><p>The target patient population for idarucizumab is dabigatran treated patients who require emergency surgery or other invasive intervention where anticoagulation may increase the risk of bleeding, and dabigatran treated patients with life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeds that require urgent intervention. The sponsor estimates that the incidence of these conditions based on observations in the pivotal trials for dabigatran that the major bleeding rate for patients treated with dabigatran is approximately 3%, and is estimated by the sponsor to be &lt;2.5% per year for life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding during or emergency surgery. The Warnings and Precaution section of the dabigatran product labels states that serious and fatal bleeding can occur in patients who are treated with dabigatran. Currently there are no approved therapies for the reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran. In clinical practice guidelines recommendations for patients who bleed while receiving dabigatran are based on the mechanism of action of dabigatran, i.e., to administer agents that may possibly overwhelm the inhibited coagulation cascade. (Van Ryn, 2010) Administration of activated prothrombin complex concentrates (PCCs, e.g. FEIBA) or recombinant Factor VIIa, or concentrates of coagulation factors II, IX, or X could be considered, however, these agents have their effects at points in the clotting cascade prior to thrombin. (Eerenberg, 2011) Other, management approaches that could be considered include supportive care with blood products such as fresh frozen plasma, fresh or packed red blood cell (RBCs) transfusions or packed platelet transfusions. However, even with these agents thrombin is a critical factor for coagulation. Dabigatran can be hemodialyzed out of a patient's circulation. Approximately 60% of the drug can be removed over 2-3 hours. (Hankey and Eikelboom, 2011) However, this approach may not be optimal in a situation that requires rapid anticoagulant reversal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2.">Current Treatment Options</head><p>Reviewer comment for section 2. Idarucizumab is a humanized antigen-binding fragment (Fab) against the direct thrombin inhibitor dabigatran developed for the treatment of patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. Currently available treatment options for these patients are mainly supportive such as transfusions of RBCs and platelets. Other treatment options such as PCC, other blood products, dialysis have their effects at points in the clotting cascade prior to thrombin or the effects may not be sufficiently rapid in an emergency bleeding situation.</p><p>3 Regulatory Background 3.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>U.S. Regulatory Actions and Marketing History</head><p>Idarucizumab is not currently marketed in the United States. two Divisions, there appeared to be a difference of opinion regarding the types of studies that were needed to provide data for the efficacy and safety of the use of idarucizumab that would support approval of the drug and the indication for which it might be approved (see IND 112278 Meeting Minutes dated August 30, 2011; Clinical Review by Dr. George Shashaty final signature date January 25, 2013 and Meeting Minutes dated February 6, 2014). The key discussion points were as follows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Summary of Presubmission/Submission Regulatory Activity</head><p>o To support a labeled indication a study evaluating clinical outcomes in bleeding patients may be required. o The surrogate pharmacodynamic endpoint, e.g., aPTT, should be associated with cessation of bleeding and/or other clinical benefits. o There may be increased risk for adverse reactions, e.g., thrombosis, after administration of idarucizumab (BI 655075) due to the underlying diseases/conditions that required the use of the anticoagulant dabigatran.</p><p>However, the Divisions have come to a consensus agreement that pharmacodynamic assessments (clotting assays) along with pharmacokinetic data and additional clinical outcomes that may be available, would be acceptable to support the assessment of the efficacy and safety of the drug. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3.">Foreign Regulatory Actions and Marketing History</head><p>Idarucizumab is has not been approved or marketed outside the US. and the inspectional outcome from the analytical site was classified as Voluntary Action Indicated (VAI). Although, the last inspection was classified as a VAI, based on the nature of the findings from our last inspection, and the recommendation to the review division, an inspection of the site will not be needed at this time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Product Quality</head><p>The Chemistry, Manufacturing and Controls (CMC) review is ongoing. No significant product quality issues have been identified from a clinical perspective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">Clinical Microbiology</head><p>The Clinical Microbiology review is ongoing. No significant Clinical Microbiology issues have been identified from a clinical perspective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">Nonclinical Pharmacology/Toxicology</head><p>The Pharmacology/Toxicology Review of the idarucizumab application completed by Dr. Emily Place final signature date July 20, 2015 states that pharmacology/toxicology studies conducted support approval of idarucizumab for the proposed indication, i.e., patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. Dr. Place states in her review that three animal models of activity were submitted in support of the application: a mouse intracranial hemorrhage model; a rat tail cut bleeding model, and a pig blunt liver trauma model. All 3 animal pharmacology models showed the effectiveness of the neutralization activity of idarucizumab, and its ability to significantly reduce anticoagulation and blood loss. Safety pharmacology studies showed no adverse respiratory findings. Cardiovascular safety pharmacology studies were not performed independently but electrocardiogram (ECG) measurements assessed during the 2 week repeat dose toxicology study in monkeys were unremarkable at doses up to 500 mg/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.">Clinical Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.1.">Mechanism of Action</head><p>Idarucizumab is a humanized Fab fragment that was developed as a dabigatran reversal agent. Dabigatran is a direct thrombin inhibitor anticoagulant. By binding dabigatran that would otherwise bind to thrombin, the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is reversed by idarucizumab.  <ref type="bibr">August 10, 2015)</ref>. In her review Dr. Sahre states that In vitro studies show that idarucizumab binds to dabigatran with high affinity. The association (ka) and dissociation (kd) rate constants are 3.4x 10 5 M -1 s-1 and 0.7x 10 -6 s -1 , respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.2.">Pharmacodynamics</head><p>The sponsor conducted three clinical pharmacology studies, i.e., 1321.1, 1321.2 and 1321.5 to support the safety and efficacy of idarucizumab for the proposed indication. In addition the sponsor provided additional supportive safety and efficacy data from the ongoing study 1321.3. These studies are discussed in detail in section 6 Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy.</p><p>Dr. Sahre states in her review that idarucizumab has no intrinsic pro-thrombotic effect as shown by its lack of effect on coagulation markers or on the endogenous thrombin potential. Administration of 5 g of idarucizumab at steady-state exposures of dabigatran causes an immediate decrease of unbound dabigatran concentrations in most patients. Coagulation markers ECT, aPTT, TT, and dTT follow the pharmacokinetics of unbound dabigatran closely, thereby leading to immediate reversal of dabigatran mediated anticoagulant activity in most of the patients. Dabigatran redistribution peaks between 2.3-18.4 ng/mL were observed in all subjects (n=26) that received the 5 g dose in study 1321.2. The peaks occurred approximately 24 hours following idarucizumab administration. One subject had a distribution peak of 46 ng/mL. Re-initiation of dabigatran treatment 24 hours after treatment with idarucizumab results in comparable unbound sum dabigatran concentrations and anticoagulant activity before and after idarucizumab treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5.3.">Pharmacokinetics</head><p>Dr. Sahre states in her review Idarucizumab disposition is dominated by the rapid initial distribution half-life of around 45 min. Idarucizumab declines to less than 20% of its peak concentrations 2 h after administration. Idarucizumab displayed dose-linear kinetics for doses ranging from 20 mg to 8 g. Age (20 to 76 years), sex, and race (Asians vs. Whites) did not influence idarucizumab disposition in a clinically relevant manner. When administered to patients with mild and moderate renal impairment, idarucizumab exposure (AUC) increased by 40% and 80%, respectively. Given that dabigatran exposure also increases with renal impairment, no dose adjustment is necessary for mild or moderate renal impairment as the effects of exposure increase for both idarucizumab and dabigatran go in the same direction. Idarucizumab does not distribute extensively to peripheral tissues. Its volume of distribution is estimated to be 5 -8 L, suggesting that idarucizumab is mainly present in interstitial fluid. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.6.">Devices and Companion Diagnostic Issues</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.7.</head><p>Consumer Study Reviews</p><p>During the Late Cycle Meeting held with the sponsor on July 27, 2015 (see Late Cycle Meeting Minutes by Alycia Andersen, Project Manager, final signature date August 5, 2015) the Division of Medication Errors Prevention and Analysis (DMEPA) stated the recommended dose of idarucizumab is 5 grams, provided in two vials, each containing 2.5 gm/50 mL. From a medication error standpoint, we are concerned that healthcare practitioners may not administer the entire dose as packaged due to the fact that one dose is comprised of two separate vials. Therefore, underdoses may occur. The applicant should provide a rationale for the current packaging of two 2.5 gram vials instead of a one 5 gram vial. During the meeting the sponsor stated that they would work on submitting a response to this information request.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reviewer comment for section 4. The OSIS review recommends accepting data in BLA 761025 without an on-site inspection because OSIS recently inspected SGS Life Science Services Clinical</head><p>Research Clinical Pharmacology Unit and the inspectional outcome from the inspection was classified as NAI. I agree with the OSIS recommendation. No CMC or Clinical Microbiology issues have been identified, however these reviews are ongoing. The Pharmacology/Toxicology review states that pharmacology/toxicology studies conducted support approval of idarucizumab for the proposed indication, i.e., patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. The Clinical Pharmacology Review states that there is sufficient clinical pharmacology information provided in the NDA to support approval of idarucizumab for the rapid reversal of the anticoagulant activity of dabigatran in emergency surgery/urgent procedures and life-threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. I agree with the Clinical Pharmacology recommendation. The Clinical Pharmacology Review also states that the idarucizumab label should include a warning that elevated coagulation parameters will occur in some patients (due to redistribution of dabigatran) with the proposed 5 g idarucizumab dose. I agree with the Clinical Pharmacology recommendation and the additional proposed wording to be added to the idarucizumab product label that elevated coagulation parameters will occur in some patients (due to redistribution of dabigatran) with the proposed 5g idarucizumab dose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">Sources of Clinical Data and Review Strategy</head><p>5.1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table of Clinical Studies</head><p>The sponsor's tables below show the studies used to support the application. In part 1 of this study single doses of placebo (PBO) or idarucizumab were administered at doses ranging from 20mg to 8 g over 1 hour or 1g to 4g over 5 minutes. One hundred ten subjects were treated (83 subjects treated with idarucizumab and 27 subjects treated with placebo). In part 2 of the study, subjects received dabigatran 220mg orally twice daily for 3 days and an additional 220mg dose on day 4 followed by PBO or idarucizumab administered at doses of 1g to 4 g intravenously over 5 minutes. Thirty five subjects were treated (26 subjects treated with idarucizumab and 9 subjects treated with placebo). In part 3 of the study subjects received dabigatran similar to that in part 2 followed by PBO or idarucizumab, 5g plus 2.5 g intravenously each over 5 minutes administered 15 minutes apart. Twelve subjects were treated (9 subjects treated with idarucizumab and 3 subjects treated with placebo). No concomitant therapy was allowed in this trial. The objective of the study was to investigate the safety, tolerability, and pharmacokinetics of intravenous doses of idarucizumab and to explore the effect of different doses of idarucizumab administered at or close to the steady state of dabigatran. The primary endpoint of this trial was the incidence of drug-related adverse events in each study part. Secondary endpoints were comprised of evaluation of pharmacokinetic parameters and pharmacodynamic parameters to demonstrate the reversal of the dabigatran anticoagulant effect by idarucizumab. Pharmacodynamic parameters secondary endpoints included activated partial thromboplastin time (aPTT), dilute thromboplastin time (dTT), thrombin time (TT) and ecarin clotting time (ECT) from baseline to day 3 and 4 after the last dose of idarucizumab. Descriptive statistics for safety, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic endpoints were used to describe the results of the study. The sponsor's tables below show the study schedule. AEs were coded The table below summarizes the mean pharmacodynamic effect of idarucizumab over time for the 12 subjects treated in part 3 (9 subjects treated with idarucizumab and 3 treated with PBO). Subjects received dabigatran 220mg orally twice daily for 3 days and an additional single 220mg dose of dabigatran on day 4 about 2 hours before the first dose of idarucizumab. Idarucizumab was then administered at 5g intravenously over 5 minutes followed 15 minutes later by 2.5 g intravenously over 5 minutes. The clotting assays that were tested include dTT, aPTT, ECT, TT and ACT. The upper table shows the results of the idarucizumab treatment group and the lower table shows the results of the PBO treatment group. Highlighted are the Preidarucizumab or Pre-PBO time point which was measured just prior to idarucizumab or PBO administration and the 30 minute time points after the last idarucizumab or PBO infusion. Selected time points that are also shown are the 24 hour and 72 hour time points after the last administration of idarucizumab. In the upper table a relative comparison of the clotting tests before and after the administration of idarucizumab shows that there is a reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran as shown by the decrease in assay clotting times by idarucizumab which is not evident in the lower table for those treated with PBO. At 24 and 72 hours the clotting test results are similar to those at the 30minute time point for idarucizumab and for PBO as well. Therefore, the clotting tests were reversed within 30 minutes of the completion of study drug administration. Similar results to these were observed for subjects in part 2 of the study where subjects were treated with dabigatran followed by single doses idarucizumab or PBO. Idarucizumab appeared to be generally well tolerated. The most frequently reported AEs in ≥ 3 subjects in part 1 were headache (n= 9 idarucizumab, 2 PBO), nasopharyngitis (n= 4 idarucizumab, 1 PBO), back pain (n= 4 idarucizumab, 1 PBO) and skin irritation (n= 3 idarucizumab, 2 PBO ). In parts 2 and 3 of the study there were no adverse events which were experienced by at least 5 subjects. There were 3 subjects treated with idarucizumab and 0 subjects treated with PBO who reported dizziness/presyncope in parts 2 and 3. Adverse events were all classified as mild and resolved without sequelae. For a short period of up to 4 hours immediately following the infusion with idarucizumab, proteinuria with small molecular weight proteins was noted, which was believed to be due to the excretion of idarucizumab in the urine in a small number of patients. There was no evidence of the development of anti-drug neutralizing antibodies among the 157 treated subjects. Phase Ib Study To Investigate The Safety, Tolerability, Pharmacokinetics And Pharmacodynamics Of BI 655075 (Idarucizumab) And To Establish The Efficacy Of BI 655075 In Reversal Of Dabigatran Anticoagulant Activity In Volunteers" is a safety, tolerability, pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic study. The study was a pharmacokinetic and pharmacodynamic, 2-way crossover, single dose study with 7 groups. The overall duration of the trial was approximately 90 days with 2 periods. There were 46 subjects enrolled in this study (12 subjects with renal impairment defined as mild renal impairment CrCl ≥ 60 to &lt;90 mL/min and moderate renal impairment was defined as CrCl &lt;60mL/min -≥30mL/min. The primary endpoint is the pharmacodynamic reversal of dabigatran as measured by clotting assays, dTT, TT, ECT, aPTT, ACT. In this study idarucizumab 1 to 5 g, with and without dabigatran 220mg (150mg in mild to moderately renally impaired patients) was administered orally twice daily. The primary analysis investigated whether at least 1 assay value (of the 2 sampling times at the end of the infusion and 10 min later) of the coagulation parameters dTT and ECT was reversed after dabigatran treatment. Generally, a similar study schedule was used in study 1321.1 compared to study 1321.2. AEs were coded and graded according to MedDRA 17.0 criteria. Descriptive statistics were used to analyze the study results. The study was conducted under Good Clinical Practice and Declaration of Helsinki Guidelines. A signed written informed consent was required in order to enroll in the study. All subjects completed the study.</p><p>The overall mean age was 63.8 years (standard deviation 9.2 years) and 44/46 (96%) subjects were white. Twelve subjects (6 each) were enrolled with mild renal impairment or moderate renal impairment. The sponsor's table below shows the demographics of the subjects treated in study 1321.2. In this study after treatment with idarucizumab, all subjects 46/46 (100%) showed reversal of the dabigatran-induced prolongation of clotting time regardless of the degree of renal impairment or age. When receiving placebo, none of the subjects 0/46 (0%) showed reversal as shown in the sponsor's table below. Idarucizumab was generally well tolerated in study 1321.2. Adverse events in this study were characterized as mild or moderate. Adverse events that occurred in ≥ 4 subjects in this study was headache (n=4 idarucizumab and 1 PBO). The sponsor reported that a total of 5 subjects had no evidence of anti-drug antibodies prior to idarucizumab but subsequently had positive anti-drug antibody titers at 4 weeks (n= 2 subjects) or at the 3 month follow-up (n=5 subjects). These anti-idarucizumab antibodies were directed against the C-terminus and were considered to be non-blocking antibodies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Study 1321.5</head><p>Study 1321.5 is a supportive study in 80 healthy Japanese male subjects which evaluated the pharmacokinetics of a single dose of idarucizumab compared to placebo. Similar pharmacodynamic results were observed in this subject population compared to study 1321.1. No serious adverse events were reported in this study. Overall the adverse event profile was similar to that reported in studies 1321.1 and 1321.2. The key enrollment criteria are bleeding that requires a reversal agent in the opinion of the physician, urgent requirement for surgery or an invasive procedure where adequate hemostasis is required and patients must be taking dabigatran. In this study Idarucizumab is administered at a 5g fixed dose administered as two 2.5g doses administered over 5-10minutes separated by 15 minutes or as a bolus. Biomarker endpoints are the basis for determination of efficacy in this trial. Ecarin clotting time (ECT), diluted Thrombin Time (dTT), activated Partial Thromboplastin Time (aPTT) and Thrombin Time (TT) are measured in a central laboratory. The sponsor's table below shows the study schedule. The study is being conducted under Declaration of Helsinki and Good Clinical Practices Guidelines. A signed Written Informed Consent is required to enroll into the study. An IRB and DSMB have reviewed and are monitoring the study. dabigatran, using several coagulation tests, i.e., ECT, dTT, TT. No dosing or patient management decisions are based on central lab determination of reversal. The interim report contains data from 123 adult patients enrolled from June 2014 until April 1, 2015. The study is ongoing. An interim report of the results from study 1321.3 was submitted by the sponsor in BLA 761025 supporting document 13 letter date June 19, 2015 and the results of this interim report are considered supportive of the safety and efficacy of idarucizumab.</p><p>All of the 123 patients in this analysis received the pre-specified 5 g dose of idarucizumab. The sponsor states that the infusion time was minutes. There were 66 patients in Group A (bleeding) and 57 patients in Group B (surgery). The demographics of patients enrolled in study 1321.3 are shown in the sponsor's table below. Overall, the baseline demographics were similar between groups. Overall, the median age was 77 years (range 48-93), 65/123 (53%) were male and 105/123 (85%) were white. There were 49/123 (40%) of patients enrolled with moderate to severe renal insufficiency, i.e., CrCl (Cockroft-Gault) &lt; 50mL/min. Overall, the median time from last dabigatran exposure to the time of idarucizumab administration was 16 hours (range 1-94 hours). Nearly all patients, i.e., 117/123 (95%) were treated with dabigatran for the atrial fibrillation indication. Most patients, i.e., 80/123 (65%) were treated with dabigatran 110mg orally twice daily. In group A (serious bleeding group) there were 27/66(41%) who presented with gastrointestinal bleeding, 24/66 (36%) patients presented with intracranial bleeding, the remaining 15/66 (22%) of patients had serious bleeding in other areas such as trauma, intramuscular, retroperitoneal, intra-pericardial, intra ocular and one bleeding location was not yet identified by the sponsor. Of the 57 patients in group B (urgent surgery group) surgery that was required in ≥ 3 patients was bone fractures 13/57 (23%) of patients, gall bladder disease (cholecystitis, cholelithiasis) 7/57 (12%) of patients, joint/wound infection 4/57 (7%) of patients and acute appendicitis, small bowel obstruction, bowel perforation in 3/57 (5%) each, respectively. • Patient number from had taken an overdose of dabigatran (estimated to approximately 125 capsules, total dose unknown) and was referred to a hospital participating in the study for hemodialysis of dabigatran. However, during the preparation for dialysis, the patient was treated with idarucizumab and the clotting tests normalized, no bleeding occurred and the dialysis was cancelled.</p><p>• Patient number from the same site in presented with acute mesenteric ischemia, was treated with idarucizumab but was too unstable to undergo the planned exploratory laparoscopy. The patient died 1 day later due to circulatory shock. • Patient number from the was scheduled to undergo a gastric perforation repair and was treated with idarucizumab. However, the patient was too unstable to undergo the planned surgery. She died 1 day later of peritonitis and acute post-hemorrhagic anemia.</p><p>Reference ID: 3812170 The sponsor's figure below shows the reversal of the dabigatran pharmacodynamic effect by idarucizumab. The maximum reversal of ECT or dTT in the first 4 hours was the primary endpoint. The dTT was tested in 40 patients in group A (serious bleeding) and 28 patients in group B (urgent surgery) at four hours. The ECT was tested in 47 patients in group A and 34 patients in group B. A maximal reversal (100%) of dTT was achieved in 39/40 (98%) of patients in group A and 26/28 (93%) of patients in group B. A maximal reversal (100%) of ECT was achieved in 42/47 (89%) of patients in group A and 30/34 (88%) of patients in group B. The sponsor's figure below shows that dTT and ECT decrease to normal levels within 10-30minutes of idarucizumab administration and are sustained for a period of 24 hours after the last dose of idarucizumab administration.  Use of blood products was more frequent in Group A (serious bleeding) 45/66 (68%) of patients compared to Group B (urgent surgery) 23/57% (40%) of patients. The most frequently used product was packed RBCs, used in 51/123 (42%) of all patients. However, assessment of bleeding and the use of rescue therapy were highly subjective.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6) (b) (6)</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1.3.">Subpopulations</head><p>Anticoagulant or antithrombotic therapy was re-started in 96 patients, i.e., 47/66 patients in Group A (serious bleeding) and 49/57 patients in Group B (urgent surgery). Dabigatran was restarted in 17/66 (25.8%) of the Group A patients and 34/57 (59.6%) of Group B patients. The restart of dabigatran was preceded by bridging therapy in 8/17 patients in group A and 25/34 patients in group B. Bridging therapies primarily included low molecular weight heparin and unfractionated heparin. The median time to re-start of any anticoagulant therapy was 5 days for group A and 1 day for group B patients. Dabigatran re-start took 18 days in group A and 7 days in group B.</p><p>Reviewer comment for section 7. Maximal reversal (100%) of dTT was achieved in 39/40 (98%) of patients in group A (serious bleeding) and 26/28 (93%) of patients in group B (urgent surgery). Maximal reversal (100%) of ECT was achieved in 42/47 (89%) of patients in group A and 30/34 (88%) of patients in group B. In patients treated with dabigatran in study 1321.3 the dTT and ECT decreased to normal levels within 10-30minutes of idarucizumab administration and are sustained for a period of 24 hours after the last dose of idarucizumab administration. The concentration of unbound dabigatran also appears to decrease with idarucizumab treatment. The assessment and management of bleeding in study 1321.3 was highly subjective. Therefore, changes in bleeding management are of unclear significance. The median time to restart of any anticoagulant therapy was 4.6 days for group A and 1.3 days for group B patients. Dabigatran re-start took 18 days in group A and 7 days in group B. Differences in the time to restart of anticoagulant therapy may be due to the nature of serious bleeding compared to urgent surgery, i.e., a surgeon may feel that she/he has better control of the operative field and the wound in a surgical patient compared to a medical patient with bleeding from a source which is less obvious. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.3.">Dropouts and/or Discontinuations Due to Adverse Effects</head><p>There were no other AEs, other than those listed in section 8.4.1 Deaths that lead to dropouts or discontinuation of idarucizumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.4.">Significant Adverse Events</head><p>Treatment with an effective reversal agent in patients who are anticoagulated exposes the underlying thrombotic risk in such patients and increases the possibility that a thrombotic event will occur. There were 5 patients with thrombotic events during the study, 3 in Group A (serious bleeding) and 2 in group B (urgent surgery). These cases are described briefly below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Patient</head><p>, is a female age 86 years and experienced a non-ST elevation myocardial infarction 13 days after treatment with idarucizumab. No antithrombotic treatment had been re-started since the index event of an intra-cerebral bleed. Baseline conditions included atrial fibrillation, hypertension, previous stroke/transient ischemic attack (TIA) and the patient was hospitalized.</p><p>• Patient , is a male age 85 years and entered in the study with an intracranial hemorrhage. The events of atrial thrombus, DVT and PE occurred starting 9 days after treatment with idarucizumab. During this time, the patient was hospitalized and no antithrombotic therapy had been re-started. This patient had concomitant conditions that included atrial fibrillation, diabetes, hypertension, and a prior left atrial thrombus.</p><p>• Patient , is a female age 82 years who entered into the trial for surgery to treat cholecystitis. She had a history of hypertension, diabetes and previous stroke. Seven days after treatment with idarucizumab she developed a bilateral DVT. Imaging indicated that it was limited to below the knee. She was not receiving any antithrombotic treatment at the time of the event. At the end of the study, the DVT had not yet fully resolved.</p><p>• Patient , is a male age 75 years who enrolled in the study for treatment of a gastrointestinal bleed. Two days after treatment, the patient was diagnosed with DVT and PE. He was not receiving antithrombotic therapy at that time. His medical history included Parkinson's disease. He was started one day later on heparin, then low molecular weight heparin, then re-started dabigatran 26 days later. He was not fully recovered from the pulmonary embolus at the end of the trial. • Patient , is a female age 72 years who entered into the study for surgical management of an infected left knee joint. The patient had a previous history of TIA. Twelve days after idarucizumab treatment, the patient experienced a rectal bleed on LMWH heparin, which was stopped. Twenty-four days after treatment the patient experienced an ischemic stroke (right middle cerebral artery infarction) and died 2 days later. The patient was not on any antithrombotic medication at the time of the event. In study 1321.3 a total of 103/123 (84%) reported any AEs. AEs reported in greater than or equal to 5% of patients were: hypokalemia (9/123, 7%), delirium (9/123, 7%), constipation (8/123, 7%), pyrexia (7/123, 6%), pneumonia (7/123, 6%).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.5.">Treatment Emergent Adverse Events and Adverse Reactions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.6.">Laboratory Findings</head><p>No significant changes in clinical laboratory values were observed in patients in either treatment group after idarucizumab therapy. Mean changes in hemoglobin, hematocrit, platelet count, liver function tests or creatinine clearance were not significantly altered after idarucizumab therapy over the course of the study.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.7.">Vital Signs</head><p>No significant changes in vital signs (temperature, blood pressure or heart rate) were noted after idarucizumab administration. Fluctuations in vital signs in the proposed indicated patient population, i.e., patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding, is not uncommon due to hemodynamic instability.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.8.">QT</head><p>Dr. Sahre states in the Clinical Pharmacology review (final signature date August 10, 2015) that idarucizumab is a fragment of a humanized murine monoclonal antibody with a molecular of weight 47 kDa, which will limit the ability of this compound to directly inhibit cardiac currents. No significant QT changes were noted on electrocardiogram testing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.9.">Immunogenicity</head><p>Reference ID: 3812170 Sampling for anti-drug antibodies (ADA) against idarucizumab in study 1321.3 was planned for pre-dose (Visit 1) and one or more post-dose samples (30± 7 days and 90±7 days, Visits 5 and 6, respectively). Not all patients were sampled for the development of antidrug antibodies (ADAs). Data are available for 47/123 patients with a pre-dose sample and at least one post-dose sample. The sponsor reports that 2 patients with baseline, non-specific ADAs (patients and ) had persisting ADAs at day 30 day but the binding is not at the variable site. One more patient (patient ) had a treatment emergent ADA at day 30 of mixed specificity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.10.">Pediatrics and Assessment of Effects on Growth</head><p>Dabigatran is not approved in the US for use in pediatric patients. The sponsor requests a full waiver of the requirement for pediatric studies in 21 CFR Section 314.55 (a) that each application for a new dosage form contain data that are adequate to assess the safety and effectiveness of the drug product for the claimed indication in all relevant pediatric sub-populations. The sponsor states that idarucizumab is not likely to be used in a substantial number of pediatric patients treated with dabigatran who require emergency surgery/procedures or who have uncontrolled bleeding or life-threatening bleeding requiring urgent intervention, when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required. The sponsor states that necessary studies are impossible or highly impractical because the number of such patients is low.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.4.11.">Overdose, Drug Abuse Potential, Withdrawal, and Rebound</head><p>There is no overdose or abuse potential for idarucizumab.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.5.">Safety in the Postmarket Setting</head><p>Idarucizumab is not marketed anywhere in the world.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.5.1.">Expectations on Safety in the Postmarket Setting</head><p>The sponsor requests waiver of the requirement for pediatric studies in 21 CFR Section 314.55 (a). Dabigatran is not approved in pediatric patients in the US. The sponsor states idarucizumab is not likely to be used in a substantial number of pediatric patients treated with dabigatran who require emergency surgery/procedures or who have uncontrolled bleeding or life-threatening bleeding</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>June 25, 2015  for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) maintained.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Breakthrough Therapy Designation Request submitted in IND 112278 for idarucizumab on April 17, 2014 for the proposed indication for patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. • June 16, 2014 Breakthrough Therapy Designation granted. • The applicant orientation meeting was held on April 13, 2015.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Study 1321.3 is titled, "A Phase III, Case Series Clinical Study of the Reversal of the Anticoagulant Effects of Dabigatran by Intravenous Administration of 5.0 g Idarucizumab in Patients Treated with Dabigatran Etexilate Who Have Uncontrolled Bleeding or Require Emergency Surgery or Procedures, the REVERSE -AD trial". This study is an open label, multicenter, single arm, safety and efficacy trial in which the sponsor plans to enroll up to 300 adult patients. The primary objective is to demonstrate reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran in patients treated with dabigatran who have uncontrolled or life-threatening bleeding requiring urgent intervention, and in patients treated with dabigatran who require emergency surgery or other invasive procedure.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Figure 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Reversal of the Pharmacodynamic Effect of Dabigatran by Idarucizumab Study 1321.3 Sponsor's figure Four Month Safety Update Report Study 1321.3 page 16</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) 10 Labeling Recommendations ..................................................................................................52 10.1. Prescribing Information..............................................................................................52 10.2. Patient Labeling..........................................................................................................65 10.3. Nonprescription Labeling ...........................................................................................65 11 Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies (REMS) ................................................................65 12 Postmarketing Requirements and Commitments .................................................................65 13 Appendices............................................................................................................................66 13.1. References..................................................................................................................66 13.2. Financial Disclosure ....................................................................................................68</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025 BLA 761025</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition</cell><cell>4</cell></row></table><note>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition 5 Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table of Figures</head><label>of</label><figDesc>Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) BLA 761025 supporting document 2 letter date February 19, 2015 for Praxbind® (idarucizumab, BI 655075) should be granted accelerated approval from a clinical perspective. The sponsor's proposed indication is as follows.</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025 BLA 761025</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row><row><cell>ETASU</cell><cell>elements to assure safe use</cell></row><row><cell>FDA</cell><cell>Food and Drug Administration</cell></row><row><cell>FDAAA</cell><cell>Food and Drug Administration Amendments Act of 2007</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Figure Number FDASIA Food and Drug Administration Safety and Innovation Act Figure Title</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1 GCP GRMP 1 Executive Summary Mean Plasma Concentration of Idarucizumab vs Time Profiles Part 1 (Study 1321.1) good clinical practice good review management practice</cell></row><row><cell>2 ICH</cell><cell>Mean Dilute Thrombin Time (dTT) (+/-SD) Study 1321.1 Part 2 International Conference on Harmonization</cell></row><row><cell>3 IND ISE 1.1.</cell><cell>Reversal of the Pharmacodynamic Effect of Dabigatran by Idarucizumab Study 1321.3 Investigational New Drug integrated summary of effectiveness Product Introduction</cell></row><row><cell>4 ISS</cell><cell>Reversal of Pharmacodynamic Effect of Dabigatran by Idarucizumab integrated summary of safety</cell></row><row><cell>ITT</cell><cell>(Pollack, 2015) intent to treat</cell></row><row><cell>MedDRA</cell><cell>Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities</cell></row><row><cell>mITT</cell><cell>modified intent to treat</cell></row><row><cell>Glossary NCI-CTCAE</cell><cell>National Cancer Institute-Common Terminology Criteria for Adverse Event</cell></row><row><cell>NDA</cell><cell>new drug application</cell></row><row><cell>AC NME ACT OCS AE OPQ aPTT OSE BLA OSI BPCA PBO BRF PBRER CBER PD CBC PI CDER PK CDRH PMC CDTL PMR CFR PP CMC PPI COSTART PREA CRF PRO CRO PSUR CRT REMS CSR SAE CSS SAP DMC SGE dTT SOC ECG TEAE ECT TT</cell><cell>new molecular entity advisory committee Office of Computational Science activated clotting time Office of Pharmaceutical Quality adverse event Office of Surveillance and Epidemiology activated partial thromboplastin time Office of Scientific Investigation biologics license application placebo Best Pharmaceuticals for Children Act Periodic Benefit-Risk Evaluation Report Benefit Risk Framework pharmacodynamics Center for Biologics Evaluation and Research prescribing information Complete Blood Count pharmacokinetics Center for Drug Evaluation and Research postmarketing commitment Center for Devices and Radiological Health postmarketing requirement Cross-Discipline Team Leader per protocol Code of Federal Regulations patient package insert chemistry, manufacturing, and controls Pediatric Research Equity Act Coding Symbols for Thesaurus of Adverse Reaction Terms patient reported outcome case report form Periodic Safety Update report contract research organization risk evaluation and mitigation strategy clinical review template serious adverse event clinical study report statistical analysis plan Controlled Substance Staff special government employee data monitoring committee standard of care dilute thrombin time treatment emergent adverse event electrocardiogram ecarin clotting time thrombin time</cell></row><row><cell>eCTD</cell><cell>electronic common technical document</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition</cell><cell>7 8</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Pre-IND meetings were held on August 10, 2011, January 31, 2013 and February 11, 2014 under IND 112278. The original interactions involved the Division of Cardiovascular and Renal Products (DCRP), because at the time of development of idarucizumab (BI 655075), the only approved indication for dabigatran, an oral direct thrombin inhibitor, was for the prevention of stroke and systemic embolism in patients</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row></table><note>with non-valvular atrial fibrillation. DCRP consulted the Division of Hematology Products (DHP) when the original submission was made. In the discussions between theCDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition 18 Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>June 12, 2015. In her review Dr. Nkah recommends accepting data without an on-site inspection because the Office of Translational Sciences recently inspected SGS Life Science Services Clinical Research Clinical Pharmacology Unit and the inspectional outcome from the inspection was classified as No Action Indicated (NAI). The Office of Translational Sciences recently inspected</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row></table><note>Reviewer comment for section 3. Idarucizumab is not marketed anywhere in the world. Idarucizumab was granted Breakthrough Therapy Designation on June 16, 2014.4 Significant Issues from Other Review Disciplines Pertinent to Clinical Conclusions on Efficacy and Safety4.1. Office of Scientific Investigations (OSI) An Office of Translational Sciences Review was completed by Dr. Shila Nkah final signature dateCDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition 19 Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The Clinical Pharmacology Review was completed by Dr. Martina Sahre (Clinical Pharmacology Reviewer, final signature date</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row><row><cell>(b) (4)</cell></row><row><cell>Reference ID: 3812170</cell></row></table><note>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition 20 Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>No devices or companion diagnostics were developed with idarucizumab.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition</cell><cell>21</cell></row><row><cell>Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>6 Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy</head><label></label><figDesc>June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) reversal of the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding, were enrolled from June 2014 until April 1, 2015. An interim report of the results from study 1321.3 was submitted by the sponsor in BLA 761025 supporting document 13 letter date June 19, 2015 and the results of this interim report are considered supportive of the safety and efficacy of idarucizumab.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025 BLA 761025 BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) Sponsor's tables Tabular Listing of Studies pages 1-4 5.2. Review Strategy All the studies, with exception of study 1321.3, were conducted in normal healthy adult volunteers. Studies 1321.1, 1321.2 were the pivotal studies used to support the idarucizumab 23 24 application. Study 1321.5 was considered to supportive of the clinical pharmacology data. Study 1321.3 is an ongoing prospective, open-label, nonrandomized, uncontrolled, observational study in which 123 adult patients, treated with dabigatran who required rapid CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition 25 regarding studies 1321.1, 1321.2, 1321.5 and 1321.3 from a clinical perspective are summarized in section 4.5 Clinical Pharmacology in this review. My clinical review of these studies is discussed in section 7 Review of Effectiveness and section 8 Review of Safety. Version date: Reviewer comment for section 5. The Clinical Pharmacology Reviewer's important conclusions 6.1. Studies 1321.1, 1321.2 and 1321.3</cell></row></table><note>Study 1321.1 is titled, "Randomized, Double-Blind, Placebo Controlled, Phase 1 Study in Healthy Male Volunteers to Investigate Safety, Tolerability and Pharmacokinetics of Single Rising Doses of BI 655075 (Idarucizumab) and to Explore the Dose of BI 655075 Effective to Reverse Dabigatran Anticoagulant Activity".</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) and graded according to MedDRA 17.0 criteria. The study was conducted under Good Clinical Practices and Declaration of Helsinki Guidelines. A signed Written Informed Consent Form was required in order to enroll in the study. An Institutional Review Board (IRB) and Data Safety Monitoring Board (DSMB) reviewed and monitored the study.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review Clinical Review Clinical Review Clinical Review</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D. Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025 BLA 761025 BLA 761025 BLA 761025</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab) Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition Version date: Table 2. Study Schedule 1321.1 Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews) Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</cell><cell>26 27 28 32</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Table 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Part 3 Mean Pharmacodynamic Effect Over Time</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Demographics Study 1321.2</figDesc><table><row><cell>Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell>Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell></row><row><cell>Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Table 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Reversal of Dabigatran Induced Clotting Time Study 1321.2 Sponsor's table Study Report 1321.2 page 131</figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>Table 6 .</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Study Schedule 1321.3</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 3812170</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_22"><head>Table 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>Demographics Study 1321.3</figDesc><table><row><cell>Reference ID: 3812170</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>8 Review of Safety</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Clinical Review</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Andrew Dmytrijuk, M.D.</cell></row><row><cell>BLA 761025</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Praxbind (Idarucizumab)</cell></row><row><cell>8.1.</cell><cell>Safety Review Approach</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">A review of the safety database from study 1321.3 is presented in section 8 Review of Safety.</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">In this study 123 patients previously treated with dabigatran who required rapid reversal of the</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">anticoagulant effect of dabigatran emergency surgery/urgent procedures or had life</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">threatening or uncontrolled bleeding were enrolled.</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">CDER Clinical Review Template 2015 Edition</cell><cell>48</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Version date: June 25, 2015 for initial rollout (NME/original BLA reviews)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Reference ID: 3812170</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Reviewer comment section 6. Studies 1321.1 and 1321.2 appear to be reasonably well designed, from a clinical perspective, to demonstrate that 5g of idarucizumab in normal healthy volunteers, elderly patients or patients with mild/moderate renal insufficiency can reverse the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran as demonstrated by decrease in assay clotting times by idarucizumab which is not evident in those subjects treated with PBO. The proportion of change in tests may not be similar because the coagulation tests evaluate different points along the clotting cascade and have different sensitivities and specificities in terms of demonstrating the dabigatran pharmacodynamic effects. The dTT and ECT assays are sensitive tests to evaluate the pharmacodynamic effects of dabigatran. <ref type="bibr">(Van Ryn, 2010</ref>) Idarucizumab appeared to be generally well tolerated in this subject population with only mild/moderate AEs reported primarily reported to be headache, nasopharyngitis, back pain and skin irritation in ≥ 4 subjects. The clinical significance of the immunogenicity results observed in study 1321.2 is not clear. Although 5 subjects in this study had no evidence of anti-drug antibodies prior to idarucizumab treatment and subsequently had positive anti-drug antibody titers at 4 weeks (n= 2 subjects) and at the 3 month follow-up (n=5 subjects), these antibodies were directed against the Cterminus and were considered to be non-blocking antibodies. The results of study 1321.3 are discussed in detail in section 7 Review of Effectiveness and section 8 Review of Safety. Patients were enrolled in study 1321.3 on the basis of their history of dabigatran intake and the assumption that the drug may have been contributing to bleeding or could increase the risk of surgery. These are scenarios that are likely to mirror clinical practice. The strengths of these <ref type="bibr">studies, i.e., 1321.1, 1321.2 and 1321.3</ref> include the broad inclusion criteria (study 1321.3) and confirmation of the results of the coagulation tests reflected dabigatran reversal by determination of the concentrations of unbound drug. The major limitation of study 1321.3 is the lack of a control group. A cohort design for study 1321.3 is reasonable because it seems unethical to randomly assign patients to receive placebo or no active treatment. Although other therapies such as PCC may be used in an attempt to reverse the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran these therapies have their effects at points in the clotting cascade prior to thrombin. Other, management approaches that could be considered include supportive care with blood products such as fresh frozen plasma, fresh or packed red blood cell (RBCs) transfusions or packed platelet transfusions. However, with these agents thrombin is a critical factor for coagulation. Dabigatran can be hemodialyzed out of a patient's circulation. However, this approach may not be optimal in a situation that requires rapid anticoagulant reversal. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7">Review of Effectiveness</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.2.2.">Adequacy of the safety database:</head><p>Patients enrolled in study 1321.3 can be expected to represent US patients. Patients of African-American or Asian descent appear to be under-represented in the study, i.e., 85% of patients enrolled in study 1321.3 as of the April 1, 2015 cutoff date are white. However, it is not expected that the coagulation cascade is different among these ethnic groups. As of the April 1, 2015 cutoff date 123/300 patients have been enrolled in study 1321.3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8.3.</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adequacy of Applicant's Clinical Safety Assessments</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.1.">Categorization of Adverse Events</head><p>AEs were graded and categorized according to MedDRA 17.0 criteria.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.3.2.">Routine Clinical Tests</head><p>Patients enrolled in study 1321.3 were monitored according to the study schedule shown in section 6 Review of Relevant Individual Trials Used to Support Efficacy in this review. requiring urgent intervention, when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required.</p><p>The sponsor should complete study 1321.3 and submit a final study report in order to support the application's full approval. Completion and submission of final study results for study 1321.3 will allow identification and assessment of any unexpected serious risk related to the use of idarucizumab in patients treated with dabigatran when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. Overall, the benefit of idarucizumab to reverse the pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran in patients who require emergency surgery/procedures or who have uncontrolled bleeding or life-threatening bleeding requiring urgent intervention, when rapid reversal of the anticoagulant effects of dabigatran is required is favorable. Significant safety risks have not been identified in this review.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.6.">Additional Safety Issues From Other Disciplines</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9">Advisory Committee Meeting and Other External Consultations</head><p>An Oncology Drug Advisory Committee (ODAC) meeting or other external consultations are not recommended at this time. 1. The sponsor's proposed indication is as follows. However, the proposed indication should be changed to remove the wording, "anticoagulant effect" and replaced with the wording "pharmacodynamic effect" which more accurately reflects that the effect of idarucizumab is on pharmacodynamic clotting parameters.</p><p>• Praxbind® (idarucizumab) is a humanized monoclonal antibody fragment (Fab) indicated in patients treated with dabigatran (pPradaxa®) when reversal of the anticoagulant pharmacodynamic effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding.</p><p>2. The sponsor proposes the following wording in the Adverse Reactions Highlights section. . The sponsor should incorporate AEs that were observed in, e.g., ≥ 5% of normal healthy volunteers in studies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>. In normal healthy volunteer studies the most frequently reported adverse reaction in greater than or equal to 5% of patients treated with idarucizumab was headache.</p><p>3. The sponsor proposes the following wording for the Adverse Reactions, Clinical Trial Experience section.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>Three clinical studies in healthy subjects have been completed, in which 224 were treated with idarucizumab. In these studies during the treatment period the overall frequency of adverse events was similar between idarucizumab treated subjects (55/224, 25%) and placebo treated subjects (26/105, 25%). Among those subjects treated with idarucizumab adverse events reported in greater than or equal to 5% of subjects was headache (12/224, 5%). 4. The sponsor proposes the following wording for the Clinical Studies section. However, the clinical studies should include a description of the treatments administered and key efficacy results of the studies.</p><p>• The safety and effectiveness of TRADENAME Praxbind . Three clinical studies in healthy subjects have been completed, in which 224 were treated with idarucizumab. Subjects in these studies were pre-treated with dabigatran 220mg orally twice daily for three days followed by one additional 220mg dose of dabigatran on day four. Immediately after the administration of 5 g idarucizumab no anticoagulant activity as measured by dTT, ECT, aPTT, TT and ACT was observed. [see Pharmacodynamics 12.2].</p><p>Reference ID: 3812170 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.2.">Patient Labeling</head><p>Not applicable -no specific instructions for administration or use are directed at patients. This drug will be administered intravenously by a trained caregiver.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.3.">Nonprescription Labeling</head><p>Not applicable -idarucizumab is a prescription drug.</p><p>Reviewer comment for section 10. The sponsor should incorporate the reviewer proposed edits discussed in section 10.1 Prescribing Information and shown in section 10.2 Patient Labeling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11">Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategies (REMS)</head><p>A Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) is not recommended at this time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="12">Postmarketing Requirements and Commitments</head><p>I propose that the sponsor complete and submit a final study report for study 1321.3 as a Post Marketing Requirement in order to support the approval of idarucizumab. Completion and submission of final study results for study 1321.3 will allow identification and assessment of any unexpected serious risk related to the use of idarucizumab in patients treated with dabigatran when rapid . This published report is an interim analysis of study 1321.3 which evaluated 90 patients who received idarucizumab (51 patients with serious bleeding and 39 patients who required an urgent surgical procedure). Patients were enrolled from June 2014 to February 2015. Among 68 patients with an elevated dilute thrombin time and 81 with an elevated ecarin clotting time at baseline, the median maximum percentage reversal was 100% (95% confidence interval (CI): 100,100%) for each clotting test. The author's figure below shows the reversal of the dabigatran pharmacodynamic effect in patients treated with idarucizumab over time. The author states that the concentration of unbound dabigatran was reduced to a level at or near the lower limit of quantification in all but 1 patient. Subsequent increases in dabigatran concentrations that occurred 12 hours after the administration of idarucizumab in 6 patients and 24 hours after the administration of idarucizumab in 16 patients were also evident by increases in the clotting times and may reflect the redistribution of extravascular dabigatran into the intravascular compartment. the anticoagulant effect of dabigatran is required for emergency surgery/urgent procedures or in life threatening or uncontrolled bleeding. The author states that an increase in the dabigatran concentration was observed in 6 patients 12 hours after idarucizumab administration. The author states that it is uncertain whether patients with an increase in clotting time after previous recent idarucizumab therapy would benefit from additional idarucizumab treatment. No financial concerns have been uncovered in this review.</p><p>Reference <ref type="figure">ID: 3812170   -------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref>--This is a representation of an electronic record that was signed electronically and this page is the manifestation of the electronic signature. <ref type="figure">----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------</ref> </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
