<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /scratch/yujieq/grobid/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-09-29">Received Date September 29, 2014</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-09-29">Received Date September 29, 2014</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>Clinical Reviewer: Daniela J. Vanco, M.D. STN: 125329/112 Page i Application Type Efficacy Supplement STN 125329/112 CBER</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.6.0-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID-SDO" when="2020-09-21T05:37+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid-sdo"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> <ref type="figure">..............................................................................................................................</ref></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Executive Summary</head><p>On September 29, 2014, Bio Products Laboratory (hereafter Bio Products) submitted an efficacy supplement application to Biologics License Application (sBLA) STN 125329/112 for Gammaplex®, Immune Globulin Intravenous (Human), 5% Liquid (hereafter Gammaplex), to include revisions to the package insert that reflect the pediatric population studied in the postmarketing study GAM04.</p><p>Gammaplex 5% is an Immunoglobulin Globulin Intravenous (IGIV) (Human) manufactured from source plasma from healthy, accredited donors in the United States. The plasma is processed at Bio Products' facility in Elstree, Hertfordshire, UK. It is presented as a ready-prepared solution of human normal immunoglobulin G (IgG) at pH 4.9 for intravenous administration. The IgG is stabilized with sorbitol.</p><p>Gammaplex was licensed in the United States on September 17, 2009, for the indication treatment of primary humoral immunodeficiency (PI). At the time of approval, the pediatric study requirement for patients 0 to &lt;2 years of age were waived because the necessary studies were impossible or highly impracticable. The pediatric study for patients &gt;2 to 16 years of age was deferred because Gammaplex was ready for approval for use in adults, and the pediatric study had not yet been initiated.</p><p>The deferred pediatric postmarketing study under the Pediatric Research Equity Act (PREA), required under 505B(a) of the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act, is the subject of this submission. The study is titled "A Phase 4, Multicenter, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Gammaplex® in Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases in Children and Adolescents," and includes a pharmacokinetic (PK) evaluation in children (&gt;2 to &lt;12 years) and adolescents (&gt;12 to 16 years). The objectives of the study were to determine the efficacy of Gammaplex measured by the number of serious, acute, bacterial infections (SABIs) over a 12-month period, as well as the safety and tolerability of Gammaplex.</p><p>The study subjects were treated for 12 months at 21-day (14 subjects) or 28-day (11subjects) dosing intervals. Three subjects were between the ages of 2 to 5 years, 12 subjects between the ages of 6 to 11 years, and 10 subjects were between the ages of 12 to 16 years. The median age of subjects was 11 years, and ranged from 3 to 16 years. Subjects were predominantly male (19 subjects, 76.0%). All of the subjects were Caucasian. Doses ranged from 300 mg/kg to 800 mg/kg. The mean dose (range) for the 21-day interval was 545 mg/kg (429 -689 mg/kg); the mean dose (range) for the 28-day interval was 521 mg/kg (316-800 mg/kg). Subjects received a total of 368 infusions of Gammaplex. The maximum infusion rate allowed during the clinical study was 0.08 mL/kg/min (4 mg/kg/min).</p><p>The clinical study achieved its primary efficacy endpoint of a 1-sided 99% upper bound confidence interval (CI) of less than one SABI per subject per year. The upper one sided 95% CI for the proportion of Gammaplex 5% infusions with at least one temporally associated adverse event (AE), regardless of causality, was 30.4%, which was less than the established historical control of 40%, thus also meeting the primary safety criterion. There were no deaths, no thromboembolic, or hemolytic events in the clinical study. Gammaplex was shown to be safe and well-tolerated in the pediatric PI subjects. An impact of subject's gender and race could not be established, due to the small sample size.</p><p>The revised final label is acceptable, and approval of the efficacy supplement is recommended.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Clinical and Regulatory Background</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.1">Disease or Health-Related Condition(s) Studied</head><p>PI is a spectrum of intrinsic defects in humoral and cellular immune function that can cause aberrations in immune globulins (IG), rendering subjects more susceptible to infections. Pathologies include, but are not limited to, the humoral immune defect in common variable immunodeficiency, X-linked agammaglobulinemia, congenital agammaglobulinemia, Wiskott-Aldrich syndrome, and severe combined immunodeficiencies. IG replacement therapy has been the standard treatment for PI since the early 1950s.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.2">Currently Available, Pharmacologically Unrelated Treatment(s)/Intervention(s) for the Proposed Indication(s)</head><p>Treatments for PI involve treating infections, generally with antibiotics, and preventing infections. Antibiotics may also be used to prevent infections in PI; however, the mainstay of prevention lies in correcting immunodeficiency. Bone marrow transplant (BMT) can be used, particularly in life-threatening immunodeficiency, and can be curative. BMT is not always successful and requires a donor who is a suitable tissue match to the recipient. Post-transplant BMT requires immunosuppressive therapy and runs the risk of graft vs. host disease. Enzyme replacement with adenosine deaminase is another option, but is only useful in patients who lack this enzyme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Safety and Efficacy of Pharmacologically Related Products</head><p>Safety and effectiveness of intravenous human IG products for replacement therapy of PI in adults and pediatric patients have been well established. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">SUBMISSION QUALITY AND GOOD CLINICAL PRACTICES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1">Submission Quality and Completeness</head><p>This supplement has been submitted electronically in compliance with Guidance for Industry: Providing Regulatory Submissions to the Center for Biologics <ref type="bibr">Evaluation and Research (CBER)</ref> in Electronic Format -Biologics Marketing Applications. The submission is also compliant with ICH guideline M4E, Common Technical Document for the Registration of Pharmaceuticals for Human Use, using appropriate numbering within the Modules. The index provides links to the relevant sections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2">Compliance with Good Clinical Practices and Submission Integrity</head><p>The Division of Inspections and Surveillance conducted Biomedical Monitoring (BIMO) inspections of two clinical sites, accounting for approximately 56% of the total subjects enrolled in the study (see <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">Table 1</ref>). The data audit portion of the inspections focused on the verification of the safety and efficacy study data for 100% of the enrollees at the two sites. In summary:</p><p>The BIMO inspections of two clinical investigators did not reveal substantive problems that would impact integrity of the data submitted in the sBLA.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.3">Financial Disclosures</head><p>The Clinical Investigator Compliance Program directs the FDA investigator to ask the clinical investigator if and when he/she disclosed information about his/her financial interests to the sponsor, and/or interests of any sub-investigators, spouse(s) and dependent children, and if and when the information was updated. The information submitted to the sBLA was verified for the investigator and sub-investigators.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">SIGNIFICANT EFFICACY/SAFETY ISSUES RELATED TO OTHER REVIEW DISCIPLINES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Chemistry, Manufacturing, and Controls (CMC)</head><p>Gammaplex contains sorbitol, glycine and polysorbate 80 as stabilizers. Specifically, Gammaplex contains approximately 5 g normal human immunoglobulin and 5 g Dsorbitol in 100 mL of buffer solution containing: 0.6 g glycine, 0.2 g sodium acetate, 0.3 g sodium chloride and ~5 mg polysorbate 80. Immunoglobulin G purity is &gt; 95%, the pH is in the range of 4.8 to 5.1, and osmolality is not less than 240 mOsmol/kg (typically 420 to 500 mOsmol/kg). The distribution of the four IgG subclasses is approximately 64% IgG1, 30% IgG2, 5% IgG3, and 1% IgG4. The batches used in GMX04 conform to the BLA-approved specifications.</p><p>No new CMC data were included in the submission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3">Nonclinical Pharmacology/Toxicology</head><p>No new nonclinical pharmacology or toxicology data were included in the submission. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4">Clinical Pharmacology</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.1">Mechanism of Action</head><p>Gammaplex acts through a broad spectrum of opsonic and neutralizing IgG antibodies against pathogens and their toxins involving antigen binding and effector functions. However, the mechanism of action in PI has not been fully elucidated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.3">Human Pharmacokinetics (PK)</head><p>The clinical PK of Gammaplex 5% has been evaluated in a pediatric population in GMX04. Data from 23 of 25 (92%) recruited subjects were used for PK analysis. One subject (Subject discontinued early, and a second subject (Subject had limited PK samples taken because of school commitments; therefore, these two subjects were excluded from the PK analysis. There were 17 males and 6 females with an age range of 3-16 years inclusive. The numbers of subjects in each age range was:</p><p>• n = 3 actual ages 3 to 5 years inclusive • n = 11 actual ages 6 to 11 years inclusive • n = 9 actual ages 12 to &lt;17 years PK parameters were estimated by non-compartmental analysis using both baseline adjusted and baseline unadjusted total IgG concentrations. The results of the study are summarized in <ref type="table" target="#tab_5">Table 2</ref> below. Reviewer Comment: The PK of IgG shows difference in the 2-5 years of age group of children compared to adults. Interpreting the clinical significance of these differences is difficult, given the small sample size (N=3). For more details, please refer to the clinical pharmacology review.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">(b) (6) ) (b) (6) )</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.5">Statistical</head><p>Both efficacy analyses and safety analyses in the submission were verified to support the claim for the use of Gammaplex in pediatric subjects with PI, and no statistical issues were identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">SOURCES OF CLINICAL DATA AND OTHER INFORMATION CONSIDERED IN THE REVIEW</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">Review Strategy</head><p>All documents submitted in the supplement were reviewed. Information requests (IR) and labeling revisions were sent to the applicant as necessary, until the subjects of the IR were clarified and agreement was reached on the labeling. The primary objective of the study was to determine efficacy, measured by the number of SABIs over a 12-month period. The secondary objectives were to assess the safety and tolerability of Gammaplex in pediatric subjects with PI, as compared to adults with PI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">BLA/IND Documents</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.2">Design Overview</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protocol GMX04:</head><p>This was a phase 4, multicenter (nine sites), open-label, non-randomized study of Gammaplex. A total of 25 subjects between the ages 2 through 16 were enrolled in the study, and administered the study drug by intravenous (IV) infusion at a dosage of 300-800 mg/kg per infusion (at the same dose of IGIV that was previously used to establish steady state), once every 21 or 28 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.3">Population</head><p>Subjects eligible for inclusion in the study: 1. The subject was between the age of, or equal to, 2 and 16 years of age, of either sex, belonging to any ethnic group, and above a minimum weight of 10 kg. This weight was based on the amount of blood required for testing. At least four of the subjects enrolled were to be 2 to 5 years of age, at least four were to be 6 to 11 years of age, and at least eight were to be12 to 16 years of age. 2. The subject had a PI, which had as a significant component: hypogammaglobulinaemia and/or antibody deficiency (e.g. common variable immunodeficiency; X-linked and autosomal forms of agammaglobulinaemia; hyper-immunoglobulin M [IgM] syndrome; or Wiskott-Aidrich Syndrome). Isolated deficiency of a single gG sub-class or of specific antibodies without hypogammaglobulinaemia per se, did not qualify for inclusion. 3. The subject required the following before the first infusion of Gammaplex:</p><p>• Documented IGIV dose(s) and treatment intervals for the last two consecutive routine IGIV treatments (one of which could be the screening visit result). The previous doses should also have met the following conditions before study entry: o Had not changed by± 50% of the mean dose for at least 3 months o Was between 300 and 800 mg/kg/infusion o Was given every 21-28 days, inclusive o Was a licensed or investigational product (phase 3 or 3b) • Documented previous IgG trough levels for the last two consecutive routine IGIV treatments: o Maintained at least 300 mg/dL above baseline serum IgG levels (defined as before initiation of any gamma globulin treatment for that subject). o Must have been ≥600 mg/dL. 4. If a subject was a female of child-bearing potential, she must have had a negative result on a human chorionic gonadotropin (HCG)-based pregnancy test. 5. If a subject was a female who was or became sexually active, she must have practiced contraception by using a method of proven reliability for the duration of the study. 6. The subject was willing to comply with all aspects of the protocol, including blood sampling, for the duration of the study.</p><p>7. The subject, if old enough (generally 6 to 16 years), had signed a Child Assent Form and the subject's parent or legal guardian had signed the Informed Consent Form, both approved by the Independent Ethics Committee/Institutional Review Board.</p><p>Subjects excluded from the study participation: 1. Had not been treated with IGIV (treatment-naive subject). 2. The subject had a history of any severe anaphylactic reaction to blood or any blood-derived product. 3. The subject was known to be intolerant to any component of Gammaplex, such as sorbitol (i.e., intolerance to fructose).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.4">Study Treatments or Agents Mandated by the Protocol</head><p>The study drug, Gammaplex, was administered by IV infusion at a dosage of 300-800 mg/kg per infusion (at the same dose of IGIV that was previously used to establish steady state), once every 21 or 28 days. The ready-prepared solution for IV administration contained 5 g human normal immunoglobulin, and 5 g D sorbitol (as stabilizer), in 100 mL of buffer solution. The infusion rates were initially at 0.01 mL/kg/min for the first 15 minutes and then, if tolerated, increased stepwise (i.e. to 0.02, 0.04, 0.06 and 0.08, maximum, mL/kg/min) every 15 minutes.</p><p>The total duration of treatment for each subject was 12 months. The total duration of a given subject's participation in this study was up to 16 months, including Screening (up to 30 days before enrolment), a 12-month treatment period and a 3-month follow-up period. Subjects received 13 to 17 infusions (i.e., 12 months of therapy on either a 21-day or 28-day treatment schedule) of Gammaplex at a dose of 300 to 800 mg/kg. Safety assessment was done during each infusion visit, plus 7 days after first infusion, and at 14 days, and three months after the last infusion. See the schema: All subjects underwent a PK profile of Gammaplex at the seventh infusion for subjects assigned to the 28-day schedule and at the ninth infusion for subjects on the 21-day • V ss volume of distribution at steady state; • AUC (0-tau) area under the plasma concentration-time curve from 0 (infusion start time) to the end of the dosing interval (21 or 28 days, depending on the assigned schedule)</p><p>• Trough levels IgG, IgG subclasses and antibodies against three specific antigens (Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae type b and cytomegalovirus) were measured before certain infusions)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.9">Statistical Considerations &amp; Statistical Analysis Plan</head><p>For the primary efficacy analysis, the SABI rate for Gammaplex and the upper bound of its one-sided 99% CI were estimated by using the exact method for a one-sample Poisson rate. Treatment success was defined as a mean SABI event rate of &lt; 0.5 per patient per year.</p><p>Secondary efficacy variables and PK variables were summarized descriptively.</p><p>For the primary safety criterion, the upper one sided 95% CI for the proportion of Gammaplex infusions with at least one temporally associated AE (regardless of relationship) was compared with the historical control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.10">Study Population and Disposition</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.10.1">Populations Enrolled/Analyzed</head><p>The intent-to-treat (ITT) population was used for safety and efficacy analyses. All subjects who receive at least one infusion of Gammaplex were included in the ITT population. A total of 25 subjects were enrolled; of these, all 25 were treated with Gammaplex and were included in the ITT population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.10.1.1">Demographics</head><p>The median age of subjects was 11.0 years and ranged from 3 to 16 years. Three subjects were between the ages of 2 to 5 years, 12 subjects between the ages of 6 to 11 years and 10 subjects were between the ages of 12 to 16 years. Subjects were predominantly male (19 subjects, 76.0%). All of the subjects were Caucasian.  Reviewer Comment: As Bio Products communicated to FDA, they had difficulties in recruiting pediatric subjects, mostly due to PK sampling and the long study duration, particularly in the youngest subject group, where only three out of the four planned subjects aged 2 to 5 years were enrolled, in spite of opening up additional sites in the United States and also a site in Israel.</p><p>One subject (Subject withdrew consent and discontinued from the study after the fourth infusion as they could not comply with the visit assessments specified in the protocol (ie. infusions every 21 or 28 days).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.11">Efficacy Analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.11.1">Analyses of Primary Endpoint(s)</head><p>For the primary efficacy analysis, the SABI rate for Gammaplex and the upper bound of its one-sided 99% CI were estimated by using the exact method for a one-sample Poisson rate. Treatment success was defined as a mean SABI event rate of &lt; 0.5 per patient per year. Two subjects had SABI, lobar pneumonia (see Section 6.1.12.4 for the narratives). Two SABIs in 25 subjects resulted in a mean SABI event rate per year of 0.09 and a one-sided 99% upper confidence bound of 0.36. The observed SABI frequency was less than 0.5 per patient per year, thereby meeting the primary end point. Reviewer Comment: As per FDA guidance supported by historical data, a statistical demonstration of a SABI rate per person-year less than 1.0 is adequate to provide substantial evidence of efficacy. The study results show that the one-sided 99% upper CI is less than FDA's efficacy threshold value of 1.0, therefore meeting the pre-specified primary efficacy endpoint for Gammaplex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.11.2">Analyses of Secondary Endpoints (N=25)</head><p>All trough levels were maintained above 600 mg/dL from Week 15 onwards. While a high proportion of subjects had trough levels below the mean of the pre-study values (18 subjects, 72.0%), there is no evidence of a systematic decline in IgG values over time during Gammaplex treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of days of school missed because of infection</head><p>Sixteen subjects (64.0%) missed at least one day from school or nursery because of an infection or other problem. The mean (SD) number of days off from school or nursery was 4.2 (8.28) per subject per year, and the maximum number of days missed was 32. No subjects in the 2 to 5 year age group had days off from school or nursery. Seven of the 12 subjects (58.3%) in the 6 to 11 year age group missed days from school or nursery; mean (SD) days missed for this age group was 2.3 (3.22). In the 12 to 16 year age group, nine of the 10 subjects (90.0%) missed days from school or nursery. The mean (SD) for this age group was 7.8 (12.06) days missed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of days of hospitalization because of infection</head><p>The majority of subjects (22 subjects, 88.0%) did not require hospitalization because of an infection or a medical problem during the study. The overall mean (SD) number of days of hospitalization was 0.3 (0.87) per subject per year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of visits to physician/emergency room for acute problems</head><p>The majority of subjects (18 subjects, 72.0%) visited a physician or hospital emergency room because of an infection or other medical problem. Eighteen subjects (72.0%) visited a physician and eight subjects (32.0%) visited the emergency room. Overall, the mean (SD) number of visits to a physician or hospital emergency room was 4.0 (4.67).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other infections documented by fever, positive result on radiograph and/or culture or clinical examination</head><p>Twenty-one subjects (84.0%) experienced at least one infection during the study. Overall upper respiratory tract infections were reported by more subjects than any other infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of infectious episodes per subject per year</head><p>Twenty-one subjects (84.0%) experienced at least one infection during the study <ref type="table">(Table  9</ref>). The mean (SD) number of infections per subject per year was 3.20 (2.713).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Number of days on therapeutic and prophylactic antibiotics</head><p>Twenty-one subjects (84.0%) took systemic antibiotic medications during the study. Therapeutic systemic antibiotic medications were taken by the same number of subjects (21 subjects, 84.0%), and prophylactic systemic antibiotic medications were taken by six subjects (24.0%). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Comparison of secondary efficacy variables between GMX01 and GMX04</head><p>The GMX01 (pivotal) and GMX04 (pediatric PMR) studies evaluated the same variables but in adults and children in GMX01 (aged 3 years and above) and in children (aged 2 to 16 years) in GMX04. Fifty subjects were enrolled in the GMX01 study and 25 in the GMX04 study. Of the 50 subjects enrolled in the GMX01 study, six were 16 years of age or younger. There were no significant differences seen in these two studies.</p><p>Reviewer Comment: The choice and the outcomes of the secondary efficacy endpoints are adequate in support of the primary endpoints and no issues were identified. For more details, please refer to the full statistical review memo.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.11.3">Subpopulation Analyses</head><p>The primary analysis was repeated for the age categories of subjects aged 2 to 5 years, 6 to 11 years and 12 to 16 years. One subject in the 6 to 11 year age group (Subject (b) (6) ear age experienced a SABI of lobar pneumonia, and one subject in the 12 to 16 y group (Subject (b) (6) ) also experienced a SABI of lobar pneumonia. No SABIs occurred in the 2 to 5 year age group. Mean event rates per year (one-sided 99% upper (b) (6) confidence bound) for the age groups 6 to 11 years and 12 to 16 years were 0.09 (0.57) and 0.11 (0.74), respectively.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Table 9: SABIs by Age Groups</head><p>Reviewer Comment: The subpopulation analysis did not yield meaningful results for interpretation due to the small sample size. <ref type="bibr">6.1.11.4</ref> Dropouts and/or Discontinuations Data from subjects who withdrew were included, where possible, in all summaries and analyses. All summaries and analyses were based on observed data. No imputation was performed for missing data.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.12">Safety Analyses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.12.1">Methods</head><p>The safety population consisted of all subjects who received at least 1 dose of Gammaplex (N=25).</p><p>For all subjects, the mean (SD) duration of exposure to Gammaplex was 342.3 (53.77) days, and median duration was 351.0 days with a range of 88 to 376 days. The duration of exposure was between 11 and 12 months for the majority of subjects (21 subjects, 84.0%). The mean dose (range) per infusion was 536 mg/kg (300-800 mg/kg) for all subjects. The mean dose (range) for subjects on the 21-day schedule was 545 mg/kg (429-689 mg/kg), and for subjects on the 28-day schedule was 521 mg/kg (316-800 mg/kg)(See <ref type="table">Table 9</ref>). No doses were outside the planned range of 300 to 800 mg/kg. Safety data were collected from screening until 30 days after the last infusion of Gammaplex (approximately one year after the first infusion). A viral screen was conducted pre first infusion and at the final visit, 3 months after the last infusion of Gammaplex. Infusions of Gammaplex 5% were administered for approximately 1 year. After 6 months of treatment with Gammaplex 5%, the subjects had a PK profile performed between 2 sequential infusions (between infusions 9 and 10 for those on the 21-day schedule, or between infusions 7 and 8 for those on the 28-day schedule). The primary safety criterion was that the upper bound of the 95% CI indicates that not more than 40% of infusions were associated with an AE, irrespective of causality. All perinfusion AEs (during and up to 72 hours after infusion) were collected. Their relationship to Gammaplex was assessed by investigator.</p><p>AE was defined as any untoward medical occurrence in a patient administered a pharmaceutical product that does not necessarily have a causal relationship with the treatment.</p><p>Infusion-Related Adverse Reactions (AR) were defined as all AEs temporally associated with infusion -occurring from the start of the infusion until 72 hours after the infusion.</p><p>AR were defined as all noxious and unintended responses to a medicinal product related to any dose administered. The phrase 'response to a medicinal product' means that a causal relationship between a medicinal product and an adverse event is at least a reasonable possibility.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.12.2">Overview of AEs</head><p>During the treatment period and up to 30 days after the last dose, all 25 subjects reported at least one AE. Altogether, there was a total of 365 AEs in the study. Fourteen subjects (56.0%) had an AR, defined as possibly, probably or definitely related to study drug. Two </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Infusion-Related ARs</head><p>Out of 368 infusions, 97 were associated with an AR. A summary of adverse reactions reported by three or more subjects and the associated number of infusions is below: The most common events reported during infusions were headache, hypotension, tachycardia and diastolic hypertension. Headache was experienced by more subjects (five subjects, 20.0%) than any other AE during infusion, and most of these subjects (three subjects, 12.0%) reported the AE of headache during an infusion rate of 0.08 mL/kg/min.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject (b) (6)</head><p>A 7-year-old male subject had a history of patchy infiltrations in the left lower lung lobe and suspected pneumonitis in the right lung base on chest X-ray during May 2011. He had also experienced a series of upper respiratory tract infections requiring antibiotics in the month before beginning treatment with Gammaplex. The subject received his first infusion of Gammaplex on 17 February 2012 at a dose level of 347 mg/kg (28-day infusion schedule). Between 25 and 29 February 2012, he was started on an antibiotic, guaifenesin and prednisone, which he completed 5 to 9 days later. On (b) <ref type="formula">(6)</ref> , one week after the second infusion of Gammaplex, the subject was hospitalized with a fever (101.8°F), tachycardia, dyspnea, hypoxia and vomiting. His diagnosis was patchy, left lower lobe pneumonia diagnosed by chest X-ray on the day of admission. However, no bacterial etiology was identified by blood cultures, and the Principal Investigator considered the pneumonia to be of viral origin or possibly due to an exacerbation of the subject's asthma. He was discharged from the hospital on (b) (6)</p><p>. The event was resolved on 02 April 2012. The investigator considered the lobar pneumonia not related to study drug. For the purposes of the data reporting and analysis, this SAE was assumed to be bacterial in nature and, therefore, met the FDA definition of a SABI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subject (b) (6)</head><p>ear-old male A 17-y subject, had a medical history that included chronic bronchitis and asthma since 3 years of age and pneumonia. The subject received his first infusion of GAMMAPLEX on 05 February 2013 at a dose level of 400 mg/kg (28-day infusion schedule). His last dose of GAMMAPLEX received before onset of the AE was administered on 25 June 2013 at the same dose level. On 06 July 2013, the subject developed fever and chills. On 11 July 2013, the subject developed a productive cough with yellow phlegm, dyspnea, chest pain and tachycardia. A chest X-ray revealed a 4 cm retrocardiac left lung base infiltrate. Laboratory results included a WBC count of 26.4 × 109/L (reference range 4.8-10.8 × 109/L), band neutrophils 23% (reference range 50-80%) and lymphocytes 6% (reference range 20-50%). On 14 July 2013, the subject was hospitalized for the treatment of severe left lower lobe pneumonia. A chest X-ray showed patchy air space opacities in the left lower lobe consistent with pneumonia. The SAE of left lower lobe pneumonia resolved on 16 July 2013. The investigator considered the lobar pneumonia not related to study drug. In the opinion of the investigator, the event was related to a concurrent upper respiratory infection and met the FDA definition of a SABI.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.12.5">AEs of Special Interest (AESI)</head><p>No thrombo-embolic events, which have boxed warning in this class of products, where reported in the study. No cases of hemolytic events were reported as well.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.12.6">Clinical Test Results</head><p>Results of hematology, chemistry and urinalysis testing did not suggest evidence of hemolysis or thrombotic events, immunogenicity, or any other safety signals. No subject tested positive for hepatitis B surface antigen, hepatitis C virus, or HIV.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.1.13">Study Summary and Conclusions</head><p>Out of the 368 total number of infusions in GMX04, 97 (26.4%) were temporally associated with at least one AE irrespective of causality (occurring within 72 hours of the end of infusion). The upper one sided 95% confidence limit for the proportion of Gammaplex infusions with at least one temporally associated AE (regardless of causality) was 30.4% which was less than the established historical control of 0.40 (40%). Therefore, the primary safety criterion was met.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">INTEGRATED OVERVIEW OF EFFICACY</head><p>Only one study was submitted in support of this efficacy supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">INTEGRATED OVERVIEW OF SAFETY</head><p>Only one study was submitted in support of this efficacy supplement.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">ADDITIONAL CLINICAL ISSUES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1">Special Populations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.1.3">Pediatric Use and PREA Considerations</head><p>The pediatric assessment in this submission and the associated labeling changes were presented to the PREA Subcommittee [Pediatric Review Committee (PeRC)] on May 27, 2015. The PeRC agreed that the PMR for PREA deferral has been fulfilled by the current efficacy supplement, and found the pediatric population adequately addressed in the proposed language of the package insert.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">CONCLUSIONS</head><p>• Bio Products have fulfilled the PMR for PREA deferral with submission of the clinical study report for GMX04, which included pediatric assessment in 25 pediatric subjects. • Bio Products have already received a PREA waiver previously for submission of pediatric assessment in neonates and pediatric patients two years of age and younger. • BioProducts have updated the package insert for Gammaplex to incorporate the pediatric findings and revised it with FDA recommendations. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.">RISK-BENEFIT CONSIDERATIONS AND RECOMMENDATIONS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.1">Risk-Benefit Considerations</head><p>There are currently no concerns regarding the risk/benefit ratio. Thromboembolic events have been described after the administration of IGIVs. Measures to mitigate the risk of thromboembolic events following use of Gammaplex are highlighted in the label as boxed warning.</p><p>The clinical study showed that Gammaplex is reasonably safe and effective in the pediatric population, without clinically significant differences from the adult population. As for all age groups, dosing for pediatric subjects is also based on body weight and the labeling clearly instructs dosing to be titrated to patient's clinical response. No pediatricspecific dose requirements are necessary to achieve the desired serum IgG levels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.4">Recommendations on Regulatory Actions</head><p>Approval of this efficacy supplement is recommended from a clinical stand point.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.5">Labeling Review and Recommendations</head><p>The final labeling was agreed upon and was submitted in the Amendment number 11.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="11.6">Recommendations on Postmarketing Actions</head><p>This submission fulfills the PMR. No further postmarketing clinical studies are needed at this time.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>Figure 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Schematic Representation of 21-day and 28-day Infusion CyclesSource:GMX04 Clinical Study Report/Version: 22 August 2014, page 29    </figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>TABLE OF CONTENTS GLOSSARY ...</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>..... 3 GLOSSARY</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>AE</cell><cell>adverse event</cell></row><row><cell>ALT</cell><cell>alanine aminotransferase</cell></row><row><cell>AST</cell><cell>aspartate aminotransferase</cell></row><row><cell>AUC</cell><cell>area under the plasma concentration-time curve from time 0 to Day 28</cell></row><row><cell>BPL</cell><cell>Bio Products Laboratory Ltd. (Sponsor/manufacturer)</cell></row><row><cell>BUN</cell><cell>blood urea nitrogen</cell></row><row><cell>CI</cell><cell>confidence interval</cell></row><row><cell>Cmax</cell><cell>peak concentration in plasma</cell></row><row><cell>CRF</cell><cell>case report form</cell></row><row><cell>CVID</cell><cell>common variable immunodeficiency</cell></row><row><cell>HBsAg</cell><cell>hepatitis B surface antigen</cell></row><row><cell>HBV</cell><cell>hepatitis B virus</cell></row><row><cell>HCV</cell><cell>hepatitis C virus</cell></row><row><cell>HIV</cell><cell>human immunodeficiency virus</cell></row><row><cell>IgA</cell><cell>immunoglobulin A</cell></row><row><cell>IgG</cell><cell>immunoglobulin G</cell></row><row><cell>IGIV</cell><cell>intravenous immunoglobulin</cell></row><row><cell>IgM</cell><cell>immunoglobulin M</cell></row><row><cell>ITP</cell><cell>idiopathic thrombocytopoenic purpura</cell></row><row><cell>ITT</cell><cell>intent-to-treat</cell></row><row><cell>LDH</cell><cell>lactate dehydrogenase</cell></row><row><cell>MCH</cell><cell>mean corpuscular haemoglobin</cell></row><row><cell>MedDRA</cell><cell>Medical Dictionary for Regulatory Activities</cell></row><row><cell>MRI</cell><cell>magnetic resonance imaging</cell></row><row><cell>PCR</cell><cell>polymerase chain reaction</cell></row><row><cell>PID</cell><cell>primary immunodeficiency disease(s)</cell></row><row><cell>PK</cell><cell>pharmacokinetic(s)</cell></row><row><cell>SABI</cell><cell>serious, acute, bacterial infection</cell></row><row><cell>SAE</cell><cell>serious adverse event</cell></row><row><cell>SCIG</cell><cell>subcutaneous immunoglobulin</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Previous Human Experience with the Product (Including Foreign Experience)Summary of Pre-and Post-submission Regulatory Activity Related to the Submission</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>2.4 Gammaplex was licensed in the United States on September 17, 2009, for the indication</cell></row><row><cell>treatment of PI. On March 8, 2013, Gammaplex received licensure for the indication</cell></row><row><cell>treatment of chronic immune thrombocytopenic purpura (ITP), for which Orphan Drug</cell></row><row><cell>Designation was granted. Gammaplex is currently licensed in the United States, United</cell></row><row><cell>Kingdom, Israel, Brazil, and Lebanon.</cell></row><row><cell>2.5 • September 17, 2009, Gammaplex was licensed for the indication treatment of PI.</cell></row><row><cell>The postmarketing requirement (PMR) pediatric study for the treatment of PI in</cell></row><row><cell>pediatric patients &gt;2 to 16 years of age was deferred with the following timelines:</cell></row><row><cell>o Protocol Submission: November 2009</cell></row><row><cell>o Study Initiation: January 2010</cell></row><row><cell>o Study Completion: September 2012</cell></row><row><cell>o Final Report Submission: December 2012</cell></row><row><cell>• March 8, 2013, ITP indication was approved (BLS 125329/55)</cell></row><row><cell>• April 9, 2013, Bio Products communicated to FDA that the ongoing GMX04</cell></row><row><cell>study had been significantly delayed due to very slow recruitment. The clinical</cell></row><row><cell>study report would be delayed until December 2014. Deferral extension request</cell></row><row><cell>was granted by FDA on July 9, 2013.</cell></row><row><cell>As per FDA's Guidance</cell></row><row><cell>"Safety, Efficacy, and Pharmacokinetic Studies to Support Marketing of Immune</cell></row><row><cell>Globulin Intravenous (Human) as Replacement Therapy for Primary Humoral</cell></row><row><cell>Immunodeficiency" and the cited literature references, IGIV administration to individuals</cell></row><row><cell>with PI have observed SABI rates of 0.5 per year, as opposed to four or more SABIs in</cell></row><row><cell>those without IGIV replacement therapy.</cell></row><row><cell>Currently available IGIV products carry warnings and precautions that include:</cell></row><row><cell>thrombosis; hypersensitivity; renal dysfunction/failure; hyperproteinemia, increased</cell></row><row><cell>serum viscosity, and hyponatremia; aseptic meningitis syndrome; hemolysis; transfusion-</cell></row><row><cell>related acute lung injury; transmissible infectious agents; and interference with laboratory</cell></row><row><cell>tests.</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Study site / Site # Location Number of subjects enrolled Form FDA 483 issued Final classificationTable 1 : Inspection of Clinical Sites and Outcomes</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Family Allergy &amp; Asthma Center, P.C. / 402</cell><cell>Atlanta, Georgia</cell><cell>6</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>NAI</cell></row><row><cell>IMMUNOe International Research Centers / 401</cell><cell>Centennial, Colorado</cell><cell>8</cell><cell>No</cell><cell>NAI</cell></row><row><cell>NAI-No Action Indicated</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 2 : Effect of Age on Absolute and Baseline-adjusted PK Parameters of IgG Following Intravenous Infusion of Doses of 304 to 813 mg/kg Gammaplex</head><label>2</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note># 90% CI contained within bioequivalence limits of (0.80, 1.25) Source Pharmacokinetic Report GMX01 and GMX04, (b) (4) Ref. No. BPL109, Table 18, Pg 51 of 111.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>That Serve as the Basis for the Clinical Review6. DISCUSSION OF INDIVIDUAL STUDIES/CLINICAL TRIALS 6.1 Trial #1 "A Phase 4, Multicenter, Open-Label Study to Evaluate the Efficacy and Safety of Gammaplex® in Primary Immunodeficiency Diseases in Children and Adolescents</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>• BLA 125329/0</cell></row><row><cell>• BLS 125329/55</cell></row><row><cell>• BLS 125329/112</cell></row><row><cell>• IND 12569</cell></row><row><cell>o Adverse event listings</cell></row><row><cell>o Audit certificates</cell></row><row><cell>o Demographic data listing</cell></row><row><cell>o IRBs and Consent Forms</cell></row><row><cell>o Efficacy data</cell></row><row><cell>o Sites and investigators</cell></row><row><cell>o Protocol/amendments</cell></row><row><cell>o Full study report</cell></row><row><cell>o Individual Case Study Report Forms</cell></row><row><cell>5.4 Consultations</cell></row><row><cell>No consultations were obtained during the review.</cell></row><row><cell>"</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.1 Objectives (Primary, Secondary)</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Number and proportion of subjects from Week 15 onwards who maintained trough IgG levels at least as high as the average of the two previous trough levels before the first Gammaplex infusion • Number of days of school missed because of infection per subject year • Number and days of hospitalizations because of infection per subject year • Number of visits to physicians for acute problems and/or number of visits to hospital emergency rooms per subject year • Other infections documented by fever or a positive result on a radiograph and/or culture per subject year • Number of infectious episodes per subject per year • Number of days on therapeutic and prophylactic antibiotics Safety Endpoints: • Number and percentage of adverse events (AEs) and adverse reactions (AR), • Significant changes in vital signs, clinical laboratory tests (including kidney and</figDesc><table><row><cell>6.1.8 Endpoints and Criteria for Study Success Efficacy: Primary: The primary efficacy endpoint was the number of SABIs per subject per year, pre-defined by FDA as: • Bacterial pneumonia • Bacteraemia or sepsis • Osteomyelitis/septic arthritis • Visceral abscess • Bacterial meningitis Treatment success was defined as a mean SABI event rate of&lt; 0.5 per patient per year. Secondary: examination during the study PK Endpoints: • C max peak concentration in plasma; • t max time to reach the peak concentration in plasma; • t 1/2 terminal half-life; • liver function), direct Coombs test, transmission of viruses and physical • CL systemic clearance;</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>Table 6 :</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Demographics</figDesc><table><row><cell>Source: GMX04 Clinical Study Report/Version: 22 August 2014, page 140-141.</cell></row><row><cell>6.1.10.1.2 Medical/Behavioral Characterization of the Enrolled Population</cell></row><row><cell>All subjects were PI patients with history of recurrent infections. The most common</cell></row><row><cell>medical history conditions were chronic sinusitis (15 subjects, 60.0%), allergic rhinitis</cell></row><row><cell>(11 subjects, 44.0%) and gastroesophageal reflux disease (10 subjects, 40.0%).</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 7 : Subject Disposition</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Table 8</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">: Secondary Endpoints</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Efficacy Measure</cell><cell>Incidence Rate</cell><cell>Descriptive Statistics</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>N (%)</cell><cell>SD</cell></row><row><cell>Number of days of school</cell><cell>16 (64)</cell><cell>4.2 (8.28)</cell></row><row><cell>missed because of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of days of</cell><cell>22(88)</cell><cell>0.3 (0.87)</cell></row><row><cell>hospitalization because of</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>infection</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of visits to</cell><cell>18 (72)</cell><cell>4.0 (4.67)</cell></row><row><cell>physician/emergency room</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>for acute problems</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of infectious</cell><cell>21 (84)</cell><cell>3.2 (2.713)</cell></row><row><cell>episodes per subject per</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>year</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Number of days on</cell><cell>21 (84)</cell><cell>110.6 (137.10)</cell></row><row><cell>therapeutic and</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>prophylactic antibiotics</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 10 : Exposure to GAMMAPLEX by Mean (SD) Total Dose</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Table 13 : Number and Percent of Subjects with Product-related Adverse Events Occurring with a Frequency of 5% of Subjects or More</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 14 : Infusion-related ARs Clinical Reviewer: Daniela J. Vanco, M.</head><label>14</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>D.</cell></row><row><cell>STN: 125329/112</cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 15 : Number and Percent of Subjects with Adverse Events during Infusion Occurring with a Frequency of 5% of Total Subjects or More as a Function of Infusion Rate</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>6.1.12.3 Deaths</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>There were no deaths in the study.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>6.1.12.4 Nonfatal SAEs</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Two subjects (8%) had a total of two SAEs onset between first infusion date and 30 days</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">after the last infusion. Subject (b) (6) experienced an SAE of lobar pneumonia (left</cell></row><row><cell>lower lobe pneumonia) of moderate intensity. Subject</cell><cell>experienced an SAE of</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">lobar pneumonia (left lower lobe pneumonia) of severe intensity. Neither of the SAEs</cell></row><row><cell>was considered related to study drug.</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">Source:GMX04 Clinical Study Report/Version: 22 August 2014, page 26-28   </note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot">The most common ARs were headache(19 events [8 subjects, 32.0%]), myalgia (12 events [1 subject, 4.0%]) and hypotension (8 events [4 subjects, 16.0%]). Twelve product-related AEs were vascular (hypotension and diastolic hypertension) (five subjects, 20.0%). Four product-related AEs of tachycardia were reported by three subjects (12.0%); one of these subjects (Subject (b) (6) ) also reported product-related AEs of diastolic hypertension, diastolic hypotension and hypotension, but these events did not occur at the same time as the two events of tachycardia.</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ARs:</head><p>Fourteen subjects (56.0%) had at least one AR. There were 74 AR, none of which were serious. By age group, two subjects (66.7%) had 19 product-related AEs in the 2 to 5 year age group, seven subjects (58.3%) had 29 product-related AEs in the 6 to 11 year age group and five subjects (50.0%) had 26 product-related AEs in the 12 to 16 year age group.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
